[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
do
good evening welcome to the private
property farming podcast my name is
imbalanco and i'm your host every
tuesdays and thursdays uh thank you so
much for watching us this evening and
we've got another amazing show all about
traditional farming methods for crop
rotation so if you're looking for a
number of ways to rotate your crop um
and obviously smart ways that that's to
ensure that you increase your yields um
and that you form just you know um using
the maximum amount of space that you
have in your land and farming
efficiently with different crops then i
think this show is for you and tonight
we are joined by lofty smiths who is the
founder who's pretty much a farmer and
founder of the friendly butchery um and
we're going to talk about crop rotation
traditional farming methods and a bit
about his enterprise and how he started
and how he's grown his business till
date luffy thank you so much for joining
us how are you doing
i'm i'm fine bali it's it's a pleasure
you know to have you and uh
yeah let's get going
awesome awesome so lofi tell us about
your farming journey um when did you
start farming are you a second third
fourth generation farmer and
give us more insight around the friendly
butchery
[Music]
it's it's uh
my father bought the farm around about
but i grew up in a farm which is
basically next door to the farm that i'm
on
and i was born there and grew up and so
on so i've been in the farming business
for many years
and then i started farming
in 1996 with farm from my father
and then
i
you
know
uh we were still in the culture
[Music]
five years and a few very funny years
where we had you know a lot of crop
losses due to heat waves
during the the flight
of wheat
i
started realizing you know we got to do
something we got to change our methods
and ways of farming and that's when i
started doing
uh going from a mona culture
i went over to
i went and i started
doing medics medics is clovers
where i do the clovers in the one year
and the following year i will do the
wheat
on the specific same land so i went on a
rotation
and and it's been
brilliant it has been it's been
yes
it happened to me because it's nice
thing about the mix is it's
it's nitrogen fixing
and um
and you can carry so many animals on on
a hectare i mean i have dormers you know
which originate from elsa moon
it's a meat nice mutton
and
i run i can run four
twin dorma u's meaning four u's with
twins on a hectare and
it's it's just amazing i mean
the the quality
of sheep that comes out of there
the
within 100 days i have my lambs market
ready off medics from their mother
so you know basically in a hundred days
you know
it's a lifesaver
and because of that um because i was
running the sheep with such good success
you know on the medics
um i started thinking
my
self you know it's it's a match
you know in the in the supermarkets and
it's always been just you know dream of
mine to start my own butchery and then
two years ago about two and a half years
ago i i got to the point where i
applied for a license
and we started the friendly farmer
butchery and it's and it's
absolutely amazing my wife does all the
admin
i'm the block man
and
it's
it's just amazing it's just picked up
and i've gone with it and i was very
fortunate that my my late mother
she's from the
area uh richmond area where she grew up
and always as a kid you know when
whenever we would meet
i i used to go and help her and she
showed me hell of a lot and um
i'm actually using
sort of all my
recipes and so on as you know from my
late mother's
so you know something something special
and i really i
it's been
it's been a long time coming that i
wanted to start a book sharing and like
i said two and a half years ago we got
going and we do deliveries
we don't have any
on the farm um shop where you can come
and buy
due to security reasons and so on you
know and uh so we do the we we do the
deliveries
um we do tape down
uh we do balls
and uh yeah it's been it's been
wonderful it really has been good
i certainly saw a hell of a change in my
soil
after going with the medics
it's amazing how much life returned to
the soil
and also with with this change that we
made
we
went into
uh
we started doing um
we got planters where we use the shank
so we we try and do minimum disturbance
of the soil
to try and keep as much moisture
as well when we are doing the week here
like i said the one years we the next
year we have medics the next year we
have wheat again
and i also do other rotation crops as
well i i use oats i do a lot of oats
and
some oats we do for otay
the other oats you know i'm at the
moment i'm actually busy harvesting oats
for seed you know for for for the
co-operandia
and uh and getting a very good yield but
it's important to
um
kernels in your in your oats so it's
very important that's why i'm doing oats
at the moment
also we have now the last four years
we've started with um
uh regenerative farming where we take
our swell and and we started doing cover
crops
you know obviously you know my medics is
is of such nice quality and it's it's it
grows you know in abundance you know
however nicely so
that to me is also a cover crop because
in the summer and when the medics goes
down and goes and lies down my my soil
is basically covered you know
and and we do
we also bring it in other cover crops we
do
a little bit of this
that the medics can also
come through and and you know
leave it spurs and everything and and
i'll find it absolutely amazing it was
incredible
it started getting its own life how the
earthworms came in
and started burrowing
and i always say to the people whenever
i walk they always say look at this look
at this earthworm life because those are
my plans those are my is what what is
you know doing the thing
and and i think i personally that's the
way i've gone and i'm i'm on a rate of
of
are
going in at about 110 kilograms of
nitrogen on their wheatlands you know so
yeah i mean that's something is very
easy like you know you can just see what
you know what lies in it and i've in
fact just finished harvesting my week
for this year and it was an amazing crop
i must i must say that for the last six
years we've really had tough times so
we've had chance last year wasn't too
bad
but we had a bit of of
the frost you know during the flowering
season
but the last six years was really it was
tough but
this year was amazing and i'm i'm sorry
that's great i'm happy for you but stop
me if i talk too much
no it's okay i mean we want information
right and um
my question then is you know it sounds
like you've you know dabbled a bit in a
number of different crops you know for
the purpose of crop rotation and when
you're going through these processes as
a farmer you know um
who are the people that you'd sit down
and talk to
to assist you to say like who made made
you say uh now you need the specific
crop to rotate with weed
wheat for example sorry um and um
how did you come about doing that
research you know um so just in case
maybe people in the audience are
thinking yes i wanna do crop rotation
but i don't know what to rotate my crops
with so how do you find a good
companionship with the kind of crops
that you're farming which first of all
was wheat um
so that you could you know rotate and
obviously grow your enterprise so at
what point did you make that decision
and who are the type of people did you
liaise with to maybe see if this idea
would work or not
yeah
um
here in the western coast you know i
always say in the area that you that you
are farming you know
it's very
what
do they do there is a success
right
and the agriculture the western
agricultural union
that
they have a very close to us about 30-40
kilometers away they've got a a farm
there where from elsenberg they
they do a whole lot of um
trials you know doing basically canola
doing loop and doing oats doing the
medics
different variety of medics
and then the rotational crop and then
you have companies like agricult
and you have barrenburg you know that
come and they do it on this um on this
farm that is that is owned by the the
western cape agriculture
from elsenberg and and and they all do
their little trials there and all
different type of trials you know and
then
what they also do is and it's and it's
it's um it's called this
uh it's normally in september beginning
of september they have a
and the farmers day
everybody's interested comes along and
we have a look
what are the varieties that are doing
good what you know what
what should you do next year
for your area which is which to me that
that's that's basically where
we
you learn a lot of things you know
because you can see what happens and i
think that's the important thing about
it also
i have a company that i do you know
the guy helps me with my fertilizer and
you know what to do and so on um
you know and i think i think that's the
biggest thing of all you must minimize
your risk by
going in with the least inset
but the best outside you know and the
best quality and i think that is very
important
and
quite honest with you i think
there's a little bit of a
you know if you if you if you see the
the quality of wheat that we get from
from our
medic system you know
uh we
and we specifically i also do um my
model that is is um i try and do
biological farming with my fertilizer
where i use a chicken
and and then of course nitrogen and it's
all in the little fertilizer little
little chicken you know manure pool they
they do it in a pool form
and then we sew but to me the big
disappointment is
that
as a farmer i don't get
because the quality of wheat that
produce doing
farming
you know from the malayan i think that's
but i i think it's something that's
that's that's going to happen soon you
know where
when people are now starting move the
quality of wheat that they get
as to other wheat that has for instance
you know had a lot of nitrogen and so on
i mean it's just a better quality you
know yeah so hopefully that's
and and also
and also we uh
you know we we we in dire straits for
next year you know with
the first
so unbelievably high
so fortunately you know i'm on my system
of farming
where i go with the low insets
and i just bring my wrist down and and
and that i do
my friends
uh
this friend of mine who you know who who
does my fertilizer and then of course
you know we use pesticides we have to
um
and then i try and lay away from things
like ronda i try i don't always
but i try my best you know to to to sort
of keep that out of my system
yeah yeah you know typically traditional
farming is uh
sorry to interject there typically
traditional farming is um you know
heavily reliant on pesticides and
chemicals and fertilizers and it sounds
like you've obviously adopted like a
biological approach as you've said do
you think that you've seen a significant
amount of
um
operational reduction in terms of the
expenses that you would have ordinarily
paid for
when if you had gone you know the
traditional farming methods now that
you've adopted a more of a regenerative
farming or biological approach as you've
put it so do you think that
with going with a different approach
maybe deviating a slightly from
traditional farming methods to rather
care more for your soil
have you seen a a change in your
business operational expenses where they
have reduced perhaps
yeah yeah definitely i mean without a
doubt i mean
my diesel my you know my fuel account
i think has been halved from what it
used to be you know
and um
my fertilizer i mean
they used to build in here with you know
full of fertilizer
i have one truck of city city tons that
comes in and does my
and and
and this is amazing you know it's
you know from
from those years to now i would say i
think there was a reduction of about
close on to 40 percent in usage of of of
fuel
and fertilizer definitely yeah
yeah one thing from your from your
experience causes the shift for farmers
just to think slightly differently from
traditional farming practices is it
things that happen in the economy or you
know like high fuel prices or high input
cost prices or is it because maybe over
the years farmers are starting to become
uh thinking yes definitely much more
long-term to say how do i preserve my
soil and therefore how do i find
companion plants to
to ensure that my soil you know could
last generations to come if i'm still
you know producing in this one specific
uh farm or piece of land so what do you
think causes the farmers to make that
shift um you know to to to to to to
focus a lot more on the production
practices is it the economy is it the
the push from high input costs or is it
just do you think that farmers are
becoming slightly more conservative
rather um um
with regards to the environment etc and
you know people are starting to just
make certain changes
yeah
molly um i think the
the thing that is really hitting home
now
is is is the weather you know
yeah
it's been amazing the last
five six years
to see what global warming and and
i believe in global warming i have
experienced it myself
[Music]
we have a september month it's very very
important that's when
just after the week's flight
and it's it it's little it's a little
grey you know it must get was set now
and and we just haven't had september
months we we just don't have rain in
september again yeah you know lately
and and i put it on to global warming
and global warming has made it that you
must absolutely at all cost you must try
and preserve as much moisture in the
ground as possible that means you don't
open the up you don't open it up
you must turn your will as little as
possible and i think that together with
the cost of insect costs and everything
as really i think um
for me that was my game changer because
i
i just i just thought to myself i just
thought my own eyes that if i wasn't
going to make a change i wasn't going to
be on the farm for very long so that is
what i did and i go with the lowest
insets as as possible
and
at the end of the day that is what it's
about you know making a profit and um
yeah and that's what's changed and
incidentally you know what really
changed my my mind as well i can
remember um you know when you when you
drive along the fence
you don't
on the fence this is like a half a meter
this side half of me to that side that
you you never work there
and
everything that grows on next to the
fence you know
it's always
looks lush and if there's a little weak
kernel that falls there or a medic
it grows with so much power and why
it gets disturbed you understand and
that is why i say i try and just
as little as possible i don't burn my
lands a lot of people still around here
they burn the stubble because they're
doing the murder culture
culture
the writings to take place that's why
they got to put on like closer than 100
kilograms of nitrogen whereas i go i
don't burn it at all i don't disturb it
because
my material must go into my swell and
that's the only way that you're going to
get your carbon
and one content in your soil goes up
then the penetration of water is so much
better for the soil and that's what what
what set me going i think all those
things together you know
yeah
yeah my last question for you this
evening luffy is um you know you've
mentioned monoculture right and um for
anybody listening and thinking wow
there's monocots culture and this crop
rotation and you're farming weeds you're
farming medics you're farming something
else um in between that um all for the
purpose of crop rotation is it fair to
say that the crop rotation practices and
methods become slightly more expensive
as opposed to monoculture because in
monoculture you're controlling expenses
you know year after year you're farming
a single crop
where you can control your expenses
control your input costs whereas crop
rotation each crop requires something
different and it could be different
fertilizers etc so is it true maybe to
uh to think that maybe crop rotation um
will be slightly more expensive than
monoculture or does it not make a
difference at all
no no not at all especially what i'm
doing with my medics you know my clovis
what
i started
um
because because i let the clover develop
the first year the second year it gets
wet the third year when it's clover
again
you know it comes up naturally in the
winter so
it's a once off it's a once or thin
it's quite expensive the seed because
everything comes from australia you know
and so it's quite expensive to start off
with one
sort
you
look after your your phosphate flux on
which which you correct in the in the
year of the wheat you know where you put
your phosphates down and so on and and
and if your ph is fine then it's a once
off thing and it's just there every
second year you have this most amazing
medics you know that you can either
harvest or you can use it for
for your animals to graze on
oats oats to me is is also a very very
nice rotation crop
oats have an amazing root system
which
i think
it's
it's it's conducive to i think magnesium
gets
you know put into the swell
which takes a lot of the
i don't know what the english word is
for all
of
them
which is amazing i i like to do the the
japanese radish
it's it's like a whole radish a huge
and it breaks up your soil you know so
so if you have compact swellings on and
you do the radish it breaks the swell it
is it it's like a it's like a twine you
know that you when you when you plot it
it sort of does the same thing it
loosens up your swell
that's also very nice
and then lupins i i i forgot to tell you
about lupine's lupines also it's got a
nice pen root
so it also penetrates that swell you
know so it loosens the soil and it's
also a
nitrogen fixing you know which your
following yeah you know you can cut back
on your nitrogen
application to your wheat
and uh yeah that's it
and what is it what is amazing is
yeah i wish i would just one more thing
i wish you could see this the sheep on
the medic now
it's amazing how
the man
i think that the
nice crust that they have on their legs
nice thick bone structures and
everything it's just
to me it's the best thing off the sliced
bread
and and really i
i enjoy
because then you know your lifestyle can
definitely benefit from it and your
butchery can also benefit from it and
that i like the fact that at every
process you keep adding certain value
into your production and into your
agribusiness but thank you so much for
your time this evening luffy um it was
great chatting to you and i just want to
say to the audience just uh you know uh
apologies for the um this connection
here and there when you was when when
lawful was speaking you know connection
is not always the greatest at farms but
yeah uh lofty thank you for obviously
bringing that wisdom and various crop
advices in terms of rotation and
different um crops that one could use
obviously um to obviously improve the
the the texture of the soil to prove the
composition of the soil nitrogen etc so
yeah thank you for coming on to the show
this evening
and all the best for your farming as
well
i hope all goes well there and i hope
i hope the rain comes eh
yeah
okay good thank you so much hey okay you
definitely need the rain if you miss
this conversation we're just speaking to
luffy smiths from the friendly farmer
butchery um he's a farmer in the western
cape and we're speaking about
traditional farming methods that one can
adopt for the purpose of crop rotation
and luffy informed us that he's a weed
farmer but also has you know dabbled a
bit to medics in clover and also gave us
some gems about you know planting
radishes to improve your soil and what
it is it does to your soil um from
farming and all these have obviously
created a great impact in his business
because he has now reduced his input
costs um and also we all i think just
trying to win it where climate change is
where climate change is concerned as
farmers so if you miss this conversation
you can catch it on the private property
youtube channel under the farming
podcast playlist if you have any
questions please feel free to drop them
into the comment section and we'll
answer them to the best of our abilities
as well um and yeah keep supporting the
podcast thank you so much for tuning in
this evening
i will catch you on thursday at 8
o'clock take care
[Music]
me me
[Applause]
[Music]
you