good morning everyone are you enjoying
the conference so far yeah
good while I'm excited to be back here
this year I wasn't sure I was going to
be able to make it and so that I'm happy
that I'm here the original intent for
this session was for dan and I to make
an announcement about some new projects
and joint projects a joint project that
we are working on rather than as a
workshop so we're going to kick off with
the description of some very exciting
news and then after that I'll elaborate
and expand on it a little bit and then
we can have an open Q&A and talk about
whatever it is that you like to talk
about as we did last year and I've done
several times before while I'm really
personal what I'm really passionate
about in this space of regenerative
agriculture is having regenerative
agriculture models become the standard
become the status quo the mainstream
globally around the world by 2040 that's
why I found that advancing eco
agriculture of why I'm doing the work
that I'm doing why we started the
podcast and freely readily share
information make it available to
everyone and one of the pieces that has
become abundantly clear is that in order
to understand regenerative agriculture
agronomy well there are so many
different areas of science that we need
to understand growers need to know a
little bit about horticulture they need
to know a little bit about the genetics
or I shouldn't say a little bit but
actually a lot they need to know a lot
about genetics a lot about 40 culture a
lot about biochemistry biophysics plant
pathology entomology there are so many
integrated areas of science that all
come together in understanding
agriculture and plant production and
this is a significant challenge this is
a challenge for growers and it's also a
challenge for us as a company when we
hire someone to join our team our
agronomy team and our consulting team we
have a challenge we have set such an
extremely high bar and a high standard
of leadership and our team is expected
to be extremely knowledgeable about all
these different areas and be able to
implement them in any given situation in
the operate
so when we hire someone to join our team
one of our significant limiting factors
to growth as a company is our ability to
train people and get them to understand
all these different areas we have had
PhDs go through our training course we
have a very intense training course and
they have said that they learned more in
the first 90 days of our training course
and they did in their entire degree it's
a very common feedback that we get so I
believe it's very important to
democratize information and to digitize
information make it widely and readily
available but the learning there is such
a large volume and quantity of
information that is valuable and needs
to be learned and it takes time to
process all of that and to assimilate
all of that one of the questions that
I've been thinking about a lot is how
can we restrict that how can we remove
that barrier to adoption and to grow if
both for our team as a company and also
for growers around the world
so our over the last four years I have
been thinking quite deeply about a
project of digitizing all of our
knowledge and putting together
algorithms that take all this
information and report results and make
agronomic recommendations in exactly the
same way that we do as consultants so
this is obviously a significant
challenge because there are so many
interrelated areas and I'm quite I'm
quite excited over the last few months
we have begun actively working on this
project as a for this moment we're
calling it the AI agronomist our goal is
by the end of next year this time next
year to have a beta launched where
people will be able to upload all of
their soil analysis data plant SAP
analysis irrigation water varieties be
able to put in all their agronomic data
that they have and we will be we have we
will have very specific
requests for information that is needed
to make the information complete and the
then the AI agronomist will give you
specific recommendations for what types
of soil amendments you might need or
what types of microbial inoculants you
might benefit from for what types of
foliar applications you might benefit
from what types of varieties might do
well in your situation so there will be
a tremendous amount of information
flowing into the backend we will be
collecting meteorological data lunar
cycle data soil information so there's
there's a lot of information that is
publicly available there is also a lot
of laboratory work that may need to be
done on some farms to prepare us and get
to this point but what I'm really
excited about is that when we make this
available all of a sudden someone who
becomes interested in regenerative
agriculture and wants to grow food in
this way for the first time they can
they can learn about it in December and
in February they can have some guidance
on what they are going to do on their
farm it really it can supersede the
learning process obviously the learning
still needs to happen the education
still needs to happen but this can help
take all of this knowledge that is
represented by so many scientists in the
field and put it into a usable practical
form that anyone can access and what I'm
really excited about is that that is
then not just available for growers here
in North America where AEA is working a
lot but also for growers in South
America and in Africa and in Europe and
in Asia and around the world so this I
believe will be a foundational piece to
making regenerative agriculture become
the mainstream here's why I'm so excited
about the conversation today many quote
what really drives many growers decision
making process and it's a very human
tendency is rather than planning of how
to prevent problems we react to problems
and so many growers are looking for
solutions to a specific insect pest or a
specific disease so all of the
information exists today to be able to
identify the underlying nutritional
issues that result in a specific insect
pest being in a crop let's say that we
have a potato farmer in Colorado who has
11 fields of potatoes it's possible for
that potato grower to get an alert that
says you need to begin scouting your
potato fields for Colorado potato beetle
because they're expected to emerge from
winter dormancy in the next 24 to 48
hours and of your 11 fields field number
3 and field number 8 are very highly
susceptible to infection field number 3
is susceptible because it has high
levels of nitrates and has high levels
of nitrates because you have low levels
of molybdenum and you need to apply 50
grams of molybdenum to per acre to
remove your susceptibility from a 9 down
to a 2 field number 8 is very
susceptible because it has low levels of
magnesium you need to apply 5 pounds per
acre of magnesium sulfate to move their
susceptibility down to it too that
completely changes the conversation the
conversation is now no longer about you
need to apply this insecticide it's
about this is why you have the problem
and this is what you can do to reverse
it all the information already exists
who put that platform together but
nobody has done it yet and we intend to
do it
[Applause]
thank you so those of you who know
Noah's only been conspiring for one of
the decade together and this has been
one of our fantasy projects for many
years and so to be able to be publicly
announcing the fact that we're working
on this together and you know there's a
real timeframe in which this is going to
occur I think is I'm just really honored
and yeah exhilarated to be here
I think the agreement we make about ten
years ago was that John ago the
for-profit and we coordinated magazines
so that's pretty much what's been
happening and we give each other a hard
time about various things at various
points in time but yeah to to build this
framework out which we've you know
established to a large degree with the
open team with the you know all the data
partners were working on with the real
food campaign collaborative framework
with companies and universities and
organizations and farmers open source to
look at the in field dynamics and then
to be able to build the hardware that
can do the sensing I think that's the
one piece John didn't talk about was the
ability to do in field assessment with
spectrometer anybody who's been working
with him do the plant set of analysis
and harvesting the leaves and sending
them off to Europe and spending hundreds
of dollars a week and getting reports
back two weeks later I think it's one of
been one of John's really systemic
frustrations over the past couple of
years is how can we get this real-time
in field data back sooner and you know
the answer is if we can assess what's
going on in the plant in real time with
something like a spectrometer then
we have the ability to actually take
that you know whatever that investment
is that you'd be spending on sampling
leaves and sending them to the to
Hollander Netherlands to be able to
basically take two weeks of investment
in in plants leaf samples and have a
piece of hardware that you can use
forever thereafter so it is a big
complicated hairy audacious project and
we don't working on it for a while and
it's gonna require resources but you
have to be able to formally announce
this and really move forward actively
and pulling an office is very
exhilarating so this is John stage I
just wanted to be here or he asked me to
be here to confirm it as well so thank
you all for being here and I'm sure
you're gonna have a wonderful next hour
[Applause]
so I think one of the important pieces
that Dan and I have agreed to
collaborate on and our collective
enterprises with advancing eco
agriculture in the bio nutrient Food
Association one of the strengths that we
have is that we have a lot of historical
data on a large scale forum right at
this moment in time we have I don't know
the exact count but we have several
hundred thousand data points closer to a
million than to the bottom end of the
scale on that represent 48 different
crops across the country 48 crops so
those are 48 crops that we have a
significant amount of data on and what
we have learned in from experience is
that many growers may have the best of
intentions but they often lack the
bandwidth and the resources to be able
to collect samples in a timely manner
during the growing season and so in our
work at AEA in any area where we have a
local concentration of growers we're
working with large number growers we
actually have our team our staff is out
in the field collecting all the data
they're doing all the sample collection
and so our collaboration over the course
as the spectrometer is developed we will
be working closely with the spectrometer
to develop all the data libraries and to
match what is happening of what the what
the spectrometer readouts are with
historical sap analysis and based on
simply on the volume of data that we go
through in a single growing season or in
as little as a few months we expect to
be able to have a very strong data
library to be able to use the
spectrometer in the field to make
management decisions very rapidly very
quickly and dan is correct we have been
dreaming about this for a decade
so in fact I I first I first wrote that
I wrote the first set of algorithms in
the first outline for what we're now
calling the AI agronomist in 2014 and I
got done with this spreadsheet that was
an absolute monstrosity and when I got
done my last sentence at the bottom said
we have everything that we need to make
this work in real time except we don't
have a sensor that can analyze
nutritional profiles in the field so
that's what we've been waiting for and
certainly we can do it and we will be
doing a lot of this with laboratory
analysis even to to help develop the
spectrometer but the eventual
expectation is that if the spectrometer
does well we believe it's going to be
capable of doing we will have an infield
tool imagine having an infield tool that
could do a soil analysis that could do
an irrigation water analysis that could
do a leaf SAP analysis you can do all of
those things and more so that's that's
the dream and the aspiration that we're
working toward it's all it's all good
all right so Dan asked me to also speak
a little bit about the some of the
information that is going into the
agronomist and some of the pieces that
are behind it and it's really big and
it's almost more than I can describe
very quickly and easily but there are a
few pieces that I will describe that I
might be unexpected I'll focus on some
of the unexpected pieces of the
unanticipated pieces one of those is we
were still reviewing data to make all
the correlations and connections but it
seems that there is a connection between
overall plant health and performance and
cosmic radiation as measured on the KP
index and the Phi angle so you can there
are a number of resources one that I
enjoy out paying attention to is a
website called space with their news and
essentially it gives us when we look at
sunspot activity and solar activity
sunspot activity correlates to well
first of all the the photons coming from
the Sun can have either a negative or a
positive charge they're not all the same
and the charges that reach the Earth's
surface depend on a number of different
factors including the radiation
shielding magnetic shields the event
Allen belts etc and there is a
counterpoint between silver radiation
and cosmic radiation and what that means
is that when we have periods of stronger
solar radiation we have that actually
strengthens the magnetic field protect
the envelope protecting the earth and
that effectively shields cosmic
radiation coming in or you can have the
opposite effect where you have very weak
solar radiation and you have much
stronger cosmic radiation coming in why
is this important why should it matter
well there's two reasons one is that
solar the
rgeous on the solar radiation actually
influence plant health very strong that
we've started observing a few years ago
once as we really dialed in to plant
health more and more we started
observing that there could be periods of
a few days or in some cases even a few
weeks where solar radiation seemed to
actually impact plants negatively rather
than positive positively and of course
that's the opposite of what you would
expect to be happening that's when we
first started looking at the qualities
of solar radiation and how it varies and
then of course for those of us thinking
about biodynamic agriculture and when we
plant seeds in alignment with various
solar cycles and lunar cycles as as
according to the various constellations
all of a sudden it because we realize
that the influence of cosmic radiation
is also mediated by solar radiation so
when you have very weak solar radiation
which allows a lot of cosmic radiation
to come through which is actually has
happened a lot this last year then the
influences of when you plant a seed in
correlation to different constant the
presence of different being in the
presence of different constellations has
a much bigger impact and this is another
topic that is a bit out in left field
for some people but I think it's a very
important one what we have observed is
that the timing at which you plant seeds
according to in association with a given
constellation has less of an impact in
fact I can say that it has almost no
impact on very challenged soils soils
that have very low organic matter cells
that have very little microbial activity
you don't see much of a difference if
you separate planting by a few dates by
a few days but when you have high
organic matter soils and you have really
active microbial activity that
difference becomes can become extremely
pronounced so the healthier your farms
are the healthier soils are the bigger
of a difference you can make by
selecting the dates of what you plant
seeds so that was some far out of left
field information what else is important
obviously we're including all of the
information on soil analysis plant beef
analysis we expect it will take some
time we don't yet have enough data it
will take some time for us to develop
the data on understanding which
varieties correlate to given nutritional
profiles and given environments but I
expect there we will without let me back
up just a moment when we first started
using plant sap analysis in 2011 plant
sap analysis really revolutionized our
understanding of the interaction of
minerals inside plants and how to best
supply those minerals with implants
because for the first time we had an
accurate and an accurate window into
what was actually happening what was
actually going on we no longer had to
guess
and as a result of plant SAP analysis
displacing tissue analysis on almost all
the operations all the operations that
we work with we there were some things
that we expected to find and we learned
a lot more that we didn't expect that we
didn't know that we had no idea what's
coming I expect the same will happen
once we begin collecting all this
initial information looking at all the
correlations and on a digital platform
we will be able to make correlations
between specific nutritional profiles
specific varieties that we can't
anticipate and don't expect right now
what we have observed already with the
plant SAP analysis is that the genetics
the given variety of a crop has a
tremendous influence on absorption of
nutrients from the soil we know that we
can have two different varieties dan
and with his work here at the BFA has
described how you can have the same
variety of carrots and have radically
different nutritional profiles from
different soils but the other additional
element is that if you then take those
that one variety and you put it onto the
optimal soil the soil where it really
thrives the best you can plant another
variety right beside it that might now
have three times a higher nutritional
profile in the original variety so there
are also varietal differences and then
to add another layer the nutritional the
these various varieties will perform
differently on different soils so on one
soil or in one environment where the
original variety tested might not do
well it might not have a good
nutritional profile there is another
variety that might have a 5x higher
nutritional profile on that soil so
there are both varietal differences in
soil differences that we expect to be
able to correlate once we have more of
the information or the data to be able
to do that so I'd like to open it for
questions do you have any questions on
what we're working on and or suggestions
on what you would like to see when are
we releasing the AEA planting calendar
don't know I haven't thought about that
we actually did release a couple years
ago the AEA foliar spraying calendar and
that one is still in existence and
floating around somewhere it's been a
while since I spoke about that but we
observed a very distinct 28-day cycle
with plant absorption of nutrients the
original observation occurred with the
Dutch team and the Netherlands that
developed sap analysis they observed
when they were working with hydroponic
growers they would measure not only the
the SAP analysis but also the quantity
of nutrients that came through their
hydroponic system so how many nutrients
were left in the water at the end of
each week and they discovered a very
distinct cycle where one week out of the
four and I can't remember which which is
which right now I'd have to reference
the calendar but out of the total
four-week cycle one week out of the four
plants absorbs 75% of all the nutrients
in the water two weeks out of 450
percent and the one week out of four
which was two weeks out of phase with
the seventy-five percent they only did
25 percent so radically different
absorption of nutrients from the soil
based on the lunar cycle so we've
actually been able to correspond to that
and try to better time when we put on
foliar applications and when we put on
irrigation applications for some crops
for growing high-value food and
vegetable crops it really doesn't matter
because we're going to be doing it
constantly all the time but for crops
where we're only putting on three to
five applications per season timing
those applications to match up with the
lunar cycles gives us a tremendous crop
response and a much greater efficiency
for the products that we're actually
applying so and again this what I get
excited about is that I can be here
having this conversation with you
talking about lunar cycles and we have
the PDF published somewhere on the
advancing iko iko cultural website but
now we will be able to take that
information and put it into a
recommendations engine to say you need
to put on your soil amendment
applications you need to put on your
biological applications this week don't
put them on in two weeks from now put
them on this week and you'll get a much
bigger soil health response and much
bigger crop response all of a sudden
that information that can be shared
verbally and trained and needs to be
also becomes immediately executable and
implementable by everyone around the
world that's what I'm excited about yeah
yes
reduction treaty on time this is to only
have been academic so all this data are
assembling analyzed against a great
exciting there's a dark I incident
after the first is that of a social
scientist which is that this is still
operating very much limited mention
paradigm of acupuncture proficiencies
the remedy that would power inputs we're
for this and the measurements you have a
second reality essential chemical use
biology as a remedy
you don't analyze violence or biology as
a cause for some of these things that's
very active do i I can see that I see
someone is reinforcing business model or
farmers are not investigators
diagnosticians analysts problem solvers
and the worth becomes our automatons
there was a really comprehensive
recommendation you as apartments do what
they're told
that's building into this this is
fundamentally the biological yeah yes so
thank you for that comment I have you've
raised a couple of different points so
to the first of influencing and managing
biology rather than purely taking a
chemistry approach the I I've framed
spoken about primary to the chemistry
piece because of the implications of
course the spectrometer that Dan is
developing however the the information
that we're collecting we are also
measuring a number of different soil
parameters including infiltration rates
and we're you're correct on those of
microbial assays those are a challenge
because we need a microbial assay that
is both quantitative and qualitative at
the same time it's we it's not enough to
just identify the presence of an
organism we also need to know the
quantity of a given organism present and
as of yet there isn't technology capable
of doing that but there there is
qualitative information on when we look
at soul aggregation we can do some
analog metrics and we are using those
analog metrics and we are also making
recommendations for compost applications
for what types of cover crops for use
for what type of tillage to use or not
to use and our entire the way we're
framing the entire conversation in the
engine that we're developing is to shift
the thinking to in two ways one is to
think about the cause of the problem
rather than just the symptom and the
second is to think about the or to have
the recommendations emphasize the
biological solution not the chemistry
solution so I failed to mention that
that is
important then to your point on the
sociological implications every time a
recommendation is made this will take
some time to develop of course because
there's so many explanations but every
time a recommendation is made we want
anyone to be able to challenge that why
is this recommendation being made and
immediately for us to provide a
reference and a link that they can look
and say okay this is why we made the
recommendation this way to give people
the capacity to see that learn that and
also to disagree with it and give us
feedback and then to your extreme
example of our idea of farmers becoming
automatons is what many farmers do today
so very different from that yeah but I
think this you raise an important
question it's certainly something that
we have thought about that we need to
think more about the the desire is to
completely change the relationship with
the crop that they're growing because I
very strongly believe that one of the
significant failures that we have in our
agriculture today is that our
agriculture has no soul it has no heart
there is no longer a heart connection
with the plants that we're producing
it's become very mechanistic very
intellectual and that in order for us we
know that if we want to produce food
that has the capacity to produce I'll
use the words spiritual coherence food
needs the plants need to be grown with
love they need to grow be growing with
heart they respond to that and there's a
lot of information behind this again
this might be coming really out of left
field for some people if you want to dig
more deeply into this I very highly
recommend stephen hara Buner series of
three books the first is titled the lost
language of plants the second is the
secret teachings of plants and the third
is plant intelligence yes the first book
is the lost language of plants the
second is the secret teachings of plants
and the third is plant intelligence
Steven Buner is perhaps my favorite
author for his writing style I purchased
every book that he ever wrote even the
ones not related to agriculture because
so much enjoyed reading his writing but
those three books are perhaps my three
personal favorites they are absolutely
incredible and I'll just give you one
hint
I've gifted these books to many
different people and many people
particularly the lost language of plants
when they start reading it they can't
put it down there I have had people read
for 26 hours straight to finish the book
more than one person more than a handful
and to give you just a glimpse of some
of the pieces that Steven speaks about I
can't possibly begin to do justice to
all the topics that he covers he
describes the science of plant human
communication but he also and he
described the science of plant to human
heart communication it's not just an
intelligent process or an intellectual
process and in the in the last of the
three books plant intelligence he
describes plant neural networks and this
one I read a lot I'm not often surprised
I was surprised and delighted by the
book of plant intelligence he describes
how we historically have thought of
human intelligence in the context of the
brain the brain being a specific organ
with a number of neurons large number of
neurons and as our thinking has evolved
we realized that it's not just a brain
but there's actually a tremendous number
of neurons in our digestive system in
our gut there's a lot of neurons around
our heart and that we need to think of
intelligence not in terms of brain
capacity intellectual capacity but in
terms of neural networks and so when we
begin thinking about neural networks
this is from from our neural network in
our body that's why we can actually have
a conversation about heart cognition
recognizing what's happening with our
hearts and also why we many times may
use the words I have a gut feeling about
something because we do have a gut
feeling about something
what really rocked me was the
realization that plants have the exact
same neural networks as we do and not
when I say the exact same neural
networks not only the their neural
network is all the growing root tips all
the growing root tips are all connected
and the the neurotransmitters that
plants use are have many similarities
the neurotransmitters that humans use as
well in fact the single dominant
neurotransmitter in both plants and
humans is serotonin plant
neurotransmission is based on serotonin
and serotonin derived compounds and
molecules so when we start thinking
about plant intelligence many annual
species have smaller root systems and
they don't have a neural network that is
perhaps as large as ours but when you
start talking about perennial species
particularly you have a large mature
tree the neural network of a tree is
significantly larger than the neural
network of most people so now which who
really carries the most wisdom
so I would really encourage everyone to
dive into that a bit more deeply yes
there is the reality is what what has
brought me to this project and the
reason I started hosting the
regenerative agriculture podcast was
learning that there is so much valuable
information out there as as Elaine's
work and I could give a long list of
scientists work who have done incredible
research that is not generally applied
in production agriculture and an example
of this is occasionally I've had the
desire for some time to put together
resource that on a collection of all the
peer-reviewed published papers that
correlate the presence of a specific
insect or disease in a crop particularly
insects with a given nutritional profile
and I started this project a few weeks
ago and when I started I thought oh
there's probably a couple hundred papers
out there and on two weeks in and the
project is going to have to be some at
some point I'm gonna have to define
boundaries and limits because it just
keeps spreading and spreading and
there's thousands of papers not hundreds
my point being simply that there is a
tremendous amount of information that
isn't widely practiced and the intent
for the podcast was to be able to make
that easily accessible to growers and
producers and then the next step of
course is how do we clearly and simply
describe in which situations they can
apply it and how they can apply it so I
don't know did I give a reasonable
answer to your comment was my best shot
yes good question that I haven't thought
about
so the question what the question was
AEA has expressed the has the expressed
intent of developing nutritional and
microbial products that are so effective
that they eventually displace the needs
to be used
that the soil health and plant helped it
also such a point that you don't need to
use the products anymore and we have
quite a number of farms who have reached
that goal now and that's personally
quite exciting to me at least so the
question the question was at what point
does the AI agronomist become redundant
and no longer necessary and so I would
say there's there are two points that
come to mind and I have not thought
about that question that's a really
great question and I am going to spend a
lot of time thinking about it but I
would say part one is that when you
again when the overall ecosystem reached
such a general reaches a state of such
vibrant health that it is
self-sustaining then you don't need to
be constantly doing the monitoring and
measuring and the second thought that
comes to mind is I see this also I
desire it to be a tool for education
about specific problems because so many
times when I teach webinars and I teach
at conferences questions and I teach a
lot about general principles and
concepts and questions are often very
specific what do do I do about X and I
want the agronomist
to be completely enough that a grower
can able be able to ask the question
what do I do about X and find the answer
for almost any pest so then as as that
learning process evolves for the grower
and he understands and learns why we
have this challenge and why we have that
challenge of what we can do about them
it has farming management shifts on that
educational pathway the reality is that
a shift to a regenerative agriculture
doesn't really happen in the field it
happens in here and in here and so as
that shift happens then the reality is
as if when we are successful in in
growers in developing that close
connection to their crops and to their
environment have such a vibrant state of
health and at that point I would say the
tool becomes redundant there's no longer
as a need for that because they're in
tune with what's happening on what's
going
that's kind of my off-the-cuff answer
without having thought about it yes have
you taken into consideration climate
change events the answer is yes the
short answer is yes the long answer is a
really long answer well there are a few
pieces one is that a truly regenerative
agriculture first is inherently much
more climate resilient healthy plants
what we've observed is that the water
consumption or the water requirements by
really healthy plants drops by at least
50%
in some cases more that's a huge water
savings that I think has not yet been
recognized I haven't heard anyone else
talk about that at all and then of
course when you have really healthy
soils the soils resilience the capacity
to store and hold water also increases
tremendously and the combination of
those two effects and the changes that
are happening within plant biochemistry
also greatly increase the plants
resistance to high and low temperatures
so you can have environments that are a
lot warmer without having the same
degree of stress impact and environment
that are locked colder how much colder
we've been able to lower the one data
point that we have at this point that
we've quantified is that we're able to
reduce a plant's freezing temperature by
about six degrees Fahrenheit very
consistently so wherever a given variety
or species might be we can drop that
about six degrees Fahrenheit with
nutrition on the temperature increased
side we don't yet have enough experience
to know how much we know that we can
significantly now all those pieces that
I mentioned are all outcomes those are
all results of a regenerative
agriculture system the question to think
about or that you raised is what are the
implications of a changing climate in
making recommendations
to a degree I mean the reality is that
we will be directly measuring soil
respiration for example soil microbial
activity will be directly measuring the
release of carbon dioxide from the soil
profile will be directly measuring
plants respiration and photosynthesis
cal almost micro indicators of what's
happening at the macro level with within
climate change
yeah those are my thoughts my short
answer I don't know if that answers your
question adequately yes Julie why do
plants only need it half as much water
there's two major pieces the first is
that when plants absorb nutrition in the
form of simple ions particularly nitrate
in a conversation I think I saw a Lydia
oliviers here and will be speaking again
this afternoon speaking yesterday he
pointed out how when plants absorb just
nitrate instead of amino acid nitrogen
that by itself can increase their water
requirement by 50 percent in addition to
that when do I have that correct Olivia
yes water use efficiency so the second
aspect is the quantity of water required
for respiration so you have essentially
fundation Li to metabolic processes
going on with implants that consume
water one of them is photosynthesis the
second is respiration respiration occurs
amongst other reasons primarily largely
for cooling and when you have a healthy
plant that has a glossy waxy leaf
surface high lipid content high fat
content it conducts heat much better and
reflects heat much better the bottom
line is that it cools the plants much
more efficiently and there's much less
water required for plant cooling so when
you have high temperatures when you have
when you're growing plants and really
hot conditions for many of our food
crops that's the
see three photosynthetic pathway plants
that's above 86 degrees Fahrenheit when
you go above 86 degrees Fahrenheit the
quantity of water required to cool a
healthy plant versus an unhealthy plant
is also significantly less I don't know
how much less but I know it's a big
number we got a question over here yes
yes yes it is possible and it is
possible simply by changing the soils
paramagnetism so when you have very high
paramagnetism in the soil profile that
fixes the problem we had a question yes
oh my goodness
the rabbit hole just gets deeper and
deeper so the question the question was
thinking about solar radiation and that
we are coming into a solar minimum both
a solar minimum on the short solar cycle
and a grand solar minimum at the same
time what are the implications for
having cooler summers and cooler growing
conditions yes so what are the
implications for the next few years and
at what point do we shift back out of
that cycle so first of all this is not
my area of expertise I have been
learning a lot about this in the last
couple of years or trying to it's my
understanding that right now we are so
we have a what is it a 10 or 11 year
solar cycle think of Tinian 11-year
solar cycle peak to trough and we are
right now approaching the bottom of the
trough so the expectation is in the next
2 to 3 years we are likely to have
cooler summers and so how do we manage
that I think the implications for us is
that we should expect that we will
probably have harder winters we'll
probably have a harder winter this
winter for the next couple of years and
we should expect a tendency towards
having later frost in the spring and
earlier Frost in the fall by a week or
two I don't expect there to be any
significant outliers more than what
we've already been observing for the
last 2 10 years then the longer solar
cycle the the grant what is referred to
as the grand solar cycle we are also
approaching the bottom of the trough are
starting to go on the downhill slope
we've been on the uphill slope of the
ground solar cycle for the last 20 to 30
years and now we're we've crossed that
threshold we're starting to go back down
so I think there's a longer cycle of
cooling as well the reality is that we
have to look at what is it that we can
manage that can make a difference and
what we can manage that makes a
difference is we can manage soil health
and organic matter at capacity to hold
water and we can measure plant health
and resilience to temperature extremes
when we do those two things by managing
plant nutrition by managing soil health
we have created a lot of resilience and
a lot of
or into the system that's what we can
manage and that's what we need to do
particularly for the next few years that
answer your question move to Georgia
[Laughter]
look at what happened in North Dakota
and Montana this year farmers had crops
buried in snow on a significant scale so
we'll probably see more of that
happening in northern climates yeah yes
so the question was in the southern
climate on a farm in Virginia should I
begin planting crops that might do
better in a more northern climate or not
more colder climate here's what you
should expect you should expect more
extreme climate variability there will
be hotter longer there were longer more
intense periods of hot weather and
longer more intense periods of cold
weather we will see more extremes so and
we will see both of those within the
same season sometimes within weeks of
each other that's the climate that we as
the climate that exists now and that's
why developing climate resilience
becomes so important yes
a nose and the principal's nachos weapon
Dacians you see that yes
exactly that's what I'm talking about
get all it could you guys hear that yeah
absolutely yes so I know there's a few
more questions out there but we've been
circling around this conversation around
the importance of biology which is
foundational fundamental I talked about
it quite a bit last year for those of
you that were present then I hosted one
of my most fascinating podcast
interviews yet a few days ago it's being
post the beginning of December I was dr.
James white from Rutgers University he's
published a number of white papers but I
want to give you just just the synopsis
of his work so he has been he didn't
originate the term but he's been popular
xoring that popularizing the term of
rise of Ag rise of Ag simply means root
feeding or root eating and he has
identified for those of you who've
listened to me on the podcast on
webinars and in live presentations you
know that I'm very passionate about the
idea that plants can absorb microbial
metabolites that they are not dependent
on absorbing simple ions from the soil
solution and that if we were to change
plant nutrition but to the one when
plants begin absorbing the majority of
their nutrition as microbial metabolites
plant health and the system's resilience
everything begins changing everything
changes very quickly well there's been
actually a surprising amount of science
around plant absorption of microbial
metabolites over the course of the last
60 to 70 year
but it hasn't certainly hasn't caught
mainstream attention and I'm really
hopeful that James work does but the
foundational idea has been that you have
a growing root tip and this growing root
tip the cells here at the end are this
tip is actually surprisingly porous and
you have bacteria and algae and fungi
and all these organisms in the soil
profile that are actually absorbed into
the root they penetrate into the root to
go inside the root and they begin living
completely inside the plant they have a
symbiotic relationship here and there
this is referred to when plants live
excuse me when biology lives inside a
plant that referred to as being
endophytes
so you may have heard of endo fright
free fresque you for example ran to
fight free plants so particularly he's
he's observed and documented fungi and
bacteria and algae to move into plants
then once they're inside the plant root
they begin moving back through the root
system and in this pathway the root
system are the root cells release
superoxide and they oxidize all the cell
membranes so the cell membranes are
oxidized and now all of the organelles
and and all of the nutrients contained
inside the cell are available for the
plant to absorb and plants actually
absorb these macromolecules through a
process known as endocytosis
so endocytosis has been known in animals
and in human cells for a long time and
it's been postulated in in plant cells
since the 60s and 70s but the idea of
endocytosis is essentially that you have
a cell which and then when you have the
exposure of a macro molecule on its side
which theoretically should be impossible
to absorb yeah I say theoretically
discount that is not possible for a salt
to absorb based on the presently
accepted science of cell physiology and
cross membrane
transfer with pumps and so forth what
actually happens is that the cell adapts
its membrane into a balloon form this
begins moving in this direction and
ultimately it becomes ompletely
completely encapsulated and this entire
organelle or this entire can be a chunk
of RNA or DNA or peptides or enzymes or
whatever these macromolecules are
absorbed into the plant cells so and on
this pathway through the growing through
the root system or through the root tip
or right behind immediately behind the
root tip this process of endocytosis is
happening but not all the biology is
killed in this process some of it
survives the process of having its cell
membrane stripped and then when it's at
some point it moves out to the outer
part of the root and it triggers the
formation of root hair and they actually
move out through root hair and they
circulate for a while here at the tip
and then they move out through the root
hair tip into the soil profile and then
when they're in the soil profile the
plant root actually feeds them it begins
exiting in that particular location it
begins exiting a lot of carbohydrates
and other Connells it actually provides
all the nutrients that the bacteria or
fungi or algae need to reform their cell
membranes because these are now
essentially naked cells without a cell
membrane and it gives them everything
they need to reform their cell membranes
and essentially farms if it's plants
farm microbes the exact same way that we
farm livestock they are feeding the
microbes here and then this population
obviously propagates through the soil
along the root system goes back down to
the root and now the plants or following
root tips that are coming along behind
this primary root tip access these
nutrients from this biology rise of Ag
yes
there's it was a dynamite interview I'm
going to be posting a number of his peer
reviewed pipe papers which are really
really good but in as if this and by the
way this was an incredible interview
these were the last 15 minutes the first
45 minutes were probably even better
than this or as good and he said one
thing that really gave me a lot to think
about so I've also said many times based
on conversations that I've had with Don
Huber and other plant pathologists that
it is possible when we change so when we
have a soil that has really active
microbial populations and they're the
correct characteristics the right
biology of present we can develop what
is called a disease suppressive soil and
it's been my understanding in the past
that when we have a disease suppressive
soil it will take it will change the
expression of all of these potential
pathogens such as verticillium and for
Syria and so forth to be sacrificed
decomposers of nonliving plant residue
so they are still present but they're
having a beneficial impact as a
saprophyte but James said that's not
incorrect but it's incomplete
when you have let's say you have a
strand of the cerium out here this is
obviously I'm a great artist when you
have path potential when you have
organisms that are potential pathogens
in the soil profile these endophytes
that have this close symbiotic
relationship with the plant will
actually colonize the Fuss area or the
verticillium or any potential pathogen
and when they colonize it they weaken it
they extract some of the sugars out of
it some of the food sources that it has
but they're an important pieces that
they change its behavior and it's no
longer a pathogen it actually changes
and it now develops into an end of fight
and it develops a symbiotic relationship
with the plant instead of being a
pathogen isn't that amazing
[Applause]
so we had we had a quite a fascinating
conversation there is one other piece
that I think is necessary pointing out
so the end of fights that he described
all of these organisms that had this
endo FIDIC relationship with the plant a
symbiotic relationship with the plant
come from two places there is
significant overlap between the
microbial population that should be
present in a healthy soil and the
microbial population on the seed coat
and I asked the question about what
happens when we treat seeds with
fungicides what happens when we treat
vegetable seeds with hot hot water to
remove bacteria and he said that we
definitely do damage the microbial
population on the seed which has a
really predisposes that plant to
pathogenic invasion in the early stages
of life but and then I specifically
asked the question about corn and he
pointed out that many of our modern corn
varieties and I asked about corn but
realizing now that this is true not just
of corn but actually for a number of
different plants he said that when
plants are propagated at some point
during the breeding processes when they
are propagated by cell culture they lose
all of their endophytes
on the seed itself so now when you begin
so what is what he's observed is that
many of our modern corn varieties no
longer carry their protective organisms
on the seed they are now very disease
susceptible so this is something that's
true for corn but I would say the
logical to extrapolate that that is
likely to be true for any seed or any
plant which has been propagated by cell
culture yes so the question was do I
know if the end of fights are entering
the meristematic area when the cells are
different still differentiating I
remember James talking about that in
some of his papers but I don't remember
what he said well what we do know
from dr. May Wong hos work she described
how we have significant transfer of
genetic material between the soil
biology and plants and I suspect this is
one pathway that we haven't been aware
of in the past for significant transfer
of genetic material I mean we know that
it's been well documented when we have a
genetically modified plant we end up
with genetically modified DNA in the
soil microbial profile in a matter of a
few days or weeks yeah so that that
actually that actually would it would be
when we look at all of the various
mechanisms and means for plant signaling
for plants signaling the slow microbial
population what nutritional requirements
that it has what nutrients that it wants
the soil microbes to release this is
probably another signaling mechanism
other signaling pathway in addition to
all the biochemical signals that we have
identified and defined so far yeah I get
pretty excited about this
nice there's a bit of a puzzle which
this helps to explain
can you speak up just a little bit
important seeds with facility versus
uncoated seeds germinated faster Wow
yeah you know what James work and not
just James work but other researchers
also similar to what you described what
they tell me about soil biology there
are no bad guys we created the bad guys
by our mismanagement of the ecosystem
that's it or by the system ecosystem
being mismanaged in some manner yes so
I'm I'm trying to I want to make sure I
understand your question correctly are
you asking how do we transfer this
information how can you transfer this
information to other growers or how can
you transfer this information to
consumers yes an important question and
one that I don't have an easy answer for
so to the point that consumers can
become drawers and I believe they should
I believe everybody should have a closer
connection with their food I believe we
need to bring back the Victory Gardens
actually we would have victory over a
lot of diseases and degenerative
illnesses and mental challenges and more
wouldn't we if that were to happen I'm
reminded of a quote that Arden Anderson
repeated over and over again he said
when the student is ready the teacher
will appear and I my personal experience
has been that I have found it to be
generally unproductive to try to
persuade someone who has no desire to
learn and the good news is that today
there are so many people who do desire
to learn that there is a tremendous
desire for knowledge and information
which is why I've tried to share as much
online as I have
and I really believe that it is very
valuable for any of us - for all of us
to become teachers because when we
become teachers is when we really begin
to learn the most rapidly so those are
my comments and response to your
question didn't really answer your
question yes can you speak up just a
little bit
[Music]
where I went to school involved through
that
problems I was using or the exacerbation
of the issues hi
this goes back a while and in my file
recently
but I'm also a student
society takes the information that they
exchange
No
I
yes yes
we have the trickle-down
[Music]
[Applause]
[Laughter]
society the biggest challenge I think is
not only people having an emotional
relationship to the earth but developing
a real heart as well as my relationship
to each other yeah I to speak to that a
bit well there's a few comments that
come to mind but actually I see I come
from a very different background growing
up in an Amish community and working
primarily outside the Amish community
I've come to appreciate many of the
values that that community holds
particularly the value the the strong
family and community and social
structure and I think one of the
significant strengths is that young
children growing up have a sense of
place of who they are in a social fabric
but I also want to speak to your comment
about the best available technology yes
go ahead
education which is experience
the way it trickles down to Farmington
learned from experience you learn from
doing and the brain is hardwired you
learn something too by experiencing it
cannot forget it and you also have
to somebody else it's a safe
so American see internet world
expression within everyone here is going
to be a teacher yes
yes good comment thank you at speaking
to regenerative agriculture and in this
this different cognition about
agriculture ecosystems becoming the best
available technology there has been a
significant shift in our work at AEA
with the new people who contact us for
the first time up until four or five
years ago generally and I'm speaking
specifically now about large scale
mainstream growers who have hundreds or
often thousands of acres of fruit and
vegetable crops often the conversation
would be something like historically the
conversation would be something along
the lines of I've heard about the work
you're doing it seems really interesting
and I'd like to try it on a few of my
acres I'd like to try it out and just
see what's happening on what's going on
today we have people calling us and they
say I've listened to all of your
podcasts I've listened to all of your
webinars and I want to do it on 800
acres that has happened a number of
times right yes
[Music]
unfortunately there wasn't a pinch
that's junk
[Music]
Barry and Karina
I mean he's not a whole lot today
in fact Korean actress Margaret was like
about formulas
mafia
but what's interesting is early on the
recommendation was like I needed
channels
plants were sufficient channels so
actually this is actually a
contradiction for
psycho theory would be more putting on
nitrogen and actually later in the
process testing later I was recommending
nitrogen and whereas the new treatment
cycle theory would have been saying well
no at that point you should be putting
on
I'm wondering if you know about the
second theory
as you can tell I love learning and I
read a lot
I'm not intimately familiar with corian
natural farming I have heard a bit about
it the question that I would love to ask
you is did you try both of them great so
we learned something oh my goodness yep
in one instance what I did I was still
using her County
a shell
awesome we learn something again no I
think I can just say simply that our
products and our approach to plant
nutrition continue to evolve every year
and they're completely different now
from what they were ten years ago
because we continue to learn things just
as the example that you that you
described and from my perspective there
is just the ultimate report card
the ultimate report card is plant health
when you have a healthy plant that is
nutritious has higher nutritional levels
that is resistant to diseases and
insects then something is working and if
you don't whatever you're doing is not
working and I am open to any and all
pathways that get us to that point
that's to me that's the bottom line
nutritional products microbial products
compost teas etc those are all a tool to
get to that pathway yes we do we think
very much about plant reproductive
cycles vegetative cycles etc it's
everything is based on that really yes
[Music]
we will never be successful at least
like I mean that can't be done by people
on it
it cannot actually I think that's I
think that's an important question to
ask so we can read the first reference
to foods implications for spiritual
knowledge coming from Rudolf Steiner
Rudolf Steiner in the period when he was
teaching described how food produced at
that time did not have enough I'm
looking for the right word didn't have
enough spiritual grounding didn't have
enough spiritual sustenance to allow
people to develop their spiritual
connection with plants and I I dislike
the word spiritual because it today
carries too many other connotations but
to develop that heart cognition with
plants so he pointed that out decades
ago and speaking from personal
experience yes I am very stringent about
the quality of the food that I eat and I
actually noticed my mental acuity and
mental clarity is the first thing that
goes when my diet starts dropping off
and where I have the most significant
challenges when I travel to work with
farmers in the Midwest the Midwest is a
good food desert and so to first of all
when I am at home and when I have good
control over over the food that I eat I
definitely try to make good sure that I
have a very good diet high levels of
healthy fats and in spite of all that
I'm not able to grow all of my own food
although I do and my family and I do a
significant amount
and I supplement intensely I supplement
all the time because I don't have
confidence in the food supply to be able
to give my body everything that it
requires for optimal performance similar
to a plant I don't care about average
performance I've experienced average
performance in my life and I don't want
to be back there again
[Music]
they're small but all together yes so
the brief answer just kind of has a
general broad umbrella is that it is
possible to either sequester or I'll
just use the word detoxify it is
possible to detoxify every toxic element
that we know of from an elemental
perspective speaking about cadmium and
arsenic and lead at etc etc it's
possible to remove all of those from the
soil profile or sequester them in a form
that they are not absorbed by the plants
that we're growing there's a lot of
research in the literature about how
this can happen with humic substances
and also how specific plants and this
this is where when you start when you
are you have a specific situation with
specific known toxins then you can begin
identifying plants that are known to
sequester those toxins and either remove
them from the soil or transmute them to
a form that they no longer show up
and by the way hemp is one of the plants
that does a lot of different things
extraordinarily well when it comes to
removing toxins from the soil profile it
actually absorbs them into the plant in
many cases so it's really interesting
cannabis producers are discovering
significant challenges because when the
the cannabis plant and hemp in general
is so extraordinarily good at picking up
toxins that when you have cadmium or
arsenic in the soil profile and part per
billion or part per trillion
concentrations they will pick it up and
accumulate it in a high concentration
within the plant itself you composted
and put it somewhere else or actually
maybe you create biochar out of it I
mean I don't know the answers to those
questions but at least we're able to
remove it from a broad area and perhaps
concentrate it more so the answers are
out there
we'll be able to validate all this yeah
and the other the other aspect of course
in addition to the elemental toxins are
the hydrocarbons and again more there's
actually quite a bit of research and
both laboratory and field validation
that were in the process of right now
but I think a year ago I spoke about a
new product that we're developing we
released it in Pennsylvania use it in
Pennsylvania this last growing season
it's if all goes well with a regulatory
process it'll be released for use by
next spring across the entire country
and laboratory evidence suggests that we
can eliminate all toxins all herbicides
all hydrocarbons from the soil profile
in when the biology is sustained and has
enough carbohydrates enough of a food
source it can happen in a matter of
weeks and that is pretty exhilarating
does not include plastics as in the
still solid plastic form unfortunately
you know one of my mentors Bruce tiny Oh
actually develops a microbe in the lab
or shouldn't say devotee found it in the
wild and cultured it in the lab that
consumed PVC and he had a flask in his
lab that was consuming four pounds of
PVC per 24 hour period and he eventually
dumped it and tossed it back into the
environment because he couldn't find an
off switch he couldn't find a way to get
them to slow down and can you imagine
well first there's there's a part of me
that would love to release something
like that into the oceans and then I
also imagine what would be possible if
somebody dumped some of that down their
drain in a city yeah so yeah but I think
knowing that history knowing that Bruce
was once able to isolate an organism
that was successful in doing that gives
me hope and confidence that that will
happen again in the future somebody will
able to be able to replicate that in the
future when the crisis becomes big
enough we will figure out the
we are I mean there is now very good
evidence that for instance mangrove
Ecology's utilizing the carbon polyester
inserted that polyethylene
resistant to any microbial organization
500 years
but there is an accelerating
as partners for better or worse in
Jersey
Plastics very much
absolutely yeah and I know there's also
been research about wax moths being able
to consume plastic films very rapidly so
I think that is encouraging again and
that is because of the microbes that are
contained within their digestive system
actually being capable of breaking down
many different plastics so I'm I'm I'm
very concerned about the particular
micro plastics that we have in the
environment today I think there is cause
for grave concern there but I'm not
without hope that we'll find a solution
for it so we've got time for one more
question yes you got it
registration but I go to events I went
to the national basis
I always ask the audience who's here
depends on agriculture
who's here on the road I hear the world
record
so hearing us talk today about education
I have none is anyone here from a land
trust no one can consult with okay I'll
take in because of that question I'll
take time for one more yes we'll go to
you
what's your opinion so to the point that
we made about corn breeding through cell
culture not having the end of fights
it's obvious that modern many modern
breeding techniques or some modern
breeding techniques have stripped the
seeds of their associated disease
resistance organisms and endophytes but
the reality is that as I see it the
large agro chemical corporations that
are perceived of being in control the
food supply actually has extremely shaky
foundations I don't expect them to
survive on their present business model
into the future for the long term
because of the point that was made
earlier is that they are no longer the
best technology best available
technology and they are particular
they're no longer the best available
technology for the large-scale broadacre
growers in one specific way that is
extremely important and that is farm
profitability we know that farm
profitability has been on the decline in
fact broadacre cropping in the midwest
have consumed equity on their operations
for four years out of the last five
except for those farmers who are
planting non-gmo seeds those farmers who
are growing cover crops those farmers
who are adopting these various practices
and going down this pathway there those
growers have higher profitability they
don't particularly necessarily have
higher yields but they consistently have
higher profitability at the very least
those farmers are going to be the
farmers that survive financially and
economically
so the existing status quo is not
doesn't seem probable to me to remain as
the status quo for another let's say 10
to 15 year time period not much past
that point because it can't sustain
itself and it also depends on has
dependent historically on an abundance
of rich topsoil which it has eroded and
degraded and caused to disappear when
that disappears my own personal story in
the story the gentleman here shared
earlier is that and it's a story of many
farmers is that many farmers that make
the switch is that they use conventional
mainstream practices until they didn't
work anymore why do we get calls today
not just from fruit and vegetable
growers or broadacre growers you say I
have listened to all the information
I've tried to learn as much as I can I
want to do my entire operation that is
happening because they recognize that
what they're doing right now and have
been doing historically is no longer
working that is reaching critical
threshold so I'm actually very
optimistic that I've set the goal for
myself if I want regenerative
agriculture to be the global mainstream
but 2040 to me that's a very realistic
and a very achievable goal and we're
well on the pathway to achieving that
[Applause]