hi I'm Lucy Edwards with the Alabama
Cooperative Extension system today we're
going to go over the basic steps for
taking your soil sample what do you have
a raised bed garden a lot of times
you're going to have high organic
material in your raised bed so this will
not be a routine soil test this will be
run as what they consider a saturated
paste test to analyze that high organic
matter it will still give you results
for nitrogen phosphorus potassium
calcium magnesium and then if you want
additional micronutrients it can also
tell you that as well so a few things
that you will need when you take a soil
sample first you'll need a container so
this is just an old pot lying around you
can use anything just something to hold
the soil if you have a soil probe you
can use a soil probe but most of us
probably have a handy trowel lying
around and so that's what we'll use
today with in this race bed I'm going to
take a couple of different sub samples
mix them together in my bucket and then
lastly I will combine them in a ziploc
bag because this is about as much soil
as you need and then we'll place the
soil in our box and they will fill out
the salt form that goes with each sample
now each form you can do up to five
samples so you don't necessarily need a
form for each box you can use five
different soil boxes to go with one form
some people will ask well do I do do I
need a separate source ample for each
raised bed my response to that would be
if you can tell the major difference in
your growing conditions so like
this bed grew really well but the wood
beside it grew portly I'd probably do
two separate samples now if they're both
having similar yields then I would only
take one sample and what I would
probably do is what I'm taking my
subsamples I would take half from this
bed and half from that bed so we're
gonna begin sampling this bed we're
gonna take subsamples about four inches
deep and we're going to take on from
different parts of this bed
then we're going to mix this sample
together that way it's a blended
representation of our bed
we're going to take our ziplock bag
we're gonna fill it most of the way up
this is about half way and that's okay
the reason why we use a bag before
putting it inside the box is simply
because this soil is moist in the boxes
cardboard and over time that moist soil
will break down the cardboard box and if
you mail this when it gets to the soil
lab this box will be all falling apart
so therefore I like to put it in a
ziplock bag as you can see it fits
nicely in the box we're gonna close the
box according to the directions it does
have a little sticky seal here so it
closes you don't need any tape or
anything and that is our box the next
step would be filling out the name of
the sender so that would be your name
the mailing address the location and
then field name so if you have your
raised beds labeled or if you have them
like tomato bed versus pepper bed you
would put the the name of that raised
bed where it says building name and then
crop to be grown so that may be pepper
tomato squash zucchini you could do
generic vegetables and it will come back
making recommendations for all of your
vegetables then last what we write on
the box we're going to then write on the
form so that way it correlates this box
name so if we named it named it box
number one
acres you have put down square footage
because obviously this is not an acre
and then the crops to be grown again
could be tomato vegetable tomatoes or
vegetables depending on what you put on
your box and that is how you take a
basic soil sample for a raised bed
garden
you