good morning I'm David Kuhn I'm a
Regional Extension agent with the
Alabama Cooperative Extension system and
as part of our grow more give more
series we're going to talk a little bit
about crop rotation today what is crop
rotation was one of the oldest
agricultural practices that we have and
it involves changing the planting
locations of different crops throughout
each growing season and we do this to
reduce damage from insect pests limit
the development of vegetable diseases
and also manage soil fertility so why is
it important each vegetable can be
classified into a particular plant
family plants belong to the same family
often are susceptible to the same insect
pests and diseases and have similar
nutrient requirements when vegetables
classified in the same plant family are
grown year after year in the same area
of a garden they provide insect pests
with a reliable food source and disease
organisms pathogens with a continuous
source of host plants that they can
infect over time insect pests and
pathogens numbers build in an area and
damaged vegetable damage to vegetable
crops increases using crop rotation
helps keep insect pests and pathogens
numbers at low levels in addition the
type of vegetable grown in a particular
area in a garden has a direct effect on
the fertility of the soil in that area
each vegetable is unique in the type and
amount and nutrients that it strikes
from the soil so crop rotation can even
out the loss of different soil nutrients
in allow time for nutrients to replenish
so when we talk about plant families we
divide those families down to four major
areas is when we're talking about garden
vegetables crucifer or cool season leafy
crops include cabbage collards kale
mustard broccoli and turnips our
solanaceous crops nightshades include
tomatoes potatoes pack
and eggplants q'bert's include cucumbers
cantaloupes squash watermelons and
pumpkins and our last category is
grasses and did you know that corn was
actually classified as a grass when we
talk about rotation in a garden we're
simply saying we're going to change the
locations of rows every year for each
plant family for plant families where
you only grow a half of a row or a
quarter of a row of its particular type
of plant you can simply change the end
of the row that you start those plants
on you need to plan for a four year
rotation meaning where you planted your
solanaceous crops this year will not be
planted with that same plant family for
the following three years if size
permits plan for a fifth year where you
allow a portion of your garden to lay
fallow for that planting season and then
add it back to the rotation when we look
at raised beds we're gonna treat each
bed as an individual row plant different
plant families at each bed each year if
you only have one or two raised beds try
to divide the beds in half and plant
different plant families in each half of
a bed each year if you need more space
you can also supplement your raised beds
with an in-ground garden space if
possible and when we look at growing in
containers we want to treat those
containers the same as raised beds
rotate crop families between containers
each planting season if you only have
one container replace the soil in that
container
each planting season and sanitize the
container before refilling thank you for
joining us today to learn a little about
crop rotation if you have any other
questions feel free to call the master
gardener helpline at one eight seven
seven two five two four seven six nine
thank you for joining us today