Hey, hey. I'm Sheay Wner and you are
listening to the Casual Cattle
Conversations Podcast. Whether you are a
seasoned rancher or just curious about
the cattle world, this podcast dives
into the stories, science, and
strategies shaping the future of
ranching. Let's get started and keep
your herd ahead of the herd. Folks,
today we are visiting with Devlon Ford
from the Noble Research Institute and we
are going to be talking about grazing,
but more specifically we are going to be
talking about some mistakes that
producers make that are really impacting
their profitability. So, Devlon is very
experienced in helping producers create
grazing plans that work for their unique
operations and improve their bottom
line. So he has a lot of expertise and
knowledge to share. He's very practical.
I learned a lot in this conversation. So
I hope you learned a lot too. Now with
that I do want to remind you that if you
are looking for a speaker for your next
event, whether that is a workshop, a
keynote, panelist, in person or virtual,
I am still taking on slots for 2025. So,
you can message me or contact me via my
website and just use the contact me form
and that goes straight to my email. But
with that, let's talk about grazing.
Does tax season make you want to bang
your head against the wall? Is billing a
bad word in your household? Does meeting
with your egg lender make your blood
pressure rise? Stress a little less with
cattle management software, Performance
Beef. It tracks important feed,
financial, and health data all in one
system. The results? You can pull
inventories, detailed financials, and
invoices in minutes. Get ahead for next
year's tax season. Visit
performanceelivestockanalytics.com to
learn more. All righty. Well, Devon, I
am excited to have you on the show today
and to talk about grazing because
grazing is a topic that I sense that you
are passionate about and I know your
co-workers are very passionate about as
well, but it's just something that
always goes over well on the show and is
important for ranchers to always be
continuing their education on and maybe
brushing up on a few things. So, the
first thing I always ask guests, and
it's maybe not an easy question, but
it's sure a fun one to hear responses,
is why do you believe in the beef
industry?
I enjoy working with livestock, cattle,
particularly uh got to work cattle with
my son and some friends this last
weekend for the first time in a long
time. And while it was a good day, I
mean, it was we was working cattle, but
it was a good day. Enjoyable. I just
like being around like-minded people
like me that want to take care of their
livestock and their land. Absolutely.
And tell us a little bit more about what
you're doing today because you're with
the Noble Research Institute, but
elaborate a little bit more on your
role.
My role is I'm one of facilitators. I
get to travel around a lot of the US
teaching courses primarily our noble
grazing essentials course and our
business of grazing course get to visit
with a lot of producers you know
hopefully when they leave our courses
they've taken something home that you
know from my past experiences and
typically every time I leave of course
I've taken home something from them so I
always tell everybody I'm a lifelong
learner I was about 50 when I finally
went back and got my master's degree so
as we go to these courses and facilitate
these programs. We get the opportunity
from learn to learn from those producers
as well. Well, I always like to visit
with lifelong learners. That's part of
the reason I started the podcast so that
I can continue to be one of those and
for all the other lifelong learners who
are constantly wanting to learn
something new, hear different
perspectives.
So, when we visited on the phone and
we're talking about, you know, what are
we going to talk about on this podcast
interview, you mentioned that one thing
that you either hear producers getting
mixed up or that you really focus on in
your courses is that difference between
carrying capacity and stocking rate.
Correct. Correct. I've been several
places and quite often people use those
two terms interchangeably. They use them
for the same thing and they're two very
distinct terms, definitions and outcomes
on your ranch when used properly. Do you
want to take some time to elaborate on
the two terms individually? So carrying
capacity is based off a mathematical
formula. It takes into account grazable
acres. It takes into account forge
production on those acres and it also
takes into account what utilization, how
much you want consumed of that forge
that's out there. Typically, that's
expressed as a percentage. And then on
the denominator side, you know, we'll
take your livestock weight and multiply
it by some intake value. Typically in
our classes, just as averages, we'll use
like a
2.6% intake per day for that animal. And
then you know how many ever days we're
planning on grazing. We'll multiply it
by that and then divide the numerator by
the bottom or the denominator. And that
will give us the carrying capacity for
our ranch. How many head our ranch will
support underneath the terms we put in
there. Grazable acres. You know, I hear
a lot of people say, "Oh, granddaddy did
it this way and he ran 100 cows and I
got the same amount of land." Well, you
might have the same amount of land and
you may not. In one of our classes at
the grazing essentials course, we talk
about this. We pull up a map that's
about 85 acres and 19 years later it's
75 acres just because the oil pad came
in, the highway moved south, different
things happen. So, and the other thing
about is if you're doing the things your
granddaddy did, you're probably running
bigger cows than your granddaddy did cuz
not many people's got a lot of thousand
pound cows anymore like my grandfather
did. So the forge
availability, you know, that's kind of
based on your climate, where you're at.
If you're more aid, you're probably
going to run less forge than say we are
here in South Central Oklahoma with 38
average inches of rainfall. So, you
know, you're only going to be able to
grow so much grass, so much forge for
those animals. Utilization, how much we
take is one decision as a manager or as
an owner that you make in that
calculation. you decide what it is that
we typically will try to push people to
take less than they want to because I've
heard the term that's wasting grass if I
don't eat it. No grass is ever wasted.
It's always useful for something
somewhere. Even if it's not ran through
a cow, it's going to it'll improve the
soil health in future once it lays on
the ground and decays. Those nutrients
can go back in the soil. On the bottom
side of that equation, we talked about
cow weight. And we just tell people take
the average weight of your cow herd. And
typically most people's going to use
1,200 lb cows and then multiply that by
the 2.6% intake. I know back in the 80s
when I was still in school, undergrad,
we talked 3% back there. Kind of the
range is 1.9 to 3.5 for cattle. So
somewhere in there, you know, depending
upon their stage of life cycle they're
in, whether they're cving or trying to
breed back up, that type of thing,
they're going their nutrient
requirements is going to be a little bit
different on a daily basis. So we just
use 2.6 as average. And then you take
that number and multiply by the days you
plan on grazing. If you plan on grazing
forages 365 days a year, that's the
number you use, 365.
If you've got a stalker operation and
you're going to be running 120 days,
that's the number you use. Once you do
all the math, it'll give you a number
and that's the maximum amount of cows
that that place will carry underneath
those conditions. Stocking rate, on the
other hand, is solely a management
decision. That is the number of animals
that we as managers and owners choose to
put on our landscapes. That's how many
animals we buy or put on that ranch. So,
it's straight up management decision.
So, what are the major implications and
problems you see when producers are
using those two terms
interchangeably instead of understanding
them for their two separate for being
two separate things? Typically what I
see happening is when they when they use
them interchangeably, they're not really
thinking or paying attention to their
ranch. Our ranches will teach us a lot
of stuff if we just look at it and
monitor it and see what happens over
time. But if they're using them
interchangeably, typically they have not
done the calculation to see if their
carrying capacity is where it needs to
be. You know, they may be low or they
may be high on their stocking rate
because they haven't calculated their
carrying capacity. Support your cattle's
health and productivity with Vigertone
Minerals. Since 1912, Vigertone has been
a trusted name in animal nutrition. The
revitalized product line offers targeted
nutrition for every stage of production
and every region. Vigertone delivers
consistent performance and simplifies
your mineral decisions. Wherever you
are, Vigorone works. Visit vigorone.com
to learn more and that link is also in
the show notes. So when producers are
looking to calculate that carrying
capacity, I know you just went through
what goes into that calculation. Are
there other resources in their area that
they should turn to to kind of get
started on that or is it pretty much a
straightforward calculation across the
board no matter where they're at? Well,
the calculation is the same, but the
numbers are going to be different
depending upon where you're at, your
situation, and your numbers will be
different than your ranches, your
neighbor ranch's numbers. The grazable
acres, you know, people say, "Well, I
own 1,000 acres." It's a good deal. I'm
glad you do. How much of that is
grazable? Well, 1,000 acres is there's
no roads on it. There's no barns on it,
no lots on it, no
houses, very little brush or woods. So
that's where people get can get confused
there. They figured on how many acres
they own, not how many acres an animal
can graze on it. Quite often, you know,
oil field pads, we have some of those
here in South Central or South Central
Oklahoma. They don't think about those.
They don't think about their lots. You
know, if you do have brush, which we do
have a lot here in the Cross Timbers
region, we do have some control over the
brush. we can go in and either
strategically clear it with dozer or
something like that or you know if we're
very progressive and have very a whole
lot of patience we could bring in some
goats or something else that might eat
some of that brush. So that's you know
the grazable acres that's where those
kind of numbers could come from. Your
forge production is one of the hardest
numbers for people to come up with. And
the way we teach it in class is, you
know, if you got history of the ranch,
you probably
know, you know, I tell everybody when I
was on the ranches every day, I might
not tell you how many pounds of forge
was out there, but I could tell you how
long those set of cavs could be in that
pasture. So, I was still equating it. I
just wasn't thinking about it that way.
So, you know, you can visually appraise
it and say, "I've got 4,000 lbs of dry
matter here." You can take a ruler out
there and do some measurements and we've
got some methods here at Noble. Uh we've
worked with Jim Garish on some our
classes and he's helped us out a bunch
and you know, we've used a lot of his
spreadsheets and tricks and things like
that or you know, methods and we can
take that measure and do some measuring
out in the pastures and we come up with
that number. Another good way that I
tell a lot of people to do it is they
can get on
the NRCS web soil survey. It's a free
website. Very good to use for some
instances and it's it's a good starting
place for a lot of things. They can get
in there and outline their ranch on that
map and it'll give them an average. You
know, you can look at a good year or a
bad year or an average year. And I
suggest either going at the high end of
average year and at the low end of bad
or the best end of bad year because if
you use a good year every year your
carrying capacity is going to be too
high because we have 38 in average
rainfall here in Oklahoma and we might
hit that three out of
10. So but that's a good place to get
that forge production number just as a
base to get started. And then after
you've gotten started, you're monitoring
your animals, you're monitoring your
pastures, you're taking notes, recording
down all this information, and that will
help you become better the next time you
do these calculations. Again, the
utilization right rate, a lot of people
think they need to take 80 to 100% of
their
forage, and I would disagree with that.
We typically talk around depending upon
the type of forge we're talking about
30% on you know some native ranges here
in Oklahoma. If we're talking the
Bermuda grass we'll be talking a little
bit higher than that. If we're talking
winter wheat which we have a lot of you
know we're talking 60% or so. A lot of
those you know those annual type grasses
you can sometimes take a little bit more
than you can your perennials. But your
native perennials they are made to take
a little bit and move on down the road
and let that plant grow and recover. the
livestock number. I I ask a lot of
people what their cows weigh and I get a
lot of numbers and then I ask how many
people's got scales and not a lot of
people have scales. So unless you're you
make a living buying cattle and know
what a cattle weighs, you might miss
your cattle weight a little bit. And
then daily intake there's you can set it
at 2.6 3% either one of those would be
fine if you want to be a little bit
safer. 3% would be good average number
to use. And then the number of days is,
you know, that's dependent upon how long
you want to graze. If you plan on
feeding hay and, you know, energy or
protein supplement 60 days, then that
number is 305 days. If you've got a
lease that runs out in 9 months, you're
looking at a 9 month or 270 days. You
know, whatever how many ever days you're
planning on grazing that landscape where
you put that number there. So, like I
said, the carrying capacity calculations
is some of
the hardest math we teach. Okay. So, I
really appreciate you walking me through
that and the listeners through that and
going into more detail there. So, we've
talked carrying capacity, stocking rate,
and before we started this, you also
talked about stocking density. So, do
you want to throw that in there, too,
and share how that's different than the
other two terms we just talked about?
Stock density is it's basically the
amount of pounds or the pounds of
animals that you put on a specific
spot. Typically, you know, most people
are going to be talking 20,000 lbs of
stock density. So, that'd be 21,000 lb
cows on an acre. That's 20,000 pounds of
stock density per acre. In our classes,
typically the last day on our grazing
essentials course, we will show our
producers what a million pounds of stock
density look like. So imagine if you
would about 30 cows in a 50 by 50 fence.
50 foot by 50 foot. 30 cows. We leave
them there for 1 hour is all we do. And
then we'll open the gate and move them.
Again, stock density allows us to do a
lot of different things. And I'm not
telling anybody to go out and do a
million pounds of stock density.
Anywhere north of 60,000 to 100,000 is
pretty good. The higher you get, the
more intensively man you have to manage
it. So, but stock density is one of the
best tools in a grazer's toolbox. One of
the things that as animals graze around,
you know, they're going after what we
call the ice cream plants. They're going
after what they really want. And if we
give them enough time and enough room,
that's what they're going to do. But if
we put them down into a smaller area,
we're going to convince them that they
need to eat something. So they probably
need to eat whatever they can get a hold
of real quick. So you'll get a little
you get a lot more uniform grazing
distribution that way. You know, you're
using more of your forages that they may
normally pass over until the second or
third time back through there. Is there
an impact on animal performance when
we're when you're seeing higher stocking
densities in those more intensive
systems? One thing we need to remember
when we're talking stock density, you
know, we're talking pounds of animals
and time. And time is a very critical
piece of that. With the high higher
stock densities, we're putting
more nutrient back into the soil, more
manure, more urine back into the soil in
a smaller area. In other words, they're
not able to go a half a mile and loaf at
the water and, you know, and spread
their manure and urine there around the
water or underneath the shade trees. You
know, they're putting it on the pasture
where it's going to give us the biggest
benefit for our
operation. The other thing about stock
density is it's a tool. You know, we can
make those animals eat things that they
may not necessarily want to eat. It's
not going to hurt them, but they will
eat that. I mean, they'll still gain
weight on those forges. The other thing
it'll do is if we have a lot of dry
standing forge that for whatever reason
we didn't graze get grazed off or maybe
it's a, you know, winter pasture that's,
you know, already terminated and went to
seed. And we can use stock density to
lay that forge that's 2 or 3 foot tall
that the cattle are, you know, the stems
all dignified. The cattle are not going
to eat it. They're going to graze around
it. We can use that stock density to
then put that taller forge on the ground
and get it in closer contact with the
soil. So now we're back to feeding the
soil and the soil feeds the grass and
the grass feeds your cows. So for years
when I was managing cattle for Noble on
different ranches, I always thought I
was a cattle manager or cowboy, whatever
you want to call me. Come to find out,
what I've since then learned is I'm more
of a grass manager and a soil manager
than I am the cattle manager. I'm
hearing more and more people share that
perspective or change in thought, if you
will, however you want to describe that.
So with all of that, when we're thinking
about the profitability of ranches and
how grazing systems fit into that, what
is that profitability impact if
producers are putting too many or too
few cattle in their pastures and not,
you know, understanding those terms
correctly and having that plan, the
problem with running more animals are
setting our stocking rate above our
carrying capacity is we are more than
likely going to increase our direct cost
to those animals because we're more than
likely going to have to feed more
substitutional feeding feed hay more
protein or more energy. Not to mention
what we could potentially do or what we
will be doing once we start overg
grazing our ranches. You know what when
we overg graze our ranches we're you
know we're declining the roots in the
soil. We're declining the quality of the
soil on our ranches because there's no
forge there to grow. One of the six soil
health principles is always keep living
roots. Well, anytime we take a plant and
bite it to the point where we remove too
many of the leaves off of it, think of
those leaves as a solar panel on your
charger, fence charger. And what would
happen if you covered up half of those
solar cells with tape? It wouldn't the
charger wouldn't function like it
should. Same way with plants. If we
remove too many
leaves, that plant cannot perform
because it doesn't have any solar. So
then it starts pulling carbohydrates up
out of the roots out of the soil up to
the plant for growth. So that's one of
the dangers of stocking your ranch above
carrying
capacity. On the other hand of that for
profitability when we start you know
stocking rate is the primary determinant
of pro
profitability. Stocking rate is the
primary determinant of profitability. If
we stock few too few of animals on that
ranch, then we're probably not going to
have enough revenue coming in that we
can cover our overhead cost as well. So,
you know, we have to think about that,
too. There's a pretty good curve. You
know, the higher the stocking rate, the
less production you get with an animal.
But there's also, you know, if I'm in a
stalker operation, I may choose to, you
know, only gain two pounds a day and run
more animals than I run fewer animals
and gain two and a half. So, you know,
stocking rates, that's pretty fine line.
And we, you know, I I typically would
recommend people to depend upon their
forages, the climate they're in, how aid
it is, how wet it is, you know,
typically set that stocking rate
somewhere between 70 maybe 85%. If
certain times, you know, if you're doing
some winter pasture graze out with some
yards, then, you know, you can run that
a little bit higher, but just need to be
aware that you may need to be selling
those animals a little bit quicker than
you thought you would. So, you know, a
lot of this just kind of goes back to a
context of that producer and their goals
for their ranch.
Do you have big ambitions for your
operation, but feel like you get so
caught up in the day-to-day fires that
you are just spinning in circles? You
aren't alone. I've been in your shoes
and know just how frustrating it can be.
That's why I created Move the Ranch
Forward. It's a guide for ranchers. This
guide is a PDF that contains the exact
process my husband and I use to stay
focused on our goals throughout the
year, even when life throws us
curveballs. You can access move the
ranch forward today at casual cattle
conversations.com.
So, you've touched a little bit on, you
know, when you're talking about stocking
density and talked about, you know, some
of the cool things you can do with that
and there's a lot of buzz around some of
those more
intensive grazing strategies, but there
are still a lot of producers who moving
cattle every day isn't necessarily
feasible or doesn't feel feasible
depending on their business plan. So,
what tips do you have for producers like
that who want to make sure they're still
being good stewards of the land and
improving those pastures that they're
grazing?
I totally understand that cuz a couple
years ago, me and my wife lived about 45
minutes from where our cattle were. So,
basically, I'd checked them about every
3 days. So I would come up and I would
move my cattle about every three days.
What we typically tell people in wetter
climates like we have here in Oklahoma,
you know, once you go in there and start
grazing an area, within about 3 to 5
days after you first move in there,
there'll be new leaves coming up on that
plant. And as those new leaves come up,
those are the plants and those are the
leaves those animals are going to target
because it's fresh growth. We all know
that fresh young growth is very
palatable, very nutritious, and that's
what those animals want. So, if we can
move them every 3 to 5 days in, you
know, a wetter climate, 5 to seven in
more aid climate where the grass grows a
little bit slower, we're okay. you know,
later in the year when, you know, we
start moving in towards fall, you know,
we might be able to extend that a little
bit of time in there just
because, you know, the plants aren't
growing as fast as they are in the, you
know, late spring, early summer. So, you
know, we have to make this fit our
ranch, fit our lifestyle, and just
understand our what our goals are for
our ranch. And if our goals are to
improve soil health and we have the
ability to move every day, great, get
after it. If you only have the ability
to move once or twice a week, do the
best you can, but always remember there
are pros and cons to everything we do.
So, you
know, someone who moves every day, they
may improve their ranch
faster, but they've got a lot more time
invested in it, too. Someone who moves
three or five once or twice a week,
they'll achieve the same results. It may
just take them a little bit longer, but
still yet there's quality of life that's
involved in all this as well. Well, and
I think about myself personally, we have
a very we have a diversified operation.
So there with the farming and other
businesses too. That's something else
that we always take into consideration
when we think through our grazing plan
and breeding groups each summer. Yeah.
on our uh business of grazing course we
work a lot on a grazing plan and that's
one of the things we put in there you
know we draw a line on the grazing plan
and said you know this we're going to
start cving here and you know we're
going to start stop cving here and you
know I want to go on vacation with my
family and we put that in there and we
do all this just as you said that way
that helps us plan those rotations and
our grazing movements and unfortunately
uh you know ranching is a great life but
It's doesn't always go the way we
planned out on paper. So, but by having
that grazing plan that allows us to be
more adaptive in our management and we
can make movements earlier. We talk
planning a lot and being very adaptive
because it's regenerative ranching and
grazing is adaptive grazing. It's not a
set in stone dynamic plan. So when you
are teaching those courses and helping
ranchers create those grazing plans or
modify existing ones, what are some
other common mistakes that you help
people work through or see or maybe it's
not a mistake so much as a missed
opportunity?
You that varies from course to course
and participants and that's one of the
reasons I love doing what we do is
because I get an opportunity to talk to
these people, understand their
particular situations a little bit
better. I was talking to one gentleman
and he realized that he was probably
overstocked. He was a purebred breeder
and he thought, "Well, I'll plant this
crop then I can graze it." And I told
him, I said, "Well, that's good. At
least you're doing something for the
soil that way, but all you're really
doing is
replacing one feeding for a different
type of feeding that you're spending
money on. Don't get me wrong, I mean,
bell grazing, you know, feeding, there's
nothing wrong with feeding hay. I've got
plans to do it on our place this year.
I've got some areas where the soil is
not where I'd like to be and I'd like to
put a little cover on it. So, I'm going
to do what we call bail gra there and
roll some hay out and allow my animals
to get there, get around it and eat. I
do not plan on taking letting them eat
that hay to the ground. I'm going to
leave a lot of it behind just kind of
put some cover on that soil. So, those
are just different types of
opportunities we get. And I talked to
one lady had a very sizable ranch and
she was want to know how to put
infrastructure in that on that this one
pasture and it was rather large. And I
said same way I do it on my 140 acres. I
develop a plan and I implement that plan
when and as I can. Slow and
easy. Anytime we start making ranching
too hard, it becomes unfund quickly.
Slow and easy. So you recommend
producers kind of
ease into it a lot of times as they make
those changes or I mean that can be case
by case too I know but case by case is
but typically when we're talking to
producers
that are ranching and farming a little
bit more conventionally we ask them to
just
get a set of land whether it's you know
10 or 50 or 100 acres whatever and start
there on that concentrate on improving
that one we typically going to ask them
to start with their better plant to do
that
with. And if there's things they want to
try on some other spots, that's fine.
But put their concentration and their
focus on this one little spot. And then
as they get more adaptive and more
adjusted to looking at seeing what
they're seeing and understanding what
they're seeing, they start seeing these
improvements. Then that gives them the
energy to go to, you know, to expand on
out to the rest of their land. You know,
that's kind of what me and my wife did
at our place. When it comes to
infrastructure, I say a little at a time
because infrastructure is not
cheap. Anytime you build any fence or
lay a water line or dig a well, it's
there's some dollars involved in there
and you know, you need to calculate that
out. Make certain you can still cash
flow or you know where the money is
going to come from. Can you afford it?
What's it going to do for you? What's
the return on investment going to be?
How long is it going to take to pay off?
I mean, there's all kinds of
considerations especially when you start
spending money on your ranch. for
producers who
are
overstocked but maybe fighting that
concept of change and how to start and
where to start. What are some questions
you recommend they ask themselves? Are
they over carrying
capacity? If they're over carrying
capacity, can they reduce the size of
their herd?
And if if the answer is yes to that, I
mean you obviously anybody can reduce
their size of the herd, but they have to
be willing to do that. You know, I know
a lot of purebred breeders and they say
it's my genetics that make me
profitable. And I will argue with them.
It's the decisions they made choosing
those genetics that made those genetics
profitable. In their mind, it genetics
has nothing to do. It's the choices they
made in choosing those genetics. So, you
know, if we are overstocked, my first
recommendation is to start, you know,
getting rid of those unproductive, if
we're straight cow calf, getting rid of
those unproductive cows. If we have
multiple enterprises, maybe we're
running goats and or sheep or stalkers
or cow calf, whatever enterprises we
got, evaluate each one of those
enterprises to make certain they're all
profitable and then choose the mix of
enterprises that's going to make us the
most money and that we want to mess with
and use those enterprises moving
forward.
setting the carrying capac getting the
carrying capacity right and setting
stock density appropriately cuz quite
often what happens down here is you know
everybody's dependent upon that spring
rain and then when we don't get that
spring rain and we go dry you know we're
not going to grow as much forge and now
all of a
sudden we've got to sell cows and if you
want to talk about an emotional decision
that's when you decide you have to sell
cows in a drought which cows are you
going to sell that becomes very
emotional to a lot of people. So, you
know, if you set your carrying capacity
below or I mean set your stocking rate
below carrying capacity, then you
automatically got a little bit of a
buffer in those years that's dry, you
may not have to destock at all. You may
be able to not destock as much, take out
fewer animals. Those years where it we
get adequate rain or a lot of rain and
we've got a whole lot of forage and
you're sitting there thinking, I've got
all this forge. What can I do with it? I
don't have enough cows. Well, there's
opportunities there. you know, we can
bring in a a set of yardings and graze
in there. We may u be able to bring in
some cows that we contract graze on our
place. Maybe there's some areas we
wanted to do some land improvements and
maybe we're going to set aside some land
that we've always wanted to burn but
just didn't have the forge. So, you
know, those gives you opportunities that
way. All right. Well, as people go ahead
and think about our conversation today,
if they want to dive deeper into this or
get more information, what resources
should they go to or do you recommend?
They can always go to our website. It's
noble.org. There's some articles. Uh
there's a list of our classes that they
could attend if they want to do that. I
know we've got several coming up in
several different states pretty quickly.
There's all kinds of other groups that
are out there, podcasts such as
yourself, YouTube channels, different
things like that. The regenerative
ranching movement is
becoming more mainstained, I mainstay, I
believe. So, there's opportunities
everywhere to look for information.
All right. Well, I really appreciate our
conversation today and your willingness
to share your knowledge and expertise.
For those of you who are listening, you
can find the link to the Noble website
in the show notes. It's under that
description there. It'll be easy for you
to find there. And with that, happy
ranching, folks.