[Music]
I was telling you that the first two
years were outstanding
we had lead we got different cover crop
mixes seeded you have these great strips
we had awesome field days with between
40 to 80 people at them everything was
great the first year so I was like wow
I'm going to get two more years of this
because this is going so well and then
we got into really wet harvests and then
we got into PPE on a couple of our
fields and so really by the end of this
I have some great baseline data but I
don't have a lot of long-term data from
it from the four years so what I'm going
to focus on though are other
partnerships and and those partnerships
of those regional for farmers that were
part of the grants are very strong we
work about them I've met a lot of other
farmers through them and through those
boxes through those field days what
we've now expanded so just on our files
that they're doing on their parts and
things that were measuring and they've
come in as co-operators on their other
projects through commodity funding or
through NRCS or Sarah or any of those
things they participate our workshops
are Sarah professional development
workshop grants as well so so this isn't
going to be directly related to the
projects I have if you go look at the
reports online area I think it's what
we've done is this has yeah push years
would be great if it's the second two
years before I go over failure but I
think you'll see after way
it's really fun some great partnerships
within North Dakota because it's going
to do this I was noticing that a lot of
farmers I was talking with that part of
the source s podcast that we have now so
I'm actually going to walk through it in
a way through their episodes and things
they're trying the things they explain
and describe so that you could go back
and listen to those different episodes
if you want to hear the farmers talk
about what they're doing whether they're
trying right but I think you know the
essence of our podcast was this which is
exactly what the partnership grant is is
that you know saw was a journey it
requires collaboration and curiosity
amongst farmers researchers consultants
and extension and those are the
partnerships we really focused on and we
have people from each of those groups
talking about their experiences in still
health on this podcast which the second
series now comes out at March 1st so
here's another example of the work that
we're doing Dave Franzen is our soil
fertility specialist and he's gone away
from doing fertility trials on research
centers and taking them out to farmers
fields because it means more it means
more to those farmers that have in field
data that made changes based on those
projects so here's de France and use one
of the most traditional rigorous
scientists that you'll find doing all
these on-farm trials because it means
more I think we can all agree to that
it also has to be trust ready we can do
always work in the world and unless
somebody trusts us in the information
we're providing they're not going to do
those things so those those partnerships
won't develop and so one of the things
we're mostly on is system crop consult
does Lee breeze is those partnerships of
those relationships so I'd said earlier
when we're talking about there's a
presentation on on you know just the
crisis that's happening with our farmers
right then things that they're going
throughout their farms and probably half
this half of this past year I spent just
trying to help farmers through that and
it wasn't always about you know that
they were in a state of crisis or there
or they have these cos it was more just
hey I'm gonna be there and let's go look
at some fields let's talk about
something more positive and and so
that's where that trust comes in and I
guarantee any of those farmers know we
have a trust that if I need anything
you're gonna help me out on a project if
they need anything they don't the help
them out but here's one farmer that we
work with closely you Sam lemon he's
episode 5 it's kind of the calendar
who's got a say mr. genius Nancy I'm far
away just turned 30 he's got his first
kid on the way and and he's he's up in
north northeastern North Dakota so many
of those guys are still harvesting right
now Sam was able to give us was pintos
off you didn't have any acres of corn
he's cooperating on a large field scale
project we have where he's looking at
notes Phil pintos will be looking at
no-till pintos corn soybean and wheat
with a cover crop and then full tillage
to no cover crop and he's got a firm
trial for that but he likes he's he's
getting more and more confident that he
can just do if he runs anything at
vertical tillage he's gonna do in the
spring and he's gonna keep his soils
covered over the winter and if he's
gonna try to get a cover crop in it's
gonna be early and if it's not early
enough he's gonna skip the cover crop
because he thinks that his planter his
drill will do more cutting up a
president or damage than it will he just
leaves the residue and doesn't have a
cover crop because he wouldn't get
enough growth so making some really good
important decisions but he's got to
figure out those new management so this
is one of his fields it's got to warm up
in the spring he's got him the plant
into it so he's concerned about low
temperatures he's concerned about it
being too wet I mean these guys have
rust everywhere in their fields this
year but the notes what guys don't have
as many ruts I'll tell you that they've
been pretty proud about this year the
seeds at hare pinning he's very
concerned about that with his equipment
his stand his emergence seeding into
this is kind of scary force and so he's
got to figure out how to manage it so
his approach he's doing cover crops with
bio strip too so in that case
it's planting his radish uses a sugar
beet play tennis in his planter 30 inch
rows facing and they comes back in the
following year and plants as pintos on
that so he's creating a space for those
for the cover crops to be very
intensified in a strip where he's going
to plant his cover crop the next year
his cash crop the next year this gives
him a little bit of relief of that wheat
straw that he's concerned about but you
know his reward news reward is that
there's no reason to tell on the fall
he's had great stance with Miss residue
you see zero you know minimal difference
if I had zero difference between yields
on his pintos whether they're planted
into residue or into and the cultivated
soil and he's looking for that moisture
in August and this year they didn't need
Meister in August unfortunately but
that's what he still in front of those
dry years he's going to see I think
he'll really see the benefits of what
he's doing at this party
Doug Toussaint was the dark operator
episode 11 the sheriff farm on this the
sare project got shared arm ser and a
lot of them different acronyms the dog
is he's one of those farmers at five
years ago he transitions one quarter
into no-till and use cover crops and the
new transition the whole farm the next
year so he's his his quote is cover
crops it's not where to quit spending
money one year he cut back and he didn't
spend money on cover crops and he said
it was his biggest regret that you
didn't get every acre covered on his
farm and so either I don't know him fail
that if you just didn't do it at all and
I think Doug is a man of few words
often times there are problems of
whatever
but he says about his system and so he
will get his come across and every
single ad here he will make sure that
happens whether is flowing on seated
however he's gonna do is gonna get it
done but this is one of the when we were
finding you know the cover crops after
leach was not happy because the harvests
are so wet we just couldn't ask a farmer
to get out there and add more to what
they were doing plus the cover crops
would have grown he switched his project
to getting cover crops with in
sunflowers and this one is a lot of
people are really interested in this he
was looking at it for the benefits of
getting some extra roots in his high
clay soil as he wants the beneficial
insects out there to be pretty
bittersweet affirmative the pest
pressures not so flowers and then he's
looking to manage weeds because he just
think about like he didn't have enough
tools to manage weeds in his system so
we did never threw the strip's we had
three fields for I think now it's been
three years if he passes out there forty
feet wide 60 feet long he sees this
cover his sunflowers on thirty inch row
spacing and then that same day he's
seeding with the journal at seven and a
half inch spacing the cover crop mixes
we've got the mix down to you know
eighteen bucks an acre which he can
spray that out if he has to and not feel
that out about it and that's kind of our
goal and we're seeing no difference it's
statistically no difference in the yield
or oil content of those sunflowers
there's still two hundred pound
difference for the cover crops are 200
pounds low and where he has no cover
crops and even though it's not stated
statistically significant to him it's
enough to be concerned about it
so he will probably never take
all fields which is fine I think he
could get away with it on the borders of
the field there you can do strips in a
field and not not have that risk of
doing the whole field or the cost of
doing the whole field but he had the
beautiful state IDs were some of these
beautiful fields we worked in because
those cover crops were blooming
throughout the growing season to bring
in the beneficial insects his approach
of cover crops on every acre this is
what he's often dealing with in the
spring this is a late spring - so he's
got a concern as he's you know his
potential issues with getting cover
crops that degree of care of man-hours
and power how many people they do does
he have to get out there and do these
things to get around that he's flying
out more cover crops and having good
establishment getting in a growth having
a bad residue other options of cover
crops which he put out there which do
not put out there what can you manage
but the reward is he's also getting in
the field not a problem and he's not got
a problem on any field or he's had cover
crops where he's not having cover crops
like cereal right but went awry he may
have potential issues and that's what
that's a few loses sleep over maybe you
can see this field so this is why I was
walking through in the middle of it no
no issues walking through all that water
on a 60% clay and then that title field
I stepped into next next to it that was
the first step by token that was the
last one I took
his approach planting into something
living so this is what he plants into in
the spring and this is very different
for the southeastern corner of North
Dakota I mean this is not we typically
see it he's got you know he's like 200
pounds of cereal rise where he's putting
on his fields because he likes a lot of
green I would recommend that for
everybody but we could have too much
growth when you if we have a job spring
and could rob him of moisture you have
too much water use seed placement
equipment he's he's played with his
cronies put things on and pull them off
they're trying to get it so he can get
that seed in the ground in a consistent
way but the reward from this is that
9:00 p.m. phone call doug is always very
respectful of my time and only calls me
during work hours but one time he called
me at 9:00 p.m. and he said you gotta
see this and so that next day I was down
there and and we look to this field this
is his field that has had cover crops
and no-till on it for I think at this
point it was four years they had a
soybean crop on it and they went through
harvest and two-wheel-drive
in the compound this is the neighbors
feel that that has had rippers chisel
plows field cultivators leech soybean
rotation on it
they use tracks to harvest this it was
the same day and you can see the ruts
and he was so excited to see that and
this is also a benefit or the guy the
aerial applicator I was flying over the
field at the time
Eric going to see cover crops in
somebody else's farm that was starting
to use cover crops and we call that very
good said hey could you swing or not
take a picture and you did and this is
and this is what we have to show for it
so this is a really really proud day for
him
this fall we went around to the same
thing we drove and we looked at it
looked at his fields and came up with a
plan and he's love zero ruts in this
field and everybody else was sliding all
around
knocked out ground and they had a really
rough harvest people were chit were
reusing rippers in full season cover
crops I got out there that were PP I
mean it was a it was there's a lot going
on but he he was pretty proud about all
of us profit off his field and this is
this is what we saw this all this
systemic field
we drove across it he started laughing
at me because we drove to a really
standing water area and he looked at my
face and this apparently looks like I
was really scared you guys didn't think
we're gonna make it did you and we sat
we looked at this field and you could
just see on this face how proud he is of
what he's done and then this other field
this child right across the road and
that's what it was like in that field my
government so those compaction issues
are gonna be reflected in that crop for
years the deep compaction this is
another farmer Tony that I work with to
Jamestown he he's been no-till for 15 20
years he uses cover crops intensively at
least a third of his land and he farms a
lot a lot of land so he's always out
there receiving cover crops as the way
he does it and he farms a lot of sandy
soils that he doesn't like see in a so
low blow away and so that for him its
erosion he wants to keep his solos in
place this is an example at one of his
sandy fields where he's he had just
taken this one over he had a short
season crop on it because it's a sand so
he adjusted his rotation had a short
season crop on it followed it with an
oak cover crop he left it just he just
did oats because he wanted to come back
in and spray over the top of it to
control some wounds he had out there so
this is how this field looks going to
bed for the winter but he does have some
concerns lack or residue too much water
he's potentially on sandy soil lack of
growth but he's been doing he's been
getting a really really nice stance he
also uses residue to his advantage so he
bought a stripper had a couple years ago
this is how he leaves his wheat straw
standing a lot of bare ground underneath
it becomes a
profit seeds it people think it's gonna
be a nightmare that next year well then
the residue and everything standing it's
not a problem to get into it and so
that's what he's learned and that's what
he's done don't catch a lot of snow and
he's caught a lot of snow this is my
turn this field but it's even and across
the field so it's gonna melt evenly into
the into the field that's not patched up
in low spots or on the edge of the field
he was that residue going around so he
has a very consistent field in the
spring to plant into and this was Tony's
reward I did a video from one of his
fields that he just took over and then
one of his fields and he's been doing
these practices on for 14 years
they were just kiddy Korner to each
other and I picked up the soils and it's
the first time he's ever seen him
side-by-side
he's never thought to take one slope on
my field and look at it next to the
other and you can see in this how dark
his soil is how much he's built up with
organic matter and how much more walk
moisture he can retain and for him that
was that he knew he always knew Rudy's
doing is working but this told him again
that what he's doing is working and he
needed that confirmation I have an
episode two for this awesome
and I talk about the program we're gonna
done so oftentimes whether you're two
miles away or you're 200 miles away
there's something that you can take from
each other's systems and so a lot of
what I do is this network approach to
getting farmers to talk and gave people
an extension to talk and researchers and
Industry and consultants to talk so the
green dots on here are our NDSU people
whether they're researchers are
extension the red wants our consultants
the blue ones are farmers and the other
ones are industry and so if you look at
the idea of this is that you have all
the locations where we've had programs
particularly this cafe talk program that
I do which stairs is funding this year
so you've all these talks and all these
farmers show up and as they move to the
center of this diagram and there's in
there dot gets bigger that means they're
they're having
programs they're potentially having more
influence on people and sharing
conversations so we have people on the
inside that are sharing a lot of
information showing up to a lot of
events we have the people on the outside
that we want to get on the inside so I
can see where we're going to go we're
gonna bring on the outside to the inside
we're going to continue to strengthen
this will get more people on the outside
and keep this network building and the
idea of this is that one person could
step away at any time and the network
won't fail so it makes it so that one
person is not important it's how
everybody interacts that's important
what we do this we do another social
network analysis where we have farmers
list names and the three people they
talk to from like research perspective
and then three people they talk to in
general about soil health and in that
one the more somebody's name is listed
as somebody if somebody talks to the
larger their dockets and so there are
farmers that that we can pick out that
are very influential in their areas
because people listed them as somebody
is a resource and they're talking to
them all the time and so that helps us
with our program you say wow I'm gonna
make sure that that farmer has the
information they need the tools they
need whatever they need to make sure
that the information they're sharing is
science-based that it's practical
applications that we can keep soil
health of science and not just an
observation type program and then here's
one of the farmers are relying heavily
Joe Rutger who's been 40 some years
no-till and his 20 years of cover crops
he's a very wise farmer and she says
every situation is unique he never
pushes what he says on anybody else
every situations neat but he thinks that
everybody has the opportunity to make
these steps on their farms it's just
what steps they're going to use and how
they're gonna make it work and so he he
helps he helps quite a bit a lot of
these farmers I call and I say could you
come to this event
because I think that that you could talk
about this person or you know they would
benefit your from hearing your message
or hey could you just be there and if
somebody has a question then you can
help them answer it and they and these
farmers will do that now because of this
network we've built it because of the
relationships we've built I'm so I'm
very grateful for that and then one last
thing I want to show you is so are we
seeing changes we do pretty extensive
evaluations every three years is what
we've been kind of doing and so this is
from our programming these are the
topics you know establishing a cover
crop a standing soybean using multiple
species diversifying crop rotation for
inclusion of cover crops establishing
cover crop and corn growing cover crop
proceed establishing after harvest using
steroids alignment and the green part on
this and this is a draft this is
literally I was like gosh I show it or
not that this is I want to show it so
they change a little bit as we clean up
continue to clean up the data but this
is in the green is what people are doing
is result attending one of our programs
called the cafe talks so they are using
these practices of cover crops now
because they learned about it at one of
our programs this black area is where we
see the most potential because they're
considering it and so these are the
practices we are going to make sure that
we show work establishing something is
standing soybean establishing a cover
crop that's where I'm going to focus a
lot of efforts because 51 percent of
people are thinking about it and they
need more information to pull the
trigger and make that decision same with
the multi-species cover crop mix let's
help them find five species that really
are going to work for them that they can
control again with establishing a cover
crop and standing corn let's find out if
you fly it on or if you seated or how
you're going to get that cover crop out
there how are you gonna modify equipment
to get that done and what fixes should
you use and then also that inclusion of
diversifying the crop rotation which we
know diversifying our operation is like
the number one tool we have and so if we
can get away from two crops or soybean
on soybean or corn on corn
benefit the system from a whole system
perspective and then the other things
like growing cover crop proceed 44%
people are thinking of doing that so
we're not going to sleep it's not going
to be something I'm gonna make sure they
don't break any laws when they sow seed
to make sure it's not protected or
whatever if they're gonna start selling
things so that they use certified see
their aspects like that but I'm gonna
keep them out of trouble but I'm not
gonna focus on it because they're not
really interested in it and then this is
another reward this podcast is going to
be played over 11,000 times since we
released in August first so when I see
this this keeps me going
this is one of those things that I need
to see that I know that what I'm doing
is is working and if I didn't see this
it was only like ten dots then I doing
it probably not the right tool so let's
find something else and ask the farmers
what do they want what do they need
so I'll take any questions
[Music]
[Applause]
you know I'm not familiar with that
study that they're that they're talking
about but my thought okay when you think
about tillage right you're incorporating
plant material from the surface into the
soil and then you collect that soil
sample and you send it off for analysis
so timing could be everything on that
did they collect it after they chisel
out it or tilt it and then set it off
and I've got big chunks of residue that
have a lot of carbon in it that are
complaining that organic matter - say
yeah this is working or is it its season
and they're capturing the roots from the
Krait you know of it and that's why I
think that test is very difficult
because it depends on timing it depends
on how the sample is collected it
depends on like I think a lot of people
when they transition from a full tillage
to no-till situation you know they
sample containers where you know they
don't have any other residue on the
surface and they could have sampled it
whenever in the season and then they
come back in and that consultants is in
their pickup and they drop the the auger
down to sample they don't brush away the
residue on the surface so then that
inflates that organic matter never that
comes back because it's determining
litter as part of that organic matter
pool but is it you know I mean that's it
so it all depends on what you think is
part of organic matter if I can identify
it I don't think it's organic matter if
I can say that's a piece of corn trash
then to me that's not sort of organic
matter so if it doesn't know it's
residue yeah organic matter something
you can't identify you look at it you
say boy I don't know what that was but I
bet it could've been rude he's a residue
it could have been imposed wasn't the
core part of the question
people to the right question have to do
the examples I haven't look for examples
for that but because the process is
flawed I can't even I can't even make an
assumption on whether that could happen
or not because summit I've seen a lot of
really inflated numbers and no-till
systems to but it's a big a so I don't
find out Ashley I don't mean fight I
guess they just don't really look at
that of her so I did you like yeah
mister annual ryegrass and Dutch white
clover oh yeah I'm sorry I think my
concern was if I did a peer stand of
clover it's a little slower to establish
and so that we would get some more weed
growth that would be coming up through
that so that was my goal to have
something that was would kind of grow
quickly it can't be over relatively
quickly so yeah I mean the mixture is
good I would certainly consider doing a
but
having some kind of grass in there it's
kind of a good good balance see look
here you're no you're not plastic
culture where the the pepper pot was
right next to the roots
at first but you didn't see any high
spikes a nitrogen that might have caused
loss memmer are any issues like that
Oh spikes an extra from having a leg you
in there yeah
no no in fact we saw quite a little bit
of a nitrogen detriment it takes a
little while for clover to get going
right so it's not doing a whole lot of
extra fixing until probably probably
realistically probably next year and
I'll guess to your operational or your
scale for a certified mechanic yeah and
then after you had your pledge stick out
and you had seven establish covered you
didn't see me go and they broadcast
whatever was left over there so I mean
you could do that I'd like to avoid it
part of the issue is that I didn't think
we were getting much benefit when we
were putting down winter I and late
October in Oregon's snow the first week
of November so certainly you couldn't
you could go you drop I don't really
have an easy way just just like bandit
on those areas that you probably drawed
cast got alcohol field in Broadway stood
some speed so certainly you could do
that and if you got a crop that came out
earlier and you thought you could
actually get some good growth then it
might be worth doing we we did probably
because it was coming out like the 28th
Rock dough
that's kind of part of the purposes well
you got we have 40 or 50 percent of our
field with like these strips you can do
a pretty pretty good job
given your New Deal which is the
constraints of the crop and production
system
you