okay so here we are at bradley nook farm
this is run by jay and katya
and we're going to go talk to them
because there's a very special
story about this farm and it's very
heartwarming and i can't wait to meet
them let's go
so jay this is your farm here it is yes
how long you been you guys been here for
um well i i was more or less born here
and it's like about the third day after
i was born i
i came here with my parents and well
they started farming
so you've been here your whole life
basically yes yes amazing
so this was a dairy it was a dairy yeah
yeah yeah
yeah everything was manual very hard
work so you've been
basically been a farmer or involved with
farming your entire life and
well that's that's what happens when
you're born on a farm base
you know it's hard to escape yeah so um
and i noticed in the area like there's a
lot of farming in this
in this area yes yeah yeah that's sort
of
dairy farming and in fact
like 50 years ago practically every
house in the area yeah was a small farm
of
some kind so your entire environment
your family life
like past on your heritage it's all
farming oh yeah everything's fine
everything's farming yeah yeah when when
you've got a family dairy farm
it's so time-consuming uh needs so much
energy and commitment
it's what you do you don't have time for
hobbies or
you know you get up in the morning you
start looking after the cows
and by the time you finished at night
you're
just too knackered to do anything
basically a lot of farmers they live and
breathe this stuff and it's
oh yes definitely yeah it's a way of
life you know it is it is a way of life
it's not it's more than a lifestyle it's
an all-encompassing
wow and that's what makes it so
difficult for
farmers to contemplate change yeah
it's not like another industry where you
like go to work
somewhere else you could go anywhere to
go to work
yeah it is a very distinct way of life
so far as to say to a farmer and say
like you've got to change this whole
facility right now and stop farming
animals like that would be a daunting
concept like that they wouldn't even
something that would even cross their
mind no no it would seem
impossible yeah you've got to have a
very good
um you know like offer or
incentive for people to change yeah all
right let's go to a different um
part of the farm and we'll talk about um
we'll start talking about your change
could call it like a awakening kind of
thing wasn't it
um yeah sort of but but um
you know i think the rocks set in for me
when i
i learned transcendental meditation
about 30 years ago i really it would be
40 years ago now
and everybody connected with that was
vegan
or vegetarian yeah even back then and
so um i found it difficult to look after
the animals and then
sit down and eat them basically which is
what
you know that was what you were expected
to do that was the way things were
um so i became vegetarian then and
um so
when the when we approached the vegan
society
i was good and ready to take the next
step wow but it was
how to do it on the farm and
i really wanted to produce food on the
farm
i didn't want to sort of sell it and
walk away and say
okay i've had enough of this i can't do
it anymore
we want to provide a some kind of
template or example that you can do
something different you can
feed people yeah but you don't have to
have fields full of animals
and animals going to the slaughterhouse
or
animals having calves every year yeah
um permanently pregnant basically and
you just don't need to do it in order to
feed
the the world's population and in order
in order to live the farming lifestyle
that
is truly hard and true to your tradition
you have to
that's it you you feel responsible for
the farm
you know it's um some
obviously you enjoy being in the the
countryside who wouldn't
yeah um and let's face it we need
farmers yeah we need farmers but
we don't necessarily need the no the
animals
the stuff that goes with it that's
30 years worth of crap you can see the
where
two cows used to live and they've got
the water bowl in front of them
we had probably 80 80 milk cows tied up
in there
okay to be milked every day and
so in the winter you'd get up get your
wheelbarrow
clean the manure from behind the cows
and then the day starts
yeah so back back then with the um
because
being a dairy you wouldn't have any sex
semen back then
did you have to send any of the calves
away um
yes the the most of the male calves yeah
had to go to it was a regular
like friday run to derby
uh cattle market to to take the calves
to market
so and back then the male cast would be
sent for beef or growing for veal um you
know i don't know i presume they went
for beef
yeah but um i was ours were not
extreme dairy breeds so possibly they
they went for beef and i think um
probably holsteins or
more extreme dairy breeds probably go
for veal i'd say
yeah a lot of them are they actually
kill them on the farm
yeah england yeah no we never did that
no
i see over here we've got some some
little friends over here
yeah yeah yes 17 friends
this is what they for the winter wow
and um they eat on average 10 of those a
week
wow even the few that we've got so um
and how many have you got
17. you've got 17 here so only a small
amount of animals
oh yes comparably to like oh yeah a
large scale
yes yes and that just shows the
environmental impact of keeping
livestock yeah because
ours are not producing anything no they
eat ten of these a week just to live
just and if you were fattening them for
beef
you'd have to supplement that with
grains barley or something or
if they were milking obviously they'd
have enormous
energy demands and eating what they call
dairy concentrates which
which contain micronized protein stuff
from all over the world
in particular soya which is very
damaging yeah
and and of course cereals that people
could eat of course yeah yeah
a lot of people think that because uh
like they see the cows on the grass and
they don't ever supplement their diets
yeah yeah no that's only part of it um
yeah there are
there are people making grass-fed
and beef and away milk but um
they're still harvesting a lot of grass
so the environmental cost of
just producing food through animals is
just
it's just magnifying all of the
resources
it just doesn't make sense anymore with
the the growing world population and the
climate crisis and the loss of habitat
uh agriculture is responsible for and
when you look around on the countryside
it's just it all is this flattened grass
exactly yeah yeah people think that's
just normal that's just normal
no it isn't it's um i mean
that's panda hello panda you look like a
panda
hello darling so so you said you started
to make the connection you went you went
vegetarian and you still had
uh cattle on your farm that you were
having to yeah yeah
can you explain that what that felt like
making the connection to the animals and
still having to do what you had to do
kind of thing you in two minds or
torn a little bit or well i was very
torn because i mean
you look after somebody like this and
or panda panda should have been a beef a
beef animal
and you sort of look after them and
i mean look into their eyes you can see
there's somebody in there
and then you have to put them in a
trailer and take them to the abattoir
it's just
it's um like it must feel like because
you're kind of their only carer they've
never known that it's like a sense of
betrayal
it is a sense of betrayal you feel you
like sending somebody you know to be
murdered basically in
terrifying circumstances we used to go
to a
you know big abattoir in shropshire and
like at the front it's all like glossy
like a supermarket
and you go around the back where the
farmers take the animals and there's
pens where you put the animals and
and you know you can smell the smells
from the
slaughter process coming out the back
and you can tell that they
you know as soon as they you can tell
they've got a pretty pretty good idea
what's coming for yeah
and you can feel the stress in there you
know the whole it's like a nightmare
place to go
and um you can see you've seen the
images of cows trying to escape the
slaughterhouse
yeah yeah yeah i never saw that i never
saw inside
yeah it was not something i had an
ambition to do
so as farmers even though they're
connected to the animals on the farm do
you think they have a level of
disconnect from the slaughterhouse
process like um
yes you couldn't do it otherwise
but i couldn't do it so i
obviously knew there was a different way
it had to be a different way a different
way
yeah you didn't have to didn't have to
put yourself to it let alone the animals
just the act of putting them in the
trailer it must completely freak them
out well it does
because they were wondering where
they're going and then when they get
there
so you've got names for all these yes
yes yeah yeah panda and
blue badger
hole in the head yeah we treat them like
individuals yeah but we have to realize
that they're cattle
yeah and they have different instincts
and different ways of reacting to the
behaviors
yeah so how long have you
has it been since you have been
operating as a normal
you know beef farmer it could be four
years now
i think it's four years um since the
vegan society
visited and um yeah we sat around the
kitchen table and
and they said well there's something
else you can do on your farm apart from
keeping animals
and that's when we decided yeah that's
what we've been looking for that's what
we want to do
yeah so phil was pretty crazy like
thinking that
you know like going back to that mindset
where you're in before and then now that
now you don't even have to worry about
taking them to this corner no no it's
just it's it's incredible
you can't believe what a a revelation
and a
a life-changing experience it was not to
have to do that
anymore and to know that um
well people animals like panda won't
have to go through what what they used
to have to go through
but as i say i was in the same position
of as other farmers up till then
i didn't know what else i could do yeah
and um yeah that would be interesting to
talk about like what would be
like let's just say there's farmer out
there that kind of felt feels the same
way they're kind of in two minds and
they feel like there's no other way like
what would you say
like to someone like that that we're at
that place in time where you were at
um well just
take stock of what you're doing you know
real think think about
what effect you're having on the animals
what effect you're having on the
planet and yourself
and realize that you don't have to do
this
you can do something else you could
grow vegetables like we hoped to still
not started
um you could turn your farm into a
sanctuary
um or you could grow trees go into
forestry
do what you know just you've got this
farm most people own the farm i know
some people
rent the farm so it's a lot more
difficult for them
um but you know the land is there you
can do
whatever you want with it yeah so what
have you chosen to do here um
well we we we've been delayed by covid
the same as everybody else but we should
have been producing vegetables this
spring yeah
and that's the overall plan that a small
area of the farm will produce as much
food as
all the animals used to um yeah we'll
grow vegan organic vegetables which
need no animal inputs whatsoever amazing
that's crazy like to think like this is
17 cows
what they're eating like what an
intensive dairy in canada
needs to feed them oh yeah yeah it's
it's just unfathomable like
um yeah it's one thing that um i mean
that will be different that i've been
sort of wandering around this huge site
for
years on my own since my dad died and
hopefully in a couple of years time
there might be
12 20 people employed here
okay so that will be a massive boost for
local employment yeah and you know
really useful jobs as well you know yeah
yeah definitely fulfilling jobs
definitely yeah
yeah that's that's something that you
see farmers saying a lot that that
you know that this movement of
plant-based eating it's just like
attacking their their livelihood
and um like if new markets open up and
you know there's more plant-based foods
available that food needs to be grown
and produced
and you know it's got to come from
somewhere well if more people
um give up meat and dairy
the market will force people to produce
food differently
it'll decide what the farmers move into
yeah and it will provide an opportunity
the opportunity will be there the market
will be there
yeah and it'll be stupid to do anything
else
yeah well it would make life on the
planet possible in the future
we've got to do it and it would be a
better world without slaughterhouses
that's
for sure definitely yeah absolutely
so this is like a little portable so
it's almost like it looks like a truck
container it does yeah yeah it
used to be a milk delivery truck well so
well that's even better so this was a
dairy milk
delivery truck we've got a cheese kettle
that um
we heat the oats and the water and the
other ingredients okay
sort of extract the products from the
oats
yeah it is a mini mini uh factory really
yeah wow see how crazy is that you can
make a little mini oat drink factory in
the back
backyard of your farm there that's it
you don't even
you don't even need a suitable building
you can convert something like this
and literally drop it off the back of a
truck and next day
could be in business and no animals um
being you know chained up and on a
milking machine in the milking club
absolutely
no no no carvings
no calves being taken away that's it
it's the only ethical way
yeah that's it wants you to if you want
to put something on your cereal in the
morning then your coffee
yeah it doesn't need to come out of a
cow no it doesn't need to go through all
that
no that process exactly don't have to
impregnate the cow
all that yeah because the milk is coming
from a cow that's been pregnant
don't forget that part now this just
seems like such a
insane way to get a beverage to put on
top of your cereal
very yeah it's such a such a sweat isn't
it basically
all unnecessary and better if
if people didn't do it really yeah yeah
this is the way forward
it is and it's all assert everything
every ingredient is certified
organic so it's it's not just animal
free it's
the highest possible production
standards amazing
well i came to the farm because jay said
i want to get out of farming but the
idea then of course was
renewable energy wow okay you are also
very much bound by what your land is
capable of producing yeah
growing up if the farmers in wales say i
can't grow avocados
that's true but you know other things
are possible and not everybody has to
produce food
you know we need timber you know we need
we need carbon capture you know other
other things are possible but they will
need a lot of support also from this new
uh hopefully from the new government
subsidies scheme
and that that might actually open a few
doors for people to get out of life
stuck into doing something different
with the land
yeah no definitely there's there's
always different alternatives not just
food i mean if you can't grow something
there's
there's like like you put a trucking
container at the back here
[Music]
it doesn't matter if they've got some in
front of them already there's always
something better
i think the two oh here comes rosie
rosie
we're rolling the hay
[Music]
they got is it got protein in that that
oh yeah yeah it has got protein
where the cows get their protein from
yeah well
they're all vegans don't don't tell
anybody
so who's got the most interesting
personality out of all the cows
[Music]
some of them are cheeky here comes uh
this one's called hole in there yes that
one's cheeky
yeah it's a bit cheeky so a lot of the
cows have gone to sanctuaries
we send we send
around 60 to hillside animal sanctuary
in norfolk
who took them all and that was amazing
especially satisfying because they could
all stay with their calves or the cows
i think when you change you've got to
accept that what you did previously
wasn't a good thing yeah i think that's
a big hurdle for people that you know
you've got to say
you think about all those hundreds of
animals who went to the slaughterhouse
or you think of all that
the imported protein
maize soya whatever that that you were
responsible for being grown on what used
to be
grassland or forest and which is now
intensive cropland until you start
really thinking about
it it's just what you do and
they talk about farming being a
close-knit community it is because
farmers talk farming amongst farmers and
and nobody else has a clue what it's
about or
you can't relate to other people i mean
i always say that um
farmers interact with animals more than
more than uh you know your average vegan
activist does
you know and so they know they know more
than me how much of a personality these
animals have
so like i try to sort of ask them to
like you know
you know you know more than me like how
much these animals are individuals and
they
want to because you've got years of um
living with them literally living with
them
and you recognize that families
have different personalities and you can
say
oh yes she's just like her mother wow
yeah so they pass on their their
attributes absolutely yes
so how do you think that um someone
could be so connected to animals but
still eat them
i think it's this thing tradition isn't
it an expectation
and um like
community it's the people define
themselves as
oh i i like my meat i like my cheese
it's who i am one thing um
referring back to your question uh you
know if farmers care so much for the
animals
i can part of the answer is
that farmers care for the animals to the
point
where they will retreat when it comes to
the slaughter
and you will hear anecdotes and people
will say oh i love the animals but when
they get slaughtered you know i just
have to clear out i can't be around
yeah so i guess like a lot of farmers
will just put them on the truck and then
that'll be it like i know some
some driving to this look like
smallholders will drive them to the
slaughterhouse yeah yeah but uh some
some will just lead them onto the truck
and that's it and then
forget that we're back to back to the
new bed yeah yeah
put it tuck it away in the back of their
mind and
most people are safely removed from the
physical reality of it they know it
happens but they they don't like to
think about it they like to buy the
little packet of
something with something with a silly
name like steak or
veal that doesn't actually refer to an
animal it's kind of a product
you're going to go to the supermarket
you buy a little tray of
yeah it doesn't say this was rosie no no
rosie went to the slaughterhouse and
didn't want to die
this is a piece of british raised red
grass-fed uh steak it's detached from
the individual isn't it yeah
yeah yeah so what we're
what we sort of think is well you can
get your protein
you can get your carbohydrate you can
get your vitamins and minerals
you don't have to feed all that stuff to
a cow first
then kill the cow yeah yeah why bother
it's it's just all bad what a silly
thing to do why not just
eat the stuff in the first place yeah
it's hazel's like the best seat
oh it turns definitely yeah like i just
push it it's got the best cushioning
it's very good here you go i'll be your
personal servant
okay so this is uh this is the product
here this is this is what you produced
in the amazing little facility out the
back look at that looks beautiful
and it's in this traditional glass
bottle here returnable
and this so you guys are doing this
actually you guys are actually
producers for uh like an operation
called refarmed yeah
yeah refarmed and and what their goal is
is to turn
animal-based farmers into oat drink
producers yeah yeah wow
oh look look at that
it reminds me of like a creamy
like like porridge well i guess it's
because of oats
but it is super creamy it does yeah it's
really good
so this is all this is just just very
very simple
ingredients in here now you've got it in
the bottle here
like and it's been a long sort of
progression from
you know where you come from to here but
um
you haven't been alone in this you've
had helpers so who's helped you along
the way to get you to where
you guys to where you are now um well
first of all the vegan society
and then they kind of offshoot the vegan
organic network
okay who um who are promoting
animal-free agriculture wow in in all
its forms
and laterally reformed and that's the
whole idea of refarmed isn't it
yeah it's to provide a real solid
genuine alternative that real people can
do
wow to change their lives and change the
way we react
the way we interact with the planet as
whole amazing so it's all good
well you have to say that refund only
found us because
of the help we had from the vegan
society of the vegan organic network
amazing because obviously
there was a lot of media exposure and
that's how they knew about us
if you ever return hopefully we can
offer you some vegan organic vegetables
amazing that would be that would be like
veganic
vegetables veganic farming is there
is a way forward isn't it absolutely so
they don't need any animal inputs
or anything like that no no no no manure
um
nothing at all amazing yeah well they
said that
they say it can't be done but it can be
done and it will be done
yes the the trick is um the knowledge is
out there but
on a very small scale in many places
um it just needs upscaling upscaling and
when you get the message out there
hopefully uh people just have a
change of heart or there's a massive
change in demand and everyone's gonna
you know a lot of people might need
something to fall back on and look
oat drink is where it's at and
yeah and for farmers don't say oh dear
somebody's trying to put me out of
business say
somebody's offering me a new business
something
exciting different something that that
enables a future for everybody yeah for
generations to come
i think we finished the that of well
unless there's anything that you guys
would want to add
support hillside animal sanctuary yes
yes
amazing hillside animal sanctuary we're
going to leave those
everyone that we mentioned we're going
to leave down below especially hillside
as well if you want to support the
animals that have gone from
this previous farm to the sanctuary
and quite a few other farms and quite a
few other farms as well
so thank you hillside thank you refarmed
thank you
vegan society and the organic the vegan
organic network
so what an amazing story hey what an
amazing place a story of like
personal revolution of like awakening of
someone making the connection
of like um moving forwards into the
future with more ethical
farming better for the environment and
just seeing
those animals in there and they've got
another chance now and all the other
animals that got taken to the sanctuary
is just a beautiful story and
the oat milk is fantastic the oat drink
is fantastic
and it's just a really positive story
and i hope this inspires some other
farmers out there who are
they might be at a crossroads i don't
like taking the animals to the
slaughterhouse well there's another way
and this is the future really
plant-based food is the future so
[Music]
amazing
you