for small scale Farmers I know you've
been wondering what are the most
profitable cops that you can manage to
do and earn some decent these are
farmers who have less than an acre of
land and most of them own one age of or
what is commonly known as 50 by 100 land
is becoming Scar and we are increasing
in population but at the end of the day
you can still make some decent profit
and especially the youth who are
graduating and you have small pce of
this is a good way to employ yourself
these are five most profitable crops
that you can grow they don't require cap
they don't require much knowledge they
fast maturing and also they have a wet
by W Market I mean you can sell them
even through your immediate neighbor and
regardless of the marketly imagine you
still get people who buy as long as you
maintain the C as minimum as possible
but first let understand what is profit
profit is the amount that you get after
deducting your cost from the revenue you
earn what do I mean I mean if you have
10,000 heads of cabbage and you sell
each at 15 shs you manag to get
150,000 sh that is Le that is not profit
if you had 10 produce each cabbage it
means your total cost of producing the
10,000 heads of cabbage was 100,000 shs
now to get your profit you take the
150,000 sh you L their 100,000 sh you
get your profit as 50,000 sh that is the
profit most Farmers don't know how toate
this they assume once you've sold your
produ that is no that is usually not the
profit that iseven and when you are
factoring the remember also to pay
yourself assume that what you put there
the energy the time and all the
resources that you put there when you
cultivating this crops assuming that you
employed someone else who similar work
how much would he have charged you if
you would have charged 300 or 500 Shing
that is your cost of Labor and you have
to factor in to get a true value of your
profit in 2025 these five crops can give
you some good cash but let us be
realistic by this I mean you cannot
expect super abnormal profits in family
there's nothing like making tens of
millions in one day now profitability in
agricult is you make 10% profit 20%
profit the problem with most of us we
are greedy and we want to have AB normal
profit we want to make 100,000 from
investing 1,000 that one doesn't happen
so if you invest 100 and you get 200 as
profit that's okay these are the five
props that you can manage to do and get
some good profits and number one is
thiss in short
this can be
either P or all those types of PS and
good thing with p is that they are fast
maturing and then also number two they
are not perishable number three you can
sell to anyone after they are dry and
you harvested them you can take to the
local market or to the seral stores so
they will still buy this makes it a good
CR to do the other thing that makes it a
good CR to do is the cost of producing
it imagine in an a of an you only need
2.5 kgs so this will cost you roughly
around 250 Shing if you put now all the
other cost of producing them around 500
Shing for chemicals and maybe an extra
additional cost of 1,000 you'll get a
total production cost of around
2,700 and 50 if you are good at it and
the season is okay and you manage to
harvest around 1.5 B each weigh 90 kgs
and you are also lucky to sell at 80
Shillings per kilo then you will earn
10,800
from your 1.5 back the second most
profitable crop for small scale Farmers
is a garden pie or what is often known
as Mii Mii tend to Bel by many though
they are also quite expensive the funny
thing with Mii it tends to come from
only one region around Yanda County but
if the farmers can manage to tap into
this Market there is high demand the
other Supply that may be experienced
around the year is also short live
meaning that prices are often High above
70 shs if you are a small scale farmer
with a name of anre you only need 2 kgs
this one will cost you 1,800 if you add
other cost of 1,500 units it means that
your total cost of of production will be
around 3,300 sh if you manage it well
thisa can manage to give you 200 KES of
Green Piece all n selling it on a market
price of 4 Shing per kilo you manage to
get a roughly revenue of 8,000 Shing if
you L your 3,300 the cost of production
you are left with a profit of around
4,700 shs and remember this is the
lowest price of 40 Shing per kilo
sometimes it goes to over 70 Shillings
per kilo the third most profitable crop
for small scale Farmers is D or what is
often known as a coriander the good
thing with coriander is it's fast within
30 to 35 days it's ready for harvesting
and my doesn't need those expensive
chemicals or even fertilizer you just
plant it and manage it and that's all
you have good to go and within those at
least let's say 40 days you will manage
to have harvested around 200 kilos from
the farm if you sell each kg for 40
Shillings then it gives you a Le of
8,000 Shillings if you L your cost of
2,300 Shillings you are left with a
profit of
5,700 this is a good profit for small
scale farmers in a month and you canate
this such that you'll always have this
produce every month making you an a
source of income a stable every month my
fourth most profitable crop for small
scale Farmers is green maze what is
green maze green maze is what is known
as mahindi Yak the demand for Mahia
green has been on the rise most people
are loving and even those who cook the
very all boiled me they buy it from
these people because they know how to
select the best one and the sweetest one
and remember the secet on this is to do
the varieties that they love not all
maze varieties is good for roasting we
have to get this and if you're totally
interested in this make sure you've
watched our video on the best maze
variety for Maze roers that one that
once you have it they will come running
for you and sure that you do the maze
that they love in one of you need
roughly 1 kg of this m these will cost
you around 500 shs if you add your cost
of production that is maybe wiing also
fertilizer it will give you a total cost
of 2,500 Shillings now this farmer will
manage to produce around 2,000 pieces of
maze or lot is often called as if he
sells it at 5 Shillings each at lowest
then he makes up a levenue of 10,000
Shillings if you L now the cost of 2,500
sh he makes a profit of
7,500 sh the good thing with green maze
is one but you don't have to sell it
green if you don't get to the market you
can manage to let it dry and by letting
this dry you will harvest around five
bags each weigh 90 kg so if you sell
each bag at around 2,000 Shillings you
earn a levenue of 10,000 sharings
however by letting it dry it may add an
extra cost of 2,000 sharings making a
total cost of production to 4,500 sh if
you L 4,500 from the 10,000 Rue you are
l to the profit of
5,500 sh my last most profitable crop
for small scale Farmers is indigenous
vegetables and by vegetables I mean man
amandas we mean
plant all those indigenous vegetables
why they most profitable is one they are
cheap to produce Imagine by less than 50
sh you have a packet of seeds that you
can plant and give you a 1,000 sh then
the good thing with them is that but
they are not that much highly per then
the other thing you can Harvest for
quite some time and also you have a
wider Market including the neighbors you
can send to the neighbor okay so these
indigenous vegetables they are good
source of income they are also quite
profitable if done well and by
consistency you can be selling to the
local grocery stores oh mama once they
realize that you have it they'll always
be coming to you because what they need
is sustainable Supply and this applies
to all these five crops once you have a
sustainable supply all year around that
you have mastered on these several props
once they realize that they will always
be coming to you