[Music]
do
good evening welcome to the farming
podcast brought to you by private
property
my name is mali wago and welcome for
joining us this
um tuesday evening i almost forgot
i was about to say thursday evening
clearly i'm rushing into quarter two
already
but welcome for joining us this tuesday
evening today's show
is a bit interesting because we get to
speak to someone
who's built their career within the
agricultural sector
but doing something slightly different
not being a farmer
not being a marketer but we are speaking
to
an agri-journalist photographer
who's also had an agribusiness within
the agri-valley chain so we're going to
get some
insights into the different or
alternative farming methods
that are available to ensure that our
beautiful
sector that we all dearly love which is
the agricultural sector
remains sustainable for the long term i
think
it's important to contributing towards
food security
but at the same time being sustainable
um
i just want to say that before we
introduce our guests
please continue to follow us on social
media on uh
facebook twitter instagram um you would
find all the information
and the weekly posters of our private
property farming podcast on our social
media
not forgetting the um the other shows
that we have
on our channel as well um relating to
property whether you're a first
time home buyer whether you're
interested in property investments
um or when you whether you'd like to see
new new show houses
um openings of new properties etc
private property and especially our
youtube channel
has got you so if you miss any of our
weekly um
shows um you can obviously catch or um
the repeats
of those shows on our youtube channel on
the
various playlists that are available
thank you once again and um continue to
share like and comment on all our live
uh uh conversations most importantly
because you get to speak to the
to the guests that we have onto the show
directly but
um i'd like to introduce our guest today
her name is mirinda lowe
and she is like i said an
agri-journalist
photographer let's get to know about who
she
is and her role to the agricultural
sector
marinda how are you doing great thanks
for having me and thank you to
all your listeners and viewers great to
be here thank you
thank you i'm sure this is going to be
interesting conversation so i really
can't wait
but uh before we get into the
nitty-gritty miranda
please just give us a short introduction
what you've done in the agri industry
especially with your compost making
business etc and what you do
now as an agri journalist etc
great question thank you very much um
my composting of my agri career actually
started as a as a packaging technologist
it was a
export table grape company exporting
grapes to
to the eu and to europe and beyond and
they wanted to convert from conventional
farming to organic farming
so the farm
and it was very sandy soil so what
needed to be done
and especially in organic farming is
that you need to build the soil
structure and add organic matter the
best way to do that is composting
so i was sent on a composting
course to austria um and i
completed the composting course there
and then i started
with idli reeling ace we started
reliance compost
which is now a national
composting company providing organic
compost to quite a few
farms and landscapers and so on
so that basically was the base also of
of organic farming and sustainable
farming as the compost
and then um eventually i actually
started writing about composting and
organic farming
and that led to a career in in
journalism took me to media 24 to eu
magazine and high school art and then
freelancing and event writing
agricultural articles on anything
ranging from
quinoa farming to goat farming and
alternative farming systems in south
africa
wow so but what is the what does
alternative farming systems mean
are we talking about changing soil and
rather farming
and compost or um you know the the new
term or kid on the block is
hydroponically etc
using growing medium etc um uh
this is regarding into crop production
but maybe moving on to livestock
what are some of the alternative farming
methods but if you could just explain
that concept broadly so we could
understand
i think alternative farming is is
looking
at historical conventional farming
but looking at it from a different angle
or farming better or smarter
um it can also mean alternative farming
systems such as vertical farming
if you live in high density areas and
you don't have land
surface that you farm vertically you
rooftop farming we see that bee hives
are being kept on top of
skyscrapers so
people farming in water acroponics
hydroponics people farming
oysters avalone and seawater kelp
and then also fresh water farming so
alternative farming is not only looking
at conventional farming
and doing it differently in terms of
organic but it could also be totally
different
farming systems you know
what are some of the upsides and
downsides of having to explore
alternative farming systems uh you
mentioned for example
uh instead of farming like the old
traditional ways
people can now farm vertically it sounds
very fancy and technical
does it come at a high price etc you
spoke about
bees being kept in skyscrapers um
you know what type of infrastructure and
uh
investment is required in that and who
looks after the bees at the top of the
skyscrapers you know what i mean
so what are what are the pros and cons
of alternative farming systems
um well
the reason for alternative farming is
that the
old or historical ways of farming is not
working anymore you see that
conventional farmings they need to to
add more chemicals they need to increase
the dosages
but also um our export markets are
starting to demand less and less
chemical sprays and
the standards are very very high in
terms of what for example fruit farmers
are allowed to use and spray
on the apples and pears and citrus that
goes to international markets
so from the one hand there's a demand
from customers
to reduce chemical and other input and
also
it becomes costly but also um
we need to look at our resources our
waters are water and
soils being diminished so from that
point of view we also need to look
differently
or look for alternative ways of farming
um
so there's pressure from both sides both
from nature and the resources we have
available and then the markets itself
the demands that we look the demand that
we look differently to
to how we farm um and then also
we need to develop new markets we we
want to start farming
different products um we need more bees
to pollinate
uh the more uh almond trees and
blueberries that
that are being planted in south africa
so you find that from
one industry another industry grows and
you also find that farmers need to
diversify even more in terms of the
product
range that they have available so um i
don't know if that answers your question
yeah i mean you spoke about from your
answer
you've also just alluded to you know the
reason why alternative farming methods
are critical
is that they help us preserve our
natural resources
you know um and that being water and
soil which is such a big
uh component into the farming industry
and you've i think
mentioned that you've just done a bit of
work or research around
water and soil can you share something
something about those two elements
for us i think the two
the two is very inter interrelated to
each other
um uh the example that i mentioned was
the sound
that when you put nutrients when you
give nutrients to the plant
and water and if there's not a good soil
structure your water will and
your nutrients will leach out so what
you need to do and what certainly what
what south africa needs to do is build
the organic
matter content in the soil what that
means basically is adding
uh composting in the soil or on top of
the soil
mulching that not only helps
with the evaporation of moisture from
the soil
it prevents weeds growing in in terms of
the mulch that you put on top um
but it also helps to create a soil
structure it
creates aggregates if that's the word i
can use that
help to maintain soil in the moisture in
the water so
your soil quality and soil structure um
goes hand in hand with the type
and the amount of water that you use um
and then um yes but it determine depends
on which
soil type you use and also which crop
and how you
are you water are you managing your
water and what type of irrigation so
there's
many other parameters in terms of water
usage that one can look at to reduce the
amount of water that one uses yeah going
back to uh
compost melinda because you ran a
business uh within the composting and i
suppose
some of the key insights that you're
sharing as well
um are you know real life
or lived experiences within your compost
business
and you mentioned that you know you sold
the compost to farmers
as well as uh private individuals in
their home gardens
um and i'm just thinking yeah i mean as
as a farmer who's just farming uh on
fast stretches of land
um you know that wants to far more
sustainably i'm sure compost
might not work for him or her um you
know unless they tried different
methods to preserve soil etc but
um do you think for professionals who
are farming you know in the backyard
gardens or sorry individuals who are
growing food systems in their backyard
gardens etc how
how can they preserve their compost time
and time again
because sometimes as a farmer myself i
get queries from individuals saying
oh my crops died what happened and then
you know they'd send their picture
um or someone would say i just bought a
new house
my you know i can never grow anything in
this
in this backyard garden what's wrong
with the soil you know is the soil too
red or yellow or whatever the case is
and people sometimes need advice so um
you know for people then maybe who are
not sure about their soil compositions
and want to go into compost
and maybe just do the two or mix the two
in there in their uh private spaces um
how can they preserve compost how can
they
ensure that you know they can grow
healthy food
um for that for their for their own
individual or family consumption
sure it's uh it's a lot of questions in
in one um
i'll try to try and give you lots of
answers as well
um composting and using compost is just
one way of adding organic matter in the
soil
adding plant matter back into the soil
because you need to feed
the microbes and the soil life that's
inside the soil
you don't necessarily only have to use
compost you don't have to buy compost if
you don't have it but if you've got
leaves or grass or weeds
you can you can use that all all of
those are organic matter that you can
put back in the soil
something else in terms of crops dying
and
using companion planting or making use
of a system or method called companion
planting
is also beneficial companion companion
planting means that you plant certain
plants
next to each other the one is the
natural repellent
of pests of the other so it means that
they
that attract certain um insects that
will that are predators of pests
and it also means some some plants
actually secrete stuff in their roots
that actually help
manage soil health so companion planting
is planting different
plants together that are beneficial for
the other ones growth
or protection so composting is one
aspect
of of farming or soil health but there's
also other aspects such as using mulch
mulch is a layer of organic matter
whether it's old leaves or grass or
cuttings or whatever so using that
on top of the soil to prevent weed
growth that is
that's another way of preventing
moisture loss and preventing weed for
using a mulch um and then
companion planting as i mentioned it
also attracts insects that's
important to reduce your insecticide
um inputs um
what are the other there's so many
questions in one but composting you
don't need
an encompassing is not always practical
or viable in terms of cost
for usual a huge fines yes on commercial
scale
ah thank you before i move on to the
next question i just want to
uh encourage any of you watching at home
this evening we are joined by
marinda low who's an agri-journalist
slash photographer um and i suppose
entrepreneur in the composting space
or agripreneur should i say and today
we're talking about alternative farming
methods and earlier on if you
uh missed uh some critical points that
you mentioned is that
um she highlighted a few of uh examples
of what
alternative farming methods are so um if
you missed the first part of
the show you could definitely catch it
um on our youtube channel but please
comment
um ask any questions that you have to
marinda
unless you want her to clarify
specifically on farming sustainably
on alternative farming methods
conventional farming organic compost
um yeah this show is for you melinda i
just want to
find out um uh with your
now i'm just thinking with the farmer's
head yeah with the composting business
and for people that are listening to you
and maybe would want to try
being in the composting industry or
start their own compost business
and you mentioned the word organic in
some examples that you explained
is every single compost in the
composting business
is it is it a hundred percent organic so
when you're going into the business do
you have to be certified organic
because i know to be organically
certified requires
some um someone to go through uh
what a certification process of some
sort
i think we need to distinguish between
organic farming and sustainable farming
organic farming is
um it's when when you go through a
certification process
to get a label that you could put in
your product
that gets sold as organic and organic
product in a retailer so the retailer
might have some standards and there
might be organic body that might have
standards
and then your product is certified
organic so it's
uh to form organically morally
to a a certification system um
to farm sustainably is to look after the
resources that you put in whether it's
looking at the chemical inputs it's not
necessarily an organic that you're not
allowed to use sprays or insecticides or
weed killers and so on but it's the
sustainable use
of all your inputs um something else i
just want to mention we we're focusing
on on
organic farming and and composting and
soil based but
um we alternative farming systems could
also
involve farming in and with water and
that
that is aquaculture which means your
plant is
is physically in a liquid medium it's
physically hanging in water so
the roots are suspended in in the water
um but um and aquaponics is
um aquaculture actually sorry um
wrong way other way around is that you
you farm
um you farm fish or you farm crustacean
or portland or something
so it's a it's water animals water
plants that's been
um it's being farmed or often in
combination
with plants so that the nutrient-rich
water of the fish
let's say use that example is then fed
through to herbs and other plants
um which then purify the water and use
the nutrients and then the purified
water filtered back to the
animals the the fish so it's a closed
loop system
not always closed loop but it's it's a
water-based system
so alternative farming systems could
intel
farming on land but it can also entail
farming within water
wow so moving on to something else i
think maybe could also that could also
come
much closer to home for our audience
this evening is that
um also you have like a non-conventional
career right um
it's not a traditional um uh line that
one would pick up
based on the um the skill set that you
have
like photography and you started writing
first and then you moved into
uh journalism etc what what are some of
the
non-farming opportunities that exist in
the agricultural
sector um you know based on
your experience and looking at you how
your career
has also turned excellent
question um in terms of photography uh
what is interesting when i was
researching uh uh
uh writing articles for south africa dot
co dot ca
uh i wrote about farming and
agricultural commodities in south africa
and that was
translated into all 11 south african
languages it was a huge project
but the absence of good photos
of south african farmers and south
african products and south african
commodities that i realize is also a
huge opportunity that there's
not a lot of images available you know
of
of um trout cages you know we're trying
to being
bred and things like millet
in south africa you know um in terms of
non-aggregate cultural opportunities in
within the agricultural sector
um sure there's a lot i'm thinking of
venues you know a few
wedding venues um training venues um
if you want to train farm workers
um you know
how to prune how to how to trim
the hooves of your goats you know that
kind of training venues
um i'm thinking of restaurants coffee
shops um
farm stores something else that's
probably
non non-farming but definitely related
to agricultural commodities is
processing i mean if you've got
you tomato farmer and your market is
satisfied with
saturated with tomatoes and you're
sitting with tomatoes
then preserving those products is a
secondary
secondary industry whether you jam it uh
dry it speckle it um
you know the you know further processing
of agricultural products
um certainly agri-tourism is is
huge and i think that that's also in
terms of people wanting to buy property
i think that
could also be an option to look at is is
how can i use this property also not
only to farm but as a
destination probably a tourism
destination it could be people wanting
to
take part and see what happens on the
working farm but it might also be people
wanting to escape the city and just
experience fresh farm air so there's so
many
aspects of of agriculture
that that doesn't that doesn't
necessarily
involve getting your hands dirty um
yeah but um and and then involving into
into other value-added products and and
and offerings that's related to a farm
yeah i like that example that you
brought in with
uh your photography that you know you
you found
a gap pretty much um
where you can't just yeah
i can attest to the fact that there
aren't so many pictures
of south african farms farmers or
farming you know
and the ones that you do find online are
always just um
mostly repetitive or it's a head holding
a cell phone
um or when you're talking about farming
it's just attracting the field
but you could see that these
destinations are non
african destinations and also non-south
african
and so um with your photography um
what did that entail were you just
taking photos around different farms
were you traveling and finding very
beautiful destinations that exist within
the sub
uh in south africa uh and taking
pictures of that
so infusing it with a bit of tourism and
farming
um what type of pictures did you send in
where did they land up
um it's it's interesting what kind of
what kind of photos get sold but also
what kind of photos are people
commenting on and what people want to
see is is
for example um uh one's
one series of articles i wrote was how
to clip
the hooves of your goat and why it's
important to trim
the hooves of a goat but no one no one
understands
not many people understand how important
it is for a goat to have
the hooves regularly clipped because he
needs to it he needs to
walk far and trade very securely to get
to where he wants to go it's a climbing
animal
so i took photos of someone trimming
you know cutting step by step of the
hooves of a goat
certainly not a glamorous it wasn't a
glamorous day
but it was fantastic um and then another
one for example was blueberry farming is
how people how blueberries are grown
that it grows in
in peat it's very it's important uh
if they grow in pots they don't grow in
soil and
the nutrient goes through the water and
dripper systems into
into the individual buckets or pots
and then the different varieties how
it's been picked um
how it's been packaged and also
just being outside eating directly
from from the plant and chatting to
people while they're
working it a fantastic experience
so i think there's a there's a we don't
see enough
of farmers and real life
farmers and what they do and the good
stories
you know that might be simple stories it
might be spectacular stories but
um the stories of people farming and
um there's so many different ways of
doing things and
alternative ways of doing things and we
can learn so much from each other
oh wow i think uh just to sum up our
conversation
today we spoke about some non-farming
opportunities um
and also earlier on in our conversation
you mentioned um
different or various alternative farming
systems or methods
um for anybody listening this evening
and is also maybe thinking of
alternative farming systems
specifically in the south african
context what opportunities
are available for a new entrant wanting
to come into the agriculture industry to
specifically farm
what alternative farming systems are
available within the south african
context that someone can take
take advantage of
sure that's a good question i think if
you're a non-farmer
and you need to decide on on you want to
farm
what do you want to farm that will
determine what the market wants
you're not going to farm something that
you won't get sold so determine
determining what the market wants if
there's a huge market for organic apples
and you sitting in an area where there's
organic or you know where it's suitable
for
growing fruit and you've got bridging
capital for five
six years until your apples become
viable then then that's something you
need to consider
so you look at the environment you look
at your soil type you look at where your
farm is situated you also look at what
the market wants
um and then that will determine what
kind of crop or livestock or what
farming system you're going to use
if you want to farm cucumbers but the
area is probably not viable then you
need to
think of an alternative farming system
and then think probably on tunnels you
know using tunnels
farming cucumbers in tunnels um so i
think
there's a lot of parameters that one
needs to look at when
you when you want to want to enter the
farming but it's certainly you want to
form something that you want to sell at
the end of the day and then
therefore you need to be close to a
market you need to be able to provide
the right product
um to the market but you also need to
look at
your soil type what kind of soil what
kind of quality of water and do you have
enough water
and then work around your resources that
you have available
and make sure that you utilize them
sustainably
awesome thank you so much so um
without um you know wasting too much of
your time
just for anybody also that's interested
and wants to know
you know where you're writing your
articles etc what are some of the
publications where you're writing about
alternative farming methods do you have
a blog or
or where can we find some of your
information
cool thank you um i wrote quite a few
articles
on uh for a company called
southafrica.co.cna
um articles range from quinoa farming
prawn uh goat farming
medicinal plants indigenous fruits
indigenous vegetables
goodness i can't even remember what i
wrote about guava farming fake farming i
don't know there's so many
i was part of an agricultural team and
all those
articles are translated into all 11
south african languages
the company is called south africa. and
under each article there would be a
choice of languages so you click on the
language and you read the article in the
language of your choice
thank you so much miranda for your time
this evening i thoroughly enjoyed our
conversation
and i'm sure that our guests did
sorry our audience uh did too i've just
got two comments to read for you that
said
um from lisa barbara saying thanks for
letting us know about the latest
in farming and uh zamila just saying
greetings family
um i'm sure they're watching the private
property podcast
uh right now and our conversation so
thank you merinda
for your insights and for um obviously
sharing that information about where you
uh have those alternative farming
articles
that we we could catch up on
great stuff thank you i had fun thanks
for your time
awesome thank you if you missed
tonight's episode you catch it on our
youtube channel on private property
under the farming podcast uh playlist
today we're joined by melinda lowe um
who is an angry
journalist and a photographer and also
um
an agri-premier i'd like to say um who
had her own composting business and but
most importantly the crux of our
conversation today
was about alternative farming systems
the different methods in which you could
begin
farming thinking about your natural
resources things like climate change
being able to still produce but really
farming more sustainably
in this environment in the environment
that is um
that you're faced and all that
specifically speaks to
um what type of commodity you want to
farm
and so yeah that was our show this
evening on alternative farming methods
but um thank you again for your comments
and for engaging with us it's always
nice to know that you are watching
and to send a little shout out to um to
myself or the guest thank you so much
for your support
that's it from me tonight and i bet you
farewell for this evening take care see
you soon
thanks molly
[Music]
oh uh
you