[Music]
so
folks an exciting day get in the
driveway installed at least most of it
done today but i do think that we were
off on our estimate just based on how
far we've come so far we've had
nine loads you'll see getting dropped
off throughout this
video nine loads of stones that's that's
10 yards 15 tons per load so 90
90 yards so far and they were kind of
thinking and hoping about 100 yards
total but part of it is i wanted to go
on thicker but i'm going a little bit
wider as well than i originally probably
planned on you're going to see there's
there's a couple areas here that it is a
steep drop off when they're dropping
this this gravel and then i'm trying to
grate it out it's like it'll it wants to
tip the tractor over just about but
we're using the summit tx 25 tractor
today have a four foot land plane on
there pretty good match for it
now this stone is a little bit wet right
and so if you're doing maintenance with
a lamp plane
you're gonna have dry material hopefully
if you're doing it uh you know when it's
when it's dried out if you can if you
can avoid doing when it's when it's wet
and heavy and kind of wants to stick
together that's going to be
preferable you get better results but
what you're seeing now is fresh gravel
that's been dropped down it does have
some moisture in it it's drying out as
as it sits here in the sun but it tends
to want to stick together a little bit
however overall you can get really good
results with it still one thing about
the land plane that i do love is the
fact and hopefully you can see it in the
videos that those those there's two
blades and they're both angled they're
not straight you know perpendicular to
the tractor they're they're a bit of an
angle tilted back on one side and so
that allows you to draw material to the
left
well let's see yeah yeah to the left and
so depending on the direction of travel
you can
you can make your driveway completely
flat you can put a crown into the middle
by drawing more material to the middle
you can do all sorts of things and and
manipulate that the way that you want to
now tom with balcoma is really good at
his job and if you can have a good
operator that can tailgate like he can
then it's going to make your life a lot
easier if you can at all avoid having a
pile of stone dropped just in a and a
big heap so that you have to spread it
out you're going to save maybe hours of
time depending on the size of equipment
that you have to move it around and tom
is just you can tell
that's what he does day in and day out
he's been doing it for years and
you know there's a
little hump here there where it's just
getting the run just starts or the run
just ends that kind of thing and that's
about it other than that he does 90 of
the work and running the land plane
behind it you just kind of drop it down
and go and all i'm doing at this point
i'm not trying to put a crown on it i'm
just trying to kind of level it out
you know
where that steep drop off is draw
material over to that side of the drive
so that we can
kind of build it up and have material to
feather it out as we need to to to
prevent any dangerous situations from
occurring
now the overall scheme that i'm going
for here along the fence is to
in theory
kind of have that that contour
everything's draining down towards the
marshy area so from up by the fence and
then draining down all towards that
marsh where kind of the the down timber
and the dead timber's at and so i'm
trying something new i'm trying to not
put a crown on that area and just
essentially have it follow the natural
contour and see if we can have that rain
as everything gets packed down and
packed in just have that rain kind of
stream right over top and maybe i'm
asking for for trouble but a few guys
did recommend that or mentioned that in
previous videos too and i'm going to
give it a shot in this one now one of
the big differences and why i'm going to
go a bit deeper with stone this time
around is we did lay down road fabric
and so i'm not too concerned for the
initial grading but if i end up having
to do a deep grade at this sometime in
the future where i have to put those
scarifier shanks those big ripper teeth
down i want to make sure that there is
plenty of material in between the end of
my teeth and that fabric otherwise
you're going to rip up your fabric
you're going to start pulling it up
towards the top and just making a big
old mess so i'm going to go thicker
because of that and that means that in
some areas we still probably have to
well i can still see some of the tarp
and we've just kind of got a base layer
on there but i probably have to add
another
four or five inches in some of these
areas and other areas towards the middle
it's definitely been packed down driven
over that's the nice thing too with
these dump trucks is that if you have it
relatively smooth and tailgated like
that
every load
that driver that big old heavy truck can
drive over it back and forth and really
help to pack down at least the tire
track lines right maybe not the middle
or anything else but they can get you a
big jump start on that too folks we are
proud to be sponsored by rimguard
solutions a liquid ballast weight it
goes right inside your tires completely
hidden we're big on safety on this
channel these tractors are just too
light and tippy right out of the factory
not only is it going to help with safety
keeping those rear tires planted on the
ground it helps with loader efficiency
and traction too the benefits of rim
guard include being the heaviest
all-natural liquid ballast weight on the
market it's not going to corrode your
rims like the old calcium chloride it's
not going to freeze and it's available
at over a thousand dealers nationwide
find the dealer near you at
rimguardsolutions.com now for those
you're not familiar the summit tx25 is a
new tractor getting ready to hit the
market nationwide next spring so we're
kind of doing the videos ahead of time
to build some interest to show you what
the tractor is about so that when it
really is ready to be
bought all over the place
you potential buyers can already be
comfortable with it and so summit sent
us this tractor and we're doing all
sorts of videos with different
attachments that we sell so you can see
how it works
so far so good what i what i like about
this thing
more and more i think that stands out
and i'm sure it's going to bite us in
the butt at some point is the weight the
weight's very advantageous for feeling
stable and solid and even as you watch
this video too when i'm on those
kind of sketchy
side inclines that lower center of
gravity these have rim guard in the
tires
just the natural weight of the tractor
helps
you feel a little bit safer not that you
want to take unnecessary risks but it's
a good position to be in the downside is
that extra weight is going to be robbing
some power if you do want to use larger
attachments
someone does a good job of telling you
what attachments is compatible with on
their website too so you can check that
out uh for us now we're using the uh the
four foot land plane on here speaking of
these lamps if you are looking for
something for your tractor like a lamp
plane a box blade a landscape break a
snow blower pallet forks a grapple you
get the idea the list just goes on and
on and on that's what i do at my company
goodworks tractors goodworktractors.com
we sell and ship tractor attachments all
over the country
and that's what my channel's about right
i show the attachments in action so you
can see how they work
maybe what you should do or not do with
them depending on how it goes for me but
you can see how it would in essence work
for you too i use the stuff that i sell
so it makes you more comfortable with it
and just gets a better understanding and
believe me we show plenty of times when
things go wrong too for those of you
interested this is 21 double a gravel a
little bit of clay content in there
you'll see a section up near the road
that was installed a few months ago and
it's been rained down and kind of
settled in and compacted and everything
else cleans up looking really nice that
clay kind of settles down in there and
and kind of binds and ties all the stone
together too you know it looks pretty
dusty and dirty right now looking at it
but trust me when i say it'll look just
like that stuff up by the road and give
a good finish result now tom's bringing
out more loads the rest of it on
thursday so we will finish up at that
point but pretty impressed with what we
got done so far i think he's got another
load or two today's but we're gonna get
out of this way and let him keep on
going as long as he needs to well that's
going to do it for us today folks just
out here enjoying this beautiful august
weather i want to thank you for stopping
by if you enjoyed today's video we'd
love to have you tag along hit that
subscribe button right down below if you
are looking for something for your
tractor we'd love to help you out visit
goodworkstractors.com i want to thank
you for stopping by and until next time
stay safe we'll see you soon
[Music]
you