[Music]
So folks that meet us say, "Oh, so you
guys are no tillers." And I say, "No,
we're not no tillers. We're regenerative
a people,
enthusiasts." because uh noill is not a
system. Noill is one tool that we
use. You can't be successful if you
think you're going to be a no- tiller
because you have to change your paradigm
about what you plant the diversity. um
keeping a living root and especially
integrating cattle because uh we think
that the cattle are the most important
thing. I'm going to name drop a few
folks that are influential in my life.
There's a guy named Jim Garish who uh
came to a grazing school in Watertown,
South Dakota, and made us repeat 10
times during his session. I will not be
afraid to waste grass, which is uh just
a real change for us. There's a man out
in western Canada named Steve Kenyon who
custom grazes cattle for folks. He has
some of his own herd and he's got sheep
now. But he said when when people say it
takes a thousand years to add an inch of
top soil, he says I can increase top
soil by an inch in 7 years through
integrating cattle. Um those people get
me excited and that's why I enjoy what
we're doing and it's just a whole bunch
of fun to have Eli agree with me and get
excited about it, too.
[Music]
I got sold from Gabe Brown. Um when when
Barry had had listened to him um before
I had and and you know I think it was uh
about January 2018 when I I saw him at a
soil health coalition uh conference and
listening to him talk about what he
does.
Um it's a goal. It's great because we
know now we have so many things we could
accomplish on our farm. It's just we're
always building on it. But when he said
that he would bet his farm against
anyone's farm that what he does would
work on their farm, uh I took that as a
challenge to prove him right instead of
a challenge to prove him wrong because
why wouldn't you want to be doing what
he's doing? And the biggest thing for us
I think was the context part. Um you you
can fail easily at at anything if you
try. But if if you look at your context
and you and you study what your climate
is, uh how things will fit into your
system, you can make soil health work on
every acre
anywhere. We've lost acres and added
acres in the last 10 years. Um, we we
added a few quarters of of heavy soil in
this area and we added another quarter
or two of just some really light soil.
And it's our approach is the same. You
it's, you know, what can we do with soil
health on those acres? And we know it's
going to work if we just stick to the
principles and and look at at our our
context of all that.
You know, when we did look at our
context, we we were thinking, okay, we
we like the cover crops. We want we want
more cover crops. We want we want to be
able to plant as many species as
possible every year. And so we were we
were doing uh spring wheat for small
grain. And and we realized that we
didn't have enough growing season to to
get the cover crop growth after spring
wheat. So, one thing we we did was we
started planting a lot more winter
wheat. Uh we're doing a lot of oats this
year, just knowing that we can get that
crop off earlier and get a cover crop
going. You know, we we did 17 species
this year of cuz we know how many pounds
an acre of each thing we can add.
So, one of the things we did is
converted crop land to pasture. Um,
and that was a learning experience, but
it worked out very well for us. And, uh,
and now we're transitioning that field
back into crop land because we can, I
guess. Uh we we never want to give up
the experiments because every conference
we go to, we hear something new that we
just got to try on this farm. And I I
guess at this point I need to say that
without the South Dakota Grassland
Coalition and the South Dakota Soil
Health Coalition, we probably wouldn't
have gotten access to an awful lot of
excellent material that we've
assimulated. And I appreciate the folks
that are willing to go to a conference,
stand up in front of a crowd, and
explain to us what they've been doing.
So, we're going to work on staying on
this land as as long as possible. And,
you know, we we've got the river bottom
land. We know none of it's native
because sand was really easy to plow.
And so, we we need to work on on that
land. We we know that the previous
practices on it had depleted it. What it
was before that is what we need to get
back to. what the, you know, the
migrating buffalo did to it. We need to
replicate that and and work with that
and and we know that it'll be beneficial
and it'll it'll make the land more
valuable and it'll it'll keep my family
here, our family here for generations.