good day everyone you may have heard
some whispers about a new design of our
Ripper pip player well I'm glad to
present that to you today so our Ripper
pip play has always carried great
strength and this new design is no
different some of the main features you
can see is a square reel as opposed to
our round reel the reason for going to
square was to give the Reel Center lower
to the ground this makes it easier when
you're loading those larger rails of
pie another feature we've added on is a
for pocket to make it easily forkable so
there's two Fork um pockets on the
Ripper so if you got to move it from
property to property it's a lot easier
to load onto the back of a ute or
trailer we've also made our legs on the
Ripper more efficient and easy to store
if you have any questions on this great
product feel free to reach out to the
team today thank you bye