ceilings have the tendency to be rather
boring
with lamps being the sole feature to
break the white monotony
let's change that how to jungle up your
ceiling
[Music]
to create such a green ceiling we
obviously
need a plant first epipremnum aureom
is truly the basic [ __ ] houseplant
originating from the french polynesia
region it is now found in many tropical
regions
and as a common houseplant around the
globe
in germany it is commonly referred to as
ifoytute
in the anglo-sphere it is listed under a
ton of names
with devil's ivy being my personal
favorite
in russian-speaking regions it goes by
its former scientific name
the latisti patos whilst in japan it is
simply referred to as
potosu devil's ivy belongs to the
arakaye family of plants
a family in part characterized by its
ability
to spawn flowers though thanks to a dna
defect
it is the sole member of its family that
doesn't actually goddamn flower
making it a basic [ __ ] houseplant or
shy flowering in scientific lingo the
only thing you should care about though
is that thanks in part to the plant's
excellent energy management
it is essentially immortal it thrives
both in direct sunlight
as well as dark corners and has a
straightforward water need
you actually have to try to kill it
so how do we even mount plants to the
ceiling
decorative vines meant for exteriors
like the boston ivy
mount themselves by a sticky fade for
the interior
this is a big no-no as that would leave
marks upon removal
so we will use a plant for vines without
the ability to stick or climb
wikipedia describes devil's ivy as
having the ability to climb via roots
which adhere to surfaces this is rather
imprecise wording
devil's ivy attempts to spawn a root
roughly once a centimeter
in between spawning leaves if the root
touches a moist surface
it will attempt to bore itself into it
yes indeed you heard right
moist if it's dry it's a no-go
so if you buy the plant with a coconut
fiber stem to glide onto it
it won't work unless you water the stem
itself as well there is a reason it's
made out of absorbent material like
coconut fiber
so guess what a photographer does on the
move to make an advertisement shot
he uses metal clips or similar for the
plants to hold onto the stem
jesus christ way to miss the point of
the whole goddamn plant
but i digress
[Music]
if the spawning roots do not feel any
moisture they instantly stop growing so
devil's ivy will never attempt to cling
to a wall or ceiling
not that the roots could even do such a
thing on a hard surface
instead we will put the vines on a grit
or pattern
created by fishing line fishing line is
essentially invisible against the white
ceiling
and gives the appearance of floating
vines
bore and pack holes in uniform distance
from one another
around the room screw in hooks to the
pegs and stick to hooks
not eye screws because hooks allow you
to place part of the vine in it
using the hooks and fishing line create
a grit or a pattern
to lane the vines on top of i went with
a diamond pattern using a total of 12
hooks
it really doesn't matter what pattern
you choose as long as the empty space
between the fishing line
does not exceed one and a half meters so
a vine will actually
reach from line to line in a reasonable
time and
so that it won't sag from its own weight
you have to tighten the fishing line
by a lot to prevent sagging even if you
do it with a lot of force
there will always be sag no matter what
so make sure to mount the hooks
as high as possible to prevent the
plants from falling below the level of
your ceiling mounted lamp
which would cause your room to get a lot
darker
speaking of which make sure your fishing
line pattern
actually leaves the lamp area empty by
the way
it doesn't have to be fishing line go
with a rope made of coconut fiber or
similar for a more pronounced effect
if the plant is happy it takes six to
eight months for one vine to grow from
sealing to the floor
depending on the pot size and how much
water and nutrients it gets
there will be at least a couple vines
growing at that speed per pot
with new vines being spawned here and
there once the vines start interfering
with your daily life
and reach the floor it's time for the
bi-early cleanup
though i must admit it is kind of funny
having to swat away
vines from the monitor every week
at this point the biggest vines are
taken back to the ceiling
where they are spread evenly throughout
the grid after this
your ceiling greenery just got a great
deal dancer
the leaves are attached rather
delicately so be careful not to snag
leaves on the fishing line and tear them
off
no matter how careful you are though
this will always happen
but do not throw fallen leaves away
put them into a shot glass and change
the water once a week
oh damn it of course i broke too more
after filming this
off into the shot glass you go a leaf
has roughly a 50 50 chance to spawn a
root within two weeks
once the root is roughly a centimeter in
size transfer the leaf into a pot
once in the pot it has again a 50 50
chance to spawn a new vine within two
weeks
once this happened the plant will
continue to grow into a fully matured
vine network
this one took six months to get from
broken baby leaflet
to small sized wine once it's at that
size
it is ready to join my jungle harem
just look at those greedy roots devil's
ivy has an incredible appetite
so when choosing a pot always go bigger
than what you think you'll need
so how do you even care for the plant
when buying soil from a garden supply
store
it usually comes pre-fertilized on that
front you should be in the clear for at
least
two years otherwise look up any guide on
diy
potting soil more important is how you
deal with water
smaller pots need to be watered more
frequently whilst a bigger part gets
away with getting a larger amount of
water
at longer intervals all that biomass is
thirsty indeed i dump three quarters of
a liter per pot once a week
though to be honest you can't actually
over water devil's ivy
you heard me right the more the merrier
dump a whole water bomber into it if you
feel like it
as long as you have
proper drainage and the soil has the
chance to dry at least once a week
the pots have to drain properly and i
cannot overstate this
as long as excess water properly drains
out of the pot
you cannot over water devil's ivy if the
water does not properly drain however
best case scenario you'll get invisible
rod setting in
with a significantly weaker plant what's
more likely though
is that your pot will turn into a
massive insect grave
and if you are really lucky and really
hit the jackpot straight up mold
at which point you best just dump the
whole thing all together
to ensure proper drainage drill way more
holes into the parts than you think
you'll need
especially bigger pots often only have a
single
big hole in the middle this is not
enough
go ham and drill more than you think
you'll need
next off fill the bottom fifth of the
pot with coarse rocks or large gravel
this will ensure that compacted soil
does not clog the holes
which the water is supposed to drain out
of and
lastly actually test it sometimes it is
not obvious
and water decides to just stay in the
pot anyways
sometimes due to a flat tray which
creates a seal against the pot
here i dumped more water than usual into
the pot and it
instantly starts filling up the tray
this is how it's supposed to work
on the note of trays they never look
particularly great
but in this case they are a must
of course ceramic on the parts look
great
but once you have enough biomass or a
bigger pot you will not be able to
separate the outer part from the
inner part and water staying in the
outer part is not
any better than a straight up clog also
make sure that the tray can actually
hold some damn water
i know it doesn't look very appealing
having trace way bigger than the actual
part
but trays like these are just useless
oh they look great size matched and all
but cannot hold any reasonable amount of
water
also if you cannot move the pot which if
the pot is big enough you
won't be able to believe me you have to
remove excess water with fabric
so make sure that you can actually get
cloth into the tray
in the first place so again as long as
the potter drains
and the soil dries at least once a week
you're golden
go ham with water the more the merrier
while stella's ivy can overcome longer
periods of drought
as with many tropical plants ideally the
soil should always be
moist but since we are confined to a
part in the interior
it has to dry at least once a week
[Music]
so now everything's going great and your
vines are growing
but oh dear suddenly the plant has
yellow leaves that go dry and fall out
don't worry
this is expected behavior and part of
the plant's energy management
a mature vine network will start
rejecting undesirable leaves
in favor of supplying new and younger
vines
even when the network has more than
ample supply for itself
look at this singular vine here the
leaves are healthy
whilst in the darker corner only half a
meter to the left
all leaves have dropped as the network
considered them to be undesirable
and yet again half a meter along the
vine a new
younger branch is growing this is normal
and a way for the vine to reclaim
energy spent once a leaf has started to
turn yellow
there is nothing you can do as it is
chemically marked for death
but don't remove yellow leaves the
leaves
don't actually straight up die just like
with hardwoods in autumn
the leaf turns chloroplasts in its cells
into chromoplasts to convert and siphon
energy upstream
as long as the leaf remains yellow it is
still a benefit to the plant as a whole
only once it is dried up should you
remove it
this behavior is not limited to leaves
by the way at some point
even whole branches get rejected though
this happens rarely
once branches are dried up you can
actually use them to support the grid
with new paths just like fishing line
if a singular vine has lost all of its
leaves but
not dried up yet do not remove them
either
naked branches are still used to
transport water and nutrients
just like with a hedge the inner part of
a hatch has
no leaves but it's still part of the
living plant
in a healthy plant the ratio of dying
biomass
should always be only a fraction of what
the network is growing
as long as a lot more biomass is
produced than is being reclaimed
you're golden this aggressive energy
management is also why devil's ivy can
go long stretches without water
during drought the plant will start to
reclaim more and more of its own biomass
to keep
pumping out new and younger branches in
search for water
two months without water will claim a
big chunk of the biomass
but resuming normal water supply should
have you reach the same levels of
biomass within half a year
this is in part why it's really hard to
actually
kill devil's ivy it's okay with little
water as well as lots of it
though if leaves do not turn yellow
before dying
something is definitely up like here the
green leaves turn straight up black
which means rot has sat in in this case
though this is traced back to simple
physical damage of the vine if you are
patient enough you can grow out the
vines from the floor
to the ceiling but ideally you should
place them high already
i used a bit of wood to create these
corner shelves
which were secured with overkill sized
pegs and screws for safety
since i actually sleep under a part and
don't want to end up like a watermelon
in those safety demonstrations
all is said and done how long will this
take you to get all that biomass
with a pot in each corner of the room
and under healthy conditions
the plant should produce enough biomass
to sparsely cover the ceiling
within two years the plant in my room
was actually gifted to her family as a
singular vine some 15 years ago though
my room doesn't actually even closely
represent 15 years worth of biomass
the wine network has been split multiple
times across multiple pots over the
years
then neglected for half a decade and
then survived being relocated
three separate times whilst losing
branches each time
it was moved in that sense you don't
even need to buy the plant
as getting a couple of leaves from a
donut plant already puts you on the path
to jungle them
[Music]
the original vine network still resides
within the spot
the oldest vine thought to be the
original gifted one
is nicknamed mother vine and is traced
out in red here
it's easily over 20 meters by now the
last time i moved
everything had to be carried by four
people so the vines wouldn't take too
much damage
as a last remark it is often stated that
when exposed to direct sunlight the
leaves get more of that white marble
pattern
this is only true to some extent these
leaves
in direct sunlight are definitely
brighter than the deep green coloring of
the leaves in the dark corners
this is also evident with the new
addition i just planted
this smaller vine walls in direct
sunlight since it was a broken baby
leaflet
however the degree of marble coloring
mostly depends on the color variation of
the plant
for instance this other devil's ivy
straight up has the marble pattern
everywhere even in the darkest corner of
the room
so if you're buying devil's ivy what you
see is
basically what you get even if
literature claims otherwise
[Music]
that's more than you would possibly ever
need to know
about my favorite basic [ __ ] houseplant
devil's ivy make papa proud will you
[Applause]
[Music]
wow