if you own land more than likely you've
got weeds and so it's a responsibility
of land owners to control noxious weeds
as well as other weeds that might affect
your cropping economics when you're
storing chemicals it is to be behind
locked doors and you're also asked to
put a Signia or a sign up that indicates
the pesticides are behind that locked
door this avoids anybody from getting in
and maybe taking it or kids getting in
close contact with it that type of thing
so also we're doing chemical pickup and
as you come to pick up your chemical
make sure that you store it on the back
of your vehicle out in the open so you
instead of inside of the car I'm also
make sure that if you're using flatbed
pickups or trailers that you secure your
load and you do not lose that in
transport another mistake that we've
seen is leaving your chemical unattended
if you're going to go out to your field
and make an application many of people
have basically chemical trucks that they
store them in and they leave them
unattended for long periods of time and
there's been mishaps of chemical getting
stolen or if you really don't have
neighbors that like you there's been
cases of people putting chemical in your
spray tank kind of as a bad prank it's
your responsibility to keep that
chemical under lock and key and under
your control at all times another one to
keep in mind is that always store the
chemical in its original containers and
you want those container labels to be
facing outwards so everybody knows where
what chemical that they are exposed to
also when you're handling chemicals or
transporting chemicals make sure that
you do have the proper safety equipment
in the event that there's a spill you
want to make sure that you've got some
cat litter or some some some chemical to
kind of absorb the the spill and then if
it is significant enough that you report
that to the poison control center and
assist with control to attempts to clean
that that mess
again we hope that everybody has a safe
spring season and you have questions
you're always welcome to contact the
your local Extension Office