hello welcome to little Garden on the
Prairies and welcome to my beautiful
Green Yard this is one of those Springs
where we've been getting lots of rain
which is great cuz we haven't had one of
those for a few years as you can see the
grass is super green Dand lines are
coming along
nicely and with this rainy weather comes
a lot of cool temperatures so we're
having a really cool spring and the
nighttime temperatures are still pretty
cold so because of that I've been really
careful as to what I'm going to be
planting out and when and in this video
I'll just go through how you should just
be careful in a cold climate like mine
here when you plant out your stuff you
really got to watch those temperatures
so let me show you what I got going on
in the Garden
today so all of my winter sewing jugs
are still intact here I'll let you see
if I can
see we got some angula coming in here
really good the sweet peas are almost
growing through the top got some green
onion and
chamomile uh basil and parsley so
everything's coming good except for mint
I'm not sure it's not going to come or
if it's just super
slow but these will be safe from the
cold they're in the best place ever they
got their little mini green houses
keeping them warm and then here are all
my bedding plants it still need to go
into pots and into the garden and I'm
just going to wait you can see I got
tons of col Aces that are so beautiful
and they're getting so big but they are
one of those plants that are very
sensitive to cold I've already had some
of them freeze that I set out in some
pots about a week ago a little bit too
early we had a cold night and they froze
and died so but my tomatoes are looking
super healthy the green peppers are
doing great
so everything's going to be fine I'm
just leaving them in here they'll be
fine for another week until our
nighttime temperatures get better I've
left this door open for the last few
nights but because we're going to hit
that
1° pretty sure it's going to freeze here
in our yard so I'm just going to shut
this door for the night and then reopen
it in the
morning so when the weather was warm a
week ago I started potting up my flowers
into my pots here and now I'm having to
bring them in at night so I'm going to
be just putting them in the garage until
those nighttime temperatures stabilize
and stay warm this is what I'm going to
have to do for
now so when I got up this morning the
temperature on my phone said it was only
0° so I knew that we must have got frost
and you can see here in the shade on the
grass there is a hint of frost still on
there so I'm happy that I had put away
all my pots and covered everything and
saved it from frost so here is where I
got my peas planted and my onions
planted and they're pretty cool tolerant
plants I can see
that I have a couple peas starting to
pop through but I think they will be
fine they can handle a little bit of
light frost this was something that I
had to cover it's a ground cherry that I
started from seed and it already got
burnt once by a frost here last week and
a couple of these plants are still
hanging in there they're looking a
little weak but I think they should be
okay kept them covered last night so
they are
fine and these are all my onions that I
had planted up they were ones I started
from seed so they were not too
established into the soil here but I
didn't cover them and they seem to be
fine like I said they are pretty cool
tolerant and can handle a little bit of
frost so these should be okay the
potatoes of course under straw are just
fine
they will be okay they just got planted
a week ago so cool nights are not going
to affect them they should be fine I got
some luses started here in my containers
that are also haven't sprouted yet so
they should be okay and my area
designated for cucumbers tomatoes
peppers is still um unplanted and
looking pretty uh rough right now I need
to do a major cleanup and get these
ready but as I said it's going to be a
good week or so before they need to get
planted so I got some time to work in my
garden this week so I always like to
check my weather and look ahead you know
14 days just to see what the trend is
looking like as you can see here coming
up on this week we still have two
evenings where the nighttime low is only
going to be 2°
Celsius and then again coming up like 5
days from now the 24 of May 2° at night
so those are pretty cold temperatures
and in my yard you know when it hits
that 2 1° there's a good chance I'm
going to get Frost so just looking at
this I'm going to be holding off on
doing any planting of tomatoes peppers
probably right till the end of May here
when we start to see those nighttime
temperatures are moving up to some
warmer evenings and probably um our
daytime highes are going to get into the
20s which is great so so even though
it's really tempting to get plants out
in the garden when you have those
beautiful warm sunny days it's really
the nighttime temperatures you got to
keep an eye on and um make sure that
you're not going to be planting your
plants out in cold weather and end up
losing them and having to start over are
good for
yeah they're good for okay put some more
we need lots more yeah oh my walk
so there's always lots of things to do
while we wait for those temperatures to
warm up and today my grandson and I are
doing some picking of Dand lines we want
to do an oil infusion so we can make
some
svvs so you really need to be patient
when you live in a cold climate like I
do the weather is so unpredictable in
the spring and you just have to wait
until Mother Nature has set everything
right and then it's time to get all your
garden planted so please hit that like
button leave a comment and we will see
you on the next video thanks for
watching