hi this is Stephanie Dale from the home
front today I'm going to be taking you
on a tour of our drip system I'm going
to show you what a well planned out drip
system can
do for your
Farmstead and what exactly you can do
with it right off the bat as you can
see there is no PVC pipe in the strip
system
it's all done with drip
tubing the great thing about drip
systems is that it saves water saves you
money it saves you
time and it's low pressure and um if we
had to we could tear it apart and
reassemble it to work with our rain
barrels this is the beginning of our
drip system this should be the beginning
of a any good drip
system ours is connect connected up to
this outdoor spet the spet has a
built-in back pressure valve so we don't
have to um buy a separate piece and
connect that up but if you did you would
connect it up right
here most low pressure drip systems
should be connected after a timer or a
shut off valve this is because the
components of a low pressure drip system
like the screen filter will not hold up
under constant pressure so you shouldn't
connect it directly up to a faucet you
should connect it up you know after
timer after a shut off valve the nice
thing about having a timer on your drip
system is that it prevents you from
overwatering it prevents you from
forgetting about the system and leaving
it on overnight or leaving it on for an
hour longer than you should um it's just
one more tool you have that saves you
time and increases the efficiency of
your system you can set this to come on
every day every other day you can set it
to come on for an hour or for two hours
um they're just really really handy
inexpensive tools for your
garden what you're looking at right here
is a 200 mesh screen filter that's
keeping all the water clean before it
hits your system stuff gets in your
system algae debris other stuff like
that it clogs it up and and it doesn't
work right and you want your system to
be as low maintenance as possible also
you'll see here is a pressure
reducer or a pressure regulator that's
bringing the pressure down to 10 psi for
our system and this is an adapter what
this is doing this is bringing the size
down to where our half in drip tubing
plugs right into it coming off here is a
little qu in line and that goes in these
are raspberries this is our Mainline
tubing if you follow it for long enough
it it will hit our garden here's the
mainline tubing in the garden this goes
off
to all my beans peas which are done for
the for the year Dale it's all taking
off from the mainline tubing right
[Applause]
here and these are
just drip tape takeoff adapters that are
plugged into the main tubing is all that
is and we've used drip tape known as has
tea
tape and that runs up each one of these
rows and Waters it see right here you
can see it working a little
bit at the end of a drip tape we have it
crimped it's not a plug it's a crimp
however at the end of a of a Mainline
tube you can see there's the
plug
this is still my upper
garden lettuce is mostly done and been
harvested and
uh each
row I have going is being watered at
this point in time by a line of drip
tape of tea
tape this drip tape is pretty cool stuff
it will operate just as efficiently as
you're seeing right now under as low as
4 PSI right now everything's running on
T 10 psi it will work just the same with
four which you can accomplish through a
gravity fed
system it's also watering my beans P
beans some sunflowers back there
beets
onions good stuff another thing that we
do with our drip system is we use it to
water our chickens so we we just get
tired of falling water to the chicken so
we've taken um a tea we've installed a
tea right here we have more this is
Mainline tubing it runs off of here up
and around and we've installed a little
valve right
here and if I were to open
that well if I would lower it and then
open it um water would come out and here
I have my
container containers and and rais beds
and they're all on the drip system too
there's my uh Mainline tubing right
there I have
little um quarter inch lines with
emitters running off of each one let me
see if I can grab one this is an inline
emitter right there you can see it
that's the emitter that's the inline
emitter right there and it's giving this
uh couple squash plants a half a gallon
an hour I
believe
and in this bed you can kind of see
it it comes up we have a line coming off
the mainline you come over here and you
can see two lines of drip tape and
that's our
cucumbers you come over here and we have
potatoes and these are also connected to
the drip system if I can find the line
right
here goes
in
and right there's an
emitter
and right there is an emitter you can
see the red
thing the red thing is an
emitter when you want to increase the
amount of water a plant is getting you
can add another emitter um rather than
getting one of those variable rate
emitters which I think are garbage and
messing with it all the time you can
just add another emitter it's not that
hard okay if you follow our main line
tubing by the
Cucumbers you can see how it goes into
the garden that way you can there's also
a te we installed a te here and we're
going to follow it this way oh there's
another line right there coming off
little Quin line and that is feeding
another rhar plant and you follow this
tubing line right here it was feeding my
my apple tree but it doesn't need it's
on its thir deer now so it does not need
to be on the drip system but you can put
a fruit tree on a drip system you follow
this tube around there it is and it goes
around to another
Garden so here we have the other Garden
still no PVC pipe
and we have corn growing this is again
these are um I
used
row
takeoffs and drip
tape see and there are the tomatoes the
tomatoes are also on drip tape you can
get drip tape to emit different amounts
of water um it just depends on
on on what you're
growing and you can hit the end of the
line
here right there the drip tape ends like
the other ones
do it works really
efficiently weeds don't like to grow in
between the rows photo bomb by the dog
weeds don't like to grow between the the
rows because there's no water it makes
weeding easier it makes keeping your
garden up
easier now let's go up to the front and
see oh actually there's one more
thing that's not the end of the line for
this particular Zone if you keep
following it
along the main line comes over here it
uh is watering my comfrey and this uh 1
quarter inch line comes off of here here
and into this little whirl barel R rust
Rusty whirl barel planter I got some
Feverfew and what is that oregano
[Applause]
growing little quarter inch line comes
along this
[Applause]
way
to the black
caps and these are my black caps I put
them
in this
year they're growing pretty good okay
and we got
more4 in line taken off from
that he those lines go to blueberry
bushes okay there's a tea there's like a
little mini
tea see a little mini tea in the little
quarter line little mini tea and that's
how it goes off to all these fruit
bushes and one cherry tree which
hopefully the
Gophers will leave alone right down
here double
emits that's so that this little tree
can get four gallons of water in 1
hour okay well that's my drip
system I hope you enjoyed the
tour if you enjoyed this
SC video and you enjoyed the the article
that I I'm going to link to this video
then um I'd appreciate if you'd visit my
blog check it out it's um called the
home front and I believe the web address
is Stephanie dale1
blogspot.com
um I'd appreciate it if you'd swing by
leave me a
comment and check up and see how how
things are going here on the home front