work with the nature and landscape
around you to design a garden spaces
where you can work play and most
importantly eat growing highly
nutritious food in nature's patterns
planting for years to come
less annual work what's not to love
about permaculture answer adapting it to
a small space for one subscribe now many
permaculture plans start with a
foundation of fruit and nut trees that
can get very large
keyline design and other water
management systems are often at odds
with zoning regulations and space
restrictions but you can still establish
beautiful lower maintenance perennial
gardens in your backyard ultimately
permaculture is about designing outdoor
spaces so that all elements of plants
resources and humans interact in a
synergistic efficient way each part of
the system can perform and support many
different functions no matter the size
of the space here are some ways to
include permaculture in your backyard
farm one use resources wisely
permaculture design includes minimizing
human created energy use designing smart
water systems and maximizing natural
resources on a large permaculture farm
efficiently using resources might mean
digging a large system of drainage
swales and holding ponds some include
solar panels wood stands and windmills
to harvest natural energy on a backyard
scale you can install rain barrels to
water the garden and align garden beds
and dig swales to work with natural rain
runoff whether that's collecting excess
in dry areas are draining it away in
swampy areas consider growing prolific
plants like hops and beans to shade
sunny parts of the house in summer and
reduce indoor temperatures use highly
efficient hand tools like a broad fork
in hand tiller to minimize gas-powered
machine use carefully use your time and
space too if growing a certain plant
takes extensive pruning or weeding and
you don't like those chores try
something else if your family desires an
outdoor cooking space or more privacy
adjust plans to create those areas to
prioritize diversity diversity of plants
wildlife and experiences is key to
permaculture systems with many plant
variety
are more productive than monoculture in
the face of challenges like difficult
weather soil or chore time
they allow space for play work and
relaxation diverse Gardens attract many
species of pollinators and birds and can
be beautiful in all their variety 3 work
with nature and existing elements
working around existing buildings and
valuable real estate can be tricky for
city growers but part of the
permaculture mindset is transforming
those obstacles those problems into
something that can benefit you and your
garden says Patrick O'Connell certified
permaculture and restoration agriculture
instructor and member of the Columbus
agrarian society for example a yard
covered with large trees will have
trouble growing lots of sun-loving
annual vegetables and fruits he says so
instead grow mushrooms and
shade-tolerant ephemeral plants that
gather most of their photosynthetic
energy before trees put on their leaves
similarly build on existing physical
structures by using fences to trellis
climbing vegetables or flowers slopes
for plants needing well-drained soil and
reused materials for paths and borders
especially in a neighborhood with lawn
and garden standards it's a good idea to
start incorporating perennials into
existing flower beds to minimize the
shock of creating something that looks
so different than the status quo 4 build
appropriately sized plant guilds forest
gardening plans often suggest a top
story of chestnut walnut or other very
large trees that could dominate a small
yard or interfere with existing
buildings and power lines skip this top
layer and start with smaller fruit and
nut trees in tight spaces layer them
together so that space and harvests are
maximized focus on trees shrubs rhizomes
and vines that are typically found in
the mid canopy and understory layers
O'Connell suggests in temperate North
America a common assemblage of plants
might be apple pear plum peach cherry
raspberry gooseberry currant grape
strawberry and garlic 5 act a favorite
saying of permaculture advocates is the
best time to plant a tree as 10 years
ago the second best time is right now
it's easy to get caught up in the
principles of permaculture
some spend months or years trying to
design the perfect system where every
element interacts precisely with every
need perfection in a natural system
doesn't actually exist though so it's
best to jump right in
start with one area of your space or one
area of need and move through the rest
of your ideas as time and budget allows
six adapt enjoy and observe your
perennial food gardens focus on what
thrives in your environment and be ready
to change or move on from what isn't
working sometimes certain plants don't
get what they need from the soil
temperatures or pressures of your
particular space and it's okay to allow
yourself to move on to other plant
families in time you may experience
gardening like o'connell does where the
biggest reward is having tons of fresh
fruit and produced a harvest while the
biggest challenges harvesting tons of
the fresh fruit and produce