[Applause]
[Music]
this particular lecture is going to be
about subsistence strategies and now
while this is a part of the economic
system we're talking about it separately
because because it conditions virtually
every other social institution it's
incredibly influential hopefully by the
end of this lecture you'll understand
why and particularly by the end of the
quarter that will be totally clear to
you there are four types of subsistance
strategies there's foraging pastoralism
horiculture and intensive agriculture
we're going to break them down and look
at them one by one fore is basically
Hunting Fishing and Gathering so 85% of
the food for foragers comes from
resources that are available in nature
for 90% of human history people were
foragers today we only have about a quar
of a million
people forgers make their own tools now
in anthropology we kind of refer to this
as simple technology that's not a
qualitative statement we're not trying
to say that making your tools by hand is
a bad thing it's just that there's not
complex Machinery with all these various
parts and so forth that you have to use
to actually make the
tools the reason for production is that
we're going to share the
resources in addition to using them for
ourselves so it's a very communal
mindset groups are egalitarian and what
we mean by this in anthropology is not
that everybody's totally equal when we
do see any kind of status as a ranking
in egalitarian societies it's usually
based on age but egalitarian in an
anthropological sense means that each
individual has access to resources that
they need to survive and additionally
everybody's going to have the skills
that they need to
survive we see relatively small
communities and that's so they
don't take away or reduce all of the
resources in a particular area Hunter
hunters and gatherers foragers are
highly mobile you will occasionally see
foraging societies that are relatively
sedentary or they stay in one place for
long periods of time but the resources
have to be incredibly rich for them to
stay in one place for a long period of
time we see high infant mortality and
again this is because of the mobility
Factor we have overlapping gender roles
and what we mean here is that the
division of labor often falls out by
gender but again everybody has those
skills they need to survive so if we
have a group where men are predominantly
the hunters women can also hunt if need
be men can gather women can gather
everybody can make tools everybody can
make the appropriate clothing for their
culture and the appropriate shelters so
again it gets back to that equalitarian
nature where everybody has the skills
that they need to
survive high degree of
sustainability hunters and gatherers or
again foragers could really go on for
very very long periods of time if
they're left alone unfortunately what's
happening in the modern world world is
that they're being relegated to Marginal
areas so it's much much harder for them
to survive so high but it is a high
degree of
sustainability we're going to use the
Kung as an
example and the Kung live in the
Kalahari Desert they don't have a big
migratory territory um vegetation is
scattered um but they do move around to
wherever they can find resources they
use about a 100 species of animals with
50 of which they eat and they use over
150 species of plants where they eat
over a 100 now if we look at the
Kalahari Desert we just don't see a lot
of plants but the Kung who live in it on
a daily basis can really differentiate
between different kinds of
plants their favorite food is the m
mongongo nut and it's very high in
protein so in the times when they can't
get a lot of meat that particular nut
really serves them well the Kung eat
their way out of areas so what we're
talking about here that they eat all of
the food they like first then they eat
their less desirable food and once
that's done then they leave so that the
resources have time to
regenerate so they're mobile when
resources get low or sometimes they move
seasonally so in dry season we see large
camps of 20 to 40 people and they gather
around permanent water sources so makes
sense in the dry season in the rainy
season we see much smaller camps maybe
two to three families and they're
scattered all over the landscape more
resources around so they don't need to
be bunched up
together again High degree of mobility
in foraging societies we see a low
number of possessions because if you're
Mo on the move a lot you don't want to
haul a bunch of stuff around and again
limited population growth division of
labor in the Kong everybody gathers
everybody hunts food is shared with all
of the members of the group if there are
any possessions those are shared among
the group and there's very very little
inequality the Kong reckon their kin
relations on both sides which in
anthropology we refer to as a bilateral
system and when we get to family
marriage and kinship we're going to go
into that in more detail um one of the
things about the Kung they do have
contact with the quote modern world
unquote so they're very quick to
incorporate new technology and most of
their contact with the more modern world
comes with contact with agriculturalist
um governmental officials and also
Traders so that's basically a foraging
Society