hi my name is nat from living the dream
permaculture
and today i'm going to talk to you about
some of my favorite gardening books
i was recently asked if i could share
this so i thought i'd make a video
and hopefully help some other people who
want to expand their library
to learn how to grow their own food
preserve their own food
and learn about permaculture
so i'm going to start off with the first
book i ever bought i bought this about
13 years ago
i got it off ebay it was a couple of
bucks delivered
and i only bought it because it was so
cheap and it's turned out to be one of
the best investments that i've ever made
he can still get this book because i
have checked recently for someone else
and why i love this book so much it's
based in tasmania which has
which has a similar climate to um me
here in hipfland
victoria i'm in a cool temperate climate
so i would only recommend
this for people who garden in a cooler
area this is not something you'd use
in northern australia and what i love
about it is that it's all organic
and it teaches you how to grow each
individual thing so here we have lettuce
and i'll talk about how to grow it
and the conditions that it likes and all
that sort of stuff
i've read this so many times and i enjoy
it and learn something new from it each
time
this is something that i'll definitely
have in my library if you live in a cool
temperate area
the next book that i'm going to talk
about
is this one that i got from the library
it's called soil food
and if you really want to improve your
soil
something like this would be really
awesome for you
in the beginning she talks about all the
different nutrients
and elements and how they impact
plant growth and
[Music]
soil health and it's really really
interesting um
she also talks about sources um and how
to naturally
put that stuff into your soil and then
we talk about
1 372 ways to add fertility to your soil
so it's a really fantastic book full of
great ideas
and if you are passionate about soil
have a read of this the next couple of
books
are from pat colby there's another one
of her books that i really want to get
and it's called
um cattle care natural cutting natural
cattle care so we've got natural farming
and natural sheep care
and basically these go through
soil health regenerative farming trees
minerals and vitamins and remedies
so if you want to farm naturally um this
is a really good book it talks about
minerals
um and how to remineralize the land
she uses different technique techniques
to other people um but i find it really
interesting
and she funds really awesome because
she's got
diseases and illnesses and how to
remedy that with minerals all naturally
so
we've used this quite a lot and that's
why we want to get
cattle one because we would like to look
up cattle diseases if that was to ever
happen to us
and be able to fix it before it became
an issue
also a local book um i do love local
because when i'm reading about it i can
really
um put that knowledge to use on my land
and this lady lives about 30 minutes
away
over the mountain ranges and she talks
about
all the different weeds and how to use
them um
let's find something um let's have a
look
comfrey or rocket salad talks about how
to
preserve nasturtiums and vinegar
[Music]
how to use it for health controlling
weeds
and how to eat them and how to identify
them so
i found that really useful in my area
especially with your foraging
but also on farmland because you get a
whole lot of weeds out here and
sometimes you don't know what they are
you don't know if they're poisonous
and you don't know if you can eat them
or not so that's been
really interesting really eye opening
because there's a heap of weeds that we
have here
that i didn't realize you could eat or
use as a stock fodder
and that's really beneficial something
like chickweed for example really high
in protein in the seeds
similar to quinoa or related to quinoa
and um yeah it's called fat hem another
name for its fat hen so
it's called fat hen for reason because
it really puts on the weight
these books are all permaculture books
so we've got the first three
permaculture books that were ever
written
so the first one ever written was
permaculture one
which is when david was learning under
bill
bill was the tutor um at the university
that david was studying at
and this was the book that he wrote as
part of his
sustainable degree i can't remember
exactly what that degree was but there's
something in sustainable sustainability
and so permaculture evolved from that um
and then permaculture ii was written by
bill
um delving a little bit deeper and then
introduction to permaculture
so these are the first ones i would
recommend
for beginners that want to learn more
about permaculture
and then the next one i would suggest
especially if you're on farmland is the
earth user's guide
um to permaculture and this is by rosary
morrow who is up in the blue mountains
in new south wales
slightly different climate to me um
or not that much different but slightly
different
but she's got some different ideas in
here and it's presented
really nicely you can see there that the
illustrations are gorgeous and really
helpful if you're creating your own plan
or just
um trying to implement some ideas on
your own property
this isn't bad for urban but this is
probably better for rural
next one i would suggest if you are
wanting to do your pvc or get into
permaculture design
is the basics of permaculture design
this helped me heaps during my pdc
and basically talks you through all the
equipment you need
and where to get started in your design
so base maps
sector analysis and then all the other
elements that you're going to
implement um in your design so it just
talks you through that
and i found this really useful so this
would only um be useful for people who
are wanting to design
i wouldn't recommend this for someone
who's just a hobby
permi um that is someone who wants to
get into permaculture as a business
as with this book the designer's manual
this touches on just about everything
you'll ever need in your permaculture
design
this is called the black book um
i use this quite a bit in my pdc just to
kind of get ideas and then i would go
elsewhere to dive deeper into those
ideas for example he touches on key line
which a lot of permaculture books do
and then you can kind of go to piero and
stuff
and dive even deeper into
what key light is and how to implement
it on your property but this is full of
so much good stuff very expensive and
hard to get
but if you are wanting to use
permaculture
as a means of income source then having
a resource like this on your shelf
is really helpful so it goes through
concepts in them and design
methods of design patterns and
understanding them
climate trees and their energy
transactions water
soils earthworking and earth resources
the tropics dry lands humid cool to cool
climates
aquaculture and then strategies of an
alternative
global nation so it's over 500 pages and
it's pretty pretty good book to have if
you want to
um keep referring back to different
ideas
the next book that i'm going to show you
uh
more cooking style books this is the
second book that i bought um actually
paul bought me this for christmas
and it's from stephanie alexander who
does the kitchen garden foundation
and this one's called kitchen garden
companion
and in here she lifts
a whole lot of stuff all the gardening
equipment you need different methods of
gardening
kitchen equipment um and she
has a really useful chart on when to
grow
um certain things so what time of year
and the different climates
and then she goes alphabetically through
a heap of different veggies quite a lot
of veggies i don't think i've found
anything
that i've grown that she hasn't cooked
with so um i'd say it's really
comprehensive let me try and find
a starter one so
we have asian greens she talks about
um they're an annual perennial
soil types soil preparation climate
position winter plants
water requirements how to plant
successive planting when to fertilize
harvest period pests and organic control
companion planting
special information and quantities to
plant for families of four
and then you turn the page and it's got
more information about all that so
growing and harvesting container
planting preparing and sharing
um especially for kids so she does do a
lot of
like i said kitchen gardens at school so
um she's really passionate about
teaching kids how to grow
and cook their own food um and then she
goes into recipes
which is really useful for when you have
a heap of something in your garden and
you're stuck for ideas of what to cook
it's nice to open up the book and be
inspired
with all these ideas and then yeah so
alphabetical and all the veg and all the
fruit you could ever want
so i really enjoyed that as a resource
i got this one for an op shop for a
couple of bucks and it's the same sort
of principle
except not as detailed he um
orders his by seasons and then he has
like the cabbage family
carrots and beets climbing beans
courgettes onions
peas and broad beans pizza potatoes
strawberries summer salad and tomatoes
now he's obviously in england because
jamie oliver
is from england so for me
i have to rethink the seasons and the
time of year
that he suggests to plant stuff um also
i can't grow
broad beans in summer so for me that's
an autumn
sorry uh late winter and spring crop
another summer crop
um but he's got some awesome recipes in
here and that's
why i've got it not so much for the
gardening advice but for the recipes
because his recipes are really awesome
easy to follow and yummy
um for australia you've got the commons
um which is from matthew evans very
similar to
jamie at home but his recipes are a bit
more fancy
um what i also liked about it was that
he's got a little bit of a diary in here
so he'll talk about what's happening on
his farm at
that particular time point in time and
um
his recipes are really awesome but
fancier so
um not as easy as jamie's but still
delicious
his other book that gourmet farm which
comes from its tv show i guess
um is also written um nick haddos in
here and ross o'meara
this is not so much veggie um but it's
more meat
and dairy and how you would preserve
them
into delicious things like cheese and
salami
ham sausages um so that's why i've got
this one um
there are a few veggie dishes in here
but it's more
so chicory um but if you
are on a farm and you're slaughtering
your own animals and want to make
chicuteri
this is a really good beginner's book
for that the cheeses in here are soft
cheeses not so much hard cheeses
but there are other books for high
cheeses and if you do need to find
a good book for hard cheeses let me know
because i've got
one that was recommended i haven't used
the recipes or all the recipes in it
because
um i'm still learning how to make cheese
and
now for some more nitty gritty books
books
that give you um lots and lots of
technical information
about growing um i got these from op
shops so i'm not sure if you can find
them easily or not
but they've been really cool um
horticulture australia
basically it's a reference complete
reference for the horticultural industry
and basically
it goes through um growing
planting harvesting um i can't remember
if this one teaches you how to
propagate by cuttings as well but this
is a nice technical book when we need to
reference um you know either an issue
that we're having in the orchard or with
other trees
um or had a graft or how to propagate
trees that aren't as easy to propagate
as others
um the ultimate australian gardening
book
great for referencing plants that we
don't know much about
um in design and in
on on and on our property sorry um
so it tells you all the different
species here we've got cholesterols
and all the different types so that's
just a nice little handy book
um and then the royal horticultural
um studies concise inclu encyclopedia of
gardening techniques so this has got
the grafting um propagating and all that
sort of stuff
if you want to go into more details this
is not just sowing seeds this is
um serious plant propagation which we're
trying to
learn more about and the last two things
that i would recommend um are two
books on c savings so i've just ordered
these books one is called
the seed savers manual and the other
ones
the seed savers handbook i'll put the
proper um
names down below and i'll also add the
names of these books down below
but basically one's an australian
version and one's
not um but they tell you how to save
seeds they tell you
how far away to plant different species
um
to stop cross-pollination timing to stop
cross-pollination
and proper harvesting and storage
techniques for all your seeds
i read the manual before
and it's full of amazing information um
but it's something that i'd love to have
on my shelf to quickly reference
because it's something like this yellow
book that i'd use a lot of
um and just keep i don't know work with
it but i'd keep going
back to it and referencing um
hiding under there referencing um
techniques and stuff like that
because um there's a lot of information
in there and a lot of it's new for me
um and it's something i want to get
really good at so we can be
self-sufficient in our seed production
so yeah i think really useful to have
yourself so i think my top ones would be
if you were to only buy a couple of
books
definitely that book and i'd say that
one too if you were to get two books
and if you were to get one permaculture
book i'd get
the infuses guide so they'll be my top
top three this one's just really really
good full of so much information about
how to grow
all your own food this one's
just great for permaculture design and
different principles in there
and then this one will tell you
successive planting and um how much to
plant for your family
but also great ways to use up everything
that you harvest from your garden
so i hope this helps you and
that you've found some new books to add
to your stash
thanks for watching guys see ya