i'm g lakshmi priya and i'm here to
explain the ideal farm
which stands for improved and developed
eco-friendly agricultural land
under the sub-theme sustainable
agricultural practices
the basic aim of the project is to
maximize the use of land
minimize the input cost at the same time
use the natural resources in an
efficient way
without depleting them in the project
we've tried to show
various types of farming first starting
with the terrace form
in which we have depicted three types of
crops
tea sugar cane corn mustard what it
basically aims to do
is that when it rains the top soil will
further shift to the
other steps instead of washing away
completely and it makes the other steps
that more for diet
then we come to the homeological farm or
the fruit farm in which we try to depict
orange guava mango plums watermelon and
other such fruits
we have tried to show many types of
farms just so that if one of them
goes bad due to bad weather or some
other such mishap
the farmer can still sustain by using
the other means of production
next we come to compost which is an
efficient way of using
the waste the domestic waste as well as
the agricultural waste
to turn it into a manure for the field
then we have the biogas which makes
efficient use of the cow dung produced
in the poultry
and it turns it into fuel which is used
in the houses then we have the
solar panels which makes use of the
solar energy and turns it into
electrical energy
which is further used for the lighting
and then we have the rainwater
harvesting
which makes sure that the rainwater that
is collected on the terrace
goes down and gets stored in the
underwater tank and the same runoff is
also stored
and then used for irrigation in the
paddy field
like such then we have the fishery or
the pond
in which we read fish which is another
means of production then we have the
poultry in which we rear cattle
livestock and other such animals
for producing milk eggs meat and other
such daily products
and then we have the rice field which of
course it is irrigated by the rainwater
harvesting
and at the same time it is it acts as a
fishery as we put fish in the same water
as uh the cultivation of rice requires a
lot of water
so the basic aim of the project is to
reduce the input cost
and increase the profits what it
basically does
it it expels all the other expenses such
as chemical fertilizers and the cost of
electricity as it both is
uh done by the compost the biogas and
the electric
solar panels this project is made
indigenously with the use of
used thermocol led bulbs cardboard
a wooden base and other such stationary
items
i consulted the officials of the
agricultural department
and also visited the website for the
same they provided
in basic information for this which says
that
if we if we imply all these agricultural
practices
we can reduce the input cost by about 25
percent while raising the profits to
about 50 percent
the basic yield in arunachal pradesh is
about
two to two point five metric tons per
year but by using these practices we can
definitely increase that
the basic uh land cultivation is about
sixty three thousand square kilometers
although germ cultivation is practiced
by using settled
practices like terrorist farming clock
rotation system and other such practices
we can definitely increase the potential
of that land
thank you