hi guys it's liz from little homestead
on the hill and today we are just doing
some morning errands so
come along with me
[Music]
i lose my breath whenever i see
you
you stole my heart what is it that you
do
my life was great till you added colors
like the moon needs to sun we don't care
about the
others
[Music]
i just wanna love you just wanna hold
you
just wanna be with you till we grow up
myself every single day
[Music]
[Applause]
i don't know what i do without you
you make me smile what is it that you do
my life was great till you added colors
like the moon is the snow we don't care
about the others
[Applause]
[Music]
you guys ready for cookies
[Applause]
[Music]
bye guys
life is a winding road
no telling where it goes
[Music]
driving through days and nights
won't stop for traffic lights
[Music]
even if i'm falling down i will keep on
searching for my
eyes
you can say i lost my mind i will keep
on holding my head
high even if the sky is falling
[Music]
down
jumping from cliffs so high
trust in our wings to fly
[Music]
sometimes we're crashing down
if let her figure out
where the road goes
even if i'm falling down i will keep on
searching for my
eyes
you can say i lost my mind i will keep
on holding my head
high even if the sky is falling
down the sky is falling
falling down
[Music]
even if the sky is falling down
oh clean it's a huge difference from the
last time you guys saw it
a lot of work
[Music]
a little insert yesterday who do you
think was the first
person or animal that was in our pool
don't drink the water puppy
[Music]
i'm not going in after you it's cold
what are you gonna do
you gotta swim
good boy
[Music]
good boy hi was that fun
god
so the newest thing just happened i
didn't realize
that my local grocery store delivers to
the house
so this is a huge game changer
they're making it very easy for me to
never want to leave
amazing i'm so excited about this
i didn't get a lot but i got some things
so
i got a gallon of milk
some gluten-free bread
some sugar
[Music]
i got some carrots
five canned carrots and i got five green
beans
i got two pounds of hamburg
i don't need these but i love these so
these are a sports item
some strawberries and two things catler
and that was it in this little trip and
i didn't have to get the store and it
was amazing and i'm so happy about it
i know i'm silly
i don't really need a new friend so
spend your time with me
looking for someone who can play though
wanna hang with me
i'm not really looking for a friend so
spend your time with me
looking for someone not afraid
[Music]
take the chances
won't be easy
[Music]
oh
get next to me
i'm gonna drink my very chocolatey i
think i put too much chocolate in it
that's okay i'll still drink it so
that'll be good
but i'm gonna drink this and i am gonna
do some more stuff around here but i am
going to let you guys here
go so i can get this video up and i can
get it edited
have a great morning guys bye
[Music]
you