welcome to my view from the woods in
today's video we're gonna transplant
some tomato and pepper plants that I
started in early February some of them
are doing pretty good other ones are a
little sickly and I want to give them a
little boost this is how I'm gonna do it
[Music]
the first thing I do is make sure that I
label them correctly so I just put the
name these are gonna be Tiny Tim
Tomatoes I started them on to eight and
I'm transplanting today on three
thirteen I put that on some tape so I
can take it off on my salad cup and then
I'll fill the cup with the on the
side around the bottom where are they
here we go so the ones that have the
slots cut in the bottom maybe you can
see them better this way
let me start did or when the cup
slide it on I'll put the soil on the cup
slotted on the bottom I don't really
label them because I generally keep them
all together so just on the outside it's
good so the first tomatoes I'm gonna do
our Arctic rose tomatoes I did I planted
these on February first I planted them I
supposed to plant three seeds but you
can see I kind of doubled two of them up
so I have five plants in here so I've
taken my cups with the slots in the
bottom and fill them with potting soil
her seed starting mix it's actually my
that's announced a new mix it's not my
seat started mixing sunny potting mix
I'll talk more about that in another
video I've just sort of sort of
compacted the bottom half and then put a
little divot into it what I'm gonna do
is take this spoon that I found at the
dollar store the other day it's nice and
pointed I really like it it's gonna dig
these out well I'm gonna dig these
tomato plants out of this Cup lay them
down on this cardboard that way I can
just put the soil into my compost bin
and put the plants right into the new
cups so let's get started on that so I'm
just gonna go around the edges where I
can get the cup in or the spoon in dig
it down under I don't know how big big
the roots are and just sort of pry
and then once they're loose sort of just
dig around here where you can see it
better and pull the plants out
now I don't put this soil right back
into here I'm gonna compost this in case
there's any problems or any issues in it
that way I'm not spreading any diseases
order funguses or anything that may be
in it I'll just restart it so here's my
root ball my two plants you can see that
well I'll put it in this hand and now I
just need to separate these two
again that ideal I might cut these it
really depends on how the root systems
break apart especially since especially
if you're new to the channel I'm
planning these in an indoor garden so I
don't need 30 tomato plants I'm gonna
give the other ones away but instead of
hurting a plant
I might just want to sacrifice one so
this one's a little bit wheat compared
to this one I'm probably gonna clip this
one plant this clip this off in a few
days and just let the one plant grow I
think that's what I'll do that way I'm
not gonna damage either of them I can
just cut the plant and have it live so
I'm just gonna take this a little root
ball put it into my divot and my cup get
it upright and then push some of the
soil around it so it's upright
compact a little bit and then add a
little bit more new soil and spread that
around the plant
tomatoes you can plan a little bit
deeper around the stem I try not to keep
it as level as I can to where it was
growing and you can see I'll probably
take this plant here and cut this one
that I'm bending down off he's left with
this plant you see how it grows so let
me repeat that through the other plants
and see how it goes
make sure I put it in the right cup
Karthik rose and I put the date again
and I put the date on it if you can see
it too once the plant date in 313 s a
transplant date again this is the salad
cup later on I'll be mixing up some
fertilizer mix and I'll water gently
from the top and then put water in the
bottom Cup stick this Cup in it and the
water will be absorbed through the
medium and in through those holes so let
me go through these elements real quick
[Music]
[Applause]
there we go it's a lot of those five
plants I'm gonna get four and I'll
probably pick the two best throw those
up you get the other ones away
[Music]
other soil I just put my compost compost
I'll throw into the rest of these and
then I'll get right back with you when I
get on all the transplant stuff so
here's what I ended up with I ended up
with four plants of the Arctic Rose
tomatoes and five of the jalapenos and
then I ended up with six seven of the
tiny arms are they tiny temps yeah the
Tiny Tim's I'm gonna put a link below
that shows you where I purchased these
seeds you want to take a look at these
varieties I'm really excited about this
Tiny Tim I think that's gonna be a great
little indoor plant so I'm gonna put
these on my plant rack and then I'll
take you for a tour how I do that and
what else I got growing I do have some
more transplants to do but I'm not doing
today I have to go to work and it's
gonna be pretty miserable there's about
six or eight inches of new snow out
there today but such is life but I
rather work outdoors and indoors so
let's take you over to the plant stand
okay we're back to the plant table
plants shelf
plant something I don't know what I want
to call it the planting area I guess now
that's planning area was the other room
so I guess this is the growing area on
the shelf so I got the plants all set i
top watered the plants today I don't
really have time to do a fertilization a
little bit of a process I'm gonna put
that into a separate video and the
reasons why I'm going through the
process and just doing a simple
fertilizer I think they're good reasons
but I'll share with those you later so
let's take a look at the plants as I
have them set up and I'm gonna talk
about a couple of the problems that I
think cause those transplants are cause
those ceilings to be a little bit short
and weak so here's the transplants I
have them under just some regular LED
lights I'm gonna lower the lights when I
get down to filming here
these lights are from Home Depot
they're just three-foot LEDs they seem
to be doing pretty good with the plants
I had because I had again the colors
because of the lights they're under now
but I grew this lettuce salad mix under
those lights and it grew well as well as
you can see them in the back those green
onions and a few little Swiss chard I
still have some endive and some basil oh
I'm gonna put into today's breakfast but
reason they're purples because of the
lights are called unit fun lights I
thought they would be great the reviews
were good but I think they stunted the
tomatoes and the pepper plants that
along with my seeding mix the first time
was a little dense I a sense of added
some perlite to it and what I planted in
today is called royal gold basement mix
it's a good planning mix it was
recommended to me I'm probably gonna
keep experimenting with planting mixes
the reason I went with a mix instead of
making my own is because I don't have
the room to compost all the forest
products that are in the potting soils I
want to use there's some basil and that
there is some cilantro that I only
putting in the pots and then these are
the ones I transplanted today only top
watered them back to the planting mixes
I don't have the room to compost all the
forest materials that are in the soils
so I had to go with again a soilless mix
I went with a coconut coir base but I
think it's worked pretty good and the
proof is in the pudding because here are
some plants and be focus these plants
are only 15 or 16 days old and they were
planted in that raw gold and I think the
other thing is this Lighting's I'll step
back these lights are the bulbs that
just go into regular outlets they seem
to work really well you can see they're
doing a great job on the microgreens
here's some I just planted two days ago
here's a bunch of basil there's some
cilantro let me turn the lights off see
if that helps with the color
they do have a little bit of color I
guess it just gets too dark but I guess
you can see the true color again I'll
shut this head up it's gonna get dark
but you can see the real they're nice
and green micro greens especially and
then it tomato plants and peppers and
cilantro so I think it's a combination
of light and the mix so hopefully I got
that straightened around again here's
the ones I did today I think they're
gonna grow a lot better what are these
lights than they are going to under
these unify mites so I don't know if I
should put these on eBay I don't know
how I feel about that whether I should
just like to cut my losses and have them
as backups or try them on something else
high that's what I'll do I don't want to
give anyone self I'll like to someone
that I don't think works well so that's
my video today
got some transplants the next time I go
over my fertilizer routine and what I'm
not gonna recommend that the fertilizer
that I'm gonna do to anyone it's sort of
complex so but there's reasons why and
I'll explain them and I'll find a
simpler method for everyone else so I'm
gonna leave you on a note it's gonna
take a while Cameron focus but you can
just see what it's like
[Music]
[Applause]
okay that's my view of the woods for
today and hope to see you in the next
video please like and comment I love
comments leave me some comments what you
think and if you what you what your
experiences are I really like the
comments and if you haven't subscribed
please subscribe and follow my journey
have a great day
[Music]