hello everyone welcome back to the
cottage today we are working on storm
prep we've got some tornadic weather
coming through tomorrow so we want to
get everything secured
and we thought we'd bring you along okay
so our first step is we're going to lay
down all of our
top heavy arbors that aren't really
secure we're going to secure our high
tunnel actually i'm just going to take
it down
it's pretty much apart because of the
wind that's already kicked in
and we've got row covers to pick up
and put away and we're going to just
make sure anything that can fly
is buttoned down or laying flat so it's
a little bit harder to pick up the wind
okay our row covers are tucked away our
barn is going to be sound
um just in case we need to put people in
and usually our storms roll through at
night
oh goody so our animals will be tucked
away during the nighttime hours
because we also live next to a huge game
preserve
so it's just not safe that we feel to
leave our animals out so we'll have
everyone tucked in
our goats will be in here along with our
ducks um
and we're gonna work on picking violets
before this batch fade away and then
we're gonna work on getting the rest of
our tarps that we've been using
stowed away in the garage
all right we've pulled down the
makeshift greenhouse because if it can
catch the land it's going to come up
like a parachute and i'll take the armor
with it
so we're just going to hold this up and
pack it in the garage so it doesn't end
up counting over um we get really bad
straight line wins so anything that can
catch
anything more than that really can catch
the wind and it's going to be blown over
or broken in the process so
just keeping everything like an umbrella
that could catch the wind and then pull
needs to come down
we're going to use our contest bags like
a sandbag on the low side of our garden
so any flooding will be diverted around
it and not destroyed
again we're going to lay down our arbors
because they don't break these aren't
secured to the ground
or blown across the yard
oh god we just come to you right now and
we ask you for protection
we ask you to protect these fruit trees
protect our home protect our animals
each and every one of the trees that we
rely on for food
for blessing of others we just ask you
to protect them in this coming storm
let no weapon formed against us prosper
lord
keep this weather calm and the wind low
not just a gentle rainfall
nothing harm us or damage us or our
neighbors
let our harvest be good and plentiful
this year
so that we may not only eat of the
harvest
but give freely to others
to be able to trade with others that
have
other things that we need protect our
animals father
this weather's pretty scary we just need
your hand to protect us and cover us
lord
tuck us under your wings in jesus name
amen