[Music]
agriculture
is the most
fundamental and ancient activity
that propelled human civilization as we
know it today
before agriculture yeah there were
people there were
modern humans but they formed groups of
hunters and gatherers
and they didn't build cities they
didn't build empires
so agriculture is perceived
by many as a very conservative
activity however it has been
over the time characterized by
a rate of innovation that was necessary
in order to be able to feed the
populations and of course the rate of
population
was statistically speaking exactly equal
with the amount of calories that
agriculture could produce at a given
time
because if you had more people and not
enough calories
there would be starvation and death
this kind of cycle of
overshooting population that will then
go
back to the sustainable level has
characterized human civilization for
thousands of years tens of thousands of
years
and it was invisible
to most unless they were the one
starving
now we have a globally interconnected
world
and we know when there is a
food crisis somewhere and hopefully
we intervene we help
we prevent famine and starvation to kill
people actually
agriculture now is powerful enough
in its ability to create
the output edible calories
that when there is famine
it is not due to lack of food
it is due to insufficient logistics
or active prevention of the population
being fed
by civil war and conflict or corruption
however the way that agriculture arrived
to the point where it is today
must change the impact of agriculture
on the environment must
be ameliorated must be enlightened
the pressure that humanity puts on the
environment
is not compatible with our future
i uh was lucky to
participate in the opening meeting
of a new think tank the think tank
farm to fork that was born
to catalyze the
rate of innovation and the rate of
technology adoption
in agriculture especially
following the european union
a common agriculture policy
that is being
put in place in
highlighting sustainability and
highlighting
biodiversity and
actually very explicitly putting
in place incentives and objectives
to reach this in the way that
every kind of activity in agriculture
and food production
is going to be influenced by it over the
course of the next
five years the
policies that the european union puts in
place
matter worldwide because of how big a
market
it uh represents both in terms of how it
produces food to be
consumed inside or for export
or its import of food from from outside
and the size of the market
also makes it so that the producers
of technologies and components
in europe or outside of the
europe that serve the european market
are
um able to to leverage that size in
order to
achieve uh both their financial goals
as well as to be able to develop new
products new services that otherwise
wouldn't be available so
just a few examples of the things that
that we are seeing that
are not only on the horizon but are
already in agricultural
practice today the ability to plow
at a depth that is much
shallower than before in order not to
disturb uh and not to
diminish the fertility of the field
the simultaneous
laying of tubes
underground at a depth that
is deeper than than the plowing depth
uh in order to irrigate the field
uh with the right quantities
of water enriched with the kind of
nutrients that the particular
plant needs exactly where
it is needed because of
both satellite-based and drone-based
monitoring of plant growth
through data analysis and integration
based on multi-spectral
imaging the opportunity
is really enormous already the existing
practices
can improve farm productivity
double digits 10 20 and more
while um diminishing
drastically uh the use of water
uh the um uh weight
uh the pressure of food production
on the fertility of terrain
and of course um quite substantially
diminishing also the use of chemicals
that that are the traditional
fertilizers or pesticides
which contributed importantly
in our ability to increase the level of
food production we have today but
where uh they are now being
labeled or recognized as uh
undesirable uh beyond a certain
necessary level
the next stages of agricultural
revolution again will come from
technology imagine vertical farming
that can be above ground or below ground
that is proportional to the volume
of uh the uh farm
rather than the area of the field
available
the availability of plant-based
meat substitutes that are being
adopted and appreciated by consumers
already or actually a
cultivated meat of animal
origin obtained by cell cultures
rather than growing an entire
traditional
animal these are just two examples
uh but also advanced techniques like uh
crispr
in our ability to intervene
and improve the
basic crops and and the basic
ingredients
of our food chain
there are uh obstacles uh
for example in italy today
you cannot apply uh pesticides
via drones uh which practice
would be able to diminish the quality
put out quite radically
because flying a drone even if applied
small camp quantity is very precisely
because it flies a meter or two meters
above ground is
equated to blasting the crops
with traditional spraying from planes
and that is prohibited and as a
consequence
the use of drones is also prohibited
or other examples where
the regulations
are not um aligning the incentives
in actually delivering the desired
outcome
large quantities of healthy food in
great variety
with as little environmental pressure as
possible across not only europe
but the world and then of course
the most radical of food production
practices are going to be on the moon
and the mars and the asteroid belt
environments where well you cannot
grow corn or feed
a cow with the corn that you grew
you cannot waste water you cannot
have almost any of the things that we
are accustomed
to have on earth the
total not only radical but total
sustainability
practices that moon colonies and mars
colonies
are going to have will be not only
advanced
but very valuable and earth agriculture
is going to be profoundly influenced by
those
practices that mars will be happy
to sell to earth and consult and advise
on their implementation in the best
possible way
the agricultural sector
uh something that i am not very familiar
with
uh except eating food
and for me it was a pleasure to
start this collaboration with the think
tank farm to fork
and i am looking forward
to the next meeting i am looking forward
to interact both with the providers
of these exciting interesting existing
already being deployed agricultural
technologies
as well as uh with the the farmers
that are the heart
and and really the the passion
that they put in uh their work of
uh what they produce
and we eat thank you very much
and see you in the next episode of the
context
[Music]