[Music]
[Applause]
welcome to this lecture on commodity
mapping i am you and together with my
colleague catching we will introduce you
to what commodity mapping is and why
it's useful
agricultural commodities are commercial
crops and animals that are grown or
raised on farms or plantations
their worldwide exports are worth
trillions of dollars commodity maps show
the dynamic production locations of
different commodities
here you can see on the slide an example
of a commodity map
commodity maps are useful for a variety
of reasons including the following
first of all agricultural expansion is
an important driver of deforestation and
forest degradation
in combination with data on
deforestation commodity maps can provide
insight as to which products are
produced after deforestation in for
example protected areas
it is important to note however that
while follow-up land use provides an
indication as to what commodities are
associated with deforestation the
follow-up land use after deforestation
is not always the actual deforestation
driver
imagine for example an area where a
plantation is opportunistically planted
in an area that
has been deforested by a natural fire a
few months prior
secondly commodity maps can foster
estimation of greenhouse gas emissions
and removals after deforestation as
different commodities are associated
with different carbon stocks and
greenhouse gas emissions
for example
a big forest or big trees store more
carbon than small bushes
thirdly commodity maps provide companies
and consumers with insight into their
product supply chains
but there might be many more
applications for commodity mapping
perhaps you can think of some
in this module you will learn important
skills to get started on commodity
mapping
two things are important to keep in mind
first of all land use forms the basis of
commodity mapping other than land cover
maps which show the physical land type
for example grassland and water
land use maps indicate how people use an
area
for example for a livestock raising or
fishery
the difference between land cover and
land use is not always straightforward
think for example of the commodities
that you will be mapping in this
tutorial
spoiler alert cocoa palm and rubber
are we talking about land use or land
cover here
perhaps surprisingly these crops are
agricultural land use classes
land cover maps will generally classify
such crops under forest
once they reach the canopy density and
height usually 5 meters to suit the
forest definition
also be aware that land use is generally
difficult to map as it requires expert
interpretation
some commodities are even impossible to
map directly from land use
for example products such as leather and
beef cannot be mapped although their
production areas
may be derived from livestock raising
at the end of this tutorial
you will be an expert on commodity
mapping ready to do some interpretation
good luck