plant friends if you are looking for
plenty book recommendations
i've got you covered on today's video
blue pengrow
youtube show planned friends i have read
so many good
planty books in 2020 uh
for a combination of reasons some of
them being me wanting to continue my
education and research
and some of them being that i have
needed an escape more than ever and i've
needed to feel connected to
nature and plants more than ever um and
i've found some really great books that
i wanted to share with you
so i'm gonna break down eight books that
i've read in 2020 that have had a really
significant impact on me
if you like this type of video let me
know in the comments because i've
certainly read more than eight books but
i'm just kind of starting with
the creme de la creme of my reading and
i was thinking maybe i could break them
down in different genres
but speaking of genres this collection
of eight books really spans
a variety of genres and styles of book
so i really hope that within the eight
there's a little something for everyone
to help everyone keep blooming and
growing
okay book number one the overstory by
richard powers
this book might be the best book i've
ever read in my whole life
and it doesn't make any sense because i
never read fiction i'm a huge self-help
reader i'm a huge educational book
reader
and this book like captured my heart and
spirit
and soul in such a way so richard powers
he won
the pulitzer prize for it
and this came out several years ago i'm
totally late to the game
um but there was like a span of a week
where
like three different people recommended
it to me and so i finally picked it up
it's
an investment of a read plant friends
but i can't suggest it enough
it's a fictional book that intertwines
five or six different stories of
different people who are completely
unrelated and
they're all about plants every person
comes from a different background
a different experience but they're all
tied spiritually to plants in some way
and the way that richard powers
orchestrates this book
the inter the intertwining of the
different characters and the deep
commitment and um connection that all of
the characters have
i felt so seen as a reader like i could
not put this book down
and the way that the book is organized
is the beginning the chapters are much
longer and then towards the end the
chapters get shorter and shorter and the
style of the book kind of changes
um i would read a chapter a morning
so this was the way i woke up um every
morning i read
only one chapter and sometimes you want
to read more but it was just kind of how
i did it i let myself just read
and that was successful for the first
half of the book which is the more like
traditional form book and then as the
book kind of takes off
i couldn't put the book down i have
never experienced this reading a book
before but i would be in my bed
late at night billy would be asleep next
to me with
my cell phone flashlight reading the
book because i literally couldn't put it
down
so i really like this book and if you
like plants
if you feel connected to nature
especially trees
especially if you have ever seen
redwoods before or if you have a
curiosity around
redwoods oh my gosh try this book i know
it's an investment of a read it's
a big book i am not a reader i do not
read big books like this but
really it's totally worth it so i hope
you try it and enjoy it
number two catalog of unabashed
gratitude unabashed right yeah unabashed
gratitude by ross gay
i found ross gay um during the black
lives matter movement because he wrote
this
unbelievably beautiful poem about eric
garner and
his time in the horticultural department
if you listened to
the episode i did called growing
together i read the poem at the end of
it
so i was so taken by this poem and i'm
i've never bought a book of poetry
before
but i was so taken by this poem that i
started researching ross gay and
he actually is this gardener and poet
beautiful prolific poet and he's got a
bunch of poems that are all about plants
and so
i ordered this book um a catalog of
unabashed gratitude it has
20 or more poems in it and once again
just like the overstory
lately i've been starting every morning
with my cup of coffee
my plants and a poem by ross gay so i
just like say
a poem a day by ross gay keeps the blues
away
um he writes with such whimsy
and depth and he makes me like poetry
and i'm not a poetry girl you know he
brings like a smile to my face
the ode to unbuttoning my shirt and um
i particularly really liked the poem to
the mulberry tree
um and obviously the title poem of the
book catalog of unabashed gratitude had
me
a little weepy and with in my morning
cup of coffee
he's so real but also there's like so
much hope in his
writing and um also he's just a gardener
and nature and plants show up in his
poems in really beautiful ways so
i can't recommend this enough moving on
to number three
the nature fix this was recommended to
me by
my teacher um in my new york botanical
garden
horticultural therapy class this book
has been the answer to my prayers
because i in 2020
am starting to realize like how screen
addicted
our generation and society is and it's
really starting to freak me out and i
think
my mission on in this world is to like
help people connect
to plants because also they need to
disconnect from screens and that's like
a big
mission for bloom and grow and as i like
really start to understand this on a
deeper level i start getting more
curious about
about the science behind why
we feel so connected to plants and why
plants do make people happy
and this book is it so this woman
florence williams
she spent two years researching the
people plant connection
and she meets with all i mean all of
these studies that i'm reading she meets
with like all of the scientists
and breaks down studies and
and really um captures a lot of the
struggle of
american but i think international um
the international struggle of like go go
go
and being stuck with uh stuck in like a
really crazy schedule
the biggest thing for me with this book
is actually not learning about plants
but learning about sound
she has a whole chapter on understanding
how sounds affect us and how little um
preserved nature sounds there are in the
world
because streets are gonna interfere with
sound so there are only a few places in
the states that still you can go
and not hear a plane or a um
car or have um light come in you know so
that has made me really think about
sound differently
and my eyes are like way more open
to like what i hear that's artificial
and that's natural
and i appreciate the crickets outside a
lot more so highly recommend the nature
fix
next up speaking of the nature fix
forest bathing so this was
one of the first books i read in the
quarantine i was feeling super
disconnected to nature super anxious
obviously i was um
quarantining in new york city in like
the epicenter of the pandemic
and i was googling the concept of forest
bathing because i noticed that whenever
i would come to phila farm
i would go for a walk in the forest with
my mom and it was just the most amazing
experience
i heard this concept of forest bathing i
started googling it and i found this
book so it's by dr
king lee who is a forest medicine
researcher in japan
and in japan forest bathing or shinrin
yoku is the practice
it's a medicinal practice that the
japanese
culture has been practicing for a while
and there are like
hospital and government approved forest
medicine centers
in forests so anyway he goes over not
only his studies behind
he's taken like subjects and
put them through this forest bathing and
it like lowers their blood pressure and
their stress and their hormones and it
increases like your ability to
fight cancer it's crazy um but he also
makes really practical ways to do forest
bathing even if you're not by
forest so for me i've started we've left
the city i've started walking in the
forest every day
but also like he talks about diffusing
essential oils and so i've started
diffusing
um tree oils in my house uh
hinoki and basically everything he
suggests in this book i bought
so um if you're interested in getting
outdoors and why it's so good for you
this book was great i loved it
okay book number five this is a coloring
book
it's an adult coloring book and it's
called a girl and her plants and it's by
my
one of my very first plant friends aisha
richardson so she
we met at a summer rain oaks plant swap
i think was the first time we met she
was one of my very first plant friends
and um she's launched her company love
and paper new york and she makes the
cutest planty pins
and accessories and greeting cards
and in the pandemics she launched a
kickstarter or
her coloring book and the coloring book
is awesome
it's got so much of her in it she's got
a really cool illustration style
but it's all um it's different women and
their plants and all the illustrations
in it
are awesome and a really great
opportunity to get off your screen
and color so if you're interested i
would highly
suggest coloring with aisha i'm so proud
of her
and it's just so fun to see you know now
that you've been in the plant space for
a while it's fun to see
how everyone's blooming and growing so
very proud of aisha
next up farming while black by leah
penniman
this was recommended to me by cola b
talking when she came on
the blooming girl radio podcast to talk
about historic black
plant parents basically we had an
amazing conversation
she recommended this book leah pennamon
founded soul fire farm
and this book is all about the black
experience being connected and
disconnected to cultivating land
and farming land um and it's actually
kind of a book about how to farm land
but for me it was extremely informative
and in my journey to examine my
privilege and try and understand
the black experience more and just open
my eyes
to more which i need to do and need to
do the work for
this was really helpful and i highly
recommend even if you're not a farmer
just getting the book and reading the
intro
leah pennamon is so smart
and writes so interestingly and
listening to her
say you know food deserts
can be called a food apart apartheid
um that really like struck and
has caused me to like really want to
examine that and food deserts and
and food injustice and the systemic
issue we've got going on in our country
so
if you're interested in learning more
check this book out
two more books and then we're going to
be done another planned friend of mine
danae
horst from folia collective launched
house plants for all in the pandemic so
a lot of influencers and a lot of my
plant friends have house plant care
books out on the market but what i love
about this book house plants for all is
it's more of a book about
styling and danae breaks down different
environment profiles
if you have a sunny room a humid room a
dark room and then she shows you the
different plants that you should
put in those rooms and how to style them
and gives you care advice
for those specific rooms so it's a style
of book that i feel like isn't on the
market these days and it's super
creative
i'm so proud of danae um and also the
cool thing about it
it's it's like kind of small it's a
perfect coffee table type book and it's
laid out it's a super easy read
um so i think it's really giftable for
the holiday season so check that out
and last but not least a family guide to
terrariums
i'm surprised that i'm recommending this
but i came across this book
um because of a recent episode of the
bloom and girl radio podcast
indoor plant projects for kids and the
podcast episode is all about the fact
that kids are indoors more than ever
parents are becoming teachers teachers
are having to teach virtually
it's this crazy time classrooms look
different so how can we
set up kids for success by incorporating
indoor garden projects with them
to learn science and also just like
disconnect from screens
it was a great episode if you have a kid
that's home virtually learning but
anyway patricia
bouzou launched this book a family guide
to terrariums and it's freaking awesome
so if you have a kid i would suggest
checking this out
she not only um breaks down i think
there's like 15 different terrariums
that you can make with kids of like all
different sizes and like levels of
difficulty
but the beginning of the book like is
really interesting she breaks down
all the different components of soil um
when she tells you about
water in your terrarium she talks about
the water cycle and science like it's a
really informative book
for your kids but also like for you like
for your plant parentness so um
check it out if you're interested so
those are my eight books that i have
loved and
have influenced me i hope there's
something inspiring for you in there and
i hope maybe
one of them piques your interest the
links are all in the show notes it's
really exciting i've partnered with
bookstore.com
i've become their affiliate so
bookstore.com is a way for you to buy
books
not on amazon and support local
bookshops
so they um support local bookshops
through the sales of the books
it's a really interesting business i
think it's still in its beta
but i have the affiliate links to buy
the books through bookstore.com to
support local
in the show notes if you're interested
in supporting bloom and grow
when buying these books so affiliate
links if you ever hear influencers talk
about that means that when you buy a
link when you click the link in the show
notes and you buy the book a portion of
that purchase goes directly to bloom
grow to support
the show and it's at no cost to you so
it costs you literally nothing to
um support bloom and grow as long as
you're buying the book
but i hope you like these books i would
love to hear what you guys have been
reading in the comments let me know let
me know which ones are you're interested
in
and what books you might recommend me
and if this is like a highly enjoyed
episode i'm happy to make more because
i've actually got
a whole bookshelf these two shelves are
plants but the shelves under there are
like literally all planty gardening
books so i hope you can get off your
screens get
into a book i can't recommend the over
story enough
i've really fell in love with that book
but i really can't recommend all these
books enough and until next time plant
friends keep bloopers
[Music]
blue