time we're gonna go through some of the
question and answers there's been
several posted on the QA farms some have
been answered in text form but we're
gonna go through them orally here as
well let's go bill first one of the
questions was on well I think this
question ended up going to both both
bill and Doug but you know the the waist
being land applied and I think the
alligator's you showed us the
demonstration of the irrigation duck
bill are there some of the solid
material some of the solid solid matter
from the nutrients well you know reality
there the biggest part of waste that we
get from fishes after processing and
there's there's actually two things we
do with that well is more than that we
we have a large mink industry here and
that that's one of the primary one of
the best resources to use for the mink
industry whether whether you like mink
or not farming but but that's one thing
we have a large company here that makes
fish hydrolysate and I actually make
that two and basically it's it's
digesting the everything that you don't
eat so that's the head though the
innards and scales everything the skin
whatever you don't eat is digested in a
cold digestion process and you make fish
hydrolysate which is quite a bit
different than the stuff you can buy in
the store this is a it doesn't smell as
bad it's not cooked or any of the
nutrients taken out of it so it's uh if
you can buy fish hydrolysate made that
way it's an organic supplement and and
people that are in the the gardening
business the flower gardens and the
vegetable gardens they just love it and
then they can also be used for also
feels and you can be written guys with
the deer farms you might be interested
also love it because are there food
plots
are as a high priority item and I'm
trying to think of another but anyway I
also have the high school's use it in
hydroponics so we can take fish I draw
the sate and use it directly and get rid
of all the other fertilizers and they
they actually like it better than any
other first synthetic fertilizer that
they've bought so but then the other
side of that is you can directly apply
fish waste right and soil to and that's
in large processing facilities that's
what they do so there's it's almost
nothing wasted on that site with
alligator farming the waste the nutrient
material can be land applied and you
demonstrate an irrigation system have
you seen alligator manure being applied
using other systems yes all right yeah
actually Ron one of the things he was
doing was trying to precipitate although
he was not really looking that as a as a
fertilizer more of an industrial source
of phosphate the I was looking at the
analyses the if you had some kind of
solid separation the solid portion of
the the pond waste was almost all
phosphorus and pretty good that it's
basically all phosphorus and then the
liquid portion is about looks like about
a hundred to one PK into the phosphate
so it's uh if you could separate the
solids and store it in a way that would
or maybe digest it so they wouldn't
smell so much that would make a very
good phosphorus fertilizer that could be
transported long ways and for cropping
systems the through irrigation basically
if you separate the solids then you you
could apply to an irrigation system like
a center pivot so I know there's no
there's nothing that would keep you
from using that other than the odor
control thanks Brandon to you Doug just
brought up transportation of manure and
the moisture content all the manure
plays into that you compared the
moisture content between the different
types of servants you want to comment on
that and and the application of that
transport transport ability of the
manure I will and that was one question
that came up when the QA typed in and I
tried there's fun about a minute ago one
of the big things would see especially
in the county where I am in Texas is we
used to be the largest dairy capital in
Texas
if since moves to the Panhandle the big
thing about dairy especially dairy
manure dairy excellent the limitation is
water content it is only viable for a
couple of miles and after that the
break-even no longer make sense for
application so we're not even as worried
with yes there are environmental
regulations there environmental concerns
one application but a lot of that
environmental concern becomes we only
have a finite area where it can be
applied and then we can't apply it any
further
that's really and I can't say that any
deer farming operations are making use
of this right now but that's where I see
the next big thing the big opportunity
is this is a dry manure you don't have
the energy input of drying it down
before it can be used so we've got
already made products that all it needs
to be done is transport thank you Bill a
question to you reiterating and that
came through the through the Q&A with
aquaculture what are thoughts about
keeping prices competitive with foreign
markets such as Southeast Asia well you
know right now 90 some percent of
everything that we do is import it it is
it's strange very difficult to get our
arms on it and I've been working on that
for about twenty years
fortunately I'm raising a product it
doesn't have any competition but I the
biggest one I see is that people are are
growing as tilapia and a lot of them are
are doing tilapia or they have to do it
indoors or
even for assault but tilapia is warm
water I think about 80 degrees is
optimum but when you come to process
it's almost none of it is process the
United States and that's a killer
they have another double set of bones
and I've been trying to figure out what
to do with it because of all the big
markets are the big tilapia producers
that I know of none of them sell their
fish process and that means that they
all have to go to live markets and and I
never even would have thought of that
but so you're you're strapped with a
large trucking live fish to live markets
and there's only a few big cities that
can take large quantities of that so
that I mean that's just one species I
know for a long long time and I'm
straying out of my my expertise in
catfish farmers were doing real well and
then they had import problems and they
had some serious problems but it's
always going to be a problem and and I
work with the North Central Regional
aquaculture center I'm on their board
and we are constantly looking for
species to raise that we can do
economically and that's the key so as
you saw in my church a lot of the fish
that we're raising now are
non-indigenous species to our our state
and we're trying to do more and more
shrimp is coming in I think Marcus first
shrimp will be very strong if we can get
the technology down if we can get the
perch going that'll be big we're working
on walleye too and the perch and a
walleye earned there's no competition
from agent imports at all so I mean
there's gotta pick your species but you
have to pick your economics too and it's
not that simple I don't know about the
rest of the audience but through all
three presentations I kept hearing some
very strong similarities to those
species
we are a lot more familiar with Doug a
question for you as I look outside my
window here in Minnesota is the
snowstorm and the blizzard has started
why are the alligators in Louisiana
generally kept under roots I think when
I was researching for this I think most
of the ones in Florida are also kept
under roof I think it's because they
they won't escape for one thing and the
other thing is probably they get a
better product if they can control the
climate heat is you saw those buildings
were very well insulated but I don't
think heat is that big of a problem for
them particularly if they have the
sprinklers but they get a better control
over the the leather which is their
moneymaker
mostly brand another question for you
with with the in Texas or larger region
if you're familiar with it what is the
the main for the different species of
servants what what is the main purpose
of raising room is it for the hunting or
is it for the for the meat rather the
hunting is always going to be the
biggest deal especially in this state
but I know in other areas to big-game
ranchers have popped up and it's
becoming a bigger thing we're losing
some public lands so there are not as
many native populations we've gotten
disease issues chronic wasting disease
being the biggest one among service
they're taking out some of the wild
populations so it's going to be the big
game army marketable meat it's always
going to take a second place to it if
for no other reason than the markets not
seeing any more questions come up in the
QA so I think well we'll start wrapping
it up here I want to thank our three
speakers
Brandon Doug and Bill for sharing their
sharing their background and their
insights into these less than typical
species for the rest of us