hey folks this is Josh Tony rich farmer
welcome to the farm blog today beautiful
beautiful day here on the farm I've been
out working in the garden and as I
started working out in the garden this
morning something disturbing has
happened what's going on right now is
there is an airplane flying about a
hundred feet above the tree line here on
the farm and it's spraying some sort of
pesticide on my farm this is a
government mandated pesticide spray
going on on my farm I can smell it in
the air I was out working in the garden
we're gonna take you down and show you
the garden we're gonna show you this
plain here in just a minute it's been
flying back and forth back and forth
over my farm all morning long and I'm
afraid to go outside I'm afraid to
breathe this stuff in I don't want to
breathe it in so I'll show you guys so
come along today we'll give you a little
garden update and I'm gonna show you
this plane that's flying over spraying
pesticide across my farm it's something
something's not right about that I had
no choice no choice in this matter at
all
[Music]
guys before we get started I want to
show you some cool new additions to the
farm family check them out guys we ended
up getting six little baby ducks for the
farm here and this is our little mobile
coop idea basically it's just a rope
right here and we just move this coop
basically every day or every other day
and the back of it is on snow skis so
pretty cool little setup you just lift
up on the front and you pull this coop
from different paddock to different
paddock little squares and that's so the
baby ducks get fresh grass every day
cool basically every morning my routine
when I'm not working is to get up go out
in the garden do a little bit of work in
the garden for an hour or so and I'll
take you through and I'll show you what
we're doing I've got some interesting
concepts on weed control and chicken
coops down here - guys please click that
like button this is your first time -
Stern your Ridge Farm channel please
subscribe to the channel and follow us
on our farm journey I'll show you what I
was doing this morning when I walked
outside I'll just walk over here in the
garden show you so these are our tomato
plants these are beef eater tomato
plants and this is our trellis system
posted a video about that a couple days
ago and these are more Tomatoes I've got
a nice decent little line of gourds out
here more Tomatoes out there squash
different squashes and corn over here
you know just a simple garden guys I've
doing a lot of weed control as you can
tell look at how nice that is
just no weeds whatsoever all natural so
I'll show you what we're doing on weed
control this area here looked like that
right there that's how many weeds were
growing up through all of my squash
plants so we went through with a hoe and
just hold them out and cleaned up the
weeds all natural no sprays no nothing
like that now my corn it's another story
I haven't been in there and weeded yet
but we'll get in there in the next day
or so now we've got a beautiful row of
green beans going right here and this is
again the trellis system that we're
using and we've got some cucumbers and
that's our orchard that you can see out
there I think we have about sixty fruit
trees growing and our honeybees these
are our cucumbers here and we have a
little trellis system and we have a
couple
rose that we're just gonna weed and
we'll be planting some okra right here
so we're leaving a few extra rows just
in case we want to plant some extra
goodies in the garden this year so
everything here in the garden is
symbiotic symbiotic meaning everything
works on everything else the honeybees
are right back there they are there for
fertilizing our fruit trees which are
there and for our garden and we also
have our chickens closeby so we can
spread chicken manure here on the garden
too
now once the garden Peters out at the
end of the season well fence this whole
area in and leave the chickens in here
and let them munch down all the goodies
and put down some good but fertilizer
for us manure that good old but
fertilizer this will be a wonderful
garden for us to feed our family on most
of the time when we plant stuff like
green beans we'll do a lot of canning so
there'll be a lot of canning videos to
come soon but I really just want to come
out here show you the garden to show you
what's going on and talk to you about
this government mandated spraying that
I'm just not comfortable with I'm just
not comfortable with it guys
post a comment down there tell me what
you think soon as this plane flies over
again he must have went and reloaded
with spray but I mean I can taste it in
the air I can taste it on the back of my
teeth and when I was out here working
this morning I actually had to go back
into the house shut all the windows and
you know I was just afraid that
breathing that stuff was gonna make me
sick not cool not cool let's get you a
shot of this plane when it flies over
it's literally skimming the top of the
trees so here on the farm channel we use
a drone sometimes when we fly the drone
around and we have to stay below 400
feet now this plane is clearly below 400
feet
that's my airspace that's the air that I
breathe I don't know again I asked you
post a comment down there should I have
to go inside for fear of this chemical
spray that's being released into the air
over my farm are 200 acre farm here it
comes here comes the plane
[Music]
I don't want to breathe this that's
flying right over my field over there
[Music]
I shouldn't have to breathe that I
shouldn't have to breathe this man I
shouldn't have to breathe this in a free
country I didn't vote for that I didn't
vote for some airplane to be flying over
my farm spraying for a gypsy moth now it
might be for the best if any of you guys
know about this stuff leave a comment
down there we're gonna actually hop on
the Gator here and we're gonna run over
and I'll show you one of these little
gypsy moth traps okay it's a big orange
trap all right so I'm over here on the
other side of my farm and this chemical
spray it just feels like it's coating my
body so right here is one of the gypsy
moth traps so you can see a little flag
from the road and right here is one of
the traps it's like a corrugated plastic
trap that's set up for these gypsy moths
now the whole area here just has a foul
smell of spring going on I don't know
exactly what the what the spray is but
we all received a letter from the
government saying that the spray was
safe and then it wouldn't harm you I
smell it if I smell it they can harm me
I don't know I'm gonna I'm gonna get
over here in the middle of my field and
get a shot of this plane coming over
here I mean I could so bad it's so bad
that I'm underneath where the plane is
flying and my neighbor's kids are
outside playing and I just want to tell
them to go inside the basic gist of this
is that the government can come in and
do whatever they want to do I guess guys
I really hesitated to make this video I
stood about it and I've stood about it
enough to where I think it's probably
just about quitting time for this spray
crew that's flying over I don't know
tell me what you think they're dropping
pesticide on my land on my trees on my
honeybees on my garden I don't know what
this pesticide is it's supposed to kill
the gypsy moth or the gypsy moth larvae
I don't know a whole lot of history on
the gypsy moth I hear that they attack
the ash tree and we have ash trees
around here but not very many of them
there's just a smell there's just a
chemical smell in the air you can feel
it in your in your mouth you can field
in your nose you can feel it on your
skin and to me something's not right
about that I couldn't work in my garden
this morning for fear of being sprayed
by government-mandated
airplane there's just something not
right about that if any of you guys know
anything about the gypsy moth or if
anything like this has ever happened to
you post me a comment down there and
just tell me what you think even if this
hasn't happened to you tell me what you
think I don't know whether they're
organic farms around here I do know that
they're organic tobacco farms around
here and they're flying over them
spraying them too so I don't know does
that ruin the organic miss of of your
garden of your tobacco farm I don't know
I was torn about doing a video about
this because I guess it's for the best I
guess it's for the greater good but to
me I should be able to work out in my
garden in the morning and not worry
about an airplane flying over spraying
me with pesticide from the government
guys thanks a lot for watching the farm
vlog today I just wanted to show you one
of the concerns one of the things that's
going on on the farm give you a little
garden update and you know just tell you
what I'm concerned about here so this is
your first time Pamela like button click
that little bell down there don't notify
when I post a new video and
we'll see you next time on Stoney Ridge
farm Channel
[Music]
Pierce we had some ways opposed to me
stone Tyrion
[Music]