thank you
thanks very much
um
so today what I want to do is try to
talk about mob grazing and I guess mob
grazing's prob probably been around for
you know maybe 10 years
and when you talk to people and about
you know what is it no one can give you
a real definition and there was an
extension uh agent in Nebraska Terry
gomper to did a study a survey of of
producers and basically you know try to
get some information about what that is
and basically there's
you know probably it's it's a high
stocking density from maybe 20 to 25 000
pounds of live weight of animals to to
maybe somewhere up towards a million
pounds and and so people are moving
livestock uh perhaps once a day to to
several times a day when you start
moving to higher stock densities
and
with that one of the targets could be
you know High Trampoline and high
consumption of forage and another
component to this of course is there's
there's more labor that's involved and
so there's really no you cannot no one's
made a definition of what it is uh there
are people that said it's an it's a high
stock density or it's an ultra high
stock density and and perhaps people
throw out things like well yeah to you
know 25 000 pounds of lightweight per
acre is really kind of a souped-up
manage intensive grazing and so really
you've got to be up towards that 200 000
300 000 things like that but when
there's really no standard definition
and no
um no no group has come up with that
definition so basically I I just kind of
showcase it is is really shared
characteristics
usually when you're talking to
to people about mob grazing or you're
listening to gurus talk about mob
grazing they're really talking about
probably two things and one is what they
call a landscaping where you're trying
to improve the probably the soil health
and the vegetation of that land so the
idea is kind of of reclamation so there
may be land that had been beat up in the
past and you're really looking at trying
to use the livestock in an intensive way
to try to in to get more of that litter
and that biomass above ground biomass
and try to trample it with livestock and
get it in contact with that soil surface
so you can let all that soil biota do
its work and try to to add organic
matter to that to that soil surface and
and it also in that process we're
hearing people are are making
improvements
um with that livestock action uh adding
diversity to their systems another
aspect about what's happening with as
you increase that stocking density uh
what we're finding is that we're
actually getting increased Harvest
efficiency so that translates to a
higher carrying capacity so what I mean
about
um Harvest efficiency is that it's that
percentage of the forage that's produced
how much of that goes down the throat of
the animal so in Range Systems rangeland
people we talk about utilization and
utilization is actually The
Disappearance of that vegetation not
that has part to do with consumption but
it's also disappearance that's lost
through a maybe destructive forces such
as trampoline and consumption by
wildlife and insects and those kind of
things and the natural weathering
process and so we've in in more semi-air
and arid systems where perhaps people
have been using more season long
continuous grazing when you have very
large pastures we've talked about
concepts of take half leave half so that
we're aiming for a 50 utilization
and that means uh we're leaving 50 of
that biomass for plant Vigor for that
plant Community to sustain itself and so
what's actually happening if we leave 50
and take 50 percent
really only half of that half that we're
taking is actually going down the throat
so in our very
conventional systems under season long
continuous grazing moderate stocking
we're only getting about 25 percent
Harvest efficiency so when you have that
assumption and you make your
calculations we can set that stocking
rate and so
societies like the society for range
management that works with ranchers and
and range professionals we've developed
these kind of safety valves where we
know in our in in the way in the
rangeland ecology that we can sustain
that rangeland with A season-long
continuous grazing model or system with
taking a 25 Harvest efficiency results
in actually 50 percent utilization and
because we were having some of that
forage that's disappearing by insects
and Wildlife and then we're we're
maintaining that
um that plant Community Integrity with a
50 utilization and so what we're finding
is actually that mob grazing is kind of
ignoring this take half leave half Rule
and just blowing past that and we're
getting much higher efficiencies of
harvest and so I'm going to show that
we're actually getting somewhere towards
35 maybe 40 50 60 percent Harvest
efficiency and and that is not in a
season-long continuous system so I'll
have to bring together these concepts of
of use and then rest periods that
happens with the mob grazing
so this study uh was funded through a
research and education Sarah Grant and
we had
um several producers that were contacted
and were interested in in developing
this these producers were already doing
mob grazing and uh what what I wanted to
do was to kind of come alongside them
and say you know we're not going to ask
you to do anything different than you're
doing what we'd like to do is actually
document what you're doing so that we
can share that with with the public and
kind of understand
um you know what is Mob grazing for some
people in South Dakota and actually this
also had some other additional funding
with it with a with a an nrcscig Grant
where we we partnered with some with
some people in Nebraska so there's
actually five other locations in
Nebraska that were kind of following
similar similar protocols so you can see
we've got a nice uh gradient across the
state of South Dakota on the east side
across the west and we had a few part
Partners up in the in the north and kind
of in this region close to Aberdeen and
if you go if you look across South
Dakota on the on the I-29 Corridor on
the eastern part of South Dakota we're
probably 23 inch rainfall and you get
out towards Rapid City and then we're
around 15 to 17. so in the middle of the
state they're probably around between 17
and 20 and further out we so we've got a
nice uh understanding of that rainfall
and how that looks in terms of the
vegetation and we're going to see that
people are adapting to that and they're
doing things differently because of that
so this is a stocking density kind of
characterizing what people are doing in
terms of the
um thousands of pounds of beef per acre
so we've got a couple of these sites
um the new Underwood site and the queen
site are out west Queen is by Wall South
Dakota and the new Underwood is just by
Rapid City and so you can see their
stocking densities are somewhere around
20 to 25 000 and as you uh move towards
the east then we're but are typically
what we're finding is they're somewhere
around 50 000 pounds per Acres our
stocking density and in 2012 there was a
quite a severe drought and so that
definitely dropped the stocking rate the
one outlier is actually Reliance and
that's actually showing on this graph at
three hundred thousand he was actually
at a million and he was doing that just
for fun to try to demonstrate what that
would look like so I think he was moving
somewhere to 12 or 5 15 times a day to
be able to achieve that so that he had I
wanna I think it was somewhere in the uh
of 300 pair that were on a piece of
ground for 45 minutes and he had set up
ahead of time some bat latches so that
they were going off on timers and so the
cattle were actually moving themselves
and so and I and it and then we had a
comparison there was a rotation that uh
that was just moving once a day or twice
a day that at 50 000. so on so he kind
of has this really extreme so it's kind
of fun fun to look at
all right there's a lot of information
in this particular slide so I've got to
take you through it to kind of draw out
some really important things here so
first of all what we did is we went and
picked four locations with a graduate
student where we did some pretty
intensives of clipping of vegetation so
we would take a quarter meter square and
run several transects and we would clip
all that vegetation uh prior to to the
cattle turning out onto these areas and
then we would we would get the staining
biomass and we'd get the litter the old
litter that was on the ground and then
after the cattle were into that spot and
they moved on to another spot we'd come
back and locate those same transects and
then we put down another quarter meter
Square paired that up with the previous
one and then we collected and separated
stuff that was newly trampled the old
litter and the stuff that was left
standing so what we could do by
subtraction is kind of get an estimate
of disappearance by of consumption and
how much is newly trampled and those
kind of things so the first part that
you see the the darker green is
basically the the staining biomass of
the vegetation before the cattle were
put into it then the the gray bar is the
post vegetation
and uh the the lighter Green in the
middle this is the pre-litter that was
already existing and then this is the
post the post litter and so some of that
and theoretically should be the same if
the cattle aren't eating litter which
you wouldn't expect so there's going to
be a little sampling here there but one
of the things that I want to draw your
attention to is this last bar which
would be the trampoline so that's that
new litter and so what I want to show is
is uh if you make the subtraction so
you're starting with your pre-biomass
and then with your end biomass if you if
you pull out how much was trampled
then you can get how much was consumed
by livestock and so what I've put down
here is the Harvest efficiency so these
numbers are the percent of that was down
the throat
of the existing the pre-biomass
vegetation so you can see that there's a
a wide variety but you but it's more
than our typical
um if we plan a season-long continuous
grazing at moderate levels that's at
base 25 so why why these producers are
doing this is because they're getting uh
with this intensive stocking densities
up to that 25 to 50 000 to 200 or maybe
a million is is they're getting higher
Harvest efficiencies
so to put this in perspective if you
think about in Western South Dakota with
our our stocking rates are about a half
an AUM per acre and that translates to
probably a stocking density for a
six-month grazing season that's less
than 500 pounds of live weight per acre
and if you come over to the east side of
the state where we have stocking rates
somewhere maybe one and a half to maybe
two aums per acre at a traditional
rotation you might be at fi you know
moving cattle once a week we might be at
5 000 pounds per acre of live weight and
so what we're seeing is even though when
we go up to 25 000 pounds that doesn't
seem like a lot but it's you know it's
probably five times more intensive than
our our typical rotations that we used
to be doing you know when we're starting
to move livestock once a day and so one
of our producers that that's by haytai
you know he was moving
um cattle twice a day and his stocking
densities were closer to that 200 000.
the Chamberlain was around 50 000 pounds
per acre so part of it is going to be
the vegetation so what we've been
finding is that
in it as the vegetation is shorter and
in a vegetative state they tend not to
trample as much because it's sparser
thin and what they're doing is they're
consuming more and it's actually hard to
get uh newly trampled so out at this
Quinn site you know we're we've we've
got about uh maybe
um 20 of that is getting trampled and
and interestingly enough at the at the
Chamberlain site
you know they're not trampling that much
but at hay Ty
um they were getting a little bit more
trampled and the hay tie sites uh a
little was about or about the same as
productivity of the Chamberlain but it
has to do with you know if that
vegetation gets taller you know they're
more apt to probably knock some of that
down so from the late there's a remember
the two goals that white people are
probably doing this there's a
landscaping goal where you really want
to trample that vegetation to try to
build soil Health you know get more land
covered and then there's kind of maybe a
a stocking carrying capacity stocking
rate uh you know Harvest efficiency goal
where you're trying to get more
consumption and maintaining animal
performance and so in that same net
standpoint then what we're probably
meeting you know that those goals from
that that increase Harvest efficiency
so this is where the economics play in
that you're spending your time you know
most of the producers probably spend
about a half an hour maybe an hour at
most to move the livestock a day and
it's it's paying off in terms of they're
able to you know increase that stocking
density and getting that higher Harvest
efficiency
and so what we're finding is that how
how do they do that if these Harvest
efficiencies and these utilization rates
remember utilization is basically the
consumption plus trampoline and so those
are pretty high notice if you just
calculate utilization that would be your
pre-vegetation minus the post vegetation
and that difference is really high so a
lot of times we're getting eighty
percent utilization and of that 80
percent
maybe 40 or so of it is is down the
throat the other 40 may be trampled or
you know there's some proportion of
those and so from a as a trained person
in the range science that is uh
stressful because we're thinking oh
we're blowing past take half leave half
and and that can't be good for the plant
Community is that actually a sustainable
practice so had to wrestle with with
these Concepts so so here's what's
happening
you graze a piece of land for one day or
for half a day and you're not coming
back to it for a whole year
so they're getting a long rest period
you got a very intensive
you know utilization very high but a lot
of rest so what I like to do to
translate what this means to me is let's
for example let's say you're you're
harvesting a hay field
well we Harvest hay pretty much every at
the same time every year so let's say
you have a hay field it's July 1st you
come in with your sickle bar Mower and
you cut it down at you know a few inches
off the ground you're probably getting
80 90 percent Harvest efficiency and we
do that for 50 hundred years whatever
and it comes back and you get the same
productivity every single year obviously
there's fluctuations based on you know
rainfall but that's a sustainable
practice because it's always producing
about the same amount so if we switch to
these higher stocking density kind of
systems where we're only on that piece
of ground for half a day or for a day
essentially we're kind of taking that
same concept and and applying it to
livestock so the livestock are the mower
yeah they're not getting 80 or 90
percent of it they're maybe getting 40
and knocking down 40 or they're getting
60 and knocking down 20 but you get the
point that because we have such long
rest periods up to a year it does not
hurt the vegetation
now we know that
some of the rest periods some of that
time period you know is going to be
dormant season so when we talk about
resting for an entire year there are
times when you can rest land in the
winter it does really no good it's going
to be key on what's the growth rate of
these plants afterwards so if you graze
these things in a stage where there the
grass is in a boot stage and you hit it
hard every year you're probably going to
set it back because plants are most
vulnerable in the boot stage if you wait
till the plants are headed out and graze
it that time of year you're probably not
going to hurt the plants because when
plants have headed out they've put down
most of of what they need from the root
structure so when I think about
simplistic way of grazing and what kind
of impact am I going to have below
ground is just think about
um when the plant is tall it's probably
tall below ground when the plant is
short it's probably short below ground
so depending upon when you graze that's
kind of reflective of the impact that
you're going to have below ground so
when we graze when the plant is tall
we're not going to hurt it because it's
probably set a lot of you know root
structure
on a side note I had a grad student that
at our Volga site which was near
Brookings to kind of play around with
different stocking densities so we had
our producers where we we let them do
what they wanted to do and and to kind
of vary between 25 up to maybe 200 000
pound stocking rate and so what we
wanted to do was look at stocky rates
from from 50 000 pounds up to 800 000
pounds so what we did is we just we
would put the enough for one day or two
days or we would go towards you know
moving maybe
um eight times a day or ten times a day
those kind of things and so we varied
that and then we did the same thing we
went ahead into the paddock before they
came and clipped the samples separated
into those standing vegetation litter
and then we allowed the animals to graze
those paddocks and then we pulled them
off and then we went back to those same
areas and put down a sample next to this
area that we clipped before and then and
we had the new trampled we had the old
litter and we had the standing
vegetation so what I'm showing you is
the the utilization so the remember the
utilization is what was
um is the pre-vegetation and you
subtract off the post so utilization is
consumption plus trampoline and and two
in 2012 we had that we had that drought
and so we had some issues of course
um didn't want to hurt the grass and and
did have as much forage and then in 2013
it was a little bit uh wetter and so
what you're seeing is kind of is that
what are we achieving you know how much
are the cattle eating and knocking
things down and what it kind of appears
that is that how much it's what stocking
density is enough
are is a 50 000 pound stock density
enough to to achieve some of these
things do you need a hundred do you need
200 do you need 400 800 because we have
producers
um throughout North America that are
going from anywhere from that 25 to 50
that maybe are going up to like Dennis
Neil Dennis up in Canada that may be up
towards a million and so is there kind
of this law diminishing returns is like
how much is enough and so what we found
is that you know in that that there's a
you know an increase in utilization then
it kind of levels off and the same kind
of thing here is that there's there's
only so much you can do and so what
we're finding out is that you know yeah
maybe
um you know at 50 000 pounds depending
upon the the vegetation where where
we're at you know maybe 200 000 pounds
is enough in that and that may be moving
twice a day in in higher rainfall
environments but at 200 000 pounds of
stocking weight or live weight in
Western environments with less
vegetation you have to move several
times a day
so and then part of the other thing was
just to kind of compare this to folks
that are doing mob grazing so at some of
the sites they had a comparison that we
could do with mob grazing and here this
is just ocular estimates of of the grass
cover so it wasn't the veg it wasn't
clipping the vegetation but we would
make these ocular estimates of before
and after and so what I'm showing you
again is the is the before you go into
the paddock and then the after and then
you can make those subtractions to get
at that utilization and and kind of
consumption things and so what we're
showing here is that yeah they're
getting more they're getting more
utilization compared to the rotation
with the mob grazing same thing so when
you just look at mob versus rotation
so so the bottom line is you know again
just reiterating why are people wanting
to do this why are they intensifying
this uh rotational grazing with this mob
grazing and it really comes comes down
to it is that
um they're gaining a higher Harvest
efficiency there's that uh higher we're
getting higher utilization but it's a
safe practice because we're only on that
piece of land for just one day and it
gets to be rested the other parts of the
year
so here are some just some pictures of
before and after
so this is a 57 000 pounds stock density
just you know moving once a day so
that's what it looks like another
graduate student looked at some uh some
of the the weeds and so we looked at uh
Western snowberry which is a native
shrub and we also looked at some of the
um the the thistles and as you increase
that stocking density cattle then tend
to to to utilize some of those broadleaf
plants that they normally wouldn't do so
that's part of it as well
this is the one that was at uh Reliance
a sandy soil where he um grazed at that
million pounds they're only on that on a
piece of land for
um I think it was a third of an acre 45
minutes with a 300 pair and so they
really trampled it and really high
distribution of of
um of dung and then the there's where
the the rotation for 12 hours on 55 000
so you get a much higher utilization
so here's new percent new litter cover
this is again an ocular the the one that
was
um Quinn and the
um
the new Underwood sites are really far
west and so only five percent maybe 10
percent new litter these are areas that
were receiving 15 inches of rainfall and
it's just darn hard
to get new looter I mean when you're
there there's a lot of space in between
plants so can mob grazing be used for
landscaping in semi-arid arid
environments it's very challenging
because there's not a lot of biomass to
begin with and to and in order to
maintain performance there's not much to
trample
and this is done uh density so we we
looked at the paths per meter square and
so that's one of the things is that
we're increasing utilization and getting
more evenly distribution of density of
of the excrement
we had a couple tours for the
researchers on the project
in 20 in 2012 and 2013 and we also made
some videos if you want to just go to
the South Dakota grassland Coalition
sdgrass.org you can find these videos
you can search you can Google them or go
into YouTube and you'll find them packed
up those the one by Quinn Charlie
tottens by Chamberlain and then Rick
Smith is by Watertown and those are
available to look at
so bottom line is producers are getting
a higher Harvest efficiency we've also
taken soil samples to document carbon
but we haven't got all our soil samples
analyzed and so we're we're still
waiting for those but what I would say
is that
I don't expect soil carbon to probably
increase that's a slow process
especially you think about those Western
environments where there's not a lot of
new litter being added
it's that's not the mechanism for it to
happen when you're only getting five
percent new litter on the ground it much
makes a lot more sense that you probably
can increase soil carbon as you move
further east or there's a lot of biomass
and you can get it trampled on the
ground
does that make sense
so my guess is that we're going to see
these benefits
returned to us from the higher Harvest
efficiency to pay for the labor and make
make these ranches more sustainable and
these guys are only doing it for maybe
60 days
it's not sustainable to kill yourself
working that hard either and so there's
there's reason you know a time period
which which they're doing for so what
we're gonna we're expecting a graduate
student in the econ Department to finish
up his thesis here this semester and
then we're going to be able to put that
economic analysis that he'll do
when we write our final report
so the question is how many how big are
the paddocks
so they'll re they're typically uh five
acres of what uh and then it's just
depending upon how many pair so the one
by uh Chamberlain he would give four to
five acres and he'd have 250 pair
um the one producer that's since uh by
Selby he's actually here today uh he's I
think he's around four or five acres and
that same kind of thing so they're at
that 50 000 pound stocking density so
the question was did the did the
producers increase their overall
stocking rate for the year and I would
say for yes for that piece of ground
they are increasing their stocking rate
their carrying capacity so these
typically are are older crop or crop
land long time ago I've been planted
back to to introduce species and they're
purposely getting more bang for the buck
on that spot there are some the one in
Reliance it was native or not Reliance
the one by uh Chamberlain was native and
we think with uh with the system that
he's doing he's probably a two and a
half times higher than the typical nrcs
recommended take half leave half first
season long so we are getting higher
stocking rates for those pieces of land
mostly um not virgin native most of them
are these old crop land that was in the
west it's crested
yep crested wheat crested wheatgrass
Alfalfa out west intermediately
wheatgrass
um brown grass kind of things Kentucky
Bluegrass and the central the one in
hetai by Watertown Rick Smith it's a
planted back blue stem big blue stem
kind of thing and and so what they're
doing is they're intensifying on land
that can handle that but remember it's
getting rested for
essentially a year
and then how did the animals perform
like how so they're watching body
condition we didn't have weights and
most people don't take the weights but
you can tell the producers that they're
doing this for 30 days or 60 days and
then they kind of go back to a rotation
where they're getting moved you know
once a month once a week twice a week
kind of thing so they can cows can
compensate there's compensatory gain so
even if they're challenged a little bit
for 30 days or 60 days you'll find that
they will make that up in a later period
yep everybody that we're working with
our cow calf Piers except Pat guptill
that he's got
um red heifers
and I should mention Gary that's um
Cliff Millsaps over by Gary
he's got steers so he's around
17 000 pound stock density and he's
actually moving through maybe two to
three times a year so he wants to make
sure he has good animal performance to
put gain on steers so there's two people
that have yearlings everybody else's
calc pair
foreign