i'm really happy that this morning we
can welcome for our keynote speak
speaker someone who really is
exemplifying the solidarity
um that jimmy has has so rightly
suggested we need
you mentioned that vex and vets medics
don't always work that well together and
we're now going to hear from a
veterinarian who is working in a medical
institution
and developing vaccines which are
appropriate for use across that divide
in both livestock and humans
professor professor george
is a veterinarian who is the a pi at the
chemri welcome trust unit here in in
khalifi
and is a assistant professor in the
center for tropical medicine and global
health at the university of oxford um he
has just been um awarded an incredible
prize by the royal society the royal
society africa prize for his work on
viral zoonoses and he's going to talk to
us today today about his experience as
um someone who crosses these boundaries
and the development
of a rift valley fever vaccine suitable
for use in humans and livestock
so with that i would like to pass across
um to professor george worriemway and
we're really looking forward to hearing
from you today so thank you so much
thank you liam and then i'd like to
first start by thanking all the
organizers for this uh fantastic
conference uh i mean one health has been
on the fringes for a very long time but
uh it's now sort of center stage and
this is our opportunity to really push
this
agenda that really makes sense in terms
of disease control so um really like you
know following jimmy smith's uh talk i
mean that's that's gonna be a tough act
but there are some things that he
mentioned about siloed thinking and uh
in all the sort of different facets that
uh we deal with in health and
you know my my
view of one health in this space of
vaccinology is looking at developing
vaccines for humans through the lens of
animal health and vice versa so if
you're developing vaccines for
veterinary you know for veterinary use
looking at the
the impact of those vaccines and the
development process from from a human
perspective so um i'm going to talk
about a program that i've been working
on for a while now so this started
sometime in
2012 which which tells you about the
sort of scale of time that you need to
develop
vaccines and and
also speaks to the sort of rapid
development of covet vaccines that we
have seen because that has been shrunk
down to about 100 days
so it's about developing a single
vaccine for using
humans and livestock against reef valley
fever
this audience i don't think i need to
talk about um
sorry myself okay i don't think i need
to talk about the the importance of
animals to uh to human health for this
particular audience in fact this this is
a photo taken
uh among a collection of lots of photos
on the ill reflector sites so i would
urge you all to look to look at that
it's got fantastic
visual representations of the importance
of animal health to humans
and i like this photo because it just
demonstrates the pure joy that animals
bring to to humans especially children
but of course we also know about the the
economic importance the you know there's
been lots of studies demonstrating the
uh impact of life you know animals to
livelihoods financial security i always
mentioned that i was
only able to go to university because my
grandparents who raised me on an animal
and they saw that animal and that
generated income you know some some
funding for me to go to university and
i'm sure there are many others in the
audience who have uh similar stories
one of the other things we share with uh
livestock are infectious diseases in
fact over sixty percent of
infectious diseases are in humans have
uh involved an animal uh sort of
transmission and uh for the emerging
infectious diseases that we're seeing
now that you know that are increasing in
incidence that percentage is much higher
so um when you're thinking about
controlling human disease it it just
illustrates the point that you also have
to think about animal health
just because of that uh connection
um
so i'm going to talk about reef valley
fever which is a virus that was
identified in kenya in the 1930s it is
an rna virus in the family fenu very day
there are no vaccines available for it
or no specific therapeutics which is why
it has been prioritized by the african
union and the world health organization
so um rvf
is is has a complex transmission cycle
by complexity meaning that you know for
me it involves quite a lot of
mammalian species and lots of
mosquito species so but the simplistic
sort of explanation is that you have
very heavy rainfall that causes floods
which increases uh the number of
mosquitoes
to transmit the virus
sorry um
able to to transmit the virus this
increase in mosquito numbers uh allows a
mechanism for the virus to circulate in
in animals some of the mosquitoes are
infected you know for life the eggs are
you know if they had had a blood meal uh
that has infectious virus the virus has
you know gone through its progeny
through the eggs uh and so the virus
transmits i mean the mosquitoes transmit
the virus uh in animal species most
commonly sheep goats cattle and camels
and during these epidemics where where
you have very high levels of viremia
viral load circulating in these animals
the viruses can then the mosquitoes can
then transmit the virus to humans
or also to wildlife now the virus um
sort of has been detected in wildlife by
way of seroprevalence studies but the
impact of rvf in livestock is really not
fully understood but in domestic
ruminants like you know the ones of men
should you you get
to about adult animals and of course in
young animals the mortality is much
higher this is over 90 percent and you
know the classic uh the classic sort of
hallmark of disease is uh abortion
storms so nearly all animals in a farm
that are pregnant would abort
in humans the disease um is described
more like um through like illness with
very non-specific symptoms but a
proportion of these individuals develop
severe disease with high case fatality
rates and and
there's been some
sort of uh
evidence uh although anecdotal
suggesting that the case fatality has
been you know of recent epidemics in
humans has been rather high so
ranging from about 30 percent at least
for from the east african uh
outbreaks
so where is rvf common is predominantly
in africa and um these maps you know are
like you would have seen much like this
for all sorts of things basically the
darker it is the
the more uh cases there are or have been
reported
on the left you've got humans on the
right you have livestock the most
important thing here to note is that
there is a lot more um
cases of rvf reported in livestock than
in humans which
possibly just illustrates the
the poor sort of surveillance systems in
in humans in some of these settings
the other thing you will notice you'll
note is that kenya and south africa
or east africa and southern africa tend
to be really severely affected by rvf
outbreaks just based on the number over
the previous years
so what can we do to control rvf
we have licensed
inactivated
vac and live vaccines for they're using
in livestock
these have some safety drawbacks and
some need multiple doses to
generate an effective immune response
you need high containment for their
production because it's an actual sort
of rvf virus that you're dealing with
whether inactivating it or modified in
some way
and it's not they're not diva compatible
so you cannot differentiate
vaccinated animals from um
non-vaccinated animals because the
antibody response to the whole virus is
similar to that that's caused by natural
infection
so there are no licensed vaccines for
human use and so the the
the thrust of this program has really
been about developing a vaccine for
for human use but also developing safer
uh vaccines that can be used in
livestock this is a very old um
table from the 1930s just that all i
want to demonstrate here is that
a humoral immune response so an antibody
response is sufficient for protection uh
because of time i i wouldn't really go
into the table but but you the point i
want to sort of make is that if you pass
into animals again you can confirm
protection uh suggesting that antibodies
are important we also have from very
many studies that have been done or over
the years demonstrating that
neutralizing antibodies uh correlate
with protection and so if you're
thinking about a target for a vaccine uh
you know construct you want to develop
antibodies you know develop a vaccine
that can elicit neutralizing antibodies
and we finally we know that if you
recover from rvf infection then these
neutralizing antibodies tend to be long
lived and this is just a case
demonstrating that
an individual hard neutralizing
antibodies up to 25 years later without
exposure in the intervening period which
is uh really remarkable
so we know what the the target of this
neutralizing antibodies are it's the
surface of the viral glycoprotein of the
of the virus and these are viral
glycoproteins known as gn and gc
uh the the analogous
sort of situation here is the spike
protein for coronavirus so it's like
targeting the same sort of surface of
the virus it's an enveloped rna
virus so we set out to use the chadox
one platform
because
at that time the chadox one vaccine
platform which is basically just a
vehicle to deliver the vaccine had been
used in humans and
had been shown to be safe in humans this
is very important as a sort of starting
point for a human vaccine because you've
already
saved so much costs by having uh already
a track record in in the safety profile
you will i will talk about the costs of
developing vaccines later but the chad
oxford platform was safe in humans
previously when used for other vaccines
and all we did basically is get the
targets the the genes that encode the
virus uh rvf gn and gc and uh
you know inserted this into the chadox
one vector which when in when you
vaccinate an individual gets into the
cell uh expresses the the proteins and
these uh rvf glycoproteins then uh
stimulate an immune response and
hopefully you've got a very high immune
response to confirm protection
so the methods of manufacture were
already well established so it really
was a a matter of plug and play
so this image just illustrates the um
the the sort of uh pipeline for
development is it's simplistic uh but
it's just illustrates the point we've
had the pre-clinical uh discovery period
where we identified the rvf i mean
inserted the rvfg and ngc into the chad
ox1 platform uh the plan was to do
pre-clinical studies in mice uh and then
go on to livestock trials and human
studies and and if you know hopefully if
it all works well then you'd have a
single vaccine
for using multiple species
so
the first
really encouraging data we found was
that if you immunize mice and expose
them to rvf virus two months later
you had 100 protection and um
you know this was very exciting whereas
the group that uh were given a placebo
uh did not uh you know were not
protected and succumbed to infection
so the next sets of studies in livestock
were studies that we did um in very
close partnership uh with hillary uh
with vishnani and others and the idea
here was to immunize animals and
following um follow them up for a month
for immune response to to develop and
then expose them to rvf virus so this is
a typical approach of evaluating
vaccines
so the long and short of it was that a
single immunization in all those species
provided a hundred percent protection so
none of the animals that received chadox
were shadows one
um developed disease and in fact as
illustrated on this on this plot the
with the blue representing chadox one
group and the black representing the
licensed product and the uh gray
representing placebo
all the chadoxon vaccinated animals
mounted on neutralizing antibody
response uh for the rift wax which is
available in kenya as a you know rvf
vaccine
uh two of the animals one in you know
cattle and and goats did not mount a
neutralizing response and were not
protected further supporting this idea
that um
neutralizing antibodies are the main
sort of thing you need to elicit to
mount an immune response so the
publication is up there if anybody wants
to to follow that
so
the next step was to look at rvf in
pregnancy again using a similar
uh
experimental design where you vaccinate
uh for this we vaccinated early in
gestation and challenge them later with
a with a with a virulent virus and then
monitoring the safety of the fetus and
also our protection
so these studies were done in the
netherlands with uh
jerome kotakaz and others
and the top
panels represent the
results of the vaccine development in in
sheep um and the bottom are the goats so
that both i mean in both species the the
antibody response was really very high
it was within the range we observed in
the kenyan study
artillery
and and uh the the chadox one vaccinated
group in red here were
um what protected against uh viremia so
you see the viral load there it just
means that the animals were protected
against um
you know rvf infection there was no
illness in the pregnant uh
animals um and no sign of infection in
the fetuses in in sheep in the goats
again we've got very high levels of uh
protection although two of the 25
fetuses uh succumb to infection
suggesting that there might be
differences in the
either the mechanism of protection or
other factor in in goats in terms of uh
the level of protection that you see
following vaccination but the primary
aim of this uh experiment really was to
demonstrate that the chadox1 vaccine was
safe which is something that current uh
you know most of the vaccines currently
uh are unable to
you know show you know that we we really
don't have any vaccines that can be used
in pregnancy other than uh the
inactivated versions that need uh
multiple immunizations so this was a
really um good point to sort of uh get
that you know proceed from
uh
yeah so
the next step was to look at the
now that we've demonstrated the um
the safety of the product in uh in
pregnant and non-pregnant animals
ensured you know very high levels of
protection
we the next step was to conduct a field
trial
looking at the um
whether the vaccine elicits uh a similar
you know performs as well as the
licensed product in a study that is
powered to evaluate data sort of
population level
so the previous studies were designed to
look at efficacy uh you know for the
first study and then the second one was
to look at safety and pregnancy whereas
this is now looking at a field level and
these are studies that we did in uh
kapiti where we um
looked at
180 animals per species so this is with
the as as indicated there that was a
study protocol and this study was done
to
very high levels very high standards so
uh to gcp
and i believe it's probably the largest
uh sort of gcp veterinary trial that's
been done globally
i haven't had anybody object to that in
the different places i've talked about
this um so as i say the study was done
in kenya it's in healthy non-pregnant
animals and the animals were followed up
for a year and the end point of the
trial the thing that we will use to say
whether the vaccine performs as well as
a licensed product is a neutralizing
antibody titers now i don't have the
results for this but um analysis is
underway uh but should be available
sometime early next year but the whole
point is that this data will be used to
support the registration of the product
for use in east africa
and other and other countries uh in
africa where there is very high uh sort
of exposure to rvf
so i'll switch gears a bit so now we're
moving to humans so the veterinary
development is of course very advanced
uh and we are now you know the point
where we're thinking about registration
but how about the human studies so
we've begun a phase one study in humans
in oxford and this is uh the typical
uh approach is to start with a low dose
go to a medium dose and a high dose for
any of you who've been following uh you
know the oxford astrazeneca kobe 19
vaccine development you will have seen
some of this sort of experimental
designs uh or trial designs very early
on
so this this sort of phase one study is
is done in a small number of
participants with the aim of just
looking at the safety profile of the
product and of course whether it also
elicits an immune response the desired
immune response
so we already have for the platform in
general so chadox1 in general we already
have of a safety database over a billion
doses of course because of the oxford
astrozone coveted vaccine but now we
want to add data specific to the rvf
vaccine and so far the vaccine is
performing well both in terms of the
safety uh and the immune response and
again we expect this data to be ready
you know for sort of dissemination uh
sometime early next year
so i've i've taken that fairly quickly
just because of time but but the summary
of this work is that uh you know we've
identified very high levels of
protection in livestock now the vaccine
is highly
efficacious and safe in pregnant uh
ruminants and the safety and
immunogenicity is expected to be as good
as current licensed vaccine which is the
sort of the smith band vaccine supplied
by
kevin vappy analysis is ongoing as is
the analysis of the human phase one
study
that is going to be available as from
next year
so in terms of so for the veterinary uh
development the veterinary use of the
product
um that has a clear sort of pathway um
that we would follow for the um are
stipulated by uh the local regulators um
and you know nba the the veterinary
medicines directorate and and so
and there is actually a harmonized
process for for doing this in eastern
africa but how about the the human
landscape
now one of the most difficult things to
do as as you know the audience might
appreciate is to predict when the next
um reef valley fever outbreak would be
if you if if you are to predict that
with very high sort of confidence you
would be able to design
a vaccine efficacy study so um but in
the absence of that it becomes really
difficult to predict uh you know to
design a vaccine efficacy study for you
for
rvf so an alternative approach would be
to
use correlates or protection as done for
the vaccines so we know
you know the threshold the antibody
threshold you require to provide
protection against rabies for instance
and even yellow fever for instance um
another another route is to think about
an animal rule which is something that's
done by the fda in the u.s
but
because this is a problem rvf is a
problem that's predominantly restricted
to africa and the arabian peninsula i
think we think that there is a need to
engage the regulatory
[Music]
national regulatory authorities in the
continent about the the best sort of
strategy towards licensure of this
vaccine whether it's emergency use
authorization as we have deemed as we
have seen for uh covert 19
and then followed by sort of a a phase 3
study where you're looking at
efficacy evaluation if ever there was a
massive sort of epidemic you also need
to think about what vaccination regimen
is going to be eventually used and so
this relies on doing
further studies phase two studies where
you look at
a single dose versus two doses and and
which of those performs well and think
about the deployment and how would you
deploy this vaccine would you deploy it
in humans only or would you deploy it in
humans and animals during an epidemic
and you know this sort of thing calls
for uh you know massive stakeholder
engagement
including the bodies listed there so
very much a one health focused sort of
uh
strategy also not just the in the making
of the vaccine and the planning of the
experiment but also in the future work
on the deployment or of the product so i
think i will stop there
um
[Music]
sorry
yeah i'll stop there and just
acknowledge that this is work that has
involved um
very many partners and uh at the center
of this has been the international
lifestyle research institute very close
partners there uh as i mentioned earlier
but also i can just or not i cannot
overstate the importance of engagement
with the
regulatory and policy stakeholders
including the national biosafety
authority and the ministry of
agriculture livestock and fisheries
because this would not have been
possible without their support um and
you know and and guidance through the
through the process uh at hillary you
know campus and kapiti so i think i'll
stop there and uh hand it over back to
you leanne or
for any
kind uh
questions thank you so much george for
that great
great talk um and uh there's lots of
questions in the chat um but i'm going
to just jump in
with one that's maybe a little bit less
technical we talked a bit at the
beginning about the the difficulty of
breaking down silos so i'm going to ask
you a personal question um
as as a a veterinarian i'm now working
at chemry how how have you felt how have
you found that transition sort of moving
from the veterinary field into um sort
of medical research how and have you got
any um suggestions for those of us here
or online about talking across
disciplines and making those forging
those connections thank you
yeah that's a good question i mean i
think um
the first thing to say is is that i
never left veterinary medicine my
background is i'm a vet as you said and
i think the the
i have sort of
enthused colleagues at camry and and
others you know that i collaborate with
uh globally about the value of
animal health not just from the
perspective of you know at the public
you know deployment because when you
think of one health
there's a there's a big
sort of bias i think towards thinking of
control programs like a country you're
deploying a control programs or
brucellosis and you have to think about
both but i think i've been using people
to think about more even at the basic
level that their difference in
differences in uh
animals and humans in terms of the uh
immune sort of the way they mount an
immune response the components of the
immune response so you can understand
pathogens and and how you know to how to
control pathogens uh by looking at how
the host paris you know house parasite
or host virus interaction differs in the
different species so it's been more
about
showing a different way of thinking
about the particular problem that you
know colleagues are working on
and applying this sort of one health um
basically exploiting synergies in in uh
in sort of immunology in both humans and
livestock it's not necessarily easy but
it to me it just makes sense
yeah no that that's wonderful and very
sort of reminiscent of that original one
medicine um concept and and also very
great to hear that you never feel that
you've left veterinary medicine i'm
sorry if that was what came across i
always have uh have this myself where
people said oh you're in research maybe
you're not a vet anymore but we're still
we're still veterinarians at heart
um so i'm just gonna pick up on a couple
of questions that came in the chat um
so
there was one question that uh suggested
that given the um the prolonged drought
followed by um very heavy rains that
we've experienced in the country you
know does this make you feel that an
outbreak might be more likely and if so
is there anything people should be
considering to protect themselves
or protect prepare
yeah i mean i think
that's again is a good question um there
are others in the audience you know
bernadette and others who can make a
really informed decision based on the
sort of
mathematical modeling and predictions
i think i will i would emphasize more
uh rather than moving rather than
thinking about you know is there an
outbreak that's going to happen because
of these
conditions i think i would emphasize
being
ready all the time which is uh something
that
jimmy mentioned in his sort of
introduction to the introduction that we
need to be ready we need to have
surveillance systems that are
ready to sort of uh
go
uh without necessarily um
sort of having to wait for a set of
circumstances to come to come into
sort of existence so
you you can always if we have
surveillance systems that are
full you know
that are not just focused on a
particular disease not just focused on
rvf then you will be able to respond
quickly
um
irregardless of whether there's a
drought or whether
there is not i think i would emphasize
more on having um
that of
you know everyday sort of readiness to
address sort of uh outbreaks i don't
know whether i'm making sense there
rather than focusing more just on an rvf
outbreak
yeah absolutely i think that that's
really clear that we really need to put
um
our efforts into preparedness and
surveillance um