[Music]
holland is pretty crowdy
our land is quite expensive labor is
expensive
so we have to be as efficient as
possible we have to be more efficient
than others to compete
and that competition drives innovation
and technology
we decided to go for not more hectares
but for more yield protector and that's
the moment that we start
looking into precision ag precision
technology
a lot of people think it's science
fiction but it really is not
we have only important in all factors
and we're producing around 100 million
tomatoes a year
the idea about this greenhouse is we
even use less water we use 50 less
energy
our tomato plants grow in hydroponic
system so we know for sure that
everything is clean and we can steer
everything very precisely
we use all the new techniques and all
the innovations with a minimum impact on
environment
my definition of precision farming is
doing the right thing
on the right moment on the right place
of course we're more sustainable because
we use less input and that's
economically good for me
we use a range of technology we are
using soil scans that measure the soil
quality
and the availability for nutrients in
the soil and then the thermal cameras
can detect diseases
or water stress implementing
precision farming is a way of getting a
better yield and a better quality
[Music]
i still believe that farming is the job
of the future
there will be more people more amounts
to feed and less area
we have to expand the yields of our food
that much
that we actually need the precision
farming to do that
sometimes sustainable solutions are
costing a bit more on the short term but
on the long term they should be more
effective and that's actually what we
are seeing
you need to have the guts to invest in
those kind of things for the long term
you