is
will just be charging the battery and
when the battery is
tag then in the evening we just connect
the bobs so this is the solar panel
it goes to these crocodile clips
you just clip those onto the battery
and then it'll charge the battery and
these go to the lights
we've got two lights here one over here
one here clip them both to the battery
and then i suppose put the solar panels
out on the roof
so it's in the sun it's charging
what do you think easy
everybody
yes
you ready
and this will brighten up over a few
seconds yes long
yes and that battery will run two bulbs
on it
yes it will run too bad just can you
avoid this one
so people will welcome the light or will
they welcome the lighting
yes they are very happy