in a small community in the Pacific
Northwest a dynamic company is growing
this company has served the equipment
dealer market for 30 years they did it
by following their principles by being
the best and by being honest to their
customers
dis technology driven people
focused
well inventory is a dirty word used but
you got to have used inventory for the
person that comes in on a given day to
have it not everybody can afford the new
one way or another if you don't have
some on the lot they drive through the
lot they don't even stop and the way our
lots are
located people are driving through all
the time and they'll say they'll call
and say well on my way through the pier
we looked at something we seen it what
have you but if it's sitting on the
country and you don't trade for it you
don't ever have it now unit wise we're
very heavy I'll admit that but
dollarwise because we don't have 10
combines 10 four-wheel drives things
like that thing there we can have
smaller inventory which looks outlandish
in most people's eyes but we're just one
small dealership with a huge inventory
that's covering a a very vast area and I
think because of that people are
stopping through on the way by seeing
what we have and we're getting phone
calls what enhances our sales through
the internet and things like that which
has been very
helpful in a small community in the
Pacific Northwest a dynamic company is
growing this company has served the
equipment dealer market for 30 years
they did it by following their
principles by being the best and by
being honest to their
customers
disis technology driven people
focused