[Music]
a growing consensus highlights that the
global food system is not delivering as
needed on a number of key sustainable
development indicators
there is an urgent need for a global
transition to agriculture and food
systems that ensure food and nutrition
security for all while reversing
environmental degradation and adapting
to climate change
sustainable agriculture and food systems
simultaneously offer multiple benefits
to society
agriculture and food systems need to
adapt different contexts by transforming
field practices and day-to-day farm
management operations to enhance farm
diversity and links to markets
agricology represents a shift from ready
to use to custom-made production systems
to assist countries in fostering
transformative change fao developed the
ten elements of aggregology framework
the ten elements are interlinked and
interdependent
they describe essential components key
interactions emergent properties and
desired enabling conditions in
agricultural approaches
ecological social economic and
nutritional diversity are fundamental to
agriculture agricultural systems that
are biologically diverse can make
greater contributions to the stability
and variety of ecological functions that
sustain food production and other
ecosystem services like pollination
biological control of pests and diseases
and soil health
diversification of agricultural systems
need to be guided by co-creation and
sharing of knowledge and practices
science and innovation proven local
practices combined with scientific
knowledge provide the best guidance on
what crops livestock and trees to
include on the farm where to place them
and how to manage them
[Music]
synergies occur when interaction between
components in space and time generates
multiple benefits to stakeholders across
a range of products and services
redesigning agriculture and food systems
aiming at synergies while minimizing
trade-offs inherently increases resource
use efficiency
[Music]
when using existing resources more
efficiently by enhancing biological
processes we can optimize the use of
fertilizers and minimize the use of
pesticides reducing both the cost of
production and the negative impacts on
the environment
[Music]
recycling is central to efficiency in
agriculture as it replaces the concept
of waste and pollution with that of new
biological resources for agricultural
production
the return of organic residues to soil
is a good example of recycling practices
that enhance biological activity
essential to soil health
[Music]
farm diversification including different
crops trees and animals increases
resilience which constitutes a type of
natural insurance
when market prices are low or a bad
season occurs due to drought pests or
diseases having diverse products and
lower dependence on external inputs
contributes to stabilizing producers
incomes having different crops and trees
flowering at different times of the year
enhances pollination and creates
habitats for predators and natural
enemies of common agricultural pests and
diseases that can provide biological
control services
protecting and improving rural
livelihoods equity and social well-being
is essential for sustainability
agricology places a strong emphasis on
human and social values such as dignity
equity and inclusion
all contributing to the improved
livelihoods dimension of the sustainable
development goals
[Music]
it puts the aspirations and needs of
those who produce distribute and consume
food at the heart of food systems
human and social values foster the
building of social capital and
collective action to make our way of
life sustainable
[Music]
agriculture and food are core components
of human heritage
culture and food traditions developed as
a result of long-term human environment
interaction and play a central role in
society by supporting diversified diets
agriculture contributes to food and
nutrition security while maintaining the
health of ecosystems
agricology plays an important role in
the harmonious rebalancing of tradition
and modern food habits enabling healthy
food production and consumption while
supporting the right to adequate food
agricultural transitions demand the
development of effective and innovative
policies institutions and markets that
enable and support transformative change
responsible governance from communities
the nations embodies transparent
accountable and inclusive mechanisms
that support producers and consumers
responsible governance also enhances
social inclusion and fair practices
[Music]
circular and solidarity economy
reconnects producers and consumers and
provides innovative solutions for
improving natural resource management
while promoting the sustainable
development goals
[Music]
agriculture is based on bottom-up and
territorial processes helping to deliver
contextualized solutions to local
problems
there is no single way to apply
agricological approaches it depends on
local contexts constraints and
opportunities
the 10 elements are a useful analytical
tool to facilitate decision making by
practitioners and other stakeholders
when planning managing and evaluating
agricultural transitions
to derive maximum benefit from these
elements we must continue to learn and
innovate together build and share
knowledge based on scientific evidence
and experience from the field and
support policies procedures and
legislation that prioritize
sustainability
partnership and collaboration are
central to co-creation and agriculture
researchers and producers play a vital
role as knowledge and innovation drivers
for global transformative change
agricology means connecting efforts and
scaling up sustainable practices to
bring about a better world for everyone
if you want to know more about the
benefits of agricology and the 10
elements please visit fao's agricology
knowledge hub
[Music]