foreign
friends this is survival doc today we're
going to take a look at my water
collection system
this is where the system starts from the
four gutters on my home here all four
corners have this type of device on it
the water comes down
it falls through this
device here
the water goes straight through but any
large particles of trash such as leaves
nuts seeds
they will roll off fall to the ground
the water continues to go through
into this four inch PVC pipe
now this has been exposed to
the Sun
and to ultraviolet radiation which
causes plastic and PVC to deteriorate so
I painted this PVC
and if you're going to paint your PVC
you need to ask the paint shop make sure
you get a type of paint that will
stick to PVC
my four inch tube from the front comes
all the way around
to the back
here it comes in
here's another corner of my home
water comes down into another one of
these traps
the two front and back join here
and they continue down
this road now this right here
is a water trap
I have two adapters in here
that fit together and close they choke
this off to a three inch hole
these are the two PVC adapters that I
use to make the
floating ball
shut off to capture the first runoff
of dirty water
these are
a four inch
and these are two different types of uh
adapters three inch it just so happens
that this one fits
right inside this one
so this creates a choke point
so
all I have to do is put a three inch
floating ball
in the pipe and as the water rises the
ball will float up
and get stuck right here and shut off
the water flow and capture the first
runoff which is a dirty water to a
to clean the dirt off of the roof before
you start capturing
the water then on the bottom I put this
clean out
valve
so this will be right in the bottom like
this and I'll put the ball
the three inch floating ball up in here
all right and then to uh to clean the
captured water out I just take this out
take the ball and let the dirty water
flow out put the ball back in
and put this back on
and ready for the next drain
and I'm going to glue these together
I'm going to glue all these together
to make sure there's no leakage
all right at the bottom I have a clean
out valve
or clean out
place
all right and inside this tube
I have
a floating ball
this is just a kids ball that I bought
at the toy store this is I think it's a
three inch three and a half inch ball
that goes up here
all right and this part of the water
collection system is designed to catch
the first runoff
from the roof because the first runoff
is going to be the dirtiest
all right so you want to go ahead and
let the first few minutes of rain wash
off that dirt
comes down here
comes in here
begins to fill up this tube
the ball floats
until it gets to right here and then the
ball chokes It Off
so this keeps the dirty water the
initial runoff it keeps it in here
all right and then at this point water
can continue on and of course this part
right here
will now serve as just a a trap to catch
heavier particles that as it's coming
through here heavier particles May
collect in here and of course these will
eventually be cleaned out
all right now the water continues
and it goes into my 375 gallon tote
all right here's the next place where
the water is filtered this is just a
standard Walmart
strainer
I cut off
the handle and the two little ears here
to make it round
this is a standard Walmart Bowl it just
happened to be the right size I took my
hacks off and saw it off the bottom
put this screen in
I ran some screws through it to make it
really strong because when this gets
dirty what you do is you take it and you
bang it on something like that to knock
the dirt out of it so I wanted to be
really strong I also used
silicone sealant
around here
on both sides
to hold it in
I cut this to just the right size
where it fits on my tote
so we need trash
that is not caught by the other part of
the system will be caught here
except very small particles that will go
through the screen
all right here's my tote
all right now I was careful to buy a
tote that did not have toxic chemicals
in it this was originally a food grade
tote
all right I also wanted one that was UV
protected
all right this tote originally was white
it was UV protected I decided to go
ahead and paint it black all right and
the reason for that is a white tote
allows light to come through and then
you have a lot of algae growing all
right this is one of my old rain barrels
of the past
and I found out that the white rain
barrels
as opposed to the darker ones such as
the blue ones there
the white ones allow sunlight to come
through
algae grows
makes the water really nasty algae grows
on the side the water turns green water
gets really nasty all right so for that
reason
I painted my totes black
and as you see here I live on a slope so
I was careful to build a good foundation
and level these totes
now another thing I will mention is down
here
all right this is the valve that opens
they came on the tote and this is a
valve that I added
all right
I wanted a standard water hose speak it
on here
I chose this particular type as opposed
to the screw in type because this is a
there's a ball in here and when it opens
up
it it completely opens up the area not
just a small spot where trash can get
lodged so I think it's important to use
this type as a ball in here
all right now what we started with here
with this tote these totes have a unique
type of thread on them and it's not easy
to get adapters for that thread so the
best but they are available and this
right here is an adapter all right it
was black I painted it white again for
UV protection where I bought these totes
the fella threw in
this adapter
for free
all right now on that what I have is two
inch PVC threaded that screws on what
this adapter does is it converts this
non-standard
PVC thread to a standard two inch pipe
thread all right so this is just the PVC
pipe with threaded PVC pipe available
anywhere
all right and this is a three-quarter
inch
adapter that fits in here in the into
this PVC piece to convert your two inch
standard pipe thread to three quarter
inch standard pipe thread then to your
water hose spigot
that's my tote
now on the other side
of my property
I have the same thing
so as you can see
I am pulling water off of all four
corners
[Music]
I have another
trout here
another clean out
attachment
with a ball in it
so this catches this much
dirt that comes off of
the roof
now my experience has been the more of
this dirt you catch the better
it would actually be better if if this
was bigger where I could even collect
more because it takes a lot of water to
wash that initial dirt off of your roof
so if you want to do anything with this
thing right here try to make it hold
more water not less
I have the same thing over here
and
with my two totes together I have the
equivalent of 10.
55 gallon rain barrels
now
the water that comes out of here of
course
um still a little dirty
it's great for water in your garden
saving on your water bill all right but
when if you want to drink this what you
want to do is run it through a good
filter and inside the house I have a
um
ceramic type
gravity fed ceramic type
filter that I got from Professor
McKinney
I believe he has the best types of
filters
now
I won't even filter this a little bit
more
before I run it through my kitchen
filter and the reason for that
is the cleaner you can get the water the
longer your
kitchen filter will last before the
ceramic gets clogged up with dirt of
course then you can take a soft
scrubbing pad and you can clean the dirt
off of this ceramic filters and keep
them going for indefinitely just about
but in order to keep
that trash off as much as possible when
it comes through here there will be
another filtering procedure so maybe
something as simple as running it
through
cheesecloth
just to catch the big pieces of trash
that so that they won't clog your
ceramic filter
this is a good little filter
that I like this is on another rain
barrel here
water comes through here runs through
the filter before it goes through the
hose
all right I actually have this this
filter is available on at many
garden supply places
is used with
drip systems
all right
it has a clean out right here
all right what this does
is the water flows
through here inside this part here
the water flows
from here through here inside this part
filters through this very fine screen
and then it's picked up
and goes back through here
all right now
an easy way to clean this keep trash off
of it
is the clean out valve right here you
just unscrew that allow some water to
flow through and it goes straight
through the inside which is where the
trash is and that's one reason I like
this filter is is so easy to clean
so this is one option when you come
right out of your rain barrel
to filter to pre-filter your water
before you take it in to use with your
about with your best drinking water
water filter
of course otherwise you can have the
water of course rain water is great
we're going into
your garden
here I have some
soaker hoses
and
using rain water saves me
a fortune on my
water bill
this is survival dock reminding you be
prepared or be prepared to be fleeced
[Music]