looking like a tree expert you know the
advice that you're giving is so
practical and simple and i can see that
you really enjoy what you do because the
passion just really comes out and shines
through your face um wendy the next
question i want to ask basically is with
the farmers that you've dealt with you
know um how have they bounced back
through the very harsh climatic
conditions that we've experienced
you know late last year and early this
year we've had
[Music]
good evening welcome to the private
property farming podcast my name is
malin walker and i am your host every
tuesdays and thursdays right here on the
private property channel this is the
farming podcast where we discuss all
things farming related
exposing you to the industry
professionals that are making waves uh
within their respective areas of
profession and also exposing you to
farmers getting to learn about their
journeys how they've navigated through
very difficult and challenging times
within their agricultural businesses um
connecting you to exporters importers
giving you insight in terms of how does
this industry operate and who do we as
farmers rely on and what the what is
what work do uh agri professionals do
across the sector we touch a little bit
on the economy so there's a couple of
things that we really discuss in this
podcast and i truly believe that this is
the podcast that you should be listening
to especially if you want to know more
about the sector if you want to connect
with farmers connect with agronomists
for example and today we have an
autonomous
show we've mentioned economists quite a
number of times onto the show how they
provide support to the farmers and today
we're going to unpack that in our
conversation so if you have any
questions comments please feel free to
ask um subscribe to our youtube channel
like the different episodes on the
podcast and also bring forth your
suggestions on what you want to see in
the podcast and so today we're joined by
wendy mazura who is an economist um at
seed coat limited we get to find out
what is her role within a company and
how does she work with farmers wendy
thank you so much for joining us how are
you
doing i'm well thank you so much for
having me bali
it's a pleasure it's a pleasure so like
i said you know we've had uh quite a
number of conversations in our episodes
around the important role that uh
agronomy or agronomists provide to uh
farmers but just tell us about what is
it that you do within seacoa limited
thank you molly so what happens is as an
agronomist at cidco limited
i'm tasked with the role of availing a
product knowledge to our farmers you
know making it in such a way that they
can understand it making it in such a
way that they can also use it to add
value in their farming enterprises
because now we are taking farming as a
formidable business so we would want to
then follow up with technical backup to
make sure that our farmers are realizing
the much needed value from the seeds
that we sell in cidco we are mostly a
seed business so we sell a wide range of
seed crops and a wide range of varieties
of those specific seed crops so our
farmers would need technical assistance
in terms of selection what they should
do then on top of that we also do
trainings we do demonstration plots
where we will be also going out to make
sure that the team understands and the
farmers understand what they need to be
doing for them to realize value out of
the genetics that they have then we also
avail extension services like what we
are doing now to make sure that out
today people understand so we integrate
traditional and digital marketing uh
efforts to make sure that uh at least we
are also adapting to what uh you know
videos brought where we cannot meet as
regularly as we want but also just to
provide information to our farmers in
terms of the farming activities that
they should be doing and should be
tasked with
right so when should a farmer start
engaging or having a relationship with
an agronomist is it before they start
planting or during their production
cycle
farmers basically need to change their
mindset and they need a mindset shift
whereby we need to then um concentrate
that it starts with you acquiring the
right skills or the right basic
knowledge before you venture into any
cropping program so we wouldn't want a
situation whereby the farmer is coming
in at a later stage and maybe some
mistakes have been made some of them
they cannot be rectified so you would
want the farmer to be in a position to
engage an agronomist or a technical
expert in the field that they want to
get into so that they can get the
information uh beforehand in terms of
what they need to prepare what they need
to look out for as well as the
profitability since we said that farming
is a business so you need to know how
profitable is it and you need to
understand the markets that are
available so all this can only come if
you plan in advance and you do it before
you venture into the enterprise
fantastic so i'm glad to mention all
these topics you know because yes
farming is a business right um and we
need to take it seriously because we
have experts like you who give proper
good professional advice so you said
planning in advance now let's take it
into a detail
i'm a farmer maybe i want to start my
new season so maybe i might i'm probably
a seasoned farmer right i just want to
start my new season and make sure that
whatever challenges that i experienced
in the previous season do not occur in
the next next season furthermore i'm
also a farmer who maybe just wants to
start
at what type of discussions would you be
having with these two different farmers
a new entrant and a person that's trying
to perfect their season so maybe give us
an insight in terms of the type of
conversation you'll have with the farmer
that's just starting out
versus the type of conversation that
should be having with the farmer who
just wants to perfect his or her season
going forward
okay so i would basically say that both
farmers still need to plan because if
you fail to plan you plan to fail but
i'll start with the seasoned farmer yeah
with the season farmer you're speaking
about someone who has already
understood the art of uh of farming in
terms of the enterprise that they are in
if they are into field crops maybe they
are doing mains they are doing multiple
cropping if irrigation allows they also
understand that uh
the times of seasons that they need to
come in but oh they need to also
constantly check on the new trends that
might be existing so in their planning
process they need to engage the
agronomist get recent information in
terms of the
the trends the varieties that are
available the new problematic diseases
that they are most likely to face
because we have said that they've been
in farming and they've been doing it
they need to understand how they can aid
on their profitability and also reduce
their input costs so that farming also
remains a viable business for them
because if they're going back it means
they've seen value in it but they need
to understand from a planning
perspective how they need to manage
certain things there might be an advent
of new problematic diseases or insect
pests but if they don't engage the
relevant uh stakeholders to provide this
information to them they might not be in
the know and get into their next
cropping program assuming it's the same
as the previous one when we have seen
clearly that climate change has really
uh changed a lot of things and
no one sees them is identical to the
other so the season farmer keeps needs
to check and also plan in advance after
that the assistant farmer also needs to
do the checklist whereby they are
looking at the good economic practices
that they need to employ uh such as the
land preparation the planting time the
management and all sorts so at least if
it's a seasoned farmer they understand
what they need to do and also they're
also going to be doing it
timelessly they just need
some refreshers and reminders but if
you're going to be dealing with a
first-time farmer you need to drill down
the basics and also make sure that they
understand that
it's not an overnight victory it's
farming is not uh one of those
professions where you can just get into
it and uh you wake up tomorrow you're a
millionaire you need to put in the work
and you also need to invest in uh in the
acquisition of uh
of information and technologies that are
also going to advance so for a
first-time farmer they might just hear
the neighbor saying oh no i made a lot
of money but there's a lot of work that
goes into it
that our first time farmer needs to
understand and appreciate and in some
instances um you find that it might take
a season or two for you to realize
profit maybe you're running at a loss
maybe you are recovering the course that
you have put into the into the farming
venture so all of this you need to
discuss at the beginning
once you have done so the first time
farmer needs to understand the principle
of soil management whereby we are
talking about them understanding what
their soil requires and coming in with
the correct
nutrient management principles for the
crop in question otherwise you would
find that our farmers would just assume
that fertilizer is fertilizer they go on
the market they just buy they come in
then they don't get the sad result but
the first cut of hope for a first-time
farmer uh my knowledge is that is for
them to make sure that they
understand and do soil analysis it's a
test that they need to do for them to
get custom-made nutrient management for
their farm after that they also get into
the good agronomic practices that we
were mentioning for the season farmer
but for them they need to go into
greater detail and understand the why
the why i'm doing it why am i coming in
with this type of land preparation why
should i also control weeds within the
first six to eight weeks why is this
insect pest a problem and how can i
manage it before it reaches levels where
it's going to reduce my yields so all of
these things they come into play for a
first time farmer a first time farmer
has more more work to do and they need
to understand that even when the crop is
established and it's looking lush green
it's not the time when they should bring
in their friends to just drive around
the field and and not go inside the
field to check otherwise some of these
problematic diseases barley they start
from inside the field then spread
outwards so if you're just going you
know taking a drive around the field you
won't really get the feel of what's
really happening so there's a lot that
the first time farmer needs to do they
need to invest their time to make sure
that they understand the venture
yeah like she's spoken like a true
expert you know the advice that you're
giving is so practical and simple and i
can see that you really enjoy what you
do because the passion just really comes
out
and shines through your face um wendy
the next question i want to ask
basically is with the farmers that
you've dealt with you know um how have
they bounced back through the very harsh
climatic conditions that we've
experienced um you know late last year
and early this year we've had some heavy
rainfalls in various regions in the
country um you know how they bounce back
um uh uh you know just basically keeping
their enterprises afloat
well that's uh now changing the mood eh
you know it's not a smiling issue
climate change is really a menace
amongst us
the past uh three to five years we have
seen a lot of unforeseen weather
burglaries that have been going on where
you find that in some instances it's a
false start to the season where you
think the season is started it's october
well ending end it's uh mid october when
the season usually starts you get rains
for three days then it goes for two
weeks without raining three weeks or a
month so that that will be a false start
then you get a premature termination of
the season mid-season dry spells that
prolong for example um in zim we had
about
four weeks with no rain in february
which is not a norm so some of these
changes are also uh things that have
caused in red havoc amongst our farmers
in terms of their uh operation and yes
are talking about the heavy rains as
well because the misconception that is
they ball is that climate change is
associated with no rain or drought but
climate change just means that the norm
what we are used to has been shifted or
changed a bit so
heavy rains also go into climate change
and the heavy rains that were
experienced in south africa in
mozambique the rays that the persistent
rains that we received in zim we got
persistent rains and a bit of flooding
in some instances so
those scenarios the farmer would not
have prepared for because according to
the weather forecast which is the main
guide that provides information into
what this isn't going to be like they
don't get to see some of these um
scenarios in advance maybe they get to
see them three to five days before
they're okay but that means the farmer
is ready if it's planting planted but
then if the rain's coming and they are
heavy that crop is going to be swept off
and if the
uh the farmer has already planted their
crop and did not do maybe some
conservation agriculture principles or
water management drainage system uh
principles you find that
flooding may also occur in the field so
it's difficult to really plan for
climate change the best we can do is to
mitigate the effects how so you need to
then
understand uh from the guidance that you
get from the meteorological services
department which is the one which is um
which governs and understands the
climatic issues that face that are going
to be characteristic of that season if
they tell you that you're expecting a
number to above normal rainfall then the
three to five day focus are the regular
guides that you need to be uh partaking
in if you know that maybe your area is
prone to flooding then you come in with
contour ridges you come in with um
drainage inside the field so that the
water gets to wash off and not uh flood
inside the fields if it's an area that
tends to be dry drier than other areas
then you know that water
is important you also need to come in
with your port hauling your chai bridges
different uh practices that are going to
conserve as much moisture as possible
mulching all those principles need to
come in so
i would say we have seen a lot of uh
disgruntlement uh amongst our farmers
both commercial and communal where even
for the commercial farmer in some
instances even when they think they want
to irrigate they don't get enough rain
to fill their water bodies so irrigation
is also then affected then the communal
farmer thinks that uh maybe since i have
done um
i've done my my ca my conservation
agriculture uh there's minimum soil
disturbance and oh when the rains come
in they're still come in and they flood
the field because there's no deep
speculation of the water into the ground
so it's not easy for our farmers really
climate change it's not easy for us as
well as an industry whereby we are also
tasked with availing uh crops that are
also tolerant to some of these
challenges that might be faced
be it the the the prolonged dry spell
you need a drought tolerant variety that
is going to remain maybe at a particular
stage for a certain time and then come
back and resume growth when the
conditions are allowing and then you
also need maybe earliness a variety that
matures earlier so that it escapes the
effects of of climate change by by
maturing before the dry spell commences
so there is a lot that the industry is
trying to do to mitigate the effects of
climate change but the farmer needs to
also take its upon themselves to make
sure that they are also doing some
mitigation measures in their own right
wow thank you for going very much in
depth into that and you've brought in
something that uh you know is quite an
ongoing debate in the agri industry
especially when you talk about um
disease resistant seeds um drought
tolerant
seeds etc you know and the ongoing
debater is that you know um there's
certain countries and the certain
organizations that have laws and
policies around uh the different types
of seeds that are meant to be sold you
know so the debate is about where the
farmer should use gmo seeds non-gmo
seeds open pollinated seeds hybrid seeds
what's your opinion around this and
maybe if you could just maybe touch on a
little bit based on gmo non-gmo hybrid
open pollinated the difference
the difference between all of these for
our audience to understand in depth the
different varieties that are out there
so what's your opinion around the use of
these various seeds um and um and you
know
you mentioned mitigating the risks so
when when we are experiencing severe uh
climate climatic conditions should we
then move over to maybe hybrid seeds
versus open pollinated so what's your
opinion
around this topic and also maybe bring
in your experience on what you've seen
on the ground
thank you very much for that question i
would say you've really put me on the
spot today but i'll do my best
so what happens you know with the the
different types of seeds i'll start with
the open pollinated seeds which also
speaks to the land races particularly
looking at um
maize it being a staple crop in most
african countries you'll find that there
are some land-waste varieties that have
existed for a very long time on the
market and they've been farmer retained
it's like the seed that the farmer is
going to return over and over and over
again
but uh initially it was enough for you
to have that seed because that was in
the advent of agriculture and
as a technology it was a good
technology for us to have those language
varieties but over time as you know that
agriculture is not constant it's also
dynamic like any other sector over time
it was realized that the yields that are
obtained from opv's open pollinated
varieties or farm saved varieties over
years
they they tend to be lower compared to
the need that was arising from the
increase in population that was being
experienced so there was a need for us
to reach food security and food security
then feeds into food
surplus for us to then export to our
other countries that might still be in
need so as africa we have not really
mastered the um
the
ability to produce what is enough for
ourselves enough for us to then sell to
other countries so there was a need a
gap there that existed that then
prompted breeders to come in with what
we are turning hybrid seed because with
hybrid seeds now you are now getting
more value out of the same amount of
seeds that you will have established for
example in the in some
varieties like hungry king which is also
an opv or the eight line variety that
our farmers do or the colorful names
that we've seen you'll find that the
number of rows
tends to be around eight six to eight
and then the number of
uh the length of the cup as well tends
to be shorter so it tends to produce
less grain when we are talking about
farming being a business where you need
to push in terms of the grain that you
get which comes from the huge components
that that also include the number of
rows of the plants the size of the cob
and also the
the weight of the grain that you're also
going to get so the hybrid seeds came in
and it outweighed the opvc in terms of
these characteristics then we also saw
that over time there was the development
of problematic diseases like your gray
leaf spots you find like mainstream
virus and all those so in those land
race varieties or pv varieties there was
not much that could be done to safeguard
the grain from from the challenges that
were caused by these new diseases and
new strains of diseases that might have
been existing before but with the hybrid
seed you are able to introduce new genes
that you are going to say because of
this particular gene we are now
self-guided against this problem because
of this gene we are now safeguarded
against gray leaf spots so now we have
hybrid seeds that is resistant which
means it will not be affected by grain
spots it will not be affected by leaf
rust if it's leaf rust some
whatever problematic diseases might
exist so hybrid seeds have resistance
and tolerance to problematic diseases
that the op v seed might not have so
um
you are seeing that the opv sit
so far it might have lower use it might
be susceptible to diseases it might also
not be drought tolerant because when it
was developed climate change had already
started the climate has been changing
for like it always changes but the rate
at which it's changing now was not the
same as what happened when those
varieties we were failed so you find
that uh the hybrid seed is able to
withstand long periods of dry spells
challenges that come with climate change
falling in the fields from wind excess
wind or excess rain
more than what the opvc will do then
moving
from the opv seat i think uh
concurrently i've also mentioned what
the hybrid seat would also be doing but
just to add on in terms of the hybrid
seats you find that it comes with a wide
range of options where you find that um
based on the pharmacy agroecological
region where they are also doing their
cropping there are varieties that mature
very early 90 to 120 days there are
varieties that take 115 days there will
be varieties that take longer in the
field but also giving higher yields like
uh maybe the late maturing varieties
that will give 160 to 150 260 days but
giving very high yields so there are
options with hybrid seeds that don't
exist with opg seeds because with opv
it's only one seed the the huge
potential is the same no matter what you
do no matter what you increase even with
soil analysis and the good agronomic
practices we were mentioning you are
unable to reach a certain level there is
a there is a ceiling to what you can do
with your opv but with hybrids there are
a lot of options then moving away from
that uh so that i don't over explain on
this particular question alone but it's
you put me on the spot
so no worries
so for gmos um it's an interesting topic
really uh where
there's a lot of misconceptions that
exist one
there is a lack of uh knowledge
amongst our farmers who are the
implementers or the people who are
supposed to take on the new technology
so
uh in some instances it might appear as
if it's bringing in negative side
effects uh to to get into the gmo
technology in farming but
sometimes it's because of the ignorance
or lack of adequate knowledge on how it
works because currently you'll find that
there are some gmo maize seeds that are
available on the market in zimbabwe we
have not adopted gmo technology yet i'll
tell you why but in some countries the
gmo technologies have been adopted but
having been adopted you find that
they come in with a reduction in cost of
production where
where a farmer is able to go in because
they see this gmo they can spray a
particular product without the risk of
damaging the crop and it becomes cheaper
for them increasing then on their bottom
line which is the yields because
profitability is what you are looking
for since farming is also a business
even at the communal level farming
should be a business a person should
just think of should not just think of
producing enough for them and then their
family they should think of producing
excess so that they can sell and also
make a living out of farming so this is
what we are talking about so this uh
basically the technology that's what
that's what it does it allows you to do
some things that you maybe were not able
to do if you're going to be applying a
chemical that was going to
also affect the crop but affecting all
the other weeds like your glyphosate
which is a herbicide if you're going to
apply it
in gmo maize you find that uh you can
apply it over the crop without risks so
gmo is a technology that people need to
understand in my opinion i think it has
a chance in the place but we just need
to understand how far we can go with it
what we can take and what we can live
for example here in zimbabwe we try to
carry out a bit of a survey on one of
our farmer uh interactive interactive
sessions or meetings where we put we
gave them a questionnaire about gmos so
the first question was do you like do
you like gmos or do you accept them then
everyone are saying no
then the next question was uh is gmo
technology good and everyone was saying
no then the third question was saying
what is gmo technology
all the answers that we were getting
there were wrong so what it means is
people don't understand what they are
saying no to so we really need to just
get more information so that
more informed decisions can be made
wow wendy thank you so much for
unpacking the the difference between gmo
open pollinated and hybrid and i think
you know we should have you back onto
the show where you could unpack what gmo
technology is because um i myself i'm
not vastly experienced in that space um
and
like you said with this server it just
shows that even us as farmers have
limited knowledge around us and maybe
just consumers because you know this is
how maybe shops have just been able to
um capitalize on the marketing adverts
around gmo versus non-gmo but it's
important that we understand why we
should vote for something and why we
should go against something you know and
especially at farm level how does this
impact a farmer on the ground because
again all the risk relies on the farmer
at the end of the day however i wish we
had more time um you know to unpack
these things and hopefully maybe we
could get you back onto the show once
again but thank you so much for also
just breaking the the the importance of
why we as farmers should have a
relationship with an agronomist a
relationship with an individual like
yourself to understand the various
varieties that can take us through
seasons understanding the geographic
locations in which we farm in and the
best varieties that will obviously
ensure that we meet our yield at the end
of the day but just before i say goodbye
to you wendy maybe just give us the top
two or three advices that you believe a
farmer should like look out for prior to
starting their season
prior to starting the season what i
think our farmers should really uh take
into account is the fact that whatever
they are growing do they have a market
for it because if you're going to be
establishing a crop and don't know the
ends the end user or where you're going
to be selling it it means you might end
up producing something that you will
fail to sell at one point there was a
farmer who did horticulture and then
they heard about brussels sprouts you
know they are very small eating cabbages
for a niche market and then they had a
friend saying no i made money with them
then they went on to establish about
half a hectare only to realize that the
local markets people don't understand
them they think they're underground
cabbages so you really need to make to
invest in understanding your markets uh
that's one thing that i want our farmers
to understand then you also need to
understand the principles of farming
which fit into the umbrella team good
economic practices that term has been
used extensively but i think the
understanding of which still needs to be
unpacked where a farmer needs to know
from the land preparation soil
management insect pest management it
goes into that so it's like a full mojo
that you really need to understand
before you start not to start saying at
a later stage you're starting to see
some issues fast in your field that's
when you want to come in to remove your
measures that would be too late so you
need to plan
planning in advance will ensure security
and success
fantastic thank you so much wendy for
your time and uh for your insights more
so continue to help farmers uh in your
regions uh whether it's working within
zimbabwe or south africa but trust me i
think this conversation uh taught a lot
of farmers something new maybe gave them
a refresher course you know because
sometimes you do tend to feel that we
know everything we've experienced
everything uh and therefore why should i
be seeking advice but thank you so much
for your insights and um hopefully you
can come back onto the show next unpack
to us gmo but yeah all the best with
your week ahead and uh with the farmers
that you're working with
thank you very much we are tasked with
wheat production so we really need to
make sure that everything goes well
thank you for having me and thank you
for this great initiative
thank you that was wendy matsura
everybody uh she's an agronomist at
seedco limited and we spoke about her
role as an agronomist agronomy uh the
purpose of agronomy why farmers should
work with agronomists especially from
the seed companies where they procure
their seeds i mean there's so much to
learn and unpack and have an
understanding in terms of what are the
what right seeds are best what seeds are
best for your for your farm are they the
right seeds are they the right varieties
that you should explore in this coming
season in the next and she unpacked the
importance of planning before a c before
you start a season whether you're a new
ancient farmer or just an experienced
farmer continuing with their production
because every single year we experience
and encounter new pests and diseases so
it's important to make sure that you
have the planning from the onset with an
agronomist to mitigate against those
pests and diseases and i like what she
said about climate change that climate
change has always been there climate
change does not necessarily mean it's
drought or we're experiencing minimal uh
rainfall but climate change could be
extreme weather conditions could be
extreme rainy conditions it could just
be anything that is just changing in the
climate within those months um something
different to what you were previously
exposed to and that is what climate
change is we can't stop it but obviously
we have to protect our farms our
businesses against it and mitigate
against those risks if you have any
questions for wendy please feel free to
comment we will reach out to her on your
behalf to ensure that the questions that
um you have post are answered and
continue to subscribe to subscribe to
our uh uh private property channel
follow the farming podcast playlist uh
this is where you could get the
interview for wendy and yeah thank you
so much for watching the show uh look
out for the next episode that we're
going to have right here on the farming
podcast brought to you by private
property that's it for me take care
[Music]
you