I'm really glad we had to put extra
chairs out that's exciting have a bunch
of different crews here which is really
nice vo ICC we have Saint Mike's we've
got UVM practicum and we got the farmer
training program so shout out to all of
you and thank you for everyone else from
the community that came my name is Sarah
De Santis I'm the co-director of the
farmer training program at the
University of Vermont which is a six
month non-credit hands-on agricultural
experience so a shout out to all my
students that are in the in the audience
so tonight we have an amazing panel for
you really lucky to have everyone who's
sitting at the table each presenter will
talk for about 15 minutes and then we'll
have a time for discussion there's mics
on either side and we'll tell you when
you can line up to ask questions I want
to thank our sponsors UVM farmer
training program UVM Catamount farm NOFA
Vermont and UVM's
Agri ecology and livelihoods
collaborative you can see our panelists
up here I'll introduce each when they
come to speak I also want to have a huge
shout out and thank you to Eric Mellon
and Foster Nye who are in the back
allowing this to be live streamed and
also archived at UVM YouTube station and
also jeremiah over here who works with
the Davis Center who's helped us with
all the IT so thank you everyone who
made this possible the reason we decided
to have this panel is the staff at the
farmer training program we often get
questions of what's the difference
between organic agriculture and
regenerative AG or what's the difference
between a gray ecology and permaculture
we can answer those questions but this
panel can answer much better than we can
so we wanted to bring everybody together
because I also as we can see here
there's a lot of other people in Vermont
that wants to know what the nuances are
between these different types of farming
and I think what we're going to learn is
there's a lot of overlapping themes and
then we're also going to learn how these
different agricultural practices diverge
and how they're different from each
other sometimes people talk
disparagingly about
one form of Agriculture over another and
they don't actually understand the
intricacies of these kinds of
agricultural practices and what we're
hoping to do here is with further
understanding about why farmers make
certain decisions we can hopefully have
a broader understanding and awareness of
agricultural practices and why farmers
make decisions for what they do so
that's why we have this panel here and I
hope you're going to enjoy it first
we're gonna have Maddie Kempner she's
been working at NOFA Vermont as policy
advisor since 2014
Maddie worked on commercial organic
vegetable farm and educational garden in
Utah in Colorado which inspired her to
engage in the way to change our food
system how its produced in foreign
policy she also worked on the right to
know
GMOs coalition to help pass the
first-in-the-nation GMO labeling law she
has a BA BS in environmental studies
from the UVM and a master's of
environmental law and policy from
Vermont Law School
[Applause]
yeah it seems like what you did should
have worked no worries thank you okay um
can everybody hear me here awesome
so as Sarah said my name is Maddie
Kepner and I work as policy advisor for
nofa Vermont which for those of you who
aren't familiar it's the Northeast
organic farming Association and we are
one of seven chapters throughout the
Northeast doing similar kinds of work in
the food system we also have a
certification program called Vermont
organic farmers maybe you've seen the
logo on the lower right hand of that
screen that's the logo of our
certification program which you'll see
on products all over the state and
beyond and I see someone with a hat with
that logo on it tonight so perhaps to
you hmm and also as I mentioned I'm
gonna talk obviously about organic I
will preface this with the fact that I
guess what I'll give you is sort of a
fairly basic overview of kind of organic
philosophy and practices in terms of you
know what certification requires and the
process involved in certification there
are at least a couple of other people in
this room who know more about this than
I do
um so please know that there are the
resources and I'm by no means the
end-all expert but I will do my best to
give you a good idea of really what
organic means so the organic philosophy
I think it's really important to
understand beyond just understanding
organic certification and the specific
practices that are required the
philosophy really started out as one of
the foundational tenets of organic is
feed the soil not the plant organic is
really intended to be a holistic systems
approach to farming we're biologically
active soil serves as a foundation to
create as you can see in this little
flowchart healthy plants healthy animals
and healthy people so the whole idea
behind organic is that it's again a
whole systems approach and it really I
would say stands out from a more
conventional approach to agriculture in
that it's again based on this
biologically active system rather than
kind of
and puts in and puts out and along with
this I think it's really important to
note that there's both what we know if n
vof referred to as the negative
definition of organic and the positive
definition the negative definition of
organic is what people often think of
you know from a basic consumer
perspective where they think there's you
know no GMOs no sewage sludge
irradiation you know no synthetic
fertilizers or toxic pesticides all
those things are true but we also like
to emphasize the positive definition of
organic which is which means that it
requires that farmers go beyond those
things and actively promote biodiversity
on their farms for example and and
develop by biologically active soil that
feeds their plants and their animals on
the farm so I think it's important to
remember that organic doesn't just mean
that certain things are absent but there
are really practices that farmers are
required and encouraged to do that are
kind of proactively improving their
farming system and hopefully the
environment so what are the organic
standards in a very basic way a set of
definitions and practices that encompass
organic farming and processing process
products as you probably know are also
allowed to be certified as organic and
includes a national list of allowed and
prohibited substances which is a dynamic
list of materials that are allowed in
organic farming and the idea also behind
the organic standards at the national
level is that they're continuously
improved with input from farmers
consumers nonprofits and private
businesses so there's just to give you a
really brief overview I'm sorry if this
is too beginner level for you guys but
the National Organic Program is a part
of the USDA that United States
Department of Agriculture and along with
the National Organic Program which is
really the kind of federal regulatory
arm of the organic program there's also
a board called the National Organic
Standards Board that is a an advisory
board to the NOP
so the National Organic Standards Board
is made up of you know folks from all of
these different groups listed here that
gives recommendations to the NOP on what
should and should not be allowed with an
organic production
so who can be organic only farmers and
processors certified by a USDA
accredited certification body can use
the term organic when the National
Organic Program was established in 2002
it basically meant that only people who
are certified organic should be using
that term with this one exception that
if an operation has gross agricultural
income of five thousand dollars or less
they can use the term as long as they
are still complying with the Organic
regulations and using the organic
practices and I think this is an
important point in that it really shows
that USDA recognizes and it's a certain
way of recognizing more broadly that and
and I will say also that NOFA and VOF
recognize more broadly that there are
lots of people who practice organically
on their farms who may or may not be
certified for a variety of reasons and I
think you know in talking about organic
it's really important to kind of
understand that outside of organic
certification the organic movement
started long before the National Organic
Program was established and there are
still farmers who are really
foundational people within the organic
community who choose not to be certified
for a whole variety of reasons so in
terms of kind of some more specifics of
what organic production entails organic
producers are required to feed the soil
and some examples of that are through
cover crops green manures compost and
animal manures farmers are required to
rotate their crops which is a way of
avoiding pests and disease problems that
can build up in your soil over time and
organic producers are not allowed to use
toxic pesticides or synthetic
fertilizers and basically this goes back
to the idea of the holistic system where
the practices that organic farmers use
are intended so that they don't need to
use certain inputs in order to keep
their plants and their animals healthy
and then in terms of livestock there's
you know similar different practices
based on the same principles may have to
be fed organic feed without the use of
hormones or antibiotics raised in a
stress-free environment
allowed to exhibit natural behaviors
healthcare treatments have to be natural
or an approved synthetic on the national
list
they must have year-round outdoor access
and they must be raised on pasture so
there are some fairly specific
requirements in terms of livestock
production as well in terms of the
process of certification farmers submit
an organic systems plan on an organic
system plan on an annual basis there is
an annual inspection and they pay a fee
to the certification body and they have
to renew that application every year
it's also important to note that we do
unannounced inspections on 10% of our
operations annually and we do residue
testing on 5% of our operations so this
is a I guess the more more to the point
maybe of the conversation that we're
having tonight one of the prompts that
sera gave us all and in preparing for
this discussion is what is we're going
to mean for agriculture at this moment
in time this could be a very lengthy
discussion and I hope we'll get a chance
to get more into it but from you know my
perspective and I think from NOAA and
the u.s. perspective organic is really a
meaningful and clearly verified set of
practices that benefits the environment
and human health if practiced correctly
that's what they should be doing I think
it's really interesting there was a
study that came out I think at least I
saw it through the National Farmers
coalition recently where young and
beginning farmers are saying that they
are using organic practices but at least
anecdotally and I think probably
empirically they're not getting
certified as often as their predecessors
and I think that's a really important
trend to notice and when I think about
that and you know you all young farmers
in the audience I'm sure would have a
lot to say about this but I wonder how
much it is analogous to you know the
feminist movement for example where for
people of my generation the feminist
movement had already happened when I you
know came up when I grew up and so
there's a part of me that wonders
whether young and beginning farmers
aren't taking up the mantle of organic
agriculture in the way that the founding
members of the organic movement did
because it's already a really
well-established set of practices and
it's often referred to as an almost 50
billion dollar industry so when you
think of it in those terms it may not
feel like a cause that young and
beginning farmers really need to get
behind but there's also lots of other
reasons why young and beginning farmers
may not be certified oftentimes if
you're selling to direct markets and you
really know your customer and they know
you and your practices that may not be
something that you feel is right for
your farm and I think that's really
important to emphasize too sir I
mentioned earlier you know the
discussion around why farmers choose to
practice in certain ways and while we at
NOFA and view I believe really strongly
in organic and I personally believe
really strongly in organic as a set of
farming practices in an approach it's
not been our role to tell farmers how
they should practice or tell farmers
that they should or need to get
certified it's that's really an
individual decision for every farmer and
you know whether or not it works for
them and makes sense for them and so
more kind of in terms of the order
Grameen's at this moment in time I think
that many of you may be aware that there
have been some challenges with how
organic is enforced and implemented at
the national level level through the
National Organic Program it is intended
to be a process of continuous
improvement but especially in recent
years organic has run up against some
walls in terms of the National Organic
Program enforcing the regulations
consistently or different certifiers
across the country of which there I
believe 95 implementing the organic
regulations in the same way across the
board so that's definitely one of the
challenges associated with this being
now under the banner of USDA which I
would say is different from the
challenges that existed when there were
a bunch of different kind of
state-by-state programs but I'm sure
there were challenges with that as well
I think it's also really interesting
that organic has come to serve
the foundation for a couple of add-on
labels that are in development currently
there is a group called a real organic
project that is developing a set of
standards currently that will be used to
create and add on label not by that name
but that will use organic as its kind of
baseline and then build on top of it and
the reason for that is some of the
stagnation that I mentioned with
continuous improvement under the
National Organic Program the goal of the
real organic project is to address you
know shortcomings in terms of USDA
Organic like the allowance of
hydroponics
which have been allowed to be certified
now as organic and some concerns about
enforcement of things like the pasture
rule and lack of implementation of
higher animal welfare standards for
organic called the organic livestock and
poultry practices rule which was
actually passed under the Obama
administration but was withdrawn by the
Trump administration immediately
thereafter and then there is another set
of standards being developed called
regenerative organic certification this
was started by the Rodale Institute and
it is a really similar project with
similar goals I would say but a very
different approach and the real organic
project really was kind of started here
in Vermont and has grown to be a
national effort and was it has always
been very farmer driven and the
regenerative organic certification was
seemingly less farmer driven but it also
is a set of standards that are thought
to be somewhat unattainable at least in
their current form so it'll be real
interesting to see what happens with
those couple of efforts but organic USDA
Organic certification will be a
prerequisite requirement for both of
those that's pretty much all I have I
don't know if I can use my extra time to
take questions now or if I should just
hold that for later okay yeah thanks
Rick
thanks so much Manny Terry Bradshaw will
be our next speaker he he's a research
assistant professor at UVM and has
worked his entire life in various
sectors of Vermont agriculture the bulk
of his research and outreach program
focuses on sustainable pest and
horticultural management specifically in
orchards mostly apples and vineyards and
includes both organic and conventional
practices he received his PhD in plant
soil science from UVM in 2015
shortly after founding Catamount
educational firm which where the farmer
training program is housed and he serves
as the specialty crops research and
teaching laboratory at the UVM Hort farm
and he's some of your professor out here
so good take good notes it's gonna be on
the quiz guys if there's extra seats can
you take backpacks off and maybe ari
could you just bring these three seats
so over here please Thanks
oh you do I don't need to give you okay
I need to give me anything good all
right
hi everyone thanks for coming out
tonight it's in I don't know how we
chose the order was alphabetical or not
but it's organic is a is a very clear
box I say that as someone who's been
certified on parts of the farm for 12 or
13 years conventional is everything
outside the box and these guys are more
fuzzy boxes I'm done No
so I want to just highlight a few things
that I that I wanted to talk about one
being the concept of Agriculture I
I teach on multiple levels but one of
the things that I often kind of focus on
is production scale agriculture where
the marketing and the the economic
livelihood is a key part of this this
piece and that's a lot of what I teach
too and what I kind of direct my various
programs to it so I want to put a little
asterisk there in terms of sort of part
of my focus one thing I wanted to
highlight this I love this picture here
I took this in an orchard last year
anybody have a guess as to why what that
represents not counting those who were
in my class last spring those are the
three primary crop three most valuable
crops in Vermont milk although it's a
beef cow maple and apples all in one
shot anyway side note one thing that I
also want to highlight and this has been
something that I sort of have to deal
with to some degree or other in in my my
life of having one foot in the
conventional if you want to call it that
bucket and one foot in the organic
bucket is this sense of tribalism and
over the years I've noticed that at
times particularly with people who
aren't don't actually have their hands
in the soil we divide more distinctly
into our tribes and there's actually
been a lot of research particularly done
in the 70s that find that actually when
once people find a tribe whatever that
tribe might be could be your knitting
group could be your you know fly-tying
buddies
you tend to avoid information from
outside of your tribe and so I welcome
forums like this and I welcome
continuing the discussion so I want to
highlight that little piece so
conventional agriculture I I looked up I
just googled you know conventional
agriculture took the first two Google
images right and then I also looked at
the at one of the initial definitions
that came out and from a pro pedia I
don't know who APRA pedia is but I
mentioned conventional farming is known
as industrial agriculture refers to
farming based on continual inputs
genetically modified organisms
concentrated animal feeding operations
irrigation intensive tillage --is
monoculture and that was really kind of
the focus and that's the not the first
thing that I think about and anybody
who's familiar with some of my talk to
you the the concept of Monsanto gas-mask
man is not what I think of when I think
of conventional agriculture but it is
what's pretty popular in you know the
first Google hits so sometimes we have
to work against this and sort of dispels
dispel this and also recognize to
embrace parts of this that we do deal
with this picture does drive me crazy
because whatever that chemical is was
banned back in 1992 so it's not even
very appropriate for the common for
contemporary discussion but we have
parts of this that that do fit into
conventional agriculture however if you
look into some dictionary definitions
the idea of conventional has more to do
with what is generally done what are
most people doing and are most people
doing bad things to grow food and I
would say that the vast vast majority of
people aren't doing bad things to grow
food so Maddie had a good point of
talking about negative versus positive
connotations around organics you can say
the same thing about conventional so
conventional is what most the farmers
are doing and one thing I think about in
terms of conventional is organic is in a
box there's there's a NLP list and
there's certain
things you do conventional is not in a
box and so we are free to try new things
the innovates and we can be a little
more responsive I think two challenges
two potential solutions to challenges
and because we're on the the front of
that sometimes we make mistakes without
question but we're not bound to an
ideology first we're bound to whatever
our particular principles might be one
of the things is important to note here
is there's nothing mutually exclusive
between organic and conventional I can
use Connect practices and materials all
day long in my conventional or tricked
in fact we do so that's an important
thing too it's it's not a black or white
mutually exclusive kind of kind of thing
and I think we'll see this across the
board so really at the end of the day
what are we absolutely limited to
whatever the laws are so then we have to
make sure that we have good policies and
good checks and balances to make sure
that as society we make policies that
that protect you know the environment
the food supply farm workers and farmers
so that people can afford to live and we
can all eat any one of us can talk about
these problems anybody who is looking at
farming at the food supply knows we have
an increase in population we have a
decreasing labor supply we don't have
any more land to grow on and students
who've heard me often hear me say that
our most limiting resource in
agriculture is land even when we figure
out the nitrogen and phosphorus issues
100 years from now we're not gonna have
any more lay in fact we'll have less
land certainly environmental degradation
and climate change is going to impact
all of these so we've all got some
really big issues to solve or at least
continue working around we're never
going to solve them but one thing that
we think about in this you know this is
a concept that sort of always been on my
mind is the idea that came about 200
years ago that at some point we're gonna
run out of things to feed the mouse that
we have and so anybody who's familiar
with mullets Theory knows that there was
there was a theory that says if
we population will increase at a
logarithmic rate food supply will
increase at a geometric rate and
eventually we're gonna we're not gonna
have enough food and this was a real
concern prior to the Industrial
Revolution and would have been a concern
if we weren't innovating in making for
better agriculture thankfully innovation
moved it moved beyond this particular
situation and we've generally kept pace
that does not mean there hasn't been
shortage of food doesn't mean that there
aren't certain regional issues but
generally speaking the productivity of
agriculture worldwide and I don't mean
conventional agriculture because this
started well before chemical agriculture
came in people started to breed better
plants people started to realize better
ways to tend to their soil and we have
kept kept pace sometimes just barely and
not always evenly across the board
around the world but we've been able to
continue to feed people if we were
growing food at the at the at the
production levels we were 200 years ago
we would have run out of land a very
very long time ago but what happened so
around 1900 we discovered a way to make
nitrogen synthetically so in organic
systems this is not allowed and you can
pretty much track agricultural
production and population growth and
pretty much plot it with the amount of
synthetic nitrogen we've made that's
been good in that we've continued to
feed the mouths of the people that get
born in the world that's also very
likely contributed to overpopulation in
the world so we are on a treadmill we
are stuck with this system to where if
we were to remove haber-bosch or
synthetic nitrogen from the system there
would not be enough food for about half
the people on the earth it's it's a very
gross overstatement but we would be in
for a major problem so we've got to find
ways to use this stuff the most
efficiently which we're not doing
generally
and also ways to try to find other
systems that will be more resilient so
that we're not tied to milking every bit
of natural gas out of the earth to just
continue to produce nitrogen so this is
the problem and this is something that
people are going to need to solve for
decades to come
so when I think about conventional
agriculture I think about as an
undergrad the term was sustainable
agriculture that's that's not in vogue
anymore but I still use the term and I
go to Maguire from Washington State who
came up with four key elements to
maintaining sustainable agricultural
production make sure my times on so
protect the soil whether you're organic
or not it is key the soil is absolutely
what we need to manage and when we ran
into Dust Bowl conditions 80 some years
ago that was a logical extension of very
poor soil management so no matter how
you're managing your farm you need to
protect the soil maintain soil fertility
if we're gonna take a piece of lands and
we're gonna pull it out of wild
condition because every farm is not wild
although Keith might talk a little bit
differently the but we are taking this
piece of ground and we're saying we're
gonna alter this we're gonna do
something with this and we're gonna
remove it from the natural system we
better make sure that we're using that
land appropriately so that we are
maintaining the fertility to get the
crops that we need for the effort we put
in and for the mouths we need to feed
and that we're also replacing the
fertility that we're removing and that's
a key thing to remember every time you
pull a crop off the soil you're pulling
nutrients out of the soil so we need to
maintain that use water efficiently this
is one of Andrews points I don't think
any of us in Vermont have a most of us
don't have too many issues with water
he's based out of Eastern Washington
worked very dry but it's something we
need to think about and we need to also
remember that the world is not Vermont
the world is not even North America so
just because we are blessed with
generally speaking abundant water
resources although the climate change
they're changing quite a bit we need to
always be thinking about this
how to design systems that are more
resilient so we can we can maintain
reasonable production and the health of
the environment and then protect the
crop and this is a key part that I feel
differentiates conventional if you want
to call conventional from other systems
where we recognize that there's a
certain amount of energy inputs human
labour capital that has gone into this
crop and we need to make sure that we
respect that by protecting the crop so
that could be something as simple as
hand picking we've done this in the
organic orchards for years hand picking
and some of the people in this room got
to hands in various fruit loops out of
our orchard sometimes that means firing
up a sprayer this is in the ordinary
quarters Organic porters do not are not
spray free necessarily sometimes that
might mean using other tactics and so
this is the classic IPM integrated pest
management pyramid which looks very
similar to the period that you see in
various organic management texts - the
effective chemical use at the tip
although there are some chemicals that
are used in organics but the key to have
a healthy resilient well-designed pest
management system is to work on all the
stuff at the bottom so that you minimize
this stuff at the tip and that's what
good conventional growers do and I would
even say the bulk least the ones that I
know then we have some issues this is a
picture mine my old boss took on the but
on the back of a deck of her car we use
as much as possible resistant varieties
to try to maintain to prevent disease
before we have it or prevent insects
before we have it so this is a Liberty
next to a Macintosh and either one got
fungicides one got apple scab one didn't
this is a conventionally bred
resistant variety sometimes you can have
yep transgenic resistant varieties so
this is a field of of BT Bowl root bull
worm resistant cotton on the on the left
on the right
non born resistant cotton and you can
see that there's a major issue there in
certain parts of the world it may take
over 20 applications and pretty hot
pesticides to keep bollworms off of the
right so this is a this is a tactic
that's used by conventional farmers and
it can be a controversial one one that I
see that is coming up that I think is
going to bubble up to the surface what
we call GMO 2.0 so there's a new group
of genetically modified crops that are
not transgenic something that might be
where they call CRISPR edited where the
genes do not leave the particular
species so there's now late blight
resistant potatoes developed in England
there are some groups in England in
their organic or I wouldn't say they're
not they're not organic because they
can't plant these but some people are
saying you know this is a system where
we can really save on the management of
a devastating disease
I wrote the numbers down here somewhere
annual worldwide cost to manage late
blight is in the 3 to 5 billion dollar
range between the sprays that are
applied and the loss of crops this is an
area that we're gonna see more changes
and I think we're gonna see some real
soul-searching around this around the
use of modern breeding to avoid having
to spray for pests and then find a piece
that I added and I don't know this is
officially in any conventional
agriculture world but it's a guy who
grew up on a dairy farm and it's a guy
who works in orchards in with farmers
and sees people day to day sometimes
making a living sometimes not any
sustainable agriculture system has to
absolutely provide a sustainable living
for the farmer in and for their
communities and so we always have to
keep that in mind so a few examples of
some of the growers that I work with not
undersell you'd work with all them but
these are all non organic farmers that I
would consider progressive you know
really good conventional growers
and I think my last slide one thing
that's very HD as we think about soil
health in the talk particularly about
regenerative agriculture when I first
started hearing about regenerative
agriculture in soil health was about
2000 2002 and it was not coming from the
organic world it actually came from
Heather Darby who was working with this
organic Apple project but she was
bringing me papers from the Upper
Midwest and the Great Plains saying look
at the stuff that's going on out there
these are farmers that were that took it
upon themselves largely to really start
a revolution in terms of paying
attention to soil health number one in
terms of managing and making for a
sustainable farm even if you're a
conventional farmer particularly
multi-generational farmers you know that
the soil is what is going to provide for
you for decades and generations to come
so this really is a focus of
conventional agriculture as well this is
a really bad Venn diagram but I'm
stopping on that I tried to make for my
AG policy class tried to show where we
all fit all these bubbles could move
around and I think that's part of the
point is how much overlap there is some
of these I don't even know where they
should fit and I think that's kind of
the point of this panel is we've got all
these names and conventionalist just
because there's more acreage I didn't
show you the scale of the acreage and I
baby will come out of this with some
some sense for whether or not the
bubbles all overlap they separates and I
welcome any discussion around that so
with that I'm done thank you
[Applause]
so Thank You Terry Cory Pierce is our
next speaker gonna address regenerative
AG she's the owner and operator of bread
and butter farm located on the town line
of Shelburne in South Burlington you
still have some seats left for burger
night this Friday no yes
if you okay so if you want to go check
that out
Brendan better farm is a diversified
regenitive agricultural farm focused on
diversity collaboration and engaging
community in many ways through food art
experiences music care and care for the
land animals plants and one another so
thanks for being here Corey yeah thanks
it's always fun to engage in these
panels all right so let's see I asked me
to talk about regenerative agriculture
and I I'd say that that certainly is a
term that we kick around as a way to
describe what we're doing I I liked the
reference that you made Terry about like
these this kind of tribalism mentality
and kind of latching onto something I
think that's something we do as humans
to kind of feel good about and support
decisions that we make and things like
that so I get that I'd say that I've
worked personally pretty hard to try not
to do that and try to you know just
follow follow what I I feel is working
through observation through just
experience through learning from others
as much as I can and I'd say that owning
and operating a farm it it's
simultaneously almost some ways harder
to do that because you're so down and
focused in your world and and in some
ways easier because now you're fully
emerged in that world and you're and
it's and you know so so it it benefits
you to try to stay has it really
open-minded as you can about what what
is going to be the best practices for
for
sell for for the future for the world
for your children etc so when I thought
about how to talk about this tonight
really how I how I my journey in farming
has has is really dictated kind of where
I am now at age 44 and being an owner of
a farm and trying to make a go of it as
a business so I thought I'd talk about
that
so initially for me I did not grow up in
a family farm I was a kid who spent a
ton of time outdoors and just naturally
loved that and then when it came time to
to get a job I was sort of panicked
about needing to stay inside in the
summertime and luckily found an
opportunity to work on a farm as a
20-acre so conventional vegetable and
fruit farm in my hometown in New
Hampshire and I literally instantly got
hooked and I I loved with the things
that it just grabbed me
we're being outside we're working with a
team were working hard I I've always
been like very physically driven like
the physic like engaging physically is
something that's always excited me and
then I you know very quickly saw the
community that was built around that
certainly learning how to grow food
seeing foods that I had never never
known about before eating the freshest
possible food was really fun and
exciting seeing these farmers and and
how they interacted with us as their
crew be like let's make this great one
shouldn't go out right out to the field
and gather a bunch of stuff and then and
cook it up was was certainly like whoa
this is awesome like this is great so
all of those things really hooked me I
worked on that farm all through high
school and then into college and really
quickly was like I want to have a farm
when I grow up but I kind of have this
like idea that like farming is you know
not necessarily seen as like a really
you know good job you know it's not
something that people go seek out this
is so this is in the early 90s and we
have certainly come a long way and
especially in Vermont New England of
thinking about for
in a new way but I you know it was hard
for me to to like sort of articulate
like his farming an option is it's
something that you can go and say I'm
gonna be a farmer I wanna do this my
parents certainly thought otherwise and
we were like oh God in farming or
seriously like what you know how she
gonna do this but that was in me and it
was like stuck in me and I started
mulling that over like how do we do that
how do I do that and and so then I
started learning about agriculture like
my only experience was this one farm and
I loved it I loved the people I loved
what it represented in our community but
then I started you know in college
started learning about the bigger scope
of Agriculture and what agriculture has
meant to the human race I started
learning about environmental issues that
we were facing that Terry talked about
again but specific to two so I was
learning it like about all these big
environmental issues but I started
learning specifics around farming the
loss of topsoil the reliance on fossil
fuels chemicals and and what we are
finally figuring out chemicals were
doing to ourselves to our to the world
all around us that that other countries
were banning things that we weren't just
all these things right and how
short-term it felt like we were you know
there is this race that again Terry
talked about of like populations growing
food needs to grow we need to we need to
make it all happen but it's sort of like
what comes first the chicken or the egg
there we are we making more and more and
more food in there for populating more
and more and more or we like what it was
you know and I'm not gonna answer those
questions that's not for me to answer
but I started just noticing those and
questioning those and then reading books
about how agriculture is potentially the
downfall of the human race that being
able to grow so much food in one spot
one farmer can grow food for thousands
of people with the help of all these
man-made things as you know maybe not
the best thing for us as a as a as a
species then I had a whole other journey
around my own health and my own you know
understanding nutrition and what makes
my body feel the best and what you know
specific health issues I was seeing
people I knew and loved have and how
Olson there's like very clear connection
to the food that people were eating and
then how they were feeling diseases they
were suddenly getting and you know so
there's there's that whole thing I'm not
going to get go into all of that but I
had a very real personal journey on that
front and then started to kind of make
connections about this shift something
something that I asked I started asking
as a little kid constantly was why are
humans why are we this only species in
my eyes that seem like we are just
outside of the rest of the natural world
like why do we need to kind of carve out
our our world why are we so reliant on
things that are not just part of the
natural world why have we created and
rely and then become reliant on so many
man-made things when I see out in the
natural world so you know every other
species is like just live in and and and
doing their thing and some boom-and-bust
some some crash so I'm going stink some
you know have been here from forever but
why are humans and and when were humans
ever really naturally part of the world
and part of the natural world in a way
that was not just like cavemen you know
whatever you know so I I that was a
really big question for me as a kid and
then when I as I got older and start
thinking about agriculture in a deeper
way I started thinking about though you
know that question came up again and
then it came into that into the form of
Agriculture like why do we have to grow
food in a way that is so clearly in a
box here is a farm this is how you do it
you run these big huge machines that we
had to make and then we had to extract
all this fossil fuel from the earth to
drive and then we have to spray all this
on it to make it work when I see then
out in the forest a thriving beautiful
highly diverse bountiful amazing
ecosystem that is supporting life of all
kinds and so that was really confusing
to me and I see all this work whether
it's like actual physical work by the
humans or whether it's like work that
were channeling through big huge
machines to get done to make this thing
there's one thing and then again compare
it to the forest and the the diversity
the beauty the health and it just does
this juxtaposition that was very
challenging for me to understand then I
started noticing that that all that
stuff over here that we were killing
ourselves to do or killing the earth to
do is making one crop and it's usually
annual crops so what's the deal with why
are we putting why we trying so hard to
make these annual crops these crops that
just come and go and die and then we
just start over the whole next year come
and go and die
start over the next year and some years
they totally crash because even with all
the protection in the world that we as
humans try to give them some kind of
infestation happens some kind of disease
wipes it out some kind of something and
it's all done and then we're we're done
right and and now those questions are
just like mind-blowing to me right and
I'm trying to figure all of this out so
I start I mean while my like desire and
love for all of those things that I was
so excited about farming when I first
started as a teenager before I was mired
in all the depressing parts of like the
human situation I still had in me and I
still wanted that and I still wanted to
like figure out how to do this in a way
that wasn't then like gonna just
contribute to all of these other parts
of farming and agriculture and human
craziness that that I was seeing and so
and so I've lived in California I've
lived in Michigan farming and I've grew
up in the Northeast and now farming in
the Northeast so I've been luckily been
able to go on to so many types of farms
and in so many different parts of the
world or this country particular
and and really you know gotten to know a
lot of farmers who are doing so many
hugely different things and and seeing
just every possible type of scenario and
you know and there's still so much more
to see and learn but I feel like I have
been lucky in order to get somewhat of a
perspective there and it was it's been
very you know eye opening and I feel
like my journey is just at the very tip
of the iceburg still and I have the rest
of you know my short life to try and
learn as much as I can and pass that on
so you know I big ace basically began to
ask myself okay is it possible to be an
ecological player to be side-by-side to
the soil to the plants to the animals to
my fellow humans in my community in an
equal balanced way like you would you
know in a in a rich thriving forest
ecosystem is it possible is it possible
to do that as a farm is it is a farm and
what is the definition of a farm as
we've been already hearing it's hugely
variable but can and so what that what
that quickly mean meant to me was can I
somehow get land can I somehow have a
business that can support my family
myself some employees my community you
know my neighbors can it blend in enough
and can it can it sustain itself and and
again I like what Terry said in always
both as a ecosystem but then also
economically is it is it gonna be viable
and and that's that's that's where I am
now so nine years into having a farm the
the term regenerative agriculture is or
and I brought a book by Mark Sheppard
called restoration agriculture which I
like that term too and I continue to
learn about really challenges me
challenges us to think about perennial
systems that have longevity that rely on
an intensive diversity and certainly all
the things that the other speakers have
said carrying
the soil first and foremost but trying
to figure out how to to bring humans
back into a on an equal playing field
with our natural ecosystem with the
animals so you know we have beef cattle
on our farm we have pigs we have a few
chickens we have perennial plants and we
do have annual plants and how can we
have all of those things intermix
together so that we're not reliant on
one one only over the other and how can
we work alongside all of those players
down to the microbes as as all super
important players to make healthy a
healthy farm system and that's our
journey yeah I think I'm I think I'm
done let's see yeah I think if you have
a few other notes but I think that's
what I'm gonna say that that's it
[Applause]
Thank You Cory Keith Morris is our next
speaker he's going to talk about
permaculture he's has been applying his
lifelong love of nature and culture and
experience as an activist to
permaculture an ecological design since
1996 he's spent over 20 years developing
permaculture with farms and schools
towns the digitus people activists in
solidarity with exploited populations
will crossing farm which is his firm I
put it up there wrong sorry it used to
be called Pacific rock it's Willa
crossing is Vermont's longest running
permaculture and agroforestry research
firm he is also the co-founder of the
permaculture Association of the
Northeast thanks thanks to my
co-panelists it's an honor to be here so
Terence mentioned kind of neat boxes and
some of us having maybe fuzzier boxes
permaculture is probably one of the
fuzziest boxes and/or frankly just
straight outside of the box and probably
I probably have the most work to do to
dispel myths or at least misconceptions
with the field that I'm representing and
especially as its interpreted in the
agricultural community first and
foremost maybe I just like to kind of
help define permaculture and maybe
clarify that in essence really
permaculture is primarily a design
system and it's a design system that
uses the study of ecology to inform the
ways that we create relationships
between people and the things that we
depend on food centrally but also of
course water shelter energy waste
management etc so permaculture is is
very holistic from the outset and I can
say for you know some of my own journey
as a farmer and it's really nice to
follow quarry and kind of her story and
kind of personal
struggle for self identity or species
role that we we all question right what
what is the role of human beings in the
world and and and at this time in place
we certainly have every reason to
question and wonder you know who we are
what we're meant to be doing and
certainly you know what is our
relationship to each ecology right so so
thanks for that and and I can say the
person I really came to farming from the
place of an environmental activist and
really looking at our intersection with
food as that most immediate intersection
with the life around us and recognizing
that I wanted personally to take more
responsibility to that and wanted to
build a deeper relationship to that both
in terms of species and places and the
other people who also contribute to to
feeding me and and us so one of the kind
of misconceptions which isn't it's easy
to understand why permaculture is often
associated almost entirely with things
like forest gardening and herb spirals
and chicken tractors and all these
things are pretty cool things but much
more importantly is the thinking behind
how we create relationships between the
parts of a system and looking in fact to
ecology as the model for how these
relationships are as mutually beneficial
as possible
so for instance again Terence mentioned
like picking apples by hand out of an
orchard and so you have a really great
jump on getting any Pugh paiting pests
out of the orchard system before they
reproduce and I've had that job and it's
you know better than other jobs but it
isn't my ecological niche it isn't I
don't thrive picking up wormy Apple
drops in the floor of the orchard and
chickens and pigs really do enjoy
picking apple drops out of the floor of
orchards
and so of course there's regulatory
issues about grazing and fruit
production so I'm not going to get into
that terrain but that is one example of
the types of relationships that we're
looking to foster where trees are not
only having pest control and
fertilization and management but
also you know being met some of their
needs in terms of food so at its at its
heart permaculture is a vision and
that's a vision of ecological
regeneration and you know regenerative
agriculture I would I would firmly place
within the umbrella of permaculture and
there's definitely people outside of it
I think that bubble diagram well you
know there's a lot of room to shift and
grow these bubbles I think it's really
interesting to look at where we see
these types of overlap and especially in
the fashion as employed by Mark Sheppard
and this and this new term restoration
agriculture I mean that book is a
permaculture text and written by a
permaculture teacher and it is very
little other than permaculture in the
specific application to like Agri
forestry based grazing systems carbon
sequestration via agriculture and really
that that in the particular case of Mark
Sheppard kind of encouraging
permaculture minded folks to move out of
their yards and homesteads
into like co-op scale production with
tree crops and grazing systems and more
diversified agriculture and especially
in the case of Mark Sheppard and his
farm the earth work and water management
strategies that we learned from
permaculture and that's one of the
pieces that I guess I want to kind of
add to this conversation is I think
we're so popularly associated with
permaculture being really the
application of ecology so permaculture
as a as a as an academic pursuit really
comes from the school of ecology in part
and saying instead of a descriptive
science where we imagine ourselves
outside the natural world and talk about
what we see we recognize as Cory
mentioned like we are in the natural
world and have a place in the natural
world and have a very interesting
cultural dissociation at the moment
imagining ourselves as something other
than or different from and as we move
into that recognition that we are in
obligation relation to ecology we take
the text of ecology from being
descriptive text to being applied right
and we look at how ecology informs how
do we go to the bathroom how do we take
a shower
what do we
how do we build our homes and of course
that always takes very place specific
shape and that is one of the most
beautiful things about permaculture that
I try to add to this conversation is
that in addition to applied ecology
really more so permaculture is frankly
applied anthropology or applied ethno
biology where we really study the best
practices that have emerged in all of
the communities all over the world
historically pre historically
archaeologically and with a specific nod
to the incredible sustainability of many
indigenous cultures that certainly
explicitly expire inspired permaculture
design I mean in fact permaculture
really at its outset as a coined phrase
is an effort to heal the trauma between
colonists and indigenous peoples
in Australia and in fact to recognize
that that power imbalance is incredible
and we have a lot to learn not only from
indigenous philosophy but indigenous
practice and indigenous crops in
particular especially in the case of
Australia where literally European
Australia's arrived and they said there
is nothing to eat here
we cannot survive without importing the
combined cultivated diversity of the
world and bringing in animals and plants
and every other food stuff from other
ecosystems meanwhile Aboriginal
Australians of course were fermenting
poisonous plants into their nourishment
and building Weir's and elaborate traps
of tidal fish catch and really
ingeniously meeting their needs from
nothing other than that ecosystem but it
is very interesting that you know in the
world of agriculture in this now global
recombinant ecology that we have you
know Australia offers almost nothing to
our palette of plants you know we don't
we don't find much kangaroo meat on the
shelves right and so that's a big part
of where permaculture comes is saying ok
you know we have a lot to learn from
indigenous culture indigenous
perspective but also and explicitly from
its outset permaculture is looking to
this you know postmodern reality
which I bristle at the phrase personally
but so I need to qualify and what I mean
is explicitly recognizing soil erosion
explicitly recognizing toxicity
explicitly recognizing peak oil and
climate change and so for 40 years
permaculture has been explicitly
oriented in these directions and
essentially categorizing the human
endeavor in saying well we need to meet
our needs and we need to meet our needs
in ways that actually increase
ecological health and actually take
responsibility for our toxic legacy and
the problems of totalitarian agriculture
and clear cuts and recognizing that if
we go beyond you know certain
perspectives of history we can look
deeply and recognize that when it comes
to major civilizations based on agro
annual agriculture they have never done
anything but destroy ecosystems create
deserts and eventually collapse and only
very recently with the aid of
essentially fossil fuels can we pretend
that that path of agriculture is going
to continue to feed us and while I think
we need to recognize you know this
incredible imbalance of power in
agriculture in the United States in
particular I don't think we need to
judge or attack our IPM or conventional
agriculture neighbors and to be honest
as a permaculturist who is at you know
production scale with various components
of our farm I frankly have a lot more to
learn from folks who might identify in
the conventional a global often and and
and then I think there's also something
to be said about organic coming
essentially from this act of resistance
also as permaculture did in this
solidarity that we find and when we have
for instance NOFA conferences you have
like full access open source I mean
basically everyone goes out every year
innovates finds ways to have better more
efficient production and then completely
shares the best develop secrets like
every winter here and you know recently
here at UVM every February
so you know all of this I think is a
part of the dialogue that permaculture
wants to have with the agricultural
community and also recognizing that as a
design system we work with systems that
utilize tillage that you know utilize
conventional agriculture that utilize
spraying and other things and in part of
that you know ecosystem relationship
between the parts are work my work is is
often just figuring out like how in a
whole farm system you know is the
greenhouse best located or where would a
vineyard system or trellis system or
water catchment system go in relation
best relation to all the parts around it
and I think there is a lot to be learned
from like our techniques that we are
popularly associated in terms of like
edible forest gardening and really most
recently kind of especially diving into
the some of nitty-gritty of carbon
farming and tree crops and agroforestry
more generally but also you know these
probably Universal techniques at this
point like bioremediation right
addressing toxicity like carbon
sequestration like increasing the
diversity in our food system with an
intergenerational perspective and making
sure we not only have you know access to
incredible cultivated diversity of
normal vegetables and animals but like
rarer fruits and nuts some of which have
been cultivated cultivated in this area
for ten plus thousand years potentially
in a in a participatory ecology fashion
right especially when we look at nuts
and then we look at the distribution of
nuts and we recognize this isn't a
natural phenomenon the distribution of
nuts is the phenomenon of human beings
who were in large part not eaters
carrying boatloads of nuts through all
the river systems and lake ways and you
know creating an ecosystem via by and
which frankly we all do everyday
especially as eaters that is what we do
is we create ecosystems so the request
of permaculture is to bring the science
of ecology and evolution as well as
ethno biology and ethnobotany and ethnos
zoology and say how do we do this best
and how do we do this best
in this modern world where our food
plants and animals have come from all
over the world and we are by default
creating recombinant Ecology's and how
do we create these recombinant Ecology's
as wisely as possible with our only hope
to know what's wise potentially being
looking intergenerationally and saying
how do we leave deeper soil more suited
to produce food in the future rather
than less right how do we leave cleaner
water and in this very specific moment
in time how do we leave this peak of our
access to energy in the best legacy
possible which i think we'd all agree
isn't more pavement more parking lots
more places where we can't grow food but
also we have this very unique moment in
history where we can use machines to
install appropriate water catchment
systems or terraced hillsides or create
really good food producing ponds that
keep nutrients out of our wild waterways
and also invest our energy at moment in
infrastructure like greenhouses and root
cellars and food processing facilities
that quite frankly only a generation or
two in the future most likely won't have
access to the same resources and
materials to do so how do we do this
with a very deep intergenerational
perspective which is which is you know
not to overly simplify all of the varied
wisdom that we learn from indigenous
cultures the world over but certainly
one thing that seems to be in common
from the most successful cultures on the
planet that is their intergenerational
responsibility and their
intergenerational perspective so in
closing the last thing I want to say is
really also where permaculture most
excitedly to me joins this conversation
is to look beyond our fields and
certainly our farm systems you know
permaculture offers a lot to them but
really permaculture enters this dialogue
about like how do we feed growing
populations and all the arable land in
the world can only feed you know so many
people to say well forget all the arable
land in the world let's look to our
yards let's look to our cities let's
look to our rooftops let's look to
create ecosystems very intentionally in
the places we live that are as
productive
and resilient as possible thank you
[Applause]
thanks Keith
our last speaker but definitely not
least is Ernesto Mendez he's professor
of Agriculture here at the University of
Vermont
he shares his time in the Environmental
Studies Program and in the department of
plant soil science where he heads the
Agri ecology and livelihoods
collaborative he also didn't put this in
his bio but I'm going to announce it
he's going to be the chair of the plant
soil science department starting in four
days same day marijuana's legalised go
down goes down in Vermont ok ok
his research and teaching focused on a
gray ecology agri-food systems
participate action research and
transducin player a transdisciplinary
research approaches that UVM is an
active member of the food systems
initiative and a fellow at the gund
Institute for the environment
most recently he is the lead editor of a
book our ecology a transdisciplinary and
participatory and action oriented
approach which is the latest Agri
ecology textbook out there and it's
great Ernesto was born and raised in El
Salvador and he has worked extensively
in Latin America the US and Spain and
I'll also say it was my privilege to
study under him to do my graduate
research so Thank You Ernesto
[Applause]
so good afternoon everyone Sahra thank
you for organizing and for everybody who
came my fellow panelists it's been great
to hear your some of your stories so I'm
gonna add a little bit of my own stories
but at UVM I lead this group called the
Agri ecology and livelihoods
collaborative we like to say that we're
a community of practice it's very
diverse there are faculty students staff
collaborators including farmers and
other members of the community and we
use a participatory action research like
sirasa to to work in agriculture par as
the acronym really tries to do research
went with and for communities so when we
work with farmers we'd like to establish
the research agenda with them moving
forward in fact I work with Cory we're
starting to work with them more and we
do quite a bit of teaching and training
at different levels our group is very
collaborative so I've put some of the
logos here of the people we collaborate
with it's a it's a value we hold that
some of the issues that have been coming
up related to agriculture are not going
to be solved if we don't work together
in one way or another so this was one of
the questions that Sarah gave the
panelists to answer what you know what
is whatever you do to you
and and I want to say that my training
my undergraduate degree was in
conventional agronomy and and that the
reason following with the life stories
that people have been sharing I came to
agriculture it was somewhat different
being from El Salvador country where
there's a lot of inequality and a lot of
inequality in land when I was growing up
so two percent of the population owned
80% of the land at one time and so this
is something that I really wanted to
work with or do something about and I
was fortunate enough to be able to come
and study in the US so I did my grana
meet the Green in California
and it was a very conventional approach
very production oriented and an
industrial AG grapes and vegetables in
California and when I was thinking about
going back to work in El Salvador to try
to solve some of the issues that I was
concerned about industrialized
agriculture didn't seem to be what was
going to help resolve those things
because it was very prescient in El
Salvador already and being used by by
very large land holders that had a lot
of capital and a lot of resources but a
lot of the small holder farmers that
were working there just didn't have
access to that so I agree ecology I
found that in the 90s more than twenty
years ago and it was an inspiration and
I just I saw it as as an approach as a
way to really take into account
agriculture and farming that would be
environmentally sound socially just and
economically viable so I like to say
that Agri college is an approach I'm a
researcher I'm a scientist and I really
like doing research but I like to do
research that has an impact and that's
why I like to do research with farmers
so that whatever we do together actually
has some meaning to their farms or or
rural communities and I found that if if
it was gonna be useful it couldn't just
be one discipline so ecology is here as
a tenant of Agri ecology just does this
in permaculture but that's just not
enough when you think about the El
Salvador issue ecology is not gonna
resolve some very deep-rooted social and
issues of inequality the other thing
that resonates with what some of the
people here have said is that
agriculture really values different
knowledge systems so even though I do
believe we have our roots in science and
in the Academy we really reach out and
and have horizontal dialogue with
practical knowledge indigenous knowledge
that can span all these different you
know cosmovision culture we really think
that is important
in our work and and finally and this
might be more personal than other
Agriculture's for me is that I really
want to do something that's
action-oriented and transformative very
recently or not too recently but has
been very recently accepted as that Agri
ecology can be seen in expressions of
science social movement and practice and
that's this has this resonates a lot
with me because I think that some of the
issues that prompted the development of
alternative agriculture I I agree that
there's tribalism but I would also say
that a lot of organic permaculture and
agriculture our response to
industrialized farming so they came up
because people were concerned about some
of the impacts of industrialized farming
there is overlap absolutely but there
but there's also you know a division
somewhere so for me what we really need
to engage these three dimensions
research in science social movements and
practice so hopefully that'll be a
little more clear at the end what I see
I see a lot of overlaps between or among
all of the alternative agriculture
models so but again I see them as very
separate from the industrial Akmal and
we have heard Keith's youth use ecology
I think we might have set it to an
environment and which is at the core of
Agri ecology organics started as a
social movement and there's definitely
the practical side and with conventional
agriculture so there are a lot of
similarities I think the main difference
with industrialized AG is that a lot of
these other perspectives really have
social and ecological stewardship as as
a guiding frame whereas I think and what
I remember from being a conventional and
gharana mist that we were really being
trained to produce and make money and
most farmers be it that their organic
agriculture want to produce and make
money the question is
you do it at the expense of the
environment and in social issues so all
again you know I'm an academic and I
think it's really important to say that
where we come from and where we're
positioned so I'll give you a bit of an
academic history of agroecology as a
concept so in in and what I call wave
one which is is that working over there
in the 70s and 90s it was basically the
field sort of like very strongly wanted
to apply ecology to agriculture this was
not happening so again I went to
California Polytechnic State University
majored in crop science can somebody
want to guess how many ecology classes I
took to get my BS anybody okay Eric wins
zero so that wasn't really a part of
conventional agronomy so a lot of the
people in the 70s and 90's that came up
with a great ecology we're saying we
need to bring in ecology into
agriculture but then wave to in the
early 2000s they realized that ecology
was just not enough and part of it was
if we really want to help farmers it's
not just about farming practices there's
political issues through land
distribution issues there's social
issues there's inequality very complex
issues and honestly as an agronomist I
was a little bit afraid of moving into
that those dimensions but I started
working with small holder farmers and
I've been lucky to work almost in most
parts of the world except Asia maybe and
and it's true in a lot of these places
technology and just farming better to
produce more is not enough there are
some really deep rooted issues but if
you really want to solve the problems in
the long term you'll have to address at
some point in 2009 what I call wave
three was this proposition that a greek
ology was a science and movement in a
practice and it had some debates at that
point but right now I can safely say
that most people accept it that this is
how it is
and wave 4 where I've participated the
most is really taking it more explicitly
into this inclusive entrance formative
approach so we want to change food
systems I'm doing it from my research
position in different ways and we want
to be inclusive we want to hear other
voices we don't want to say that just
science is the voice that has to be
predominantly there we have to take into
account the issues that Keith brought up
colonization a lot of people that reach
out to Agri ecology are groups that have
been oppressed in one way or another and
that's because they see at just this
perspective I had a conversation with
some Cuban permaculturist and we we had
a whole discussion about similarities
and differences and they kind of said
well permaculture seems to have more
ethics and I agree ecology more justice
we should talk about thank you so one
really interesting thing about the
social movement piece is that la Via
Campesina which is a international
person organization 182 organization
members 81 countries an estimated 200
million smallholder farmers so here's
where a friendly challenge to Terry yes
so I would say that maybe more land is
being cultivated under conventional
agriculture but there's probably more
non conventional farmers yeah thank you
so so what you see which is really
interesting is that these social
movements have really embraced our
ecology as the way that they want the
farmers that they work with to farm and
part of the reason is because they see
this opening but it's not a science that
rejects the political economic issues a
lot of my scientist colleagues really
cringe at this you know don't talk
politics we don't talk politics in Agri
ecology we kind of have to engage it
because we believe that some of the
issues we face our political economic so
that doesn't mean that I have to be the
activist and the Advocate all the time
maybe my role is more doing this
research with farmers and with community
members but I acknowledge the fact that
the
issue is there and that it is important
so there's a lot of these movements all
over the world less so in the US
although growing I think another thing
that I wanted to say is Agri ecology has
has emerged and and taken a seat in
international policy when I started
working in a great ecology it was really
at the fringe and it was it was
considered or taken seriously by a lot
of scientists or policymakers we have
now are in the radar of the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations which is not that important in
the US but pretty much very important
everywhere else because it's the UN arm
of Agriculture and in Central America
the Ministry of Agriculture listens to
the FAO and in a lot of different
countries so it's been huge that the FAO
has kind of like embraced Agri ecology
they have an agriculture knowledge hub
and they just had the second sim global
symposium this year
IPE s food is the equivalent of the IPCC
the climate change panel so I invite you
to look it up if you want it they just
published a report on from uniformity to
diversity it's a lot of really great
people Olivia the shooter is the leading
director and he was the UN Rapporteur
for the right to food so in the US there
are some organizations that are
affiliated with Agri ecology and
advocating the u.s. food sovereignty
Alliance food First Union of Concerned
Scientists it's been interesting for me
I've been in at UVM for 11 years looking
at who is engaging in Agri ecology in
the US a lot of them are Native American
groups African Americans people of color
that are doing agriculture so this sort
of like again groups that have some kind
of marginalization or oppression are
reaching out to this approach to do that
we are starting to work more with
whyhunger they have reached out to us
recently and you know this dialogue that
came up among the tribes is also very
difficult between scientists advocates
and practical farmers right sometimes we
don't speak to each other that well so
that's part of what
I really like to do is how do we break
those barriers in terms of practices
since this was a farming practices in
Agri ecology as in permaculture we use
principles and one of a lot of what I
like to do is this how do these
principles hold all over the world so
soil health is is a principle that's
been coming up for me everywhere I work
we did work with on on climate change
resilience in Haiti Nicaragua and
Honduras and people concluded that those
farmers were like we need to take care
of the soil when you look at some of the
work I've done here in Vermont
everybody's talking about so help so
it's a principle that seems to hold
regardless of where you are and then
your practices would adapt to your
context so maybe to maintain soil health
in the tropics agroforestry is really
good although I'm hearing Keith saying
that here too great but here in the US
I'm more used to hearing cover cropping
it's a really good practice for
maintaining so health which is not that
great in a tropical environment but
maybe could be tweaked so there are also
other Agri ecology associations around
the world again kind of getting really
strong in other places and less so in
the US but we're really working hard to
change that
and I wanted to end just by bring to
your attention this opinion piece in The
New York Times that came out today that
discusses agroecology and gives you a
good summary of the things that are
happening globally so I have this very
global vision I can't help it given Who
I am and where I come from and even
though I love to work in Vermont I'm
always keeping this sense of what it you
know it's important to contribute I
think Vermont has a lot to contribute to
the world all of the things that are
happening here and sometimes we don't
bring it out enough I guess I'll leave
it there
[Applause]
thank you to all the panelists it was
great to hear all of your stories and
it's time for you guys to participate so
we have two mics so you can come up to
the mic if you have a question we ask
you know it's time for a question and
comments if you have a specific question
for a panelists please address it to
them so that all five panelists have to
answer every single question obviously
you're allowed to chime in but we just
want to have the most time for you guys
to give comments yeah so anybody have
any questions can you go up to the mic
yeah thanks hi everybody thanks for
being here tonight and engaging with all
of us I heard some of you talked about
like a global food shortage and rising
populations and some of you not address
this topic and I just wanted and I was
wondering if you could all speak about
how your respective disciplines think of
is there a global food shortage is there
not and yeah just a little bit about the
discussion within your respective
disciplines
so a great college II has a very strong
position and this and it's mostly that
we are producing enough food already
that the issue that we're facing is that
its distribution right and and the other
issue is what are we producing so we
have for example millions of acres of
soy in in South America and in Argentina
so that's quite a lot of production but
it's all going to animal feed or some to
biofuels so we contest the notion that
we need to produce more to feed people
again it seems to be this more political
economic issue of who's producing for
what are they producing and who's
getting the who has access to thanks
yeah that's a great question
and I would say personally and then
there's by no means consensus within the
permaculture community but generally you
know we work against this scarcity
mentality where the problem is there's
not enough to go around and the reality
is you know even historically when we
look to the Irish potato famine there
were record-breaking wheat exports
happening at the time of the Irish
potato famine and the people who lived
on potatoes were the only people who
were in famine and I think it's a really
interesting problem in our economic
system and I think that's certainly
where we have much better leverage
because the reality is there is food
held under lock and key for purposes of
stabilizing prices the reality in the
United States especially is that vast
embarrassing portion
I won't quite say majority but an
embarrassing bortion of the food that we
produced never reaches plates much less
even after reaching plates is is fully
nourishing people and we are in fact
over producing tremendously relative to
the eaters needs on the planet at
present and only driving ourselves
deeper when we're over producing in like
soil eroding agricultural systems so the
answers are easier or harder to
to come up with but I think it's a very
important question because as we enter
the dialogue for instance with genetic
engineers and things like Golden Rice
and these you know they say hey we're
going to end world hunger well the
reality is of course genetic engineers
at present are primarily herbicide
manufacturers and primarily genetically
engineered herbicide resistant plants so
that they can increase herbicide sales
and I think we have a very important
conversation to have about you know for
instance scarcity versus abundance and
also really addressing a kind of
import/export commodity oriented
agriculture which might make sense from
an investment perspective and perhaps in
some cases from a GDP perspective but
that is something where you know
permaculture has has the reason
permaculture became a global movement
essentially was to go to these places
which were engaged in export
monocultures and if there was ever
economic you know if there was price
fluctuation with those crops these
communities would be in tragedy if there
was pest or disease issues with these
crops these communities would be in
tragedy and to encourage a incredibly
diverse agriculture system that meets
first immediate needs which isn't to say
it doesn't engage in any export or or
production for sale
I'll just add that I I just wonder I
think so yeah how long we can keep up
what we're doing and you know a point of
discussion for me and as someone who
raises animals in a way that is not the
way that when we talk about animal like
food growing the crops being raised to
feed animals that's a totally different
way to work with animals on a landscape
and so that's like the product the end
result of raising meat for human
consumption there's two very different
ways to do that that is part of this
whole discussion as well but I just
wonder how long we can do it in a way
that is you know currently happening but
I agree with everything that you just
said the overproduction right now for a
very short term human scale short-term
gain well I had those graphs so so what
I would say is no we don't have a
shortage in and I don't see there's a
couple things that I see as promising
one is that we are expecting the human
population to level off at about 10 or
11 million and to finally reach
replacement population so as long as we
can find a system by then to feed that
many people in theory we can go on long
as our resources don't run out the those
graphs you know chicken or egg you know
do we have more people because we had
more food or do we have did we make more
food for more people I think we probably
have more people because we had we
produced more food and allowed people to
breed more was that a good thing or bad
thing that well we can argue that all
day long but we're all here and we all
have to eat I think two parts that I
want to mention one that I like that
Corey mentioned we animals animals are
fabulous creatures for converting
non-digestible plant proteins into
proteins digestible by humans that's
what we when we bred animals domestic
animals you know over millennia we
created these creatures that could
convert food that we can't efficiently
eat mostly grasses we can eat soybeans
into food that we can eat in store I
mean they stood they you don't have to
refrigerate a living cow until you cut
it up the butts and what I see is the
biggest problem is our Western diets is
far too dependent upon you know fossil
fuel dependent nitrogen dependent crops
to feed all the animals we eat too much
meat and more concerning is that the
rest of the world's we don't want to
just have it all but the rest of the
world is catching up to us and then we
see a lot of the issues with
particularly say the soy tariffs that
are happening right now that are
probably gonna decimate a la lleve a
more more ghost towns in the Midwest
those soybeans are being grown to ship
to China to feed the pigs to feed a
Western diet so we eat too much meat
without question we need to address that
there the last thing I like to point out
there was a piece of New York Times
November of last year I think it was
looking at the food waste issue and one
really important thing to think about
with this is that of the food that's
wasted yes we produce enough calories
worldwide and then and significantly
more to feed everyone between 60 and 96
percent of that waste is pre consumer
before it hits the plate so we need to
again protect the crops and design a
system where we can move those crops to
people during that chain that don't get
wasted there's a whole lot of societal
implications we need to come up with to
do that we're not perfect human
necessity to make sure we're all fed has
been a great driver of innovation but as
resources start to shrink we're gonna
need to have different drivers which is
how do we do this in a more sustainable
way
I want to add too much but I will say
that generally speaking I would
definitely grow at the what Ernesto said
that the problem is not production or
food scarcity but access much more so
which is a much more complex problem to
solve and in terms of I guess addressing
specifically organic and how I think
organic views this issue there's a lot
of discussion kind of outside the
organic community about feeding the
world and whether organic can really
ever accomplish that I would say that
the 200 million smallholder farmers that
Ernesto mentioned are probably
practicing a lot closer to can organic
than conventional industrial farming
practices and they are feeding a huge
portion of the world as it is right now
and used to feed a larger percentage of
the world and then kind of within the
organic community and I think this is
fairly minimal but I have had
conversations with people who are part
of I would say the organic industry not
necessarily the organic farming movement
who are concerned or or share this
mentality of food scarcity and feel that
we need to kind of loosen up the
regulations are on organic in order to
allow organic to feed more people and I
push back really strongly against that
because if we loosen up the meaning of
organic too much it's not going to mean
organic anymore and I don't necessarily
think that that's what needs to happen
in order to feed our population we need
to address the issues of distribution
and access yeah thank you and there's
lots of research out there that does
show small-scale organic agriculture
kenfield the world if we put our focus
on that Badgley article was an article
that came out in 2014 or 12 I can't
remember four four seven all right it
was when I was in graduate anyways look
that up and there's lots more research
out there but we don't to focus you
don't want me to start giving my opinion
here I'll never stop ok so Dave misko
please step to me since
1973 and it's really really exciting to
see that you young people you know you
are it what we've started you need to
really go with I'm along with Dave
Chapman and he's set for Vermont we
started an organization called keep the
soil and organic about six years ago to
fight the USDA illegal certification of
hydroponic farms as we were doing that
we found more and more that the the
industrial organic industry was not
following the rules of the organic
regulations whether it was the
hydroponic or whether it was the CAFO
chicken operations the CAFO dairy
operations which are group very quickly
for they putting out of business the
real organic dairies in Vermont and
elsewhere the family farms we're in a
crisis situation with with the dairy
yeah organic dairy industry throughout
the United States we're becoming a
crisis situation with the hydroponic
greenhouses taking over the markets
whether it's here in Burlington at City
Market or whether it's in the
supermarket's whether it's in the Whole
Foods and so we thought that we lost as
USDA National Organic Program
illegaly is allowing the hydroponics as
we're doing that we found that there
were a lot of other instances where the
rules weren't being followed
the senator leahy was the originator and
to push the National Organic Program and
the standards and they're not being
followed we have groups like NOFA and
Vermont and around the New England who
are following the rules I'm certified by
the Vermont organic farmers I did along
with a number of other small group of
organic farmers in Vermont we started
Vermont organic farmers and the
difficulty now is that the nofa's and
the true certification organizations the
United States have to follow the rules
of the the National Organic Program and
yet those rules are shaky because other
certification organizations like
California organic farmers and a number
of other ones aren't following the rules
so you go into the city market you go
into the supermarkets and you see the
USDA label that USDA label does not mean
the same throughout the United States
about 80 to 90 percent of the
certification farms in the United States
are following the rules and the bigger
and the bigger and the bigger ones
aren't yet you go into these stores you
don't know the difference so when we
lost we all we start an organization
which Maddy mentioned the real organic
project and what that is meant to do is
it's meant to really look at where what
the rules are and how to make them
better
and to give something higher than what
the USDA standards say and but even more
important on how the USDA standards are
being certified throughout this country
so our focus is two things one thing is
to have the standards which we've we met
together in the end of March and with a
group of farmers and organic advocates
from all around the country and sort of
improved on what the USDA standards say
and we're doing a pilot project with 50
farms around the United States to see
how what these how these standards work
within the within some of the top farms
in the United States the other thing is
is we're doing a just ask campaign where
you go into the stores and you go to
City Market and you see Driscoll's
Barry's Driscoll's is the biggest
producer of organic berries in the world
almost all of them are hydroponic they
never say that on the label so to ask
people in the stores is that hydroponic
is that organic most of them don't know
so the the push is to have something
that really means organic as you people
here are wanting to become organic and
become organic farmers I'm just about
done my farming
but if I don't leave the legacy that we
and other ones don't leave a legacy that
organic means something you won't have a
market and you and your what you're
trying to do with the good things with
with your organic farms you're the
industrial organic agriculture will have
the markets so thanks do you have a
question for anyone else have a question
Braham from rural Vermont thank you
thank you all that really appreciated
everything y'all had to say in this
discussion here tonight so I do work for
morover Mott but I'm also a small farmer
and such Vermont and work as an educator
as well my business partners over here
and it's really like I said great to
have you all speak but also to see
everybody here it's really inspiring and
one of the questions that comes up for
me both my personal relationship to this
work but also my professional
relationship and I think Dave really
gets to part of the point here is what
do you all see as the role of policy in
trance in shaping the future of farming
of agroecology of our food systems of
our agro ecosystems and maybe is the
second layer to that question which hits
a little more home and something that I
think a lot of a lot of people these a
few of these people at the table here
are dealing with directly is and which
is a partially a consequence of policy
is you know how do you see a just
transition from some of these systems of
management but also as Keith mentioned
the larger economic and political
systems and social systems that are
meshed within it
accounting for sure ecological impacts
but also the history and current
situation of Industry and policy
pressure that made these farms where
they are and specific I would say the
dairy industry whether it's called
conventional or whether it's it's called
sustainable or and organic is now you
know it's still part of this commodity
system and we're seeing
organic dairy producers also at the fate
of that system so I'm curious what just
transition looks like to you accounting
both for ecological impacts but also
socio-economic well-being in history
that's a part of all of this and where
these farmers find themselves in the
role of policy in your work or movement
building or other methods of change
thanks Graham does anybody want to take
that up to answer whoever wants to
answer so we can get more questions in
if we yeah it's it's a really hard
question to answer for me in a succinct
way but that's what my job I hope is all
about and in response to your specific
point about kind of a just transition we
recently I know if I did a survey of our
members and we asked them you know what
they want us to work on in our strategic
plan over the next five years what they
think our goal should be for that plan
and a lot of them mentioned exactly what
you're talking about
a transition for Vermont agriculture
away from sort of the commodity based
dairy model via conventional or organic
to a more diversified type of you know
maybe smaller family scale or mid scale
agriculture and I think that that's
really been our vision and of course we
do want to support organic dairies and
and also other types of family scale
farms that are succeeding economically
and ecologically our mission is to build
an ecologically sound an economically
viable food system in Vermont and so I
think in terms of policy there's so many
ways it's really hard to again
succinctly answer that question but just
today I actually was looking at an
amendment that's being proposed by
senator Sanders on changes to the way
that dairy is regulated in the farm bill
under the farm bill and there's a lot of
kind of small tweaks that you could make
that may help farmers in this time of
crisis and that's sort of you know a
stopgap measure but I think the larger
question of how do we transition away
from these systems that that may not be
sustainable in the long run is a much
larger one and I think it's going to
take really concerted and collaborative
long-term effort across lots of
different types of Agriculture and lots
of different organizations to work on
policy that will accomplish that it's
sort of a non-answer but it's a really
complicated
question I got something I'll bet you so
yeah without questions since the farm
bill came about even a little bit before
that there has been a false advantage
given to field crops corn and soy corn
is a is a incredible plant in terms of
productivity if you feed it it'll just
keep producing especially how we've bred
it but the policies and the subsidies
have given it a false advantage and
therefore we've been able to build up
systems whether they be however you
convert that protein into milk or meat
that take advantage of corn and soy this
is a little Liron dear to my heart I
grew up on a dairy farm and what would
be considered for the idealized small
dairy farm when we moved back to the
farm I was three years old my
grandfather had I think 26 head of cows
in the classic Red Barn when I was a kid
four or five years olds we had two
milkman we had the guy who picked up the
milk and we had the WIC guy who brought
our food systems allotment because you
could not make money at that scale and
there was a real transition at that time
so as a fundamental problem with dairy
there's a price disconnect between
there's a disconnect between the price
signal when the price goes up you make
more milk when the price goes down you
make more milk until enough people go
out of business you know the price keeps
going down people go out of business it
crashes and that's how we supply how we
affect our milk prices what we need what
I feel we need and I go back to papers I
wrote in this class I now teach an Ag
policy that my father thought this was
crazy that I was proposing this and I
wasn't proposing it's not a new idea
the problem with dairy in particular as
well as some other commodities is that
it is a supply driven system not of man
driven system so where dairy has worked
particularly we looked to the north is
when there's a supply management system
organic dairy I have cousins that are
that are in the organic dairy business
farming on a farm that looks exactly
like my farm when we've sold the cows in
2004 they were doing well feeding three
generations of the fam
they're struggling right now and at that
time in Central Vermont where we had 35
to 60 head dairy farms organic was the
only way to make it work and that was a
bubble for a short period until we
figure out it's not that there's too
much conventional milk there's just too
much milk and until we find out a way to
balance the supply with the demand we're
gonna keep running into that no I don't
have any great answers aside from trying
to figure out I think that's the
fundamental policy issue we need to get
to stop subsidizing field crops as much
and come up with some way to balance
supply with mint
I don't know and and I'd say that the
the strategy that we're working on is
just trying to come up with structural
for our own business like a legal
structure that that can protect us as
best as possible and that takes a lot of
time and resources and energy to figure
out and and I don't know if that's the
answer but I think we have to be super
creative and I want nothing to do with
the commodity world on that front
because how you know with all already
all the unknowns about farming then to
add that unknown to seems really scary
to me so that's that's just our approach
is like really digging into the legal
structures and try to find all the
different type of protection mechanisms
we can thanks yeah thanks for an
important question and I think we are in
a very unique position in Vermont when
it comes to these questions because I'd
like to think that we have more folks
able to hear me but I'd like to think
that we have more than elsewhere a more
direct democracy or more participatory
democracy or at least greater access to
our representatives here in the state I
think we have the tradition of Town
Meeting and we have you know generally
people who you see at the store or
school or have town-hall type meeting
where hopefully policy can be a little
bit more responsive and and respond
quicker to our demands and I think you
know we have a really interesting
dilemma here because I don't think you
know generally any farmers want more
regulations and at the same time you
know we believe everybody may be
benefits from more transparency except
for those with something to hide right
so I think it's really interesting when
we look to other states where the laws
are passed for instance if you wear a
camera into an animal production
facility you are charged with criminal
trespass even if you were hired and
that's the law that they pass and and
say you know all right now we've
protected farms right and it's really
interesting I guess I want to weigh in
on this with a little bit of you know
personal background and in the case of
my farm with frankly what I think we
will face most significantly in the
immediate future here in Vermont which
is is cannabis so we we are a cannabis
farm we produce organic CBD hemp which
is medical hemp it's directly from the
branches of it we don't grow fiber hemp
or seed hemp we grow you know sinsemilla
we grow seedless flowers female flowers
for medicinal purposes and right now
that entire game is indirect dance with
every little tenth of a percentage point
shift with our breeding with our
extraction with our cultivar selection
and we're in the responsive position
where we basically adjust as the law
change and I think what what we as a
farm and group of people are trying to
do is be much more proactive rather than
responsive and if we take our cues from
corporate agribusiness and say well
here's what we can and cannot do and
what's isn't isn't legal they show up
and they whine and time the legislators
and hand over like pre-written bills and
say this is the one that we need cite
thank you very much and that's not
necessarily I don't think we should
adopt that model entirely but I
definitely think we need to be much more
proactive and vocal with a positive
vision
and and use that vision to drive what we
see the need what policy limits and what
policy supports and in the case of
cannabis I don't want to weigh in on
where policy should be but it's really
interesting and we particularly find
ourselves at this month so at this very
moment we're hosting a residential
intensive cannabis culture course where
people are learning to grow cannabis
ideally in as ecologically regenerative
ways as possible and specifically I
think this is an opportunity for us to
be proactive and pre-emptive in a
business with incredible financial
interest with which the tides will turn
very quickly I mean right now we see the
greatest opposition to legal cannabis
coming from essentially the biggest
breweries and pharmaceutical companies
in the country and they are also at the
same time ready to invest and become the
primary means of distribution of this of
this crop or this product and I think we
in Vermont have this very unique
position just like we did when we
decriminalized raw milk thank you we're
all Vermont and created more immediate
liberalization of like the ability to
process animals on farm and serve them
publicly in a restaurant without like
the Clark brothers the chicken who
couldn't which couldn't cross the street
if you're familiar with the story one
was a caterer the other was a farmer and
they were on the same farm and they
couldn't sell the chicken from the farm
to the caterer without like going all
around the state and that was a part of
how we created policy was was but with
that kind of as an example of how what
we wanted as a community we wanted to go
to a farm that like had the chickens
grown and if they were serving meals in
a restaurant fashion like know that that
chicken was actually the same chicken
and not necessarily like miss tagged
from a major facility so I'm sorry to
take as much time with this as I have
but I think especially in the case of
cannabis we see this incredible
dissonance between federal policy and
state policy and need to lie and rely on
our directly participatory democracy
broken as it may be and
and and vocally have a voice for what we
want which in the case of cannabis I
would hope is a part of a diversified
family farm a part of ideally organic
agriculture a part of our tradition of
direct marketing and direct added value
and right now we have the opportunity to
shape that law because I guarantee you
that law will be rushed through the next
legislative session as we simultaneously
see legalization in Canada and
Massachusetts and literally millions
dozens of millions of dollars just
leaving the state to engage in a legal
market on both sides of our borders so I
don't want to make this about that but I
think it's you know a very interesting
part of where we have to shape policy
proactively rather than respond to
policy and determining our farming
practices I'll be very brief I think
this is really important and I want to
agree with everything that's been said
policy engaging in policy and and
advocacy's is hard we all have jobs and
families and adding one more layer it's
hard but I think that it's very
important that we do it and because if
we look at the policies if we believe in
a broad umbrella of sustainable
agriculture in food systems that's not
where the current policies are taking us
so if we want to make a change we have
to engage however we can I know that for
me I'm I'm opening up more to engaging
with social movement organizations that
are interested in Agoura ecology they're
asking for data they're asking for talks
it took educating some of their their
staff so that's one way that I've been
able to engage and and I think it's
really important as someone who hasn't
done it that much but I'm convinced that
we have to do it we have to change it at
that level
thank you so much to the panelists into
the audience and I just want to remind
you that this is going to be archived at
the UVM YouTube website so if you think
other people would want to hear this
please pass it along thank you so much
for coming out tonight
[Applause]