and he could mourn it you guys ever wake
up in the middle of the country and guys
are staying with like hey can you go out
there and try to shoot some of those
coyotes my wife's killed about seven of
them months back porks lately and we're
having a bad problem them taking her
cattle out this year do me a favor just
locking load and send some lead
downrange if you see a furry critter out
there it's kind of what I woke up to
this morning
me and flare out here at favorite
favorite ranch we're doing a little rod
design this week and just kind of
hanging out in the country so anyway
that's what you do you just grab you cup
of coffee you look for Jody's I believe
that's a white van coming in right now
well I think Winston's working on
something out here at the crib meanwhile
I'm loading a high-powered rifle flare
doing some Glasson right now this is
this is high stakes hunting right here
next to the septic tank and we got we
got guys working on the pole over here
waiting on something to come out there's
actually a real beautiful field out here
I don't really know what we're doing I
guess we're just kind of waiting on
breakfast discount what you do out here
you just wait for varmints to come out
and shoot wonderful one comes out then
you go grab you some eggs and some
coffee and start your day let's flare
improvising in a pinch brilliant
I can almost hear it over the semis down
the highway hey Poochie
you look like you have problems oh what
a cutie
I don't think the coyote huntin is
really gonna happen but I did manage to
scrounge myself up stout a cup of coffee
free-range I might add a lot of stuff
happening right here there's a lot of
big equipment
besides the the pool building this is
going to be like a favorite fishing
hangout area and just also for just
general pool use at the at the favorite
ranch all this back here is going to be
a massive I think it's gonna be a
38-acre Lake with 60-foot deep a damn
crappie it's gonna have bass it's gonna
have big bluegill all laid out very
nicely and I think Jimmy Houston is
actually gonna help with the design of
this maybe a few other anglers I don't
know if you guys know about Jimmy
Houston but he's got some phenomenal
ponds I've actually been there and I've
seen him I fish them they're incredible
he has an incredible place nose thing to
you about building ponds this all back
here where we were looking for coyotes
morning this is going to be a giant lake
so it'll be something really neat where
we can just come up take boats out and
test lures test rods test all kinds of
stuff go hang out at the pool it'll be a
phenomenal place to be in the outdoors
so looking forward to that pretty
excited you know what I see some rods
over here right now see flare and see
one soon with some rods so I think it's
time to go your pooch this is Pete's
baby okay she likes to talk Daisy
Poots Daisy Poots well I guess that's
the only coat or LC today huh oh don't
worry
it's that Tucker life right here you're
having a cup of coffee
hop in the mule grab your dog daisy
dukes
but the t-bones with the tape and he
just kind of cruise the farm maybe look
for some snakes McHale make sure things
are checked
fall apart out here if you're lucky and
to cast a line
there's thank is hamburger steaks ready
hey what's happenin here what's
happening here well I think that cows
upset I can't go chasing the Sheep in
cow vicious do you know
cows have been known to be for nippers I
think we need to know will you do that
for bidi I'm not getting out of the
vehicle
a passive part they're coming right to
the pond to where we're supposed to fish
we'll take old Jimmy it's an alum
of course we gotta have a llama there's
a herd of cows and then there's just a
llama randomly out in the middle is that
what they do
the llamas protect the cows we're
supposed to do this there it is
just right out of the middle like a
giraffe just and trotting around it
looks so funny man you gotta open the
old cattle gate here
I know I know eat more chicken and all
that good stuff definitely wanna lock
that back up I don't have anything today
sorry I'm sorry
I eat chick-fil-a all the time don't
worry
the valley beyond what's out there girl
how to call a man not
it's called you gotta go whoosah
[Music]
[Laughter]
come on whoa how do you call this llama
now look at that thing's cocked his head
sideways lady hey Paul Paul look at him
Jabberjaw on over there God look at
Paul
that is the funniest a creature I've
ever seen hey Paul oh come on get in bed
yeah you know that does work Winston it
doesn't look this was problem oh yeah
no you cannot
[Music]
this way please come on what's that big
man that is all Baker Willis about say
Oh Wilbur he's pretty daggum big look at
that hair on him dick just got to get a
couple more mamas to go through and then
all these little ones are gonna follow
suit
get in there all right we got a pond
we've got Flair therefore I mean there's
probably gonna be fish guts
you know let's see well you already got
a top water tight on there's a couple of
couple rods or nothing that are ready
for something remember that on the end
cap at Bass Pro the walking worm
features a lifelike tail action go
straight up in the air to mimic leeches
wall I say absolutely slurp and group
look at that tackle box
frog season I mean scary frog or
ChatterBait thank you I just think other
than thats about all I got
just uh just break a lot of like rules
there's a barrel swivel clip on the hog
I did that until I was 18 years old
really it's all good I snapped it on I
saw someone do this out cringe so I look
at the guy yet you have absolutely no
idea what you do that was true right now
so it was true he put it on the sink oh
it's extra dive action my dad had a box
of these randomly these little tiny ones
I want to take him up to Canada because
you know the mayflies they'll probably
slurp that thing like a little candy
corn hula popper I just like being
around fishing it kind of makes me happy
yep dodge cow patty or to give the old
popper toss now when your pond fishing
you got to stay back Matt I can see you
already
I promise y'all I didn't just snag that
fish you came up and tried to tag that
top water by the bank these fish are
just now starting to spawn it's crazy oh
he came off well I think we had three
bites captured one got a second little
fishing hole over here and the goats
need to be fed Tucker's gonna get in
here and feed him ago got to give give
him some roughage to keep the rooters
going I think is what he said by the way
most tick infested region in all time
okay you got to call him in with a bush
here they are they come right on in so
they just cook you just bend that tree
over and they just come right on in you
look at them going to town so they have
to have that to keep the rumen going oh
I got you so they just go crazy when you
give them a nice fresh tree oh that's a
persimmon tree those are those fruits
that aren't very good right amazing good
they're amazing good yeah you don't eat
them under green Kazu okay that's what I
did when I was a kid somebody dared me
to those leaves are almost gone now that
whole branch so these goats are now
gonna have a nice rheumatory system
flush their units out I probably need to
give a the old top water a sinned oh hey
there hey easy you're trying to get old
yeah get up in there reach them Wow that
sucker seven feet tall when he wants to
be okay let me get this pop are out of
the way for we hook a goat so when you
get when you get home from all these
business trips you just come out here
and you bend the tree over and herd the
cow yeah okay these goats have kind of
exhausted area they need some help
meanwhile he's over there fighting Billy
look they're just gonna ravage this tree
gotta like his farm life
so Winston was saying that they lost 30
goats
year the codis y'all can't believe that
so they got just these wild dogs running
and they lost about a hundred chickens
to raccoons and Cody's got a big problem
we need to come up here and do some
coyote maintenance
I think nope don't eat the popper
organic what kind of berries young
about three weeks will be blackberry ice
cream
homemade ice cream the dough
[Music]
that might be a five pounder lay down
one of these days
look at that stuff Winston saying all
this is gonna be underwater he's leaving
it for building a big lake for the pond
see the field turning oh yeah so this
little Bank will be that'll be the water
edge right there's will drive around
I'll show you where the dam will be at
the top it'll be 1,200
1,250 foot long be 54 deeds in the dam
it'll be
about 280 feet wide
I mean and then you can just sit up
there and wait for the deer to come
[Music]
right there huh
how many Springs as you Sanders
[Music]
according to the
laughing spring 11 spring speeding it
that's awesome
we're gonna drill them out put a big
piece of steel then incorporate the
holes away we have
lily pads drink on it looks like this
your middle cut this Bank this will be
part of them best love that stuff in
those pads have been here for
there's to see frogs in there they're
gonna escape get much my mondo slow ride
you hear will be the top of the thing
right here all this brush look will drop
around where it's clear can see this
this would be where the dam starts an
indigo
straight 1200
ultimate it's like an oval giant
horsefly right there was a big son of a
dick oh yeah
auxins up here for real well that's
great
so we're gonna come down here and get a
bunch of these little flat river rocks
before we flood it for the things do
through here yes you can get some cool
stuff for the pool yeah I'm gonna lay
them around that little ditch around the
pool this is gonna be really worth of
crappies in the mondo bass
we're probably catching about halfway up
that tree baby yeah we'll be in about
well the water line so that corner will
be the dam but I got I bought this the
neighbor's property we're going to those
all that out
54 foot there so we should be about 3035
feet right here
that's insane so I think this is going
to be that the lfg mondo tree right here
and then we got flares crappie Kingdom
over there something like that Woodson
was just talking about making little
landmarks all over the lake kind of
since we're gonna you know do videos on
the build and help out with some stuff I
think that would be pretty sweet
tadpoles and frogs and crawdads is
already already got him in here natives
I mean it's made this was supposed to be
a lake it's a lot but just been waiting
I love that look at that frog jumping in
there comes out right under this tree
there's another one oh I see I see what
you're saying so it probably runs it's
connected to that little spring pond up
there this whole like we call it runs
underground hey hauler but it's it's
actually a swamp like there's probably
10 or 15 artesian zits everywhere like
if we walked across it right now we'd
sink up this deep and we could just take
a sip
mmm that's where that natural water is
gonna come out and feed this glorious
nutritious feels like boys now he's
pretty strong down here leaves of three
stay away how old is that true Stan
there there you gotta be
fifty-five years old built in the early
fifties saw the quality back there we're
going to try to leave that so we can
scuba dive down here if the water gets
it's clear because there's some other
big spring out of here so we're hoping
they'll be clear enough we can sit in
that tree standing sheet of catfish this
will all be gone for letting them get
back through the dam will be up there
[Music]
and that trees going to be left in here
no coils just chillin always getting
ready duck out yeah he sees Ruger there
it goes bobwhite point there it is just
named it well after a long morning of
hanging out on the farm
we're actually here at the favorite
headquarters we're gonna be going aside
doing a little designing just talking
about some stuff for for next year but
just after seeing that whole entire
layout of what that Lake is gonna be
like I cannot wait to get up here it's
gonna be the perfect place to come up
here test out new rods go fishing film
videos and just hang out and just have a
good time out in the country definitely
gonna bring Stephanie up here
Winston's family's pretty awesome too
listens why she she makes her own like
jam she pickles her own stuff you know
it's it's like dream stuff for Stephanie
so I got to bring her up her sometimes
she's met it okay you guys wanna see the
this is the room this is where it all
goes down I don't know if I I can
actually show everything in here but
this is the full-blown selection Mexico
memorabilia right here this is that
tournament that me and Winston fished in
right here Team USA representing they
actually won that tournament and we got
some major league baseball action
happening right here for all you Rangers
fans we got Rangers rods the mondo
warehouse this is a new memorabilia wall
how long ago was that
yeah that's oh wow man sure bear all
that right there ladies and gentlemen
favorite fishing rods heading out the
door maybe it's going to your house
there's so much fishing stuff in here
it'll blow your mind
oh my head can't hurt to be honest with
you coming out one headache right now
everywhere you look there's something
you never know when you need rope okay
I'll take some rope but oh hey guys you
need some flashlights in your life maybe
some calls about a little call action in
the world
most calls or let's load up on some
stuff here literally I had a fox in my
backyard
two days ago I want to try to get some
of the stuff on camera see what's roving
around back there it's a new morning I
just woke up wanted to come out here I'm
just kind of soaking the sunrise that's
incredible I don't know if y'all could
see the the deer better don't pass the
tractor down there by the creek they're
actually sitting in where the deepest
part of the lake is gonna be
besides the dam lie down in the creek
area so that's just gonna be phenomenal
you know I can't wait the the date on
that around September when we get this
thing up and rolling there's a lot of
things involved in building a lake of
this size because it's gonna be the
biggest 30 or 40 mile radius this is
gonna be the biggest Lake around here so
it's not just a little pond in the
backyard it's a natural lake that will
sustain wildlife in this county and
probably a lot of other counties
surrounding here so I just can't wait to
see this project get started and we're
gonna be coming up here and doing videos
on it guys I love it up here
I love it up here I really want to take
Stephanie up here show her the farm this
is exactly why I told you guys in the
beginning I wanted to work with favorite
is because it's more than just fishing
and a corporation it's a family they're
my friends so I'm gonna sign you off on
that good note it is time to go back and
get with ocean spoon girl
I have heard she is made my favorite
cookies they're done they're available
so I got to get back there and get me
some of that but I'm wishing you guys
the best wherever you are I hope you're
catching mando's I hope you're having a
blessed blessed day and I wish you the
best and if you want to subscribe right
here to the channel guys going to do hit
that subscription button hit the ding
dongs for all the notifications
especially if you want to follow along
with the pond stuff this summer and
leading in the fall it's gonna be huge
project it's gonna be a lot of fun I
wish you guys the best
[Music]