all right everybody this is ross i
thought in today's video we would talk
all about pruning fruit trees and not
just
you know these peaches behind me here
but also a lot of the stone fruits a lot
of the apples the pears
we'll probably look at the persimmons
and we may even look at the grapes as
well
but i want to just cover pruning
and show you some of the pruning i've
been doing
over the last week or two
i've already at this point
come over the trees about two or three
times and have made my cuts
i've come back again later and then made
more cuts and have reevaluated the trees
and i thought it would just be you know
rather than just showing you guys
this whole process of every cut i made
i think that's an entertaining video but
i don't think it's a very educational
video i wanted to really just
show you guys the shape of the trees now
this i think is worth more than just
showing you where the cuts are
let me show you
and talk about why i made certain cuts
on these trees um
so that you get in it you can get an
understanding you know you can get the
blueprint you get the book
the manual so that when you actually do
this at home on your own trees
this makes a lot more sense to you
we're going to show you guys older trees
younger trees
trees of different sized root stocks
and many different species of trees so
these are the espalier peaches
the only real way that peaches work and
every tree is different
is if you renew the wood every year
right you have to have one year old wood
to get the fruit buds so this is one
year old wood you can tell by the color
of the wood
it's typically a redder color
and the older it gets it becomes more
gray or more brown
so you need to have one-year-old wood
but if if you have a tree as an example
that's an espalier which is really not
what you should do
or even if you had a tree that was a vas
shape you still have to renew that wood
it doesn't necessarily matter what the
form is
you got to make sure that you can set up
a system and that's kind of what i've
done up here at this top tier
right we have three tiers
in this espalier system
you have to set up this open vase open
vog shape because you're going to be
able to renew the wood a lot easier that
way
now
as an example we've already cut out a
number of these
big scaffolds here big branches that
were three or four years in age so you
can see this one here this branch is
probably three or four years old as well
and there's a number of these these are
probably two or three years old
this one back there is probably four
years old
this one coming out in front of me that
actually is quite a nice branch i like
this one how it leans outwards
getting that sunlight and opening up
that center of this top tier
this is probably four years old as well
so
you know some of these scaffolds on a
typical tree and we're going to look at
that typical shape in a minute of what a
what a peach tree really should look
like
when you have something like that
you know you want to be able to take out
these scaffolds at a certain age to thin
this out and then have the scaffolds
renew and replace themselves over time
so these younger ones here
are coming in to take up this space
but at some point having both of these
two right next to each other or maybe
even this one right next to this one is
just not gonna work we're not getting
enough light
we're not getting enough airflow and
especially in the summer i mean if you
can imagine these trees i've done a
great job this year
of opening up that center you can throw
something right through that
but even in the growing season in the
summer this is going to fill itself in
real quick right in that center so you
got to come in here
if you want good fruit quality you want
less disease pressure on your fruits
and even on your trees you got to come
in here and thin out the center and even
keep up with that during the summer
so that's what i've kind of focused on
this this bottom layer here of uh
espaliers typically what i like to do no
matter what the species is
have the tr have the branching come
outwards and sort of downwards
um and that way it can uh you know take
up this lower space it's easy to harvest
even if i were to cut off everything up
here
i still would get a great harvest from
what's below
and it would get good light you know in
that sense
but if you're gonna have this upper
stuff again
and this is exactly what i focused on is
cutting this stuff out in the center
and making big cuts you know we cut out
a scaffold there
we cut out another scaffold right there
and there
smaller cuts actually on on those trees
or on those branches and i've kind of
thinned this out a bit more
what i probably should do is even
consider this again
is because right here we have one two
three potential new scaffolds that are
coming in of a similar age i don't need
all that
you know even this branch here kind of
is shaded out by this taller thing this
taller system excuse the camera
right above it
so again this one here is kind of shaded
out by this
right here and if you kind of picture
this it's hard to imagine
but this whole thing right in this area
is kind of a mess so
that's
just the struggles you know and it's
better i think to cut out more than less
because
you know like i said all this stuff down
there at the bottom
will give me so much fruit i mean how
many peaches can you possibly eat
in a season i mean
it's crazy how many peaches i get we're
talking this year probably
it's going to be easily in the thousands
so how can i eat that many also i don't
want to preserve that many or really any
at all
so the best thing i can do is give them
away but giving away you know hundreds
of peaches peaches
you know that can be uh
a difficult task
unless you got like a food bank or
something so
you know i don't know to me it's just
not worth it to have all this disease
pressure up here that then lowers the
fruit quality on the entire tree
you know it's all about getting that
light not just
you know having that open center because
that gets you
the light in the center it makes use of
the most photosynthesis on these trees
right
you want to be able to have every single
leaf getting photosynthesis that is
going to give you the most amount of
sugars and carbohydrates
the tree can generate to then put that
into the fruits and you're going to see
that
in the the measure of your bricks if you
were to take the bricks squeeze out some
juice put it on a refractometer
you would see a higher brix just by
having a more open center
having more photosynthesis hit your tree
that's absolutely critical the other big
benefit is the air flow which then
uh you have less disease pressure
right so it's a no-brainer on the
peaches you get something called rot and
it happens all the time in these humid
climates
it's so hard to fight and you could
fight it with sprays and other things
that you might want to do but just
having the right form can go such a long
way
i mean it's almost impossible to avoid
it
but like i said if you get the right
form and if you if i cut out more up
here then probably
i really should come in here again i
need to come in here again to these
trees specifically they grow so quickly
their standards i need to thin this out
even better than i have
i'm going to get the best fruit quality
possible and this alberta
that's what this tree here is is here on
the right
did not fruit and has never really
fruited that well in terms of its fruit
quality right it's put out plenty of
fruits
but the quality's never been up there
and i wonder if oh well maybe it's a lot
to do with the way i was pruning my
trees you know i it's crazy you think
you know about pruning
so you really get a crop of peaches or a
crop of plums
and they're just a disaster you know
here over here let's see this is a
younger
persimmon tree
and this guy is getting its form this is
proc
i probably could cut this out but i'd
rather
you know get all the fruit i could but
this is the main leader here and i've
made a cut there to cut out that central
leader open this up a bit more you can
see the scaffolds
one two three four and we have some uh
scaffolds up here potentially if i want
to cut out something
lower down on the tree like this one
probably will come out in the future
as it might be a bit more shaded than
the others
just based on the angle of the sun
this is kind of the standard thing right
you want to get your tree grow it up
and don't be afraid to cut it you know
that single stem whip as an example
don't be afraid to make that cut do i
have any single stem whips at this point
i mean this is kind of
here's a young
seijo persimmon here it's just the main
whip at this point there's some
branching here at the top
i just really want this thing to grow
it's been taking a while to get
established but uh
you know that's it's very similar thing
is that you want it to grow up as a
single stem whip cut it back at a
certain height maybe around your knee
maybe at your waist depending on how
tall you want your tree
same thing over here with this quince
this guy actually got killed back
um
by some branching that fell on it
from the the shade tree above
you can see that big shade tree there
it's the same thing you want to make
your cuts bring it back to a lower
height and it'll start sending out these
branches so even though i have you know
two nice branches here on the left and
right
what i want to do is actually take off
the tips and what i probably want to do
is even bring it back even further at a
lower height and really get that
branching to come in
at a lower point
the more space over here this is more
traditional sense
younger trees these are plums of what
you might actually want to do with the
with your aspaya is actually grow
something that should be a spy a to plum
it's very similar situation having the
lower growth down here
forming this open center at the top and
even if i wanted to i could bring this
these branches way back
and have some lower uh branching here
keep that in check in the summer
rather than letting this grow all summer
just keeping it in check and i would get
nice plums
i don't have to have
crazy sized espaye trees right they
don't have to get like that
you know i think it's nice to have all
that fruit but
um
you don't really have to do that you
don't have to maintain the trees like
that i could if i really wanted to like
i said bring back that top layer in the
summer i mean we're talking about winter
pruning right now but
to be honest with you summer pruning is
really important and i i think it's um
something i'm really really going to
focus on this year on all the trees
you know i think it's important to get
them established and not really worry
too much about summer pruning where i'm
at maybe in a longer season climate
that'd be something you would do
but getting them established i think you
could just do that in the winter by keep
cutting them back to a lower height
getting that branching that you want
keep doing that over time you're going
to see success the birds are uh
they're out and about it's just so warm
out right now
and then if i bring you guys over here i
want to show you these two plantings
this is really critical i think you'll
learn a lot from these two here's
actually by the way two of our cherries
the white gold and the black gold
just cut out the center that's all i
really did made sure i even cut out the
center within the trees themselves
to have even more of an open center i
made a big cut
right in there i think i need to
actually get a saw and chop that out i
forgot about that
but uh opening up the center of the
trees but also making sure there's
nothing here in the middle
you know even in the future probably
cutting out some of this other stuff
that's going towards each other
you got to keep that center clear
and this is a great really good example
over here because
these trees are my plums
um plum cots
and apricots
so these are all very similar in how
they fruit
and
you can see i've done a an interesting
thing here that you know dave wilson
nursery has
promoted and other people have
recommended where you
plant a lot of trees in the same hole
and you can see look how many of those
white things down there at the bottom
there is there's quite a bit there's one
two three four five six seven eight
there's eight trees
in a very small area
you know it's just not something i would
recommend it's it's difficult to
maintain
you don't really need to do this
you plant one tree in the center and
then you graft all the varieties onto
that one tree
probably a standard is the way to go
and
i think that's a little bit more
difficult for the average person but
it's way more difficult i think
to maintain this and especially if you
don't plant the trees correctly so this
one here
you can kind of see
this tree is uh i think my satsuma
or this might be the um
you see here
santa rosa so this is the santa rosa
plum and this guy was just planted too
much in the center of this planting
so it's kind of occupying weird space
and i've had to force the branching
outwards because you don't want anything
in the center right you want to be able
to throw that hat through the middle you
want to be able to even stand in the
center
this is going to fill in probably quite
a bit in the summer got to keep on top
of that as i said with the peaches
but
this is kind of just positioned poorly i
i think and then even this plum cot
this one here behind me i don't even
the tag is now gone
might be somewhere down here
but uh this guy was planted even even in
an even worse position excuse me
and i'll show you guys actually
what i mean
if you can see that
so ignoring these two trees this is a
bit weird because there was one here
that died
so this one was growing out this way
but
you see what i'm saying here is that
this is supposed to be clear
and this tree should be
more over here
that was the santa rosa we looked at and
then this tree back here this plum cot
is right in the center of the whole damn
thing
and that's just not good
because this thing is now occupying
all that space in the center
and i've really had to focus on pruning
all the growth that was growing out this
way or growing out in in just the wrong
direction
and this tree is in a sense kind of
paying for it last year and this is why
i've really come to this realization
you know just with the peaches we did a
video on the peach trees not too long
ago
and the peach
video that we did talked a lot about
disease and a lot about that alberta and
how it didn't
put out good quality fruit and how it's
really fighting with disease over here
and this planting that we're going to
look at in a minute
this tree here put out hundreds of
peaches
and it did not
i did not get to eat a single one
because of disease
i know bugs plunker curlio is definitely
a big part of that as well but
you know between the rot and the plumka
curlio i didn't eat a single one
and you know what they weren't even that
good they were nowhere near as good as
they should have been because i couldn't
get them to ripen to perfection
and also because the tree was heavily
shaded it was not getting the
photosynthesis it wasn't getting the
bricks that these plums need
so by opening this up and really pruning
out a lot of this tree
pruning out all the center we should
have a lot more success this year with
this one
um
again it's just in a bad spot
you know this italian prune plum is just
odd and how it's shaped and how it's
doing but
you know we're making do with what we
got and i think this is just a really
good example of what not to do
and that's why i'm showing it to you
guys you know having this tree here in
the center if you're going to do this
here's how you should do it
okay this is going to make a lot more
sense
because i have another planting in the
front these are peaches and nectarines
and the peaches and nectarines
in addition to the trees i already have
by the way
it's amazing actually that you can just
walk right through the center of this
look how well pruned
that is
i mean that just looks gorgeous doesn't
it
now this is the back side this is the
north side of the planting
the sun comes from over here on this
side of the house and then finally sets
over here
west
so the sun is really coming through here
like this
and
what you want to do again is be able to
walk right through this i can stand in
here there's no issue whatsoever so this
is kind of what you want to do with
these trees is have one planted here
one of these guys even if you're going
to do it like this which i again i don't
recommend it but if you're going to
plant this many trees in one hole here's
four and there's two of them behind me
this is how you have to do it angle them
away from each other
pretend as if this is a scaffold this is
a scaffold this is a scaffold and etc
on one
tree and you know what these are now a
part of that whole system as well so
instead of thinking of this
as four different trees this is now one
tree with all these different arms
coming out again keeping the center
clear
and open that's the only way you're
going to get good disease pressure
good air flow
you know good fruit quality with the
sunlight coming in here getting as much
photosynthesis as possible
and that's it i made some big cuts right
here in the center i'll show you guys
and this is the key
really has become the biggest
um thing that i've done with the pruning
this year and i think it's absolutely
critical i would not be showing you guys
this
if it wasn't but look here's a big cut
here in the center
another cut right here in the center
even these branches here in the center
i've even topped them off and made sure
that the growth is growing outwards
again all that's growing outwards
and then the same thing
behind me look this is a big cut in the
middle
this was the biggest and most
problematic
branch of the entire system because this
was a giant scaffold that was way in the
center
taking up all the space all this real
estate
same thing with this one and this one
and that's really all i've done
is i've come in here
pruned out the middle
this planting makes a lot more sense
it's going to get a lot more light the
fruit quality is going to be better
but again i got to keep i got to stay on
top of this
because if i don't stay on top of it in
the summer it doesn't matter it's going
to continue to grow it's going to
continue to do its thing
and those branches are going to fill up
the middle there's
prime real estate for the sun
in the middle of the trees
so the tree is naturally going to think
oh i got to fill up that middle space i
got to take advantage of that
but you don't want that you got to prune
out that that middle stuff there and
keep up with it throughout the summer
that's how you're going to get the best
air flow
fruit quality so rather than showing you
guys
you know my actual cuts my actual
pruning i thought this was a lot better
to come in here and actually show you
guys how i've actually pruned these
trees
the pears are a little bit different
but
you're trying to get that pyramid shape
actually with those
but even
you know this is just good principles
every tree is a little bit different but
you're starting out young in a very
similar fashion getting that lower
branching
getting an open center in most
situations
trying to think about light when it
comes to actually pruning
your trees and making those cuts
thinking about airflow because
everything we do
is in an effort to promote fruit quality
you could have you know 100 500 1 000
peaches a thousand fruits whatever it is
if they're not of a good quality you're
not going to enjoy them
you're going to be actually pretty
creeped out you're going to be pretty
down on yourself because your tree is
just diseased
the fruits are diseased
all this hard work and all this effort
is just finally
coming to a point where it's actually a
problem
you know as the trees get older you're
going to realize this as the trees get
bigger as the trees grow more quickly
this especially in humid places you're
going to realize
that's what i have to do
it's gonna probably hit you then now i
hope it hope this got through to you now
but
we need to focus on this
first and foremost
in the beginning and it's so hard to
realize that so don't be down on
yourself but
there's my advice guys thank you so much
for watching take care hit that
subscribe button you got this far and
share this with your friends somebody uh
you know that's just now getting into
fruit trees
i'm sure this is a good video for them
to kind of understand what is it that i
should at least be doing
all right we'll see you guys later take
care