hi there welcome to the channel so in
this video today I'm going to be showing
you my favorite method for starting
tomatoes from seed indoors this has no
potting up involved we are using some
Solo cups but not the double Solo Cup
method this method will give you strong
healthy tomatoes that will flourish once
you plant them outside in your garden so
I'm going to go through the steps on how
I have had success in getting strong
healthy tomato plants ready for the
garden so let's get
started so as you can see here we got
the Solo cups you see lots of videos and
people having great success using just a
plain old Solo Cup and I'm going to be
using these right from the get-go we're
going to be starting the seeds in these
cups I've gone through them and drilled
holes in the bottom because you always
want to have that good
drainage you have any Nursery pots that
are like that 4 in size the larger size
that you want to use those will work
good as as well so you've seen a lot of
videos The Double Cup method which I
have tried in the past and I understand
you know how it is kind of neat how you
can just water in the bottom put your
cup in here I've done it but I find that
once you get a whole tray of these set
up in that Double Cup method you got
them you know under the lights and when
it comes time to watering it it becomes
very finicky in my opinion you got to
pull each one out lift water you have to
you know make sure you don't overwater
it and drown your plants with too much
water sometimes people put small stones
in there and stuff to try to avoid that
again to me that's a little finicky so
what I've been doing that works great is
I just use the the bottom watering
method make sure you have a tray like
this that's got you know about a 2 or 3
in uh Rim around it so it contains your
cups you know keeps them from falling
off
so as you can see here you can get a lot
of these Solo cups into one of these
trays I'll leave a link to them down
below as to where you can find them on
Amazon something like this that you can
just get from the dollar store one of
these turkey uh Roasters disposable
these work really great for holding a
whole bunch of plants it's got the nice
you know 3 or 4 in edges that'll hold
them in place okay so one of these will
work good as well so the first part of
my method is how you fill up the cup
here and what we're going to do is just
fill it up halfway starting off with
some seed starting mix you want to make
sure you moisten it ahead of time so
that when you put it in here you got
moist soil cuz when it comes time to
bottom water it'll Wick up better if
that soil is moist I've done it with dry
soil and then try to moisten it by
dumping water into the tray and it it
doesn't work very well cuz sometimes the
the seed starting mix is very dry and
Anor robic and it just doesn't absorb
water so make sure you got some
moistened seed starting mix so this is
not potting soil this is seed starting
mix and I'm just going to show you how
I'm setting up one of these it's
actually a little bit early here for me
in Zone 3 Saskatchewan to get my
tomatoes going so for most of us that
are in the cool growing zones like zone
five and down our last frost date will
be early May to miday here in Zone 3 I
like to hold off till the end of May
before I put my tomatoes outside just to
avoid those late spring frosts that we
seem to get a lot of so about 6 to 8
weeks before your last frost a is when
you want to get your Tomatoes going so
there's no benefit in starting them
early you just end up having to look
after them indoors and they become
overgrown and these cups become too
small for them so it's best to keep it
at 6 to 8 weeks before your last frost
date so I am just filling up the cup as
I said halfway with the moistened seed
starting mix make sure you pack it down
pretty good so that it there's no air
pockets in
there so the reason we're only packing
it halfway is we are going to plant our
seeds here put them under the grow
lights let them start uh sprouting I
usually put in two to three seeds so
that we have you know a good chance of
germination and then having to thin them
out to to one plant will become
necessary once they get past that two
Leaf
stage and then you just let them grow in
this cup and as you will see that I'm
going to show you here that you just let
them grow until they start to get above
the rim of the cup so I'm going to show
you
here that I'm just going to be putting
in two or three of these seeds on the
surface of this soil here and once I get
them in place I'll cover them up with a
little more of the seed starting mix and
that's all we're going to do for
now so I put about a/4 inch of soil on
top of those tomato seeds and then added
a light layer of vermiculite that just
helps kind of retain the moisture and
help prevent damping off which is that
green mold and stuff that you sometimes
see on your soil that can kill off your
seedlings so instead of the two cup
method where we're going to be watering
each of these cups individually all the
time I just water right into the tray
here I add a two or three inches of
water and it'll soak it up I find a
little easier to control how much water
your tomatoes are getting with this
method of just pouring it into your tray
directly I'll put you know a couple
inches in there every day or two
whatever it doesn't soak up in an hour
or so I'll pour off just so that I'm not
overwatering them you can also do
spritzing from the top just to keep the
top moist but I try to avoid that until
the tomatoes start sprouting because I
don't want those seeds to become
displaced when I'm spritzing them but
you can use this as well so I just find
over time over that six week period that
you're going to have these tomatoes in
your house and you have to look after
them I just find the watering directly
in to the tray is a lot easier you have
this underneath the lights it's easy to
pull out add a little bit of water push
them back in so this is recommended you
have a grow light or something because
these are going to be down below the
surface here they're not going to get
much sunlight if you have them in a
window so I'd recommend you know a grow
light over top of them for that initial
time where they are sprouting so the
potting up process is a lot simpler
because you're only going to be just
adding more soil to the cup so I just
took this clip from last year so that I
can show you what the potting up method
looks like so this plant is about 4
weeks old and as you can see it has
grown up above the rim of the cup quite
a bit now so what you want to do is just
trim away any of those tiny leaves that
are below the rim of the cup and you
will see that there's a lot of tiny
little hairs on the stem of your tomato
and those once we cover them up with
some soil will turn into Roots so that
will help give us a really strong root
ball so once you've trimmed away any of
those leaves that are below the rim of
the cup we're going to fill it up now to
pretty much the top of the cup with
potting soil so we won't be using any
seed starting mix now we've switched to
potting soil so that there's some food
in that soil and it will help feed that
tomato plant so this is what it looks
like now and it is ready to go back
under the grow lights or by this point
you might have some Sunny windows that
you can put your plants into which is
usually what I do move it out to the
garage or out to your
greenhouse and then here is what the
plants look like at about that four to
six week stage you can see I have some
beautiful strong healthy tomato plants
here and usually in the next couple
weeks they will be ready to go outside
and start hardening off I just want to
show you another closeup here of what a
good root system this cup has and I did
trim a little bit more at the bottom
just to get some more air in there so
that those roots don't become root bound
and that extra layer of soil now that we
filled up the rest of the cup with those
will fill up with roots as well and this
will be a beautiful strong plant ready
to go out to the Garden so that's kind
of the the basics of this method that I
find is a great way to be able to plant
tomatoes in one container and one
container only you still are technically
potting them up and helping them grow I
find the one cup method is a lot less
work and a little faster if you got a
lot of plants you got to water every day
and check on I find just being able to
water right into a large container like
this is much easier and faster and a
little easier to control so depending on
where you live and when your last frost
Aid is I hope that when it's time to
start your tomatoes that you'll give
this method a try I'm very confident
you're going to end up with very strong
healthy tomato plants that when you put
them out in your garden is going to give
you a bountiful amount of tomatoes
during the summer season so please smash
that like button leave me some comments
on how you grow tomatoes I'm always open
to new ideas and see what other people
do and what is successful for you and if
you haven't already done so please hit
the Subscribe button and we will see you
on the next video