my name is Zach buckle and I run a
Halfacre vegetable farm that's projected
to produce $100,000 worth of vegetables
this year and I don't actually like
gardening I used to love it and I still
love certain parts of growing vegetables
but I spend 40 hours of my week growing
vegetables for other people so when it
comes to gardening having a smaller
space SP in my backyard where I get to
grow whatever I want my passion is just
not what it used to be so I don't really
like spending a lot of time watering
weeding planting
seeding doing the
whole romantic aspect of gardening that
people talk
about so because of my lifestyle right
now I try to automate as much as
possible and and spend as little time in
the garden as possible because really
when it comes down to it all I want to
do is eat delicious vegetables that I
grew myself and be around pretty plants
as much as possible I don't want to deal
with all the maintenance and work
involved in creating that
stuff this
season I spent very little time in the
garden basically because I had to spend
very little time in the garden
because I originally planned on turning
this very bad into a food factory to
make all sorts of fun videos
explaining gardening techniques that are
very similar to my farming
techniques uh but the reality is I had
almost no
employees from March through
July um I didn't really get employees on
the farm until about mid July and that's
a whole long story
but I was exhausted just didn't have the
energy to come in here and lift a finger
I even looking at a plant growing was
depressing to me because I had so many
other fires to put out on the farm um
especially any kind of weeds or anything
like that because honestly the weeds in
here are nothing compared to what I was
dealing with on the farm I had literally
whole beds full of dandelions I was
digging out and my back was killing me I
was literally
bedridden uh for days um just because I
was doing all the work myself and that
just kills a lot of your motivation for
doing this kind of
stuff but the cool thing
is I sort of took track of what was
actually in this bed a couple weeks ago
and there's still 36 pounds of food that
came out of this bed and I didn't do
anything my mom came out here and
watered once a week for about 2 hours
using this sprinkler this wobbler
sprinkler and might have pulled a few
weeds here and there but other than that
there's nothing that happened and this
bed's a disaster to be honest there's so
many things that went wrong here I
planted it I spent about 20 minutes
planting it in June and then I just
forgot about it because I just didn't
have time or motivation and so this was
supposed to be filled with carrots right
now and turnips and there's nothing but
all of the stuff that I planted in here
like the scale the broccoli cauliflower
still has a bunch of weight right there
and there's celery and uh green onions
and stuff behind me there's still a
truckload of food there's actually
probably a lot more than 36 pounds in
here and I did a video explaining what I
mean by 36 pounds but I mean I basically
spent an hour of my time this whole
season managing this bed and that's what
happened I think that's a pretty good
result um and that all comes down to the
style of gardening that I teach in my
gardening course Link in the description
on that but
it just actually turned out to be really
cool because it proves how little effort
you need to put into a garden to really
produce a lot of food you just got to
set it up right and use a couple of fun
tools and gadgets that I'm going to go
over in this
video so one of the reasons why I was
able to spend zero time in the garden
and still get a good result was because
my mom was watering every week but if I
didn't have myom
mom this could do the same thing this is
the
raino two Zone automatic water timer
battery operated and this could
basically do the same thing as what my
mom did I just got this thing and I set
it up and I didn't even look at the
manual and I figured out how to use it
in about five minutes which is actually
a big deal because I've
used much fancier water timers on the
Farm I am using much fancier ones on the
farm and it take me about a half an hour
to figure out how to use them because
they're much more complicated watering
schedules and stuff and I had to read
the manual on those this is amazing
because all I had to do is figure out
how all these buttons work and it's real
simple there's two zones you could use
on this um I'm only using one cuz I
don't have drip irrigation set up here
but so this is set up just for our
wobbler sprinkler but I set this
for um 2 hours once a week and it's very
easy to do this um like I said I didn't
even use the manual but you could set it
to uh two different zones so said you
say if you had uh drip tape along
flowers next door you could set those
onto a different time and I'm not going
to go over gory details on how to do
this they have great stuff on their
website um and how to set it up but it's
very easy I mean compared to the one I
use on the farm it is lightyears easier
they actually come with um Teflon tape
to uh make your seal leak proof which is
a big deal I love using Teflon tape on
the farm for all of my Plumbing I pretty
much end up using that more often than
not on all of my fittings because
especially with plastic fittings cuz
plastic fittings generally fail and have
terrible leaking problems so including
teon tape is a big deal um I actually
had to switch to a brass fitting for the
fancy water timer I use on the farm so
it's nice to have that Teflon
tape and uh the bottom line is with this
tool is you can walk away from the farm
for a long time and by Farm I mean your
backyard farm AKA a garden uh I use farm
and garden pretty much interchangeably
um English is a funny language but uh
it's a constantly evolving language but
anyway the cool thing about this is you
could set it and forget it and with all
things like that you know it you you
take that with a grain of Sal you're
still going to need to check the
batteries and stuff all this takes is
two AAA batteries I'm sure you're going
to need to check those every once in a
while but bottom line is you can set it
and forget it and not have to worry
about watering because if I was to hand
waterer this Garden it takes about 20
minutes to a half an hour of my time and
you know my time is pretty valuable
right now in my life if you've got a
family with kids 20 minutes half an hour
a week could be a lot so this saves that
time for you and it does it right the
thing I love about watering with the
sprinkler is when you set up a wobbler
sprinkler like we have in the garden it
Waters so evenly but it takes a long
time you can't do that you know watering
by hand you almost never do it right
because you don't want to sit there for
20 minutes on one plant to make sure
that water seeps in deep in the ground
you know the best way to water is to
water very deeply and infrequently and
so this allows it to happen really
really easily because even when you do
it manually if you do it for two hours
you got to come out here turn it on come
out here and turn it off that's two
times you got to walk out here and if
your garden is you know 300 yards away
from your house that's kind of annoying
and
the easier it is for you to water the
more likely you are to do it and so a
rain
Point water timer like this is a really
simple way to make that happen um it's
something that you got to have in your
garden tool Arsenal is a water timer and
this one's really really simple you can
turn off one zone like I have because I
don't want to use both zones all you got
to do is set it up so you say I this is
Zone one I wanted to select that and I
set it to 1200 a.m. but zero minutes and
that means it won't run at all because I
don't want this to just leak out water
so you can set it up to just run one
length of Hose um which is what I'm
doing and uh but if you wanted to run
two you can and you know like I said
it's super easy to set up I just the the
you just use on off if you want to turn
it off you can just switch it to off and
then if you want just turn it to manual
you could hold this down and say you
were here and you wanted to water for
like a half an hour just to germinate
some stuff in you could hold this down
and set it to 30 minutes and then you
know walk away and then deal with it
tomorrow or something there's all sorts
of cool things you could do with this um
once you get good at watering in general
but uh that will save you time because
even if you think it takes 30 seconds to
come out here and and turn this on
if you're doing that you know more than
twice a week that's something that you
got to check off your list every time uh
you know throughout your week and it
adds a little bit of pressure to your
life you know I have four Farm hydrants
that I'm managing on the farm to keep
all the green houses watered so I love
having water timers because it gives me
peace of mind I don't have to think
about two of them at least you know it
it really saves me a lot of mental
effort and this does the same thing for
your garden so definitely look into it
there's a link in the description where
you can buy these
and I highly recommend you get a water
timer and honestly the number one way
that this thing is going to shine for
you in your garden is if you have drip
irrigation set up that's how I use water
timers on my farm is because I'm
watering things like tomatoes and
cucumbers every single day for a certain
time period and that's where this is
going to shine you do not want to be out
turning a farm hydron once a day for 45
minutes on and off it's going to drive
you crazy and if you are growing a large
amount of tomatoes and cucumbers in your
garden you're probably going to want to
have drip irrigation set up because
those don't like to get their leaves wet
so drip irrigation is a whole rabbit
hole and it it is somewhat complicated
to set up it's not complicated but you
do kind of have to know what you're
doing because there's a lot of water
pressure gallons per minute kind of
stuff to be aware of at least but um I
do go over that in my gardening course
by the way uh but the actual timer is
really going to be a GameChanger for you
because it's going to control um how
much water you put on the ground per day
like for example I'm watering my
tomatoes the it's the end of the season
so I'm watering them very little but I'm
still watering them 4 45 minutes a day
in my greenhouse and I have a water
timer for those and it just saves me a
lot of stress and I could also set it to
go off in the morning like way before I
even get to the farm literally you could
water your garden or your farm while you
sleep and that's sort of a GameChanger
because um you could come out and do all
of the gardening stuff you need to do
and the garden's already watered it
doesn't like you don't have to worry
about getting sprinkled on while you're
working in there that's really not a
problem in a garden but in the farm it
does matter because we have a lot of
work to do in a greenhouse or something
while it's getting watered um so it's
nice to have that checked off the list
before the day even really starts for us
but same thing goes for gardening
everything pretty much likes getting
watered while direct sun is not on it so
it's a big benefit to just have it done
while you're sleeping and having it
automated on a daily basis for those
kinds of crops gives you a much higher
quality cucumber or tomato um most
tomato splitting issues happen because
tomatoes are not getting watered evenly
so they'll get like one inch of water
one day and half an inch the next day
and that's where the splitting will
happen and then same with cucumbers
getting bitter they get bitter usually
because the water's not even so if you
have a way to get that water even on
them and you live in a climate where
there's not a ton of rainfall you could
really take advantage of a of a water
timer like this and it's just going to
save you a lot of a headache and give
you a much higher quality product
basically so gadgets are great and all
and I love gadgets I love tools I use a
lot of them on the farm and in the
garden but they all can fail so I rely
on them all with a grain of salt you
know when I first started
farming I got all excited about the
gadgets because I'm like oh it's going
to make my life so much easier all my
stress is gone it's all automated I
don't have to worry about
anything and then I got
a faucet that automatically shuts off
when the water level gets above a
certain level and it failed like one out
of five times and it turns into a a
flood of water in my wash Pack building
which is not really designed for the
floor to get wet that's happened like 20
times now and that's just one example
all sorts of stuff like this fails
automated vents automated fans tools
break you know um that's why I generally
like using hand tools at on the farm as
much as possible as opposed to big
mechanical tools or gas powered tools
and
stuff but all these things can fail and
so even with a water timer like this no
matter where it's coming from you know
there's moving Parts involved so you
can't
just rely on it forever you know you got
to pay attention to it sometimes these
things they save you a lot of time and
headache C like over time but there are
points where they can fail so you just
got to take into account if this thing
fails is it going to be the end of the
world for you you know probably not uh
like if you if this thing doesn't turn
on or something most likely you're G to
be fine unless you're like germinating a
whole bed of carrots or something uh and
you need it to come on every single day
for 10 days and it fails that's a
problem sure but just take that into
account when you set these kinds of
automations up and tools of any kind
because they all fail you know all farm
tools fail at some point so you can't
just be in that uh naive state of mind
that I was when I first started farming
and assumed it's all going to be fine
and dandy forever you know there's
there's you still need to pay attention
to them and check on them every once in
a while you know so I check the battery
level on my water timers you know once
every couple weeks just to keep an eye
on them you know stuff like scales I
keep the keep an eye on the battery
levels because if something like that
fails for me it's a big deal um on a
farm but for this it's not really that
big a deal but it's just something to be
aware of you know you need to be mindful
of all your tools and maintain them a
little bit but it's easier to maintain a
tool like this than maintaining a
garden watering schedule by hand every
day or doing it by hand or whatever so
um just think of it that way it is
ultimately saving you a ton of time and
headache and making your life easier it
just requires less maintenance but it
still requires maintenance
so if you're interested in setting up a
garden like this where it takes very
little time to manage and can still
produce you the kind of results I talked
about at the beginning of this video
I've got a free Garden starting guide in
the description where I go over how to
set up a garden like this in four simple
steps and give you the Bare
Bones necessary to build a garden like
this cuz it's not hard and it's a free
Microsoft Word document you can download
save it and I have links to some of the
things you'll need to buy to make it
happen and I highly recommend you check
that
out and if you like this video please
subscribe give it a like share with
anybody you think would like it and I
hope you enjoyed it I will see you in
the next