hello my name is Leonor Rodriguez I am a
professor of Technical University of
Madrid and today I will be introducing a
little bit the elements for the D
irrigation systems what do you need to
know
when designing re Iration system in an
ecological Orchard organic Orchard the
orchard that we be on belongs to the
Technical University of Madrid and the
faculty of the
engineer agricultural engineering school
and we will see here the different
elements that the
systems need
to be aware of their characteristics and
they function it first things you need
to think of is about where the water is
how the water will be conveying to the
different small Orchards and if we are
talking about this irrigation systems
you need to know that water will move
along
the circular pipe as this one and the
whole section will be filling with water
that means that pressure along the pie
will be higher than atmospheric pressure
Now we move on to see where the water
comes out in this particular or water
comes to this point from the central
water uh company of Madrid it's called
Canal Isel sea this Lo in a special
places afterwards there is various
underneath the soil the different pipe
and it comes out in this point you will
see here this is
a hyraulic
Val this this one over here this is open
or close bar that goes forward to
connect
another five B of different material
this one is fibro cemento and the other
one is polyethylen the diameter of this
material is 40 mm and it comes along to
the whole
length of the F showing the
pressure at this
point but in this case it is connected
with a pressure regulator what do we
mean a pressure regulator here the
pressure of this pip could be as high as
17 and water M col so that is too high
for uh Bri Iration system so in that
case if we need a very high pressure
more than 20 or 30 H water met colum we
will need to use that pressure regulat
device in the point where the
distribution pi ends afterwards we'll
continue to
the head or the tail of the
different areas from the small Bri
irrigation system on this aricultural
oras and that five will be the same
diameter and the same material that's
this one you see over here this is also
bared let's move to see which are the
typical elements for adri irrigation
systems but first of all let me reminded
how much water you need to apply B
irrigation system how to calculate the
water requirements or each plants in
different Orchards it will depend on
variables such as climb precipitation
solar radiation wind soil structure
texture organic
matter and the
physiological behavior of each crop
there are public programs to calculate
this CLW requirements such as the crossw
by file that everyone can take Link into
those H specifical web download the
program and calculate the water
requirements for each gr and and each
location we know that information what
should we do what should we do next next
is decide which type of irrigation
system we need for our organic torture
like that we need a very efficient
irrigation systems if we think of the
barriers type of irrigations method
where we think of the surface irrigation
method is really too complicate nowadays
you can do it we can think of the splink
regation method but uh for that
Horticultural C is not worth it since we
have a many a evaporation losses and we
also need a very high pressure so the
best irrigation methods should be th
irrigation methods this Iration method
it also has the advantage doesn't
be affected by wind so in the specifical
locations where the wind is could be a
problem that's the the method to go and
the efficiencies really very very high
is the the management of the system is
well organized
this so what are the
typical elements forre irrigation system
they are the drippers these are
different type of drippers that's this
online emitter emitter and they had the
advantage in case you will need several
dischs you can't do it with this small
tube we have a inal line emitters means
that the path is cuted both ends and
inserted within the emitter
and the
most typical models are the integrated
model like that all of them have in
common our Labyrinth structure as you
can see here you will see that this a
Laing with um protu and different angles
what does this is required for as we
think of the three Iration system is a
localizing system that mean water
deserts drop by drop near the plant and
the pipe has a pressure over the
atmospheric pressure that's mean over
One bars we need an element to L to drop
off all pressure that means to keep it
close to atmospheric pressure what are
these elements usually the Labyrinth
so the water comes into this lence moves
along and then the discharge from the
different Outlet usually one or two
houret and when it is discharged this is
atmospheric pressure so that means that
water uh can't like it it it wear a drop
you can also try a home if you have a
pile like this by pressure try to punch
it a small hole you will see that there
is a jet free jet coming out that
doesn't mean
that even though you have the same
diameter outl from the meter this H the
meters and the one in the PIP you won't
see the same effect this is UN localized
because the labyrint and this is not
localized this a typical FL we
observe that uh
you have a really tiny SE no more than 2
mm between 1 and 2 mm there so this is
one of the disadvantage of this system
you have to be aware that water is
doesn't
carry a small minerals with this so a
small organic matter that can PL those
section that means that emit with the
plug it and the discharge will be lower
than expected in order to avoid that
disadvantage you have
to
add to the system a filter the most
typical system for this irrigation
system is the dick filters this is a
very fine disc press it together water
comes from the outer part and the all
the material
that this coning with the water stay in
the greenest part of the of the this and
the clean water can to the inner part
and move to the irrigation
units well we know the elements and now
a question to answer is what should be
the optimum this chart for the meter
well you can have in the market from 1 L
per hour till 8 to 10 L per hour so this
is a a wi interval range what you
say when we are dealing with pressure
don't forget to leave a pressure G like
that at the beginning of the irrigation
unit that's the typical if this is liid
and you can
go there so it's time what the pressure
is otherwise you want to do that yes a l
a pressure button over there and go with
a digital manometer like this Sy time
you want and going with this element
that is connected to the digital
monometer punch it into the bottom
outlet and measure the pressure
finally we need a volume meter like that
that's the Walmart volume meter it can
be used for progamming the
irrigation or yes simple to pay the bill
of water that will canalot everyone or
two mon for this irrigation system we
have to an integrated model no
compensating 2.2 L per hour this is the
a design of the meter that
goes inside the
pipe now let's move to the orchin and
see how the irrigation unit
is as you remember this was the point
with the pressure Reg
and the pressure gut to know which is
the regulator the pressure at this time
and and in at every moment remember this
system has a pressure over
40 water colon meter even 60 water colon
meter because it comes to
the general
water networking from the city of M you
wouldn't have this pressure and that's
probably you may have in in in
feel located at the Summers of the big
cities you probably will have to install
a little pond at
the beginning of the whole system in
this case we don't need it we we need
the contrary we need to to drop off some
energy because the the the pressure is
really high and then it will just we
keep it there let's say between one and
two bars we move with the same diameter
for p 4 mm and we need to think of the
best design for this CH and this
Orchards first you have to make all the
L settles for the plants that's the
first thing you need to be decided once
this is done the Iration system needs to
cover all the water Closs water
requirements for that
needs what should be the best designs
for this specific case we have try and
calculate different options and the best
we found in terms of Energy savings is
the one that takes the
same
P for water
distribution all along to the middle
area between this small clots and the
left and right clots that go in the
middle to the middle cor of the
here and from here is a split with two
Tes on two
different
containers each
containers will
dgate four different
blocks so we have one container inting
this four
blocks
behind this other
container will
irrigate this other four
clock and finally this is a symmetry
just think of in the v solution taking
into account symmetry as much as
possible according to the Topography of
the field and this last two the the the
lateral with move the final P will be
this one here and there is a coat elbows
that moves one to the left one to the
right and from here they will distribute
water from these four blocks and behind
from the other four blocks so once we
have
the p 40 mm SP here we need to change
diameters
usually for the
tertiary Pi this is this one 25 mm and
from the tertiary Pi we have the Cherry
pip that goes very close to the
blocks we'll move
to
the end of the plot down end of the plot
and in the middle part
we rise a little bit with a different
diameter polyethylen P this is usually
from 12 mm to 16 and we have an open and
close B to open and close the water
so each
container
will get water
for every four plots but you have to be
aware that water comes from the start
point that means that you have unlimited
water so in order to make a right
programing to irrigate simultaneously
one two three or four flock or even more
you won't have to surpass the quantity
of water delivered by the a start point
you can irrigate
simultaneously with as many units
as Water
Supplies we see here in the container
two different elements that um may be
very useful for this types of irrigation
one is
the electro
valve for irrigation programming this
types of program me is by time you said
that the time of
irrigation this is the open BX for here
this valve open and the irrigation will
go on to the different sub genit and we
have also in that case this element this
is a pressure reductor we say that at
the beginning it was a regulator
pressure that was
H setup to
2.2 bars and this
one
reduce the pressure at that point to 1.1
so that means that water that comes
along this
tary
pip will have no more than
1.2 bars the the other
element
beond
the electr and the pressure reactors is
the
volumeter
meter so it will lock all the volume of
water us it in its irrigation afterwards
we move along we
have the open and closed wall we saw
before and this is our small irrigation
unit it is compon of the tertiary
p and four laterals in that
case the distribution water is in the
middle we could have Chen other
designed taking the distribution of
water either in one side on the other
what will be the advantage
or Distributing the water that way means
that the pressure is more
compensated in both ends so we have the
laterals the laterals goes from one end
to the downstream
end
the emit expansions are choing according
to the CR physiological requirements the
cross planting in this case is 30 cm
apart for a typical D Rion units at the
end of its lateral we have a plaque to
stop the water running but in the skates
we have a non
branched design that means that the end
of the lateral are connected to
another part that means that water
moving from the upper stream going to
the down stream will move downwards and
can go to
reverse we attend with this Ty of design
that the pressure variability is you
know as higher so that will mean that we
have a more water distribution
uniformity and more
efficiency
so finally we don't need to forget what
is the pressure of each irrigation unit
so that means that we need a point where
we should
with the pressure it that case we are
using the pressure
button and will be locating in a
uni
pip that case how can we do that we to
use the puncher is that here we can buy
the puncher in
it small store gardening store or
supermarket and
we open a hole we
inserted
and this is a measure
meter the volume meter is also a meter
so don't forget for every meter located
in a
uniform pip otherwise the reading you
will be taking will be
outrange you never know this is will be
lower or higher than this should
be I hope you can enjoy this brief
explanation and probably you can try
doing yourself in your bget thank you
for
l