i'm gonna host welcome everybody
uh this is the last of six uh seminars
that we've organized as part of a
webinar series on targeting
and community networks and anti-poverty
programs
and we're very happy to have uh marcel
fashion give the last seminar
um marcel was the
first person to teach me about
development economics
way back when at stanford in graduate
school
so it's always great to see him and he's
going to share some of his work on
mobilizing p2p diffusion in bangladesh
marcel it's all yours
thanks a lot well it's a great pleasure
to to be uh
to be uh talking to you guys
um this is work with uh
joint work with assad islam who i
believe is uh attending
abdul malek who also said he would be
attending and devayan pakrashi
um and it's a second paper we've uh done
together about uh basically about how to
um
to promote the diffusion of agricultural
technology and focusing on a specific
technology called
systems of rice
intensification sri
which has
[Music]
the advantage and drawback that it
doesn't
include
it doesn't require additional input so
it's an advantage for for for also
because you don't run into issues of uh
people having liquidity constraints or
things like that
um
but then
the downside is that it's actually a
difficult technology to master and so
people uh the difficulty with this
technology is um
how to to train
farmers in applying it
okay
and so
of course you could try to train all the
potential beneficiaries or put because
you know if you don't know who's going
to benefit from it you can try to train
everybody
but that's obviously going to be costly
and so with brac we've been trying to
break in bangladesh we've been trying to
find ways of
of targeting
many beneficiaries if you want the
farmers who would benefit from this
innovation
of targeting them better the first the
first article we wrote about that which
we tried to get
we trained some farmers and then we
asked them to recommend to refer
basically
um
all the farmers they thought would
benefit from the from the training so
that was the first step we did
that kind of worked and
it didn't really work like the way we
were expecting we were expecting the
the referred
trainees to be
adopting you know to be better adopters
basically we
basically better targeted
and that's that's not really what we
found
so this time we tried another approach
which is um
you know has a long history in
agricultural extension which is is
basically based on the idea of a model
farmer
uh but we try to improve it basically so
but if you remember the model farmer the
extension agent comes to the village and
says i can't i can't you know teach
everybody so i'm going to uh to select
some
farmers who i believe are
role models for others
who are also more receptive to
innovation and i'm going to train them
and then
i'm going to hope that
this will then naturally
diffuse
through an unspecified process through
the the local population okay i'm sure
they are more more more structured ways
of doing it but
that's kind of a a rough
characterization of what the model
farmer approaches
and um so what we try to do here is
we're going to try to we're going to
start from that
and um but instead of hoping that these
these model farmers
um
you know do viral marketing basically
they basically become
your your champions your marketing
agents for your for your for your
innovation
uh we're gonna actually ask them
to train two farmers we're gonna assign
them these two farmers when we say okay
you know you're gonna train
jack and jill
these are the two the two trainees were
assigned to you and there you go you
know
um
[Music]
try to do a good job of it so that's the
that's the basic idea that we have our
intervention is basically
taking
trainees people who have received this
one day
course on uh
on sri from brac
and we're gonna
assign them
to
other uh farmers
who could have been trainees could have
been black trainees uh but we're going
to say well what do we can we go can we
what what fraction of
the effect of brac training can we
achieve by asking this these trainees to
themselves teach other farmers that's
that that's the logic so each each of
the so we call them teacher trainees
sometimes they call them teachers for
short but obviously they are not school
teachers they just
asked to teach other other farmers in
our experiment
can i ask a clarificatory question
please
so how much uh experience do these
teacher trainees have with the
technology before they're expected to
train others no
they don't have any
ex experience with the technology
so you set the experience so they have
been they received a one-day
training
from black
and then they are asked to you know can
you teach the the
the instruction list that you you have
been
[Music]
you know told and
to talk about
uh to these two other people
and people take a quiz
and so basically we're going to be we're
going to be comparing adoption between
teacher trainees and trainees and of
course we also have control farmers who
didn't receive any training we have
control farmers in the
treated villages where some people
receive the training we also have
control of uh farmers in villages where
there was no training whatsoever
so i'll talk about that in detail in a
minute but that's the that's the way
we're going to try to see whether
um
whether this model uh transfers
knowledge so we're going to quiz the the
trainees the teacher trainees
at the end on what they're supposed to
be learning
and we're going to teach the
the students of these uh teacher
trainees who did not receive the brag
training i'm going to quiz them about
about their knowledge as well and then
we're going to see whether they have you
know
we we also have uh we know that uh the
the average farmer who has not been
trained does not know what sri is in
this particular part of the world so
it's not it's not like they would not
naturally know what it is and then we
also look at adoption um of the
recommended practices later on
and we which is measured by brac and
then we also um
have a deadline survey where we measure
uh agricultural outcomes like profits
and yields
so that's the that's the basic idea i'll
go through the to the intervention more
detail in a minute
um
there are some villages we incentivize
the teachers to
basically we thought maybe if we
incentivize them they would do a better
job so they are incentivized to teach
um
to the test
so basically they they've already taken
a test and they're told well you will
test your students uh using the same
quiz
and then we'll we'll give you an
incentive if they answer the quiz
questions well
so that's basically testing whether they
can
they can convey these key information
about sri to their to their students
and uh we hope that that knowledge and
translates into into a higher adoption
adoption
and then you know from the model farmer
idea this modern farmer idea
so remember the the key idea of that
model was that this person was a role
model for the farmers and therefore the
other farmers would want to copy him or
her
so we thought well maybe we can emulate
that as well i mean here
so the way we did that
is that we ask in baseline we ask each
of the farmers in our sample
to
list at most five other farmers in in in
the list we given them
whom they would regard as as role models
basically
whom they would basically
whom they would consider as sources of
valuable information for for
agricultural technology so that's the
that's the idea
and um
and then basically in a way i'll explain
where we
you know remember each teacher trainee
gets two students assigned to him
they're all male
um
so
and one of them is going to be someone
who has
who has nominated that farmer as a role
model who has listed him as a role model
and the other one is someone who is not
normally anything as a role model so
that's the idea
and the idea is
based on this
smaller farmer idea is that it's a role
model therefore it's going to work
better
in terms of diffusing the innovation
from teacher trainees to those farmers
that nominated them to those farmers
that regard them regarding teacher
training as a role model so that's the
that's the key idea
um and and this is done through an
algorithm i'll describe in a minute so
that's the basic idea of what we do
um
in terms of and i'll explain that the
experiment more detail obviously
in terms of just to remind i'm sure some
of you already know what uh this system
perhaps even better than i do what the
system of rising intensification is
but my understanding of it is basically
it's a set of different practices that
have to do with transplanting the way
you do the transplanting the data
transplanting and especially things like
spacing thinning and
the way you water the plant the
regularity of the water in the plant and
so on
so this is
space they have to be
basically spaced
further apart from each other and and
there's going to be more thinning that
what farmers would normally do and as a
result these these
single plants that survive grow bigger
and they get they get more grain so
that's that's the logic of sri as far as
i understand it
now you can see there's no
you know these are all practices there's
no um
inputs required so there's no there's no
purchased inputs i mean uh that are
related to adoption of sri
so that that means several things um it
means things that
if it was a fertilizer or a new seed or
a new pesticide or something farmers
could in principle go to the to the
seller of this input and
ask them you know what should i use on
my rice how should i use it how should i
apply or when
there's no such thing here so we don't
have to worry about contamination of our
sample by some external agent who comes
and gives them
information about this technology okay
so that simplifies our work it's it
makes uh eliminate it reduces
contamination from external uh actors or
vendors in this case
um
it also means that you don't you don't
have to worry about externalities
through input markets i mean if you if
you introduce a new uh and use a new
fertilizer let's say
and uh
there's a whole value chain has to bring
this fertilizer to the villages
and only you know nobody only you are
the only one who wants to buy it you
know chances are you're not going to
find it because the
the traders are not going to find it
useful to bring the fertilizer to the
village just in the off chance that you
might buy
this one bag of fertilizer so they it's
so they're going to be networking
externalities in the sense that you know
the more people are buying it the more
it will make sense for
um sellers of agricultural inputs to
stock it and therefore you would have
and you will have more information and
the other farmers will have more
information so you get into this kind of
system of externality so we don't have
to work that the problem with that is
that that would break sudvas so
so i mean we're already looking at
diffusion which is something that's very
already by name by nature kind of breaks
breaks and subverts somewhat
so we we we don't want more to have to
worry about more violations on server
uh that we have to
could there be an effect on the quantity
of inputs that they purchased i'm
wondering if you have to space out yeah
you will look at that but we're not
introducing any new inputs yeah
but we'll look at that yeah
um
the the main thing though is it's it's i
would
people sometimes describe this
technology as more labor-intensive it's
it seems like we just because the
farmers have to go and visit the field
sometimes more often but really it's
more management incentives intensive
they have to be more careful and they
have to also change
the way they were doing things but they
would they have to measure they have to
count how
to thin properly and so on so they it's
a little bit more scientific
and so as a result it's a bit more
demanding in terms of attention and care
and and a bit harder for the farmer to
delegate
so uh that's the sense in which it's
more demanding on the farmer
so that's the idea
so but these things again means that if
it's it's about management it's not
something that will diffuse naturally
through observation you can't just copy
people oh he has a new iphone i'm going
to have it on your iphone
you can't just copy people's behavior
just by by observing what they're doing
so you have to really be taught how to
do it
so that's the that's the idea uh of this
there's going to be some diffusion
happening and naturally of course people
will talk
but it will come
you know the hope is that it all comes
from
from the training that uh uh brag does
and then the way that this diffuses then
to students and perhaps then eventually
to some other people in the village and
as we will see later there's very good
command contamination across villages so
which again confirming that people don't
seem to know this technology before
[Music]
now
i'm not going to spend too much on this
slide but but there's there's obviously
a very large approach on diffusion of
innovation here i've picked a few uh
papers that uh
that are more in the development
economics literature reasonably recent
papers
um so that but it is of course a much
larger literature behind it
uh including of course in marketing
uh because you know diffusion of new
products these are innovations so
there's there's going to be some some
lit the larger on that
and basically the base the basic the
main message of the signature is that
sri is not for everyone
you you need to be
a dedicated farmer to benefit from it if
you're not um
up to snuff let's say if you're just
like uh
somebody who does it because they can't
earn an income from
something else you might not naturally
benefit from it because it's actually
demanding in terms of of understanding
what's going on in the field
so that that's the sense in which
it's not a technology that we expect to
benefit everyone and therefore it's a
technology for which targeting is
important you know you have to be able
to i think you want to economize uh on
the cost of training by focusing your
training on people who will benefit from
it so that's the idea
um of course there is also a larger
picture on p2p transmission which is
what we are trying to uh achieve here
and of course more generally on the role
of social products proximity in in viral
marketing so i'm not gonna you know
these are just a hand just a
very small number of papers been citing
here
so let me if
if there are no more questions about the
no questions about the
setup the context
i can
delve into the immunity delve into the
experimental design as i said it's with
brac
um we've selected a hundred villages uh
from these two districts uh rank poor
and bagura in uh bangladesh um
and
the way that brac works um
as far as sri is concerned they go to
these
when they arrive in a village they start
by
identifying
or 30 potential sri adopters and these
are people who obviously have to grow
rice otherwise there's no point
and
they have to they have to be
large enough
in other words
more than one decimal
i forgot exactly it's in the paper but
the lower limit but they're trying to
find these intermediate farmers who have
enough
uh uh
land that they grow to to to signal that
they're actually farmers not just uh
gardeners if you want
and they also not too big okay so they
kind of
live in this intermediate uh
size so they kind of uh generally poor
people but they are a little bit uh more
focused on rise than than some of the
very small ones
um
and if the village is too big and they
have more than 30 and basically what
they
would end up doing
um
not necessarily here but what they would
end up doing is kind of to say this two
groups of 30 and then there was like one
in the eastern part of the village one
of the western part of the village
because you know it's a densely
populated country so you you get uh
sometimes you get large villages so they
would do that so basically they
and that's that's how they proceed
um in their sri
training campaign so we we wanted to to
kind of and we didn't want to change
that because we wanted to be policy
relevant we wanted whatever we whatever
we introduced whether we
find we wanted this to be
immediately you could slaughter into the
normal strategy the mobile practices
of brac
in the country so that was the idea
um
and also we you know because they're not
stupid they they they also want to save
on uh the economize on on on
train waste wasting training time
on on people who never adopt we hope
that
through that system we the 30 farmers
they identify are probably farmers
among whom the property sales option is
higher it's not 100 by any means but
it's it's it's higher so that's the idea
so basically uh
let's focus on those people um
and we're going to be looking at
diffusion be among that group
we start with the baseline questionnaire
on the household composition in
pharmaceutics it's a fairly light
baseline
and then we assign 60 villages to
treatment and the 40 remaining ones to
control
in control there is no
sri brak intervention
and then in the treated villages um a
selected number of teacher trainees uh
farmers
uh receive one day training in sri okay
and uh
of the 60 villages selected for
treatment there's 30 that are also
assigned to an incentivized teacher
treatment assist
a treatment whereby the teacher trained
trainee
um is is gaining a compensation for
training students that depend on their
performance in the quiz
while in the other 30 villages
the teacher trainee receives a fixed uh
compensation per per student relates to
logic
and if you look at the
more precisely what is the how does this
compensation uh constructed
well they get a fixed
fee if you want a participation fee of
uh for 300 taka or four dollars
and then in the incident device
treatment they get 250 taka additional
per student at the end of the teaching
week
and then another uh they get they are
given a week to train them because
i'm expecting them to be training them
uh every day all the time but
you know you have to give them some time
for them to meet them
so that's the logic of it
and you don't wait too long so there's
no point um and then the incident
question
yeah yeah how are the people how are the
teacher training selected
i i'm getting to that it's the next okay
get into that right right away
anyway so that's the easy part
explaining the this kind of uh
incentives is basically you get a fixed
amount and then you you lose something
every time the
the the your student uh
answers the quiz wrongly
um so now let's let's talk about the
assignment rule um
so as i explained earlier in the
baseline in the treated villages each
farmer nominates up to five as role
models with the opinion leaders over our
models
and then
we have these 30 farmers and then we we
have to assign them into to four
different roles basically
some are going to be teachers they're
going to receive the training
some are going to be
receiving nothing at all they're going
to be the non-students they're going to
be
going to be able to look at
if you want
and
an incentivized unorganized diffusion
and then we're going to have the
students and there are two types of
students the students who nominated so
remember there are two students for a
teacher trainee one
who nominated a teacher trainee as a
opinion leader a role model and one who
did not nominate that particular teacher
training so that's how it's uh so they
have to be assigned to these four groups
how do we do this
so
we start by picking
uh six teacher trainees so those are
going to receive the black training
and um
this we did um
by dividing so remember once we get the
five nominations per nominating farmer
per per each of the 30 farmers we can
look at who they nominate
right so
maybe all of them nominate albert so
then you know albert will be nominated
by you know it will have 29 nominations
and then uh you know maybe dilip is
going to have 28 or something so you you
get a sense of and then some people will
have none
so basically we basically divide the
the the 30 farmers into those that
received uh above the median number of
nominations and those that receive less
than the median number of nominations
that's the and then among the
those that are above the median we
select four teacher trainees
and the others we select two digit
training so this is basically stratified
sampling
right we had a variable where we
collected ourselves
it's known to us
we do sampling
is stratified
okay so they don't they don't have the
same
based on their observable
characteristics as baseline they get
slightly different probabilities
of being assigned to a particular
treatment
okay
so we'll have to correct for that when
we
in a minute because that that that that
stratified sampling which is
not pure randomization
now what about the other 24 farmers so
then we have assigned these six people
at random
the way they are explained so you're
left with 24 farmers we know we want 12
students
and 12 non-students
and then we want six students who are
matched with a teacher that they
nominated and six students who are
matched with somebody that did not
dominate so how do we do this well we do
this using an algorithm this algorithm
is a mechanistic so it just basically
you can think of the of the algorithm as
um
you start by randomizing all the farm
the 30 farmers in the village
then
you you know based on that
reshuffling of the farmers you picked
the four the first four
who are above the median in terms of
nomination and the first two who are
above the median
uh below the median in terms of
nomination these are going to be the
teacher trainings so now that you have
the teacher trainings you start looking
among the the the 24 farmers for farmers
who nominated them farmers who did not
dominate them and so
and you go through the list
you go through the list of farmers
in the order they've been shuffled
until you finally
allocate everybody
so the the order in which they've been
shuffled will determine
the order in which they are considered
by the algorithm to be assigned to a
teacher or not
does it make sense
so that means
marcel it seems still seems like it's
not going to be very random if
for each of the
teachers you have to find one student
who nominated them because maybe for
some of the teachers there was only one
or two students who nominated him right
if i'm understanding the algorithm
correctly yeah yeah but that's enough
that's okay
that's okay yeah i don't think there is
a village where we we had the problem of
uh of selecting
uh a teacher who was nominated by nobody
i don't think it happened because this
is an issue that we raised at the
beginning but this didn't occur
okay so you always find
they be nominated by at least one person
uh one other question i mean when they
are asked to nominate somebody as a role
model
are they you know one criterion could be
who who do you think is going to be the
most successful in adopting the
technology
himself
the other is who is going to be the best
teacher
and those two need not be the same
sure so what what is your understanding
of what you know what they think
of when they say role model
um well i mean
you will see it actually this has no
effect
okay so we we can talk about what they
meant maybe they didn't mean anything
it's possible um
but
the wording was
basically whom would you be look i mean
the word the wording is not in
it is phrased in terms of agricultural
technology
so who who would you be going to for
information about the new agricultural
technology that's the basic idea
now it may be that they they just go to
their neighbor
so it may be that this person is not
particularly
knowledgeable about it
but that's that's that was the intention
the intention was to identify someone
who was perceived as a as a more
at least by by the student farmers by
perceived as someone who would be more
authoritative that was the the intention
and so the idea was that if he's more
arthritic of you
you probably would will listen more to
what he says we might do better on the
quiz
and you might also um
follow this person's example more
therefore and therefore um
if they adopt you might adopt it uh
adopt as well in fact we're going to be
testing for those things in the in the
paper
but before i go to that
to the the more substantive issues of
the paper which i actually where the
interesting stuff is
i need to be
i need to basically address this issue
of um
weights i mean clearly this algorithm
um generates different probabilities of
being assigned to one of the four
treatments for each of the 30 farmers
and um
and so you might think well wait a
minute i mean i know how to deal with
this problem if it if it's stratified
sampling because it's stratified
sampling i just look at the
stratification ratio that i use and i
correct for that using weights
but here you say well wait a minute i
don't i don't know it's just the
algorithm it's a black box what but the
thing is that the algorithm you can
reproduce it that means me as many times
as you want you can reshuffle the
farmers rate again use your philosophy
again right again right again wait 500
times look at how you know of these 500
times how many times does albert gets
assigned to be a teacher and how much
does marcel get assigned to be a teacher
and that
that becomes your probability of
assignment
right the problem is going to be if
there is somebody who's always assigned
to be a teacher somebody who's never
assigned to be a teacher then you you
think well wait a minute those people i
can't compare because they uh you know
they basically i don't have people who
are
um
so i i would look at that i'll have to
check that this is not the case because
those people then would have to be taken
out because they they never they have
zero chance of uh the account
constructor you can't construct a
uh a
sampling weight for that
right it's infinite basically
or zero
so that's uh well i'll get back to 90
minutes but that's the that's the id but
the main the main
the main thing here is that
it's going to rule the rule-based
deterministic aspect given a certain
ordering of farmers
in
reshuffling of farmers and it follows a
rule so it's and this rule is entirely
based on
things that we observe at baseline just
like if you were doing
stratified sampling you have some kind
of baseline information on the people
and then you're going to organize your
sampling based on that
so it's not it's not about selection on
observables
they're going to be things that are
correlated with these observables for
sure but uh
but uh we
that's why we need to correct for uh for
sampling weights but
so that's the idea
um so as i said we've got
four types of treated farmers
um two types of treated villages
incentivized teacher and non-study vice
teacher we only have one type of control
farmers
and basically what we'll do is we
compare say teacher trainees to control
farmers or teacher trainees to
non-students or
um
and so so that's the that's what we're
going to be doing
so let's talk a little bit more about
this assignment treatment type
fine
so remember
this assignment treatment is under our
full control there's no there's no
self-selection whatsoever we assign them
is based on observables which we have at
baseline
and uh it's it's it's based on an
algorithm which we can replica use to
replicate
many times the the the
the assignment process so that's the key
so basically we can we based on that we
can as i have explained we can
reconstruct
what the what the probability of being
assigned to the to each of the four
treatments
uh would be for any particular in fact
for any individual in the sample we can
do this individual by individual
okay
and so that way we can recover the
probabilities so let me show you just
how it works in practice
so let's say you have two populations
untreated
and the control
the the normal way of measuring the
average treatment effect would be just
to look at the mean of the treatment and
the mean of the control if they have
been randomly assigned to it
and if there's it's there's no
ratification whatsoever you just take
the sample mean okay
now in our case we can't do the sample
mean we're gonna for the for the for the
for the so this is this is people
assigned to a specific treatment
so we're going to to basically use
inverse probability weighting so that's
that's something you already know so
you know we we
this is the pro this is the
the probability that somebody would be
assigned to this particular treatment
we normalize this by case or which is
the sum of these uh
pi so that
you want to normalize because you want
this thing that is saying the
probabilities is one for everybody in a
particular
unit you want this thing to be one over
one
right so that cancels out and you you
back to the standard uh mean
everybody
i had a question i mean this all makes
sense to me but if you're going to
re-weight to try to make it in some
sense representative then why didn't you
just randomize at the beginning
and then you don't have to deal with the
weights i'm just curious about you know
the decision to stratify in this way and
then to re-weight it back to the random
representativeness no but
no but the uh no
that is uh
why do you stratify a sample in
any any you know when you ever solidify
a sample
it's because you want to be able to
compare to populations in this case we
wanted to compare nominating and
non-nominating we wanted to compare
uh teacher and the other so we wanted to
be um
and the big the big challenge was
nominating and non-nominating because we
didn't control who's nominating who so
basically that's the that's the way we
uh
we ended up approaching it right but the
cost is you get a higher variance and i
mean the greater variance in the weights
reduces power in some sense right so
yeah but i can see the trade-off right
no i just i agree with that yeah i agree
with that but we we've been having
enough power so
so my interpretation is that you
wanted to try to understand the
mechanisms as well
and
if you're trying to think about
mechanisms
i mean what i would be inclined to do is
to well there's obviously heterogeneity
let's say that people vary in
skill
which and there's just essentially one
kind of skill
you know
you're better role model
or not
and there's information about your skill
that's in the in the population
so you ask people
and uh
you know to nominate people so you try
to elicit community information about
skill
but you've got that fundamental
heterogeneity and there could be a
second order of heterogeneity which is
that the effectiveness of
you as a teacher also depends on the
skill of the student
so it could be math specific
so what you want to do is estimate
you know for any pair of skills for the
teacher and the student you know how
effective is the transmission of
diffusion going to be so that's what
you're going to try and back out
uh then uh you know i presume that this
this design will get at that
uh because you've randomized and then
you've got a third dimension of
randomization which is
the uh
the incentives for the the teacher
yeah
that would have rationalized the design
and and all the effects that you want to
isolate i imagine that that's at the
back of your mind
yeah it's at the back of the mind i i
didn't for this paper we didn't we
didn't write a model
i i confess we didn't write a model no
we just focused on the
i yeah we just didn't do it for this
paper
um
and maybe i should have added i mean
there's some discussion of that in the
in the paper maybe i should have added
some slides about that but i thought i
was just going to talk talk you into it
as i was going i was presenting the
different pieces of evidence i have
um
but you're right so so you raised
several points here so there's one i
remember which is the
what about much specific
gain
so remember
maybe you maybe you saw the paper i
wrote with demo about that these are
kids who are assigned to to do a course
a math course with one other kid in a
chinese school
and so there we actually looked as at to
at the math specific game
but then they it was easier much easier
because everybody was in pairs they were
just assigned randomly by design
to another person
there was no there was no need for a
matching algorithm like this like we did
here which is basically randomized
matching and so there we could see
whether you know if a
less abled kid kids match with their
more able kid whether
whether the the less able kid
learns more it turns out they do
actually and the the more able kid
doesn't seem to
learn less so so that was actually a
good a good result for that
um
so that's an example of uh uh of lo so i
know but here we go we're just gonna be
looking at the average so i'm not i
don't i don't i don't ambition to
identify pay white because i don't have
a as you you're right i don't have very
good um
identification there
so i i don't want to make any any
statements about that it's not that i
don't think it's important it's just
just that i i don't think i'm very i'm a
very strong
terrain there
so i'd rather
avoid seeing that
um
i suspect you the way you stratified you
have the identification but you may be
not be having enough power i i don't
know about that
but we'll see about power i i think
we have power and we actually um
cluster standard errors at the village
level so we we have a hundred villages
so it's fine so i mean it's not like
we've been very uh
conservative i mean you know
that's not not for the average treatment
effect but for the the heterogeneous
treatment effects
we don't have heterogeneous treatment
effects i know i know if you did if you
did what i was suggesting write down a
model and try to identify the
heterogeneous treatment effects to
understand the mechanism you may be
underpowered to estimate the
heterogeneous treatment effects oh yeah
yeah yeah so i understand okay but
you're mainly talking about power for
the average treatment effect which is
fine yes
yeah that's good that's true that's very
true
um
okay so i've explained this
you can also using you the same once you
since you
recalibrate
these means
to be representative of the control
village population
you can also compare them to each other
so once you have recalibrated them you
should compare them so you can compare
one group of treated with them to
another group of treated
um i've already explained this i mean
the easiest way to explain how you
recover the priorities the easiest way
to uh to understand it is that
if you think that each person is a
different x vector so then you you would
uh you know run a bunch of simulations i
think we've run 500 simulations
so you would run um let's say first
simulation
dilip gets assigned to be
a teacher
and so therefore it's one
zero zero zero so that's one sample
and then in another sum in another
simulation it gets assigned to be a
nominating student so he's here and then
he's there
okay
really do this for other times some of
them get frequencies frequency how often
does dilip get to be a teacher you know
maybe a lot of times so therefore he's
going to be
you know he's over represented if you
want in the in the teacher population so
we're going to want to
weigh his
to re-weight the teacher population so
that he gets less weight that's the
that's the idea
so that's how this is done here
all right
now the thing you have to worry if you
do that the thing
you have to worry is that people who
never get assigned to a particular
role because then
then as i said they they basically um
don't have a kind of
comparable person
so so this is not what we get so these
are basically the these uh these
normalized
probabilities
that the weights that we are using
and
the sum and and so you know they are of
course centered on one
which is the mean
and
it doesn't even reach 0.5 and it doesn't
go
it you know the couple observations
above couple people above uh above two
but very few so basically
the the range of values of these of
these weights
is not crazy it stays within a
relatively narrow range and so that
means that um
the rewaiting we are doing is not is not
is not insane okay so it's not like
one person is 99 of the time
always a teacher and then you you take
his inverse sampling where he's going to
be one
over 99 and so it's going you know it's
going to be so
it's going to be very large
no it would be it would be a 99 over one
so
it would be very small okay anyway so
the
so that you you want to look to whether
you have very large value very loose one
value so you don't have that so that's
actually quite uh quite encouraging
balance there are lots of tables about
balance in the in the paper they are
only the appendix um balance across the
different types of treatment and
there we
we don't find any problem with balance
note that we do balance
uh controlling for sampling weights and
we also cluster standard errors by
village so so
we try to do this the same way we would
perform the rest of the analysis
so this is the
this is the first table i have these are
just descriptives and
well a bit more than the scripture i
have some have some tests but the first
part of the table if you want the first
half the table the top half
is about um
perhaps uh you know issues of possible
interest one is uh
you know how do people score on the test
whether the test has got
um
actually should be zero to one to eight
the test has eight questions so they
could either answer them all wrong i
think you should
say zero to eight or they could answer i
think nobody does that but
they could they could answer all of them
right then the average is about seven so
they're pretty good at remembering what
the correct answer is this is on in
general note that we didn't ask these
questions in the controlled villages but
we know from uh
from other
observational data that they don't know
much about sri
um
and this is just another variable we use
is whether they can
uh answer the three main questions
correctly and you get they get 88 of
farmers who can treat farmers intrigued
not not 3d farmers
farmers in treated villages can do that
in terms of nomination remember they
could make up to they could make up to
five nominations they actually make
make nearly all five of five nominations
so it's very stable we don't have to
worry too much about some of them
nominating one because he's the only one
who matters and then some nominating
five like nearly everybody nominates
five so that that helps us as well
and now we already have i can already
show you some of the average
uh treatment effects uh or at least the
the means the the
the means in each of the samples so
because i i have the means in the
control villages these are
these are the the the adoption variables
that i have
um
this is just basically comparing control
villages to treated villages these are
means village level means okay i'm of
course i'm going to be looking at more
than that but
so the first variable is basically
whether barack estimated
that
the farmer has adopted at least some of
the practices of sri
and in controlled villages by you know
about two and a half percent of the
farmers in that village are estimated by
brackets uh
so basically less than one farmer
um while in treated villages about a
third of the farmers okay
this is across the whole village
um
in terms of the proportion of land and
of course that that is massively
significant
uh we have three thousand i forgot to
tell you the sample size but we but you
know you have 30 farmers times 100
villages where you have 3 000 farmers
all together
so
this kind of difference across
villages versus 40 villages you know
it's certainly significant
um proportion of land is just a
percentage of the of their cultivated
acreage
uh that is uh that is
on which sri uh practices have followed
um so that's uh
that that's there again you get you see
that uh in treated villages you get a
much bigger proportion
these are the number of sri principles
adopted on the plot
in central villages actually they they
are recorded as you know adopting 1.4
but that could just be that they by
chance uh
adopted one of those uh one of those uh
practices but
very few of them adopt more than one so
there's basically
it's it's a means it looks like a high
mean but it's not the same practice that
every farmer adopts right so they
basically randomly adopt certain things
without knowing that this is called sri
um very few of them this is very
important very few of them actually
follow the the the transplanting rule
which is about the age of the seedlings
very in control villages very few of
them
um follow the recommended distance
between bundles the places where they
transplant the rice
um
but it's it's exactly quite a bit higher
in in
in treated villages even though this
still remains very low but they still
don't like to follow the age of the
ceiling so it's certainly not complete
adoption
and then
[Music]
and then in terms of number of seedlings
per bundle
you have a bit higher at practic you
know this practice is already kind of uh
somewhat there even in control villages
but even there is higher in uh
treated villages so that's that's in
terms of practices well actually the so
that you see
we're not it's not like you say
you know have you adopted this
fertilizer meaning have you used this
fertilizer of any of your of your
fields here you have
you know uh
a whole bunch of uh
six main recommendations from sri
recommendation and basically
what is being tracked here are the main
recommendations that they make
these are this is the data that we have
on
agricultural performance at end line
we have yield value of crop output input
costs labor costs
um
total cost and profits
and here
these are all in
so this is in kg per decimal a decimal
is a very small unit of uh len land land
area
used in uh in bangladesh
um and these are bangladeshi taka per
decimal so these are in local currency
and you can see there are differences uh
like for instance it's about 30
some taca difference here
uh here there is there's very basically
if anything is slower in terms of costs
uh it's the same in terms of labor cost
on average
and it's the same in terms of total cost
so there's a little bit of a higher
value of output and so you get a little
bit of higher
imputed profit
okay so that's the and these these
things are significant
there's also something significant this
is even that is significant even though
it's reasonably small
so these are all average comparisons so
now we we haven't divided uh uh
farmers and treated villages into the
different treatment categories so let's
let's do that now so here we've divided
them into teacher training immediately
student
non-nominating student and non-student
these are the control means that i just
showed you a minute ago
and these are the adoption levels so you
can see immediately that
that you know the teacher trainees
adopt a very high probability uh
about 70 percent of them the the this
are
the dependent variable is is is uh
it takes a value 100 if they adopt and
zero if they don't adopt so that each
coefficient is easily readable as a
percentage point
um
and remember the baseline level of
adoption is very small so so everybody
here is significantly above that that
that that value
so they're all all quite significant
once you and then if you start looking
at the at the rest of the table you get
lots of uh lots of stars so basically
you know
even here where even in
control villages
is you know
close to 18 of the farmers who follow
this practice
anyway but then you get a much higher
much higher these are these are you
you know you have to add 18 to 17 to get
uh how much a non-nominating student
uh how much if he follows the number of
seedling cabernet that's the way to read
it
so that's the intercept if you want
are these about just the plot on which
they're doing it or the plots on which
they're doing it or is it right so here
here all the plots are included so this
is basically a regression that runs by
plot
uh that's why there are some in there
more than 3000 observations
because farmers could uh could mention
up to three plots they collected
information up to the three biggest plot
decorative information on that
and that's basically what the focus of
the study is because brac is not gonna
go and visit all your little tiny little
thing so they basically focus on up to
three plots per farmer
and these tend to be the biggest ones
and rice could typically be included so
that that's okay
so that's the that's the way
it's done
um
so so basically the the lesson from this
is that yeah with but pretty good effect
on on all these practices on adoption as
measured
you know in a really relatively generous
way here
um compared to uh farmers in controlled
villages so that's the that's the first
lesson
and then if you look
well you know these numbers are
different so what about this number
compared to this one what about this
number compared to this one and so on so
what about this number so what
so here we just basically
using these regressions so for the first
column we use this regression and we
just
do these pairwise t tests you know this
is the coefficient
of teacher trainee
significantly different from the
coefficient of
nominating students so basically we do
these pairwise comparisons to see
whether
there's a difference in treatment
effects
and you can see that when we're
comparing teachers and students
you always get these are p values here
so we just report p values
um since it's a test
and
so they basically they are they are more
adopting than other people you can see
lots of zeros everywhere these zeros
everywhere here you see teachers are
clearly
overwhelmingly
adopting more sri
in terms of the students
um
you can see that both both students you
know all of them is like also nearly all
uh there's one two here but other than
that they've pretty high a pretty low p
value so i get a high
uh significant effect that they they're
more likely
to adopt than non-students in treated
villages okay so it's not just that
there was some kind of diffusion in the
whole village
and they benefited from it
it's that they basically the fact that
they were targeted by our intervention
through a teacher a
trainee to receive a summary instruction
it actually made them more likely to
adopt these sri practices
um there is the only place where it is
except for this one which is borderline
significant i would say
everything else here is not significant
so basically this idea that we we had
which is basically behind the model
farmer
logic
the idea that people would pay more
attention
if they are matched to somebody they
look up to somebody they regard as an
opinion leader as a
as a as a source of valuable information
um
and so if this was the case you know
being matched with a model farmer
somebody you regard as a as a model
makes you more likely to adopt what they
tell you to do
what they teach you
then you would expect this number
you would expect all these numbers to be
positive and significant they're all
negative
yeah thankfully they're not
significantly negative but they're all
negative
except for this one's just borderline
but marcel the the teacher trainee has
been nominated by somebody right they're
all above media nominations
isn't it no no no no no no no there's
four above media and two below media
okay so is this coming from the above
median or the below median or is it the
same no matter which
so what i'm trying to get at is
i think your interpretation was it
doesn't you don't have to be a model
farmer you're equally effective at
disseminating i think is what you were
saying but but i'm saying that out of
six four were considered
uh modeled by
by a larger number of people right so i
may not have nominated them but my
neighbor nominated them so they're
probably still pretty good
yeah
yeah it's a good idea we could do that
we haven't done that but we could do
that we could compare
we could do that that's that that goes
in the direction of what the lip i was
mentioning earlier basically looking at
the
yes
we could also i mean we haven't done
that we of course we have the the whole
network of uh recommendations so we
could see whether
extend you know how much variation we
have in centrality for in degree
centrality in this case in centrality or
even a
more sophisticated measure of centrality
yeah this is this is something we could
do
yeah yeah this is a good suggestion
thanks
thank you um
okay but
in terms of
uh being matched to
somebody you didn't nominate doesn't
seem to disadvantage you here so
but i see what you hear what you're
saying and you say well maybe it's
because
you know what if you have been matched
with somebody who was nominated by lots
of people maybe that that's that's what
the role model would be okay okay so i
for that i need to document the fact
that
what is the variation in centrality and
uh because if there is not much
variation in centrality everybody
mentions their five neighbors and
basically everybody is the same there's
no there's no central paper but it's a
good yeah it's very good point i will do
that we'll do that if you will add to
the paper thanks
um
okay so this is now again looking at the
average three no i have to be careful
because i only have 15 minutes left um
the average treatment on
on agricultural performance
these are now in log
because you know there's noise in the
data especially these values is always
noise so if you take a look it kind of
dampens a little bit the the upper tail
and you don't have to wins horizon all
that so
so the the the news is that in terms of
yields you get you get slightly higher
yields so basically seven percent higher
yield for
teacher training four percent for the
five percent for the students
and in terms of profit they get about
four you know the teachers i get about
fourteen percent high profits nine
percent and fourteen percent
um compared to the control so so there
is a there is some benefit
that that is uh
that is you know achieved through that
it's not just that they
learn to
to
to mimic what had been told
uh they also actually benefit uh from
that so that that's the good news
um so now we
we so that's that's all about average
treatment effect so now i want to focus
a little bit more about
uh i want to do a little bit more one is
the i want to compare
the students
depending on whether their
teacher is incentivized or not so
basically the this is the mean for
unincentivized
uh teachers
and this is the the mean the additional
increase in score
um in the quiz of of students who have
been assigned uh to an incentivized
teacher training and you can see there's
a little bit significant or you know
mindless significant uh improvement in
in and it's a little bit stronger if you
look as to whether they answer the three
main questions correctly
um
so that means that incentivizing the
teacher seems to
have induced the teacher to do a
slightly better job
in teaching them uh to the test of
course in teaching them to to take the
test
okay
um
and this is whether
we also looked as to whether it has an
effect on the teachers so basically
do the teachers do better on the test
because they
they taught
uh
they know you had to teach the test
there we don't see well there's a
positive
but
if you know coefficient here but it's
definitely not significant and you can
see that the teachers do in general very
very well on the test okay so it looks
like they were paying attention uh
knowing that they're going to be
teachers
not doesn't really depend on them being
incentivized
um
this is um
um this is the effect of or rather the
absence of effect of
so you see that if you incentivize a
teacher the students
do a little bit better on the test does
it translate in higher adoption the
answer is no
so the yeah we have slightly
the point estimates are very
the small
nothing is ever significant
there is a very large relative to the
coefficients so basically there is no
that incentivization did not induce more
adoption
okay and it also did not induce more
adoption by the teachers the reason why
we worry about that is
is uh because in the other paper the one
we did
on referrals what we found is that the
farmers who referred all the farmers
um the other farmers kind of learn about
that they know that they've been
referred oh you know marshall you
referred me okay
and then so marcel suddenly decides oh
me now he's observing me is he you know
he knows that i referred him so maybe i
should put my money where my mouth is so
basically you know i better adopt a
little bit or maybe pretend to adopt a
little bit so that i don't completely
don't look completely silly to have
recommended
this person for training
otherwise he would say why did you send
me something completely useful to do
something completely useless panel sorry
so so that's why we we we just looked
this to whether they don't do that here
we did not induce excess
adoption by teachers by incentivizing
them which i think is good news
[Music]
now so this is about incentivization
this is about the other treatment
whether you are assigned to a teacher
that you nominated or not
so does it affect the performance
of the student on the quiz well there's
a there's a point estimate which is
positive here but it's definitely not
significant same thing here this is very
small
so basically the answer is no the fact
that you are assigned to somebody you
you regard as you listed as a role model
doesn't affect how much you learn from
them even on the quiz
and this is what happens um
on your adoption itself if anything
there's one one thing here that's
negative
but uh which i kind of already saw
before
borderline significant at ten percent
level but other than that it's all it's
all negative and so yeah let's just
confirms what we already looked at
before
what about mediation analysis it's going
into a bigger direction of um
heterogeneity analysis so
so here basically we're
gonna we're gonna we're gonna think
about what could be the process by which
the teacher
is um
is inducing adoption is it because
he's transferring more knowledge and
this knowledge is useful for adoption
okay well you have to know what the
practices are before you can actually
follow them and be
measured as following them
or is it that
people follow the example so basically
you know if the if the teacher is
adopting and
maybe he can can take the the trainees
to the field or at least he can talk
them through it
on the field so that so that's the
so to do that basically we thought well
why don't we put
um
[Music]
that should not be
so this is the incentivized teacher
trainee
and then we thought well
if it is uh
uh no this this is not this is the quiz
performance of the something here
sorry
i think this is not the teacher's value
it's the the student's value of the so
basically
if if the effect of um
[Music]
is no no this is okay sorry sorry i got
confused for a second this is the effect
on on the
on the the the students performance in
the quiz this is the student and the
quiz and basically students whose
teacher does better on the quiz
also do better on the quiz so basically
there's some transmission of knowledge
from the teacher to the student so
teachers who learn more
translate more
to their to their students even
controlling for the fact that the
teacher may have been incentivized so we
control for that so that here's a
control we're just looking whether the
transmission is through or at least some
of the transmission is through
knowledge transformation
the teachers who learn more transfer
more
to their to their um
to their students
and this is by nominate the same thing
by domination status so again you know
is also there
um
this is the effect of the of the quiz
score on on
adoption and so basically you look as to
whether this has an effect on adoption
as well
and so you get
you get a couple significant terms there
but other than that it seems to be
pretty flat
and the same thing
is reproduced if you
if you compare
nominating students non-nominating
students instead of comparing
incentivized
uh teacher training students to
non-instant device teacher training
students so so basically what this says
is that
performance on the quiz score
uh of the teacher just just has some
some transmission to uh
uh to
to adoption suggesting that
knowledge is is one of the channels of
transmission
as you would expect i mean you would
hope this is true but but now we have to
look at the other thing which is
um
examples teaching by example so so here
we go we're looking at the teachers
value
of the the corresponding adoption
measure so basically
are people more likely to adopt is if
the teacher adopts are there people more
likely to plant on a large proportion of
their land
if the teacher does that and so on so
basically we you can see that in all
these cases that these things are are
positive
the only exception being this one where
teachers are already quite high start
with
so
so there's nothing perhaps a bit less
variation there but so what you find is
that it's basically the evidence that
both channels are operating here one is
that
if you are taught by a better teacher
someone who is paid more attention to
the course knows more you do you adopt
more it's a channel of transmission and
you're also better you also know better
on the quiz
and
and then the other thing is that if the
teacher adopts you you seem to
be more likely to follow his example so
these two things are there
so the last thing i'm gonna do um in the
three minutes i have
i should have stopped earlier but um
um
so we also would like to know whether
inviting trainees to be a teacher has an
effect of of on their adoption okay not
relative to their students but relative
to trainees who would not have received
this task of training other students so
fortunately we have this other
uh experimental events you know it's
also an rct
and in that experiment we have a whole
batch of
um
trainees who are randomly selected among
the 30 farmers and we're only trained
they only receive the training so we can
kind of compare them
to the to the teachers so that's
basically what we do in this in this
first comparison here and what you find
is that so p2p the me is basically means
that you were in the in the teacher
training experiment and not in the other
experiment
what you find is that so if the average
adoption in um of the of the
uh of the randomly selected trainees in
the other experiment was 36
then among uh our teacher training you
know we know it's it's like close to 70
so it's basically 34 higher than that
okay so that's that's the idea
so basically what you get is that
um inviting people to be teacher
training makes them adopt more
okay
um
and it doesn't necessarily do that for
the for the food you know if you these
these other comparisons are not more
significant but perhaps the surprise is
that
um
the the student farmers if you compare
them to or to to to other trainees
they're not
that you know sometimes a little bit
less sometimes a bit more
but they're not
massively different from
people who actually receive the black
training
which i think is quite remarkable these
are these are people who have not seen
any bracket uh training agent so they
basically all they've learned about sri
is from other farmers and and their
adoption and behavior
in general is relatively similar to to
people who in the other
um in the other uh experiment received
and trained directly from black
we did we do a small
back of the envelope cosmetic analysis
the details of
the calculations are in the appendix
we get a
we estimate a social return of two
points basically you value the profits
and so on and compare it to the cost
that we have incurred
and you know you get a two
point two and a half dollars per dollar
invested in the program which generates
a rate of return social rate of return
which is not bad it's lower than what we
got in the other experiment but the
other experiment
um suggested that
um
if you incentivize me if you push people
they tend to over adopt so they
basically
you kind of induce them to experiment
with uh with the technology and then
everything experimented they discover
it's not for them it's too difficult for
them and then they withdraw from the
technology the year after we noticed
that so here by inducing more people to
adopt with
you know it's great we have induced lots
of people to experiment but as as we
said not sri is not for everybody and so
so as a result maybe there's excess if
you want excess experimentation i don't
know if it's success but
lots of people experiment who don't
necessarily benefit from it certainly
not in the first year they try it so
that's the that's the kind of the
general uh
lesson here
and maybe i should i should stop here
and if there's still time for
some questions if people still have
questions
have any questions from the audience
so marcel just to follow up on dilip's
earlier question
you don't really look at heterogeneity
with respect to any characteristics of
either the teachers or the students
no yes
and is uh
and is that because of lack of power or
lack of data or or lack or you think
it's not really identified
it's probably due to
perceived lack of patience for it by
editors and referees i think that's the
thing oh you are picking winners you go
you have 27
heterogeneity tests you just report the
one that gives you a big kick and
so
and then in any case it's not uh
it's not as it's not experimentally
assigned and so on on
so we tried to
but i think that the but you have given
me some suggestion for
for uh i really liked the suggested
suggestion earlier
about looking at uh
nominations i think it's a very good
suggestion and we should do that in the
paper because it really fits in the
paper and it fits in the motivation of
the paper
and uh it's it's of course related to
what dilip was saying as well so
yeah i had i had another sort of broader
question here it's
i mean can you reject the uh story where
there's just one kind of heterogeneity
which is uh skill
and denominations basically were a way
to identify the more skilled
farmers
and the students themselves were
selected by brac on the basis of
something which i probably assume is
related to farming skill
so you've already got a pre-selected you
know high-skilled farmers and then
within them you're selecting the most
skill and they just happen to be
teachers
so can you reject the hypothesis that
it's just about selection of skill
that all this teaching stuff is
you know it's not doing anything uh i
mean of course yeah
there's some diffusion obviously
uh but you know but basically you know
it's not nothing to do with
skill and teaching or anything like that
i mean
it's just skill in picking up stuff
that's now
generally available in the village
no but i mean
that's fine but
but
it's not true that we have only selected
as teachers those that were the most
skilled as measured by the number of
nominations they received
with four four people among them you
know but it was biased in favor of the
people with high nominations so i think
you know doing what sujata was
suggesting is a good idea is you know
actually why not just look at the number
of nominations
that you received and just look at you
know how performance varied with that
uh that that would be one way
okay
yeah i can do that i can do that but
remember in terms of the test itself i
mean
we have corrected for the stratification
so
so i don't think that's the
that's that's
i don't think that is invalidating our
results because we have we thought about
it it's a different interpretation i'm
just saying i'm not disputing the
statistical validity of your results
it's just a question of what what you
think is sort of going on underneath and
whether teaching has anything to do with
it
yes
so in the first experiment the one with
the 182 whatever villages where you
didn't ask them to teach but did you
select them the same way
it was simpler because we were not
trying to match but uh okay so
the the the
guy can so in that experiment
the the start is the same we take 30
brac shows up
picks their 30 farmers because that's
the way they they kind of line up
farmers for sri training so they kind of
identify them and then they keep them
and they then they bring the
the training agent
so so and they train them in groups of
so basically we basically
randomly selected 12 farmers of the 30
and assigned them to
for the first training session and then
at the end of the training session
each of them was asked to so there were
18 farmers left on the list so before
they left
they say oh before you leave and because
they get paid their little stipend
so before you you know here's a list
pick a name on the list as to
who would most benefit from
uh the brock training
so they basically look at the list and
say oh okay i can see uh albert's on the
list so i'm gonna mention albert and
then
the next person comes and say oh i'm
gonna mention albert two no no look it's
already been crossed you can't mention
albert anymore you have to mention
someone else okay i'm going to mention
juja so they basically mentioned simon
basically then you can see the people
who have been so in that paper we
actually use that
order if you want to see
the bottom line is that um they did not
they did not recommend on average so
everybody they recommend 12 people out
of 18. so normally you should you should
you know the six worst farmers at least
able farmers or least skilled farmers
should have been dropped out of the list
so they you should basically see that
this
selected sample of 12 out of 18 farmers
should be better
than the 12 randomly selected farmers
right
because the second sample is a
is only two thirds of the 18
and they've been selected to be
the most skilled farmers
so you should see that they are adopting
more because they understand what's
going on
and they they get more more benefit from
it
that's not that what we find at all
so the reason i was asking was i was
wondering if that helps you answer
dilip's question about whether there's
something about having to teach that
makes you a better adopter yourself
but you can't actually answer that
question because the way that these
teachers those guys were selected is
different
it's random they're not both being
selected the same way then some get to
teach and others don't get to teach it's
not as simple as that
i mean everybody could have been
selected to teach
everybody has a
probability of being selected if you are
of the 15 above median you have uh four
out of 15 chances if you are above the
15 you have two out of 15 chances
everybody could be a teacher
and we correct for the probabilities of
of you being being a teacher
yeah yeah that i do understand that
okay
i think we're a little bit past time so
uh i'd like to thank myself very
interesting presentation
and i'd like to thank i also want to
thank the staff at iems who have been
coordinating the webinars for all six
seminars so that's carla who's managing
today carla chan and joey chu
who's uh the manager at ims
i think it's been really well managed so
you know silent applause
and uh
this was obviously a second best
event
in lieu of having a workshop in person
uh but i think
it's been really valuable in the world
of covid to still be able to have some
intellectual exchange and bring you know
leading people working on common issues
of interest so i want to thank all the
participants yeah i appreciate very much
you having me i really enjoyed it and
thanks for the excellent comments thank
you
thank you
goodbye everyone
bye