good afternoon folks we have recently
had some very cold weather here in
Missouri and I've wanted to give you an
update on the greenhouse to let you know
how it did we got down to six degrees
the lazy way outside and the greenhouse
temperature got down to 1630 typical
d'affaires results of course that's a 22
degree difference in temperature and
when it was six below it was blowing
outside it was pretty nasty we still
kept 22 degrees warmer inside the
greenhouse considering we have not had
enough Sun and warm days to actually get
our heat sink charged I'm pretty happy
with those results as always thanks for
watching if you have any questions about
the greenhouse or growing a mittleider
garden let me know