one of the most important thing about
micronics is that you have the number of
chicken you have up there the ratio has
to match the number of uh uh fish down
there ABS today we be discussing with
you about micronics my name is mar John
I your host in betel Farm where the fish
are if you can look at it carefully we
have our M massive pump here our suive
pump is inside the water so from from
the water the submassive pump takes it
to to this filter here we build our
mechanical filter and from our
mechanical filter we have our biological
filter this is where all the bacteria
are formed after after the bacteria is
formed it runs through the PVC pipe down
to the grow beds and from the grow bed
that is where the plant absorb all the
nutrient that is taken from the pond the
fish pond and also after observing it it
sent it back you can see the water comes
back here as a clean water so that the
fish can have good oxygen one of the
most important thing about micronics is
that you have the number of chicken you
have up there the ratio has to match the
number of uh uh fish down there so if
you are putting if we put 10 chicken to
100 fish which is very important because
if you miss the ratio the amount of uh
the amount of chicken if you supersede
that of the fish then the water will
become so acidic and all your fish will
die so it's it's 10 chicken to at least
100 fish in the pond depending on the
number of uh depending on the size of
the pond you want to build so your ratio
has to be accurate about uh micronics so
here what we do is that this Pond right
here is uh 22 M by by 3
m and we put 10 chicken 10 chicken to
100 fish
so if we put two chicken 20 chickens
that means we have 200 fish there so
that is the ratio we use so that the
water will never be acidic because it's
very important that your water remain in
an alkaline form so that is very
important because from uh just as I said
from this place here from the pond it
goes to the mechanical filter from the
mechanical filter to the biological
filter and everything what the what the
chicken release to the fish and the fish
come consume it and whatever the fish
release it pass out to the plants and
the plant in return absorve all the
nutrients and in return send it back to
the fish as a clean water why do we do
this kind of farming is very important
micronics mimic natural ecosystem it
encourage the growth of both plant and
animal in a way that minimize
environmental impact it redu dependency
on large scale industrial agricultural
practice making it more sustainable
choice is for food security micronus can
be implemented in a small space making
it suitable for urban environment small
household or communities which is
limited to land resources this makes it
very valuable too for promoting local
food production and improving food
security particularly in urban areas or
region with limited agricultural land
yes so thank you so much this is our
topic today on micronics because I
wanted to educate you on more what we do
with micronic
and please I want you to subscribe to
our Channel better F and HS and please
like share comment on the video and if
there's any specific question you have
please put it on the comment section let
us know and if there's anything you
disagree about feel free to contact us
and we can talk about it thank you for
subscribing and see you next time