with your agricultural knowledge did you
decide to pursue a niche in poultry
production so you've got 30 000 there's
a 20
room of era or margin what else should
we know about egg laying um for example
when a person wants to pursue uh poultry
production and specifically an egg
laying does one need to find clients
first before the chickens start to lay
the eggs which one comes first
it's it's
making sure that the chickens start
laying eggs
and then you can find the clients
because when you start right you don't
have to have the market when you start
[Music]
welcome to the private property podcast
my name is mbali mwaka and this is the
farming podcast
joining us once again i'm your host and
we always speak to agricultural
professionals people who are pursuing
their careers in the agri industry
farmers entrepreneurs
and it's quite an exciting podcast
because we have a diverse set of guests
who always drop gems right here on the
farming podcast continue to like and
subscribe to our youtube channel follow
the farming podcast playlist under the
private property youtube channel and
that's where you can get all the
information and all the previous
interviews we've done thus far
i think we're approaching episodes 200
so it's been quite a milestone uh doing
this farming podcast and i can say as a
farmer i'm definitely learning something
each and every time i speak to the guest
today we're joined by a poultry farmer
and like i said i'm always excited to
speak to female farmers because you know
we don't typically interact with one
another on a daily basis so excuse me
for being biased but i'm super excited
to be speaking to yet another young
female farmer learning about her journey
understanding her journey and how she
became successful in her own right and
what path she's trying to pursue what
goals she's trying to attain and how can
we support each other within the agri
industry as farmers so introducing my
guest is zondi sajayo
she's a poultry farmer and let's get to
deep dive into her business and get to
know a little bit more zandi thank you
so much for joining us on the podcast
how are you doing
i'm doing fantastic super excited to
have you on we've had many poultry
farmers on the podcast
very few females so maybe if you could
tell us about your farming business
what's the name
why did you decide to farm poultry and
not any other commodity
okay um the name of our business is
mazapa trading
um and we are doing poultry
[Music]
uh
crops and
piggery right but we
we mainly focus on
poultry
because when we got into poultry we
realized that almost every house has
eggs
could be for breakfast could be for
lunch could be for dinner but almost
every house has eggs
so that is why we decided to get into
poultry and everything else just
balances it out
yeah so you keep saying we
uh uh are you are you uh running a
family farm
do you have business partners um or are
you saying we thinking of yourself and
the team that you employ
it's okay it's a family business it's me
and my mom
but we also have a team that helps us so
at the end of the day it's not just the
two of us that these this business
supports it's us and a whole lot of
other families that are involved
yeah so you know we do get a lot of uh
farmers who have
joined generational family farms or
joined in the family business what made
you to decide to pursue farming with
your mother and
just also expanding a little bit on
poultry are you farming broilers or
layers
okay oh
i came with the idea right but i did not
have money so i was like okay you can
bring in the money and i will bring in
the skills because at first i was even
studying psychology and then i dropped
out of psychology to go to go pursue
agriculture with unisa
and then she brought in the funds i
brought in this skills and we just ran
with it and yeah
and oh yeah they they farm
um we're focusing mainly on the eggs
right but
on the side we have brightness
we also have
the old cheeks
right so maybe tell us a little bit
zondi in terms of um the layers you know
how many layers should one start with
just to you know break even and what are
the type of conditions that the the
chickens need to successfully lay eggs
in if you could maybe just share share
that with us
okay um first of all with the layers
it's it's a go big or go home kind of a
game
you can't start with 100 um chickens and
because you get roughly 80
of the eggs of your total number if you
have 100 eggs then per day you should
look at 88 right which is not enough
because that's roughly 2
not even three trays
so you just have to go big and currently
we farming with about three thousand
chickens
from two different chicken houses right
and then from that three thousand at
least we know that we have eighty
which is enough
yes
yeah
and so
with your agricultural knowledge did you
decide to pursue a niche in poultry
production so you've got 30 000 there's
a twenty percent uh
room of error or margin what else should
we know about egg laying um for example
when a person wants to pursue uh poultry
production and specifically an egg
laying does one need to find clients
first before the chickens start to lay
the eggs which one comes first
it's it's
making sure that the chickens start
laying eggs
and then you can find the clients
because when you start right you don't
have to have the market when you start
because you can just start for household
consumption before you even go big you
know
the neighborhoods around the farm are
you
start off consumers if i should put it
like that because before you get to
produce for shop ride and spa and and
um you start off with the people around
you you know the household consumptions
are the first people that we started at
because
you can just stand anyway and sell eggs
and they will fly off
yeah
yeah so what would you say to someone
who says uh for example you said you
know firstly they need to go big or go
home because starting with 80 chickens
is not it's not sufficient that's about
two trays and if you started selling to
um your nearby community
why would there be a need for them for
someone to go supply to establish
retailers because at the end of the day
those same people buy from the retailers
so doesn't it make logical sense to just
expand to your immediate community and
then broaden it outside your immediate
community and start supplying other
communities
yeah it definitely does because
at some point
people people work with
um
i wouldn't say you channel people but i
would say it's easier to build
relationships with people around you
right and people work with referrals so
if one person can tell the next person
that i found fresh eggs at so and so
store then
chances of the business growing are very
high
[Music]
zone if you can share with us uh uh you
know without
revealing too many business trade
secrets
who is your market um you know
how are you selling to them is it weekly
daily and how are you managing cash flow
within your business do you have certain
payment terms um or do you do that or do
your customers have to pay cash because
we all know that in the broiler
poultry industry you know chickens need
to be fed every single day almost every
hour so how does one manage their cash
flow especially if they want to go into
poultry production
okay we work with cash on delivery we
are very strict on catch on delivery
right because chickens need eggs and
feed is expensive with petrols going up
everything going up feed is also going
up right so we cannot afford to have
people maybe taking stock on account and
the payment and because the business is
still growing
um there's always room for improvement
it's our fourth year in the
game and
there's still room for improvement so
cash on delivery makes things easier
right and
we sell on a daily basis because
just
not far from the farm we have a store
where people come in at first we were
selling for the around neighborhood
and before we knew it we had people
coming in to stroke
right so that is what has been helping
us keep the cash flow and another thing
is the crops see the crops also help us
with the cash flow of the business
because crops are growing at three
months three months rotation and that
it makes it easier to have a constant
cash flow for the chickens the feed and
everything else yeah i like the fact
that you are diversifying so that you
can maintain both enterprises because my
follow-up question there was
why did you decide to also diversify
into piggery and crops you know that
also seems like very very intensive
farming uh in their own right but at
what stage having been in the business
for about four years did you guys decide
let's venture into crops and if you are
venturing into crops what crops are you
farming and also why piggery at the same
time
okay piggery was a hobby right because
my mom just left figuring
and she started off with just four pigs
and
now he's sitting at about 80 200 but
it's it's a hobby i wouldn't say it's
something that we focus on too much but
it's they and it it also generates cash
flow right
and then the the
crops the crops we we currently
plant okay we just
sold
sweet potatoes and mealy meal right and
then we're currently in the process of
planting cabbage so now with crops it's
three months three months till the
months so
those three months is we just
see we just we just grow we sell and it
generates cash flow
fantastic and tell me are you guys
farming in your own private land or is
it state-owned or are you leasing
it's
privately owned because we have two
farms
one farmer is my mom's and the other
farm is my dad
all right and so what advice could you
give to young farmers especially
managing their cash flow you know a lot
of young children unfortunate enough to
have parents who are really in business
maybe to assist them on cash flow a lot
of other children um are not also
fortunate enough to go into the farming
industry with their parents having
farmed i know you said to your mother
she needs to bring in the cashew
bringing the knowledge
but having fun for four years managing
all these various commodities poultry
piggery as well as crop production what
are some of the the the learnings that
you have
acquired throughout your farming
experience around managing cash flow and
the importance thereof and what advice
could you give to other young farmers
maybe we just studied agriculture but in
theory you know and don't have actual
practice in managing cash flow because i
heard you say you you take cash on
demand now for a person who's not used
to getting cash
um
you know on hand
and and
thinking that i have to reinvest this in
the business they might use that
you know to spend other things so what
are some of the things that you've
learned around handling cash cash flow
management managing finances in your
business that you could share to other
young farmers maybe who are less
inexperienced in financial management
you know i would first say that the
business does not find the lifestyle
because
it's a completely different world
because as much as cash flow cash flows
every single day there's something to be
bought every single day for the farm
whether it's feed
electricity water to be paid
medication there's just
something that needs to be bought every
day right and
it's very tricky because the first
the first three years
there is no profit you just farming
farming farming producing meeting
deadlines but there is no profit you
start to break even maybe at the end of
the third year
then that's when you start to break even
then that's when you start to see where
you're working where what are you
working for and where you're going
what's the vision for your farm business
i mean where do you see yourself in the
next three to five years
i would like to see our eggs in
woodworks i'm sorry but i would like to
see our eggs and regrets because that's
where the niche
that is like the top bar
of every farmer or producer or
anyone who's into product food
production
yeah and how do you think you're going
to get there because you know dealing
with the big guys comes with a lot of
red tape so how you think you're going
to get there
i would say quality speaks for itself
because
when you're producing quality
everybody around you will see it and
everybody will talk about it you can
start at like the close supermarkets
eventually quality will speak for itself
yeah yeah zondi uh before i let you go i
would just like to know maybe for
someone who's inspired by a story and
wants to start uh egg laying what are
some of the infrastructural development
that one needs to start off with how
much maybe cash do they need to start
off with as well because you said start
by going big or go home what does that
going big look like is it 30 000
chickens is it 10 000 is it 5 000
roughly how much can one
look at as an investment to start off
with and what type of infrastructure
must i have to just get my operation
going
okay the first of all the infrastructure
should be very warm right because
these chickens are going to be in there
for roughly a year
so they need a very warm
atmosphere because if they get too cold
then the production drops and if the
production drops then it's bad for the
business and
price wise i would say
it depends on on your structure right
but i would say minimum 2 000 chickens
minimum as i start off i mean you will
grow as it you will grow
as it goes right so
i would say 2000 as a minimum as a start
off maybe in the first year and then
from then on there should be growth
right and for for someone who's
interested in
farming or poultry i would say do your
research do your research because
what works for me might not work for you
or there's different kinds of breeds
that you can start with you know
so just do your intensive research and
figure out what you want to do
and yeah it will grow
yeah thank you so much for your time
zondi uh maybe the last last question
this is quite interesting it is youth
month and
what message can you impart to other
young people within the agri sector
i would say invest in your craft because
the best thing you can do is to know
your craft master it so that nobody can
tell you anything about it just invest
in your craft you know if it takes you
okay for from my side there was a yeah
where i had to leave the city leave
everything and go live at the farm for a
year a full year i was just a farm girl
you know
and that has paid off because now the
the business is at a stage way i would
say i'm seeing growth
so invest in your craft
yeah thank you so much sundy for your
time i think that's the big uh
um closing of point that we're going to
take home today to say invest in your
craft i couldn't agree more but thank
you so much for your time and the best
of success for your businesses
thank you so much
it's a pleasure if you just missed it we
are joined by zombie tajio she's a
poultry farmer and she told us you know
the journey into agriculture um and how
she got to pursue her mother to to be
the financier in her farming enterprise
while she came with the agricultural
knowledge and i guess that should give
you an answer to say this is how you
could raise your own capital to start
your own farming enterprise seek and
look advice and financial assistance to
those close and immediate to you instead
of running off to investors financial
institutions who will obviously lend and
borrow you money with high interest
rates so if you're fortunate enough to
have maybe friends or family that can
believe in your idea your business idea
or your farming operation maybe give
them some equity let them become
involved and you could follow the
footsteps like zondi now she's managing
an operation four years down the line of
about 30 000
chickens
layers to be exact and she's also
diversified into piggery as well as
crops to manage the cash flow that she
has within a business she obviously has
big hopes as well she would like to see
an enterprise growing and i think what i
took lastly out of her is that you need
to manage your craft and i think this is
something that we need to do year in
year out no matter how much you
experienced how many years you've been
farming you still need to keep on
upskilling yourself as a farmer as an
entrepreneur as a business person
because you know decades change seasons
change operations change and they come
with various different demands that need
your attention so definitely own your
craft um you know sharpen your expertise
so that you could be a successful farmer
at the end of the day that's it from me
i'll see you next time and thank you so
much for watching
so
you