good morning and also good afternoon for
those that are joining from europe
i'm very pleased to share this panel
today
at the online dcmi 2020 conference
dedicated to challenges finding
information in food and agriculture
on the web what can we do better
and this panel is going to focus on food
and agricultural sciences
and as you will learn over the next 90
minutes
agriculture and disciplines related have
special
characteristics that make data
interoperability particularly
challenging
and so the work of certain genes to
collect scientific data
from one side in this particular um
sciences gray literature is crucial
while journal articles are not
necessarily the only scholarly
communication channel that counts
and secondly and the most important and
that is going to be
very much highlighted today is that
while in other sciences
english is the pivotal language in the
case of the foot in agriculture and due
to the diversity of languages behind
used it's necessary to consider
multi-language multilingualism and
semantic strategies as a way to increase
accessibility to all the scientific
literature through the use
we hope that at the end of this session
panelists will share some thoughts about
possible ways to address some of the
identified challenges as well possible
common synergies
to build on how how to bring them
forward
today we have panelists from the footing
agriculture
organization of united nations cgir
land portal foundation usda national
agricultural library
and the beijing academy of agriculture
and forestry sciences that unfortunately
is not going to be physically
in this panel session due to time
constraints the time zone constraints
but we have a recording to present the
use case
that they would like to share with you
about the work that they are doing in
this field
we encourage to all of you to submit
your questions
through the chat box anytime don't be
shy just share
if you have any specific request for one
panelist
please add her name at the beginning of
your comment this will make
easy to go through the questions and
answers part
and don't forget that we like to hear
from you as well this is an interactive
session
where we would like also to learn from
your thoughts and experiences if you
have
any in this field or in any other field
that you think that could be
also of interest for the audience
so this panel will start with a short
presentation
by each of the panelists and this is
going to bring us
uh to take more or less 60 minutes
and after that we will start with the
questions and answers
but uh before we continue with the
session let me introduce myself
because of course probably you don't
know me at all
so i'm in mr village i'm a senior
information management
um uh at fau and i'm the program manager
for agrees in anger work which will be
also presented today
during our discussion instead that you
have here in the zoom
all the panelists um we will start
um by the order that was
displayed in the announcement of this
session before
i would like to introduce our first
panelist which is
eddie antonioli erin is coming from the
usda national agricultural library niel
and she is the lead veterinator
librarian and data creation
team in the knowledge services division
of the usda
nil thank you erin and you can share
your presentation it's over to you
thank you emma can you hear me yeah
thank you excellent
excellent thank you i'm here today to
talk about the ag data commons usda's
general
ag data catalog and repository which is
designed to help usda researchers
publish and disseminate data products
the national agriculture library is one
of five national
libraries of the united states it houses
one of the world's largest collections
devoted to agriculture
and its related sciences
nal provides a variety of online
resources including journal articles
digital collections and other materials
relating to agriculture
i'm going to focus on the ag data
commons for today's presentation
the ag data commons is a catalog and
data repository for usda-funded research
data
it provides expert services for creating
curating and enabling access to complete
and machine readable
scientific metadata it creates
infrastructure for linking information
data data publications people and more
and it helps the usda funded research
community meet public access
requirements
an ag data commons data set consists of
data files and associated metadata
we provide tools and services to make
each data set richer and more
discoverable
the ag data commons strives to deliver
fair metadata that are machine readable
and available via apis and other
automated means
as a generalist ag repository we focus
most heavily on the f
and the a of this matrix since
interoperability and reusability
generally require subject-specific
adherence to more regimented
data and metadata standards
to that end the ag data commons provides
discovery
and access as its core function search
and discovery tools
and linked information promote
findability
we enable access through the catalog and
public apis
use of open licenses and dois for
digital assets
the ag data commons synthesizes metadata
to achieve a variety of services
i like the analogy of lego blocks to
represent ag data commons metadata
because the pieces come in different
colors
shapes and sizes and can be assembled in
a variety of ways to perform a variety
of functions
our metadata system is no different we
ask for essential information about the
data and rearrange that input to satisfy
the needs of each service that the ag
data commons offers
we often work with geospatial metadata
which must use the iso 19115 standard
and this standard underpins our internal
systems because it's robust enough to
handle the information from the other
standards
one use case that illustrates this
metadata synthesis
includes our work with the ag cross
repository
ag cross specializes in geospatial data
and uses an iso 19115
flavor of metadata in an esri platform
we ingest metadata and data by
harvesting from agros using
microservices architecture according to
best practices
and create the ag data commons record
and store the data files locally
we then reformat that metadata to the
data site format and reserve a doi
using an internal system which then gets
added back to the ag data commons record
finally the doi is pushed back to agros
for display with their record using a
restful api
records tagged with specific bureau
codes are also forwarded to data.gov
this way agros researchers can utilize
their subject specific platform
but also benefit from the discovery and
access services the ag data commons
offers
we offer a wide assortment of fields to
data submitters with a great deal of
linking potential
but we need to strike a balance between
information that makes data fair
and how much data submitters are willing
to fill out
when we present too many requirements
people simply won't fill out
they simply just won't submit their data
or they opt for repositories with a
lower bar of entry
when we allow submissions with too few
completed fields the data set
findability
and potential reusability suffers
after reviewing the requirements for the
services ag data commons facilitates
we arrived at this core set of essential
metadata for each record
this list doesn't account for some of
the subject subject-specific
requirements certain research
communities may need
but we cover our bases as a generalist
ag catalog with this set of metadata
during the curation process our staff
also adds nal thesaurus terms to ag data
commons records
the nal thesaurus is used to select
controlled vocabulary terms for
subject indexing in several of the
library's databases
the thesaurus is produced in part by the
national agricultural library
is updated annually and contains over
260 000
terms it's available as linked open data
for anyone to use
the ag data commons provides the
infrastructure for linking metadata and
objects to enable analytical tools
we provide specific fields for these
relationships to maximize the linking
and machine readability of the metadata
this includes different types of
relationships between data sets and
documentation
author identification links like orcid
and version guidance
we provide features to promote credit
for usda researchers as an incentive to
deposit data with us
and to provide more complete records
with linked information
u.s federal data should be openly and
freely available
but the ag data commons makes it easier
for researchers to give
and receive credit for their work
citations are automatically generated
for all records in the catalog and
researchers can link to their scholarly
publications
data papers and other related content
we also provide dois for locally held
data files which has been a big
incentive for researchers to share their
data publicly
now as much as we do well there are
still plenty of challenges we face in
making data findable
and accessible
our search features offer a particular
opportunity for improvement
we've been working with our stakeholders
to develop search requirements to use
while we evaluate database platforms for
our 2021
upgrade
our data content represents a diverse
set of research topics and metadata
needs
we can't be all things to all people and
instead focus on the services we offer
and the metadata required to accomplish
those tasks
an ale thesaurus application is not
currently automated and that's a problem
we plan to work more closely with nal's
indexing and informatics branch to
improve not term application and provide
better linkage
between various library systems and yet
another challenge
involves which controlled vocabularies
to implement and how to link them to
authoritative sources
we chose taxonomies related directly to
nal's services
but seek a better and more effective way
to integrate controlled vocabularies
used by the different
specific areas we support
our metadata enriches our data sets but
doesn't always make them more
discoverable outside of our own platform
some of this relates to infrastructure
and some to culture
for instance orcid accounts can
automatically link data sets with dois
we issue
from their author profile pages but many
account holders
don't turn on that feature we can
capture rich information
but strive to increase the linked
information we provide
to that end we work to convey the value
of linked information to the researchers
submitting the data
more fields often represents more burden
for data submitters
so we look for ways to make the
submission process easier and to
communicate the added value
as information professionals we
understand how complete and linked
information enhances data
sets however to get the absolute most
utility out of data sets we must educate
submitters
and communicate the value of linked
information while lessening the
submission burden so data becomes more
easily findable and accessible
thank you that's my presentation here
are a few of the links that i
showed throughout my presentation and i
will hand it back to emma
thank you so much erin also for really
doing on time
very interesting presentation i would
like to bring on board
our next panelist um
fabrizio celli um fabrizio
is part of um the team that is managing
aggregates the international system for
agricultural science and technology
actually he is the technical leader
and he is working for the food and
agriculture organization of united
nations welcome
to the panel fabrizio and over to you
thank you very much emma
okay in this session
we will be looking at how aggress is
addressing challenges in finding and
integrating research in food and
agriculture
i want to give you some background about
phao
and aggressive fallow is the food and
agriculture organization of the united
nations
and it's the organization that is
maintaining aggressor
faust's goal is to lead the
international efforts to defeat hunger
and to improve nutrition and food
security
he was founded in 1945 and
the headquarter is in rome even if our
operates in over 130 countries
in 1974 uh foul set up an initiative
together with the member countries
uh to uh make information on agriculture
globally available
the outcome of this initiative was
aggressive
agaris is a database of almost
12 million of multilingual bibliographic
metadata agriculture research
but it is also a big network of
as you can see 434 data providers
from 150 countries uh
the uh importance of aggress is also
given by the fact that it's highly used
so according to google analytics aggress
receives around 8 million of visits per
month
and is accessed from all over the world
200 countries and
territories
before talking about the new challenges
that
agrius has to address uh i want to
show i want to describe a little bit how
uh
the data providers so the aggregate
provider has changed over the time
so at the beginning uh in 1974
government
centers whose role was to collect all
the scientific production
in their country and to send the data to
aggress then
from 2005 aggressors started to accept
also data from institutional
repositories from publishers
and from aggregators usually in this
case agrees doesn't go
to an institution and ask for data but
thanks to
the visibility that tagri says
institutions come to aggress
asking if they can publish data and we
can face here problems
of integration of the data on the other
end
with the evolution of the technology and
also of the
open access institutional repositories
agrees uh
uh as to cope also with problems related
to
automatic discovery automatic harvesting
and processing
of data and metadata available on the
web
so just to summarize uh there are two
big areas in terms of challenges
on one side we have the problem of the
integration of new data so when there is
a new data provider
there are several problems to be solved
in order to guarantee that the metadata
can be correctly published in aggression
that can benefit
of all the features that give a lot of
visibility to aggress data
so for example uh considering uh the
variety of the data providers and the
fact that they come from all over the
world
they always use different metadata
formats and different standards
and most important uh there are very
different levels of metadata quality
so while there are data providers who
has made a
very rich metadata records on the other
end we can find
some data providers with very poor
records and these of course create a
problem of
balance inside the aggress database
other issues are for example related to
the full text links
and also the stability of the links
agrees uh uh
always suggests to add the link to the
full text
but uh considering that agrees uh
the agree started in 1974 most of the
links
are corrupted so aggress needs to
periodically review all the links to
guarantee that they are still working
then the other important problem is
about multilingualism
in fact uh considering the tag is just
metadata in
up to 90 languages the pro some problems
can
can exist when aggress receives regulars
especially with text encoding
everybody should use unicode utf-8 in
order to guarantee
interoperability of the metadata in all
the languages
the second area is about the automatic
discovery and the ingestion of data
directly from web apis for example using
the iph protocol or using like restful
apis
uh two big problems here are the
relevance
of high volume data in fact when you
uh search for data on the web and you
want to automatically
uh harvest and ingest data into the
database
it is difficult to be sure about the
relevance so
the fact that the data is relevant to
the topics available in the address
database
the second issue is really the two
content classification and to the
integration
of uh this data automatically are vested
from the web
now about the integration agrees uh set
up an orchestration
of uh software components
even if at the beginning we have a
manual validation
of the metadata so there is a physical
person who
receives the metadata and checks the
metadata
uh for uh in order to understand this
first of all it is relevant to the
aggress domain
and second if there are semantics error
for example or problems with encoding
this is something that is possible for
regular data providers but
not when metadata are automatically
harvested from the web because they're
the volume of the data it's very high
and it's impossible to do this manually
after this is done uh aggress has a lot
of processes to
convert and harmonize all the metadata
from a lot of formats to an aggress
internal format which is aggressive
and then to perform some operations like
data cleaning metadata enrichment
in order to reach the final version of
uh
the the record which is the aggressor df
so these allows aggress to enable
the usage of linked open data
technologies
so aggressor is not giving any
suggestions in terms of
input metadata format
[Music]
agrees tries to accept everything even
if there are
several challenges here poor metadata so
like missing metadata fields
uh lack for example of controlled
vocabularism
wrong usage of metadata properties and
as i told you in case of multilingual
regulars also problems with encodings
this is why aggress recommends to
consider the load of bd recommendations
which are recommendations in terms of
metadata properties to use
and also in terms of vocabularies to use
and they can help to standardize a
little bit uh
the situation and to help the
integration of the metadata coming from
uh such a variety of data providers
uh of course it's important to build
also some capacity
development development this is uh
because agaris has learned a lot over
the time
and the only way to help data providers
to produce better metadata is to
uh train also data providers so the
first step is email exchange so when
there are new data providers
and aggress understands that there are
errors
uh or semantic errors or other kind of
problems
there is a chain of email exchange with
the data provider
to guide the data provider to produce
better
richer and meaningful metadata then
there are also webinars guides on the
websites and
recommendations as i told you before
with the lord apd recommendations
now an important piece of the
aggregate's infrastructure is agrovoc
this is a controlled vocabulary covering
all the areas of interest of file it's
translated into 39 languages and
it's the backbone of aggress so this is
used for example 12 pages
with automatic data discovery and
classification aggro
can factories use them within some
machine learning algorithms
that allows agris to understand the
relevance of the metadata which are
automatically harvested and downloaded
from the web plus aggro voca is also
very important to enables a lot of
additional features on the website
like the multilingual search like the
improvement of the precision and the
recall
like the possibility to connect
different resources
so using linked open data technologies
and as i told you also
in several machine learning algorithms
both to determine
the relevance of harvested resources but
also to classify
resources according using these
multilingual tests
and that's it from my side thank you
very much
thank you very much fabrizio so we move
now to our third
speaker uh shio yin ping is from the
institute of agriculture information
and economics at the beijing academy of
agriculture and forestry sciences
she is responsible for the construction
of agriculture information resources
data sharing
information analysis and semantic
technology technology research
as i mentioned before unfortunately
she is um she couldn't attend this panel
session
um i'm not sure whether you can all
all of you can share can you see the
video
yes okay could you confirm as well
that you can hear the sound
hi okay so i will put the video now it's
about
nine minutes and then we will move to
the next panel list
china great honor to have this
opportunity to communicate with you
now i would like to introduce some of
the work our team has done
for construction and sharing of
agricultural information resources
challenges and how to deal with these
changes in the future
first i grateful introduction to my
organization
varis was founded in 1958
it's a comprehensive agricultural
research institution in beijing
there are 14 specialized research
institute
and the business fields cover all
aspects of agriculture
there are more than one certain
employees
ai is a specialized research
institute under baffs it manually
carries all to
research and extension service in the
field of
agriculture information resource
construction agricultural information
technology
agricultural economic management et
cetera
our team has been engaged in the
construction of agriculture information
resources
data sharing and economic analysis for
nearly two decades
we set up the basic agriculture think
tank plate
form in 2017. the goal of this
platform is to build our resources with
well organized and functional of
agricultural science and technology
so service and platform to provide the
data sharing service
and the in-depth uh information analysis
service
for decision makers managers and
research
researchers we have been working towards
this goal
at present the platform has gathered
more than one million pieces of
agricultural information resources from
china other countries and a few
international organizations
according to the resource tabs the
platform brings together
12 categories of information resources
including patents news
policies etc according to the
agricultural theme the data is
divided into cedar industrial planting
industry animal husbandry
fisheries etc at
present resources is mainly in chinese
and english resources for mice include
text pdf or
new numerical values and so on
there are four unknown tenures for data
acquisition one is the internal
data of dafs as baafi's owns
a lot of primary data resources
such as the expert information
technology achievement
research report another one is the data
from the government and academic
association
they get it through comprehend
concrete and creative construction
data exchange and so on suddenly the
open data from the internet
the last one is the commercial databases
i think a good resource sharing platform
should have several heretics
abundance in resources uh
a story authority authoritative
and reliable family in update
standardized
food in um
for data specialists
spec picture and the data organization
with the data and the semantics
okay it really can change the
and how theoretical data into
standardized
and available data facilitator
data management and the data quality
assessment
submitted the data into grid and sharing
semantic technology can deplete
diseased and nearly potential
or releasing zipper amount data
and that can be applied can be applied
to resource
retrieval resource recommendation data
association
data discovery etc we have also held
down some preliminary work
in the regard metadata standards has
been established
to standardize the data processing and
management
a communicative model of agriculture
information resource database
dataset is established by fully
considering
the metadata content necessary for data
content
data display data development etc
including include the title subject
object keyword type for provider
etc on the basis of
common metadata different data is
extended under either their own unique
metadata
fields so as to the metadata standard
of this business such as the science and
the technology projected database
implies the projector committed and unit
funding amount of projected time etc
and we direct 12 types of
metadata standards when resources
are collected on a platform they are
converted into standardized
data and stored into the database
through format conversation data
cleaning
with data attribute extend extraction
with data extension and other procedures
st course is adopted as the basic
vocabulary of
knowledge organization astikos is a
super vocabulary of
science technology edited by nstlcs
stscc mscs currently
st cost has collected more than 240
thousand
agricultural terms and more than 90
certain concepts
asti course is used in platform data
retrieval and the keyword extraction
challenges agricultural information
resources are limited
and the tennis agriculture information
resources
are many resources data formats
are varied and the most are not just
submitted
according to limited data standards
homemade
data qualities abstract keywords sims
etc are often missing are
often missing with data attributes arrow
on low level of automatic and artificial
intelligence in data cleaning metadata
attribute
extraction extension and other aspects
still need plenty of manual
participation
multi-legal problems platform including
includes
chinese english and other languages so
it is difficult
to achieve the unified resource
retrieval and the data association of
multiple languages
future plan carry out extensive
cooperation with more organization of
agricultural information resources
stronger the research and application
of ai technology in abstract
extensive extraction
automatic tagging of a keyword subject
class fixture and so on try to achieve
almighty language unified retrieval and
the intelligent
recommend recommendation and based on
our
work strengthen the research and
application of
semantic knowledge of analysis and
technology
and look forward to completing with our
peers
this is the end of my speech thank you
for your listening
thank you so much for our panelist in
beijing and i'm really sorry that she
couldn't make it
in any case if you have any question for
her
and for baths
all right sorry this is
yep so if you have any question a
specific question for
for her please uh don't don't don't
hesitate to write it
in the chat box i i could um
simply send this to them and i would
like to welcome
our next panelist um
this is uh meda de vara she is a senior
research fellow at ift this is the
international food policy research
institute
medal led's one of the three models of
the cgir platform for big data and
agriculture
spur heading efforts to operationalize
the fair principles towards
fundable accessible interoperable and
reusable
data across the cgir's 13 centers
thank you for being here medline over to
you
thanks emma and thanks to the organizers
for having me
let me know if you can't hear me clearly
or if you're
something goes awry with the screen
sharing but you should be able to see my
screen now hopefully correct
yes okay good good um
so i'm going to launch right in uh first
of all i'm going to acknowledge my
co-authors who could not be here uh so
thieris and pythagoras
from scio and they have helped us
uh greatly with this and a lot of what
i'm going to be talking about
is in fact thanks to them uh let me
start in with an introduction like the
others have given about cgir because i'm
not sure how many people know
uh that cgir is
a network of 15 research for development
centers focused mostly
in the global south it is the largest
global
agricultural innovation network and um
we so i mentioned the 15 centers we we
have a local presence in over 100
countries most of those countries
with gdps of less than a dollar a day
we've been around for most of most of
the centers have been around for about
50 years
and we have large networks of
partnerships um
we also have uh uh some of the
the work that we do is across uh our
gene banks which hold or are stewards of
um
a very large number of crop seed
essentially accessions is germ plasma
accessions
um so in a nutshell uh that's that's
really cgir
what what we focus on really is uh
poverty reduction particularly in rural
areas
um uh we work on on issues related to
food
food um security and and nutritional
security
and we try to do that in in a sort of a
an
environmentally sustainable way with
regard for
natural resource management um and
ecosystem services
um so so that's just to sort of set the
stage a little bit on what cgir
is uh as we work um
in our centers what we find is as
as everybody here has i think alluded to
is a
is an increasingly digitized and digital
agriculture so this is sort of a
conceptual model of a future farm
uh not not in the us or in europe but
actually in
africa somewhere or could be south asia
this is really where
um things are going very digital as many
of the speakers have mentioned
ai artificial intelligence and machine
learning
uh i come from the big data platform
where we have the technologies to be
deriving
um insights and solutions from data
large pools of data in fact
but to do that we need to be able to
find and access the data something
you've heard about in earlier
presentations as well we need to be able
to interpret that data not just as
humans but as machines as well
we increasingly need to be able to
aggregate large amounts of
related data sets and we we generally
need to be able to visualize
map and of course analyze that data to
derive insights from it
so that's kind of the the scenario that
we work in
and for the big data platform one of the
things that we're trying to do
is assume open uh open access to our
data our research data by default but
focus on fair data and i don't think i
need to go much more into what there is
um other people have mentioned this what
i'm
showing you here is sort of our kind of
overall approach to doing this
this is a schematic that shows uh the
the organized modules
uh uh efforts to make data open
and fair and and and so the heart of
this
is the guardian data discovery portal
which enables
um sort of wider discovery and use by
google data sets for instance
uh and other search engines uh by
external apps for
farmers and policy makers uh and and it
does that by harvesting metadata from a
number of different uh
repositories or data platforms and by
data here i mean both publications and
data
platforms so for cgir centers we have 15
centers as i said
uh that amounts to 30 odd repositories
because each center typically
tends to have unfortunately a one data
repository and one publications
repository
typically unlinked so you don't know
what
publication was built using what data
very often
so that's 30 repositories we're also
making data discoverable from usaid's
digital data library from what used to
be diffid
um and i can never remember what that
fcdo
stands for but it used to be diffid uh
the the the
british equivalent of usa roughly
speaking
we have some data and an increasing
amount of data and publications from the
world bank
uh we also make discoverable uh what
aaron talked about earlier usda usda's
ag data commons
and we have the genesis platform from
our uh gene banks which i've already
mentioned
um earlier we also have data and
publications
visible from the government of india's
open data portal
focusing primarily on the ag part of
that because there's much more there
um and there's a dataverse sitting
behind this uh for those who want to
upload their data
and for that we have built workflows to
comply with um
based on ontologies and control
vocabularies that that form the
standards so these workflows
we the fair workflows are intended to
generate data that's that's um
consistently described uh in terms of
the the semantics
of the data and then uh we're also
developing digital tools to collect data
that's already standards compliance
already built on ontologies and and and
such
um and of course the the the primary
piece of all of this is the so what you
can find data as a big deal
and here what i'm showing you is the the
sort of pipelines that we're building
out
uh to be able to analyze the data to
visualize it and explore it
both semantically as well as visually in
in maps and being able to query it that
way as well so
um just a quick view of what this looks
like uh this is a search done in
guardian on
on the terms here on nutrition women uh
the idea is i want to find
data on nutrition as it affects women so
i go to guardian i type in those
keywords and here you see a quick grab
which you see data coming from three of
our cgir centers if brielle re and sip
as well as fcdo which used to be diffid
uh
usaid's ddl data.gov and you may not be
able to see the bottom one which is the
world bank
um there are a number of publications
and data sets that are being discovered
here there's
different ways to filter uh across the
top
and and to to and to look at that data
here and of course i did i did mention
usda act data commons gene max
if you go further down this you're
likely to find data sets from
particularly from ag data commons not so
much from gene banks here
um so to do this to to be able to enable
this sort of view
um you you need somehow to harmonize a
number of different metadata schemas and
this is where
uh that a lot of the work uh that
pythagoras sensor theories do
particularly
for guardian uh comes into play so
guardian enriches
the native metadata that comes in from
uh
the repositories where the data sits uh
to enhance their fairness particularly
focusing on the findability and
accessibility um
so here's an example this is this is
from one of our centers
um uh uh this is a publication from one
of our centers simet
um and and here what what uh
what what was done when you look at this
particular uh the same publication
as it's viewed in guardian what what's
been done
is a sort of a standardization of the of
the
first name last name format of the
authors from what you see
here which is kind of you know mixed
it's
it's not a consistent format to a much
more consistent format
um and then also a deduping so so this
this same date this same publication is
available both from the
from the diffid um repository as well as
simmets repository we've deduped it and
made it
uh you know consistently available just
from this one place
if you go further down in that same
publication you see a set of keywords
and these keywords
um are both keywords that have been
input typically by
the the information and data managers uh
but as it's been enriched as well
uh by pulling from aggrovac as well as
ontologies
and so that's that's something that's uh
very powerful and enhances the
definability and accessibility of data
this is another example
uh which we showed you here uh a data
set from um
actually not a data set it's a
publication from acresat one of our
other centers
in india um and here you see um
an enhancement of of the resource
um using geonames so it's it's this was
something that was absent in the
original
uh publication sitting in the repository
uh the metadata enrichment uh algorithms
that are used by guardian allowed this
to to happen using calling on geonames
and the last example i want to uh give
you is is sort of
uh again the keywords that are enriched
here um
this is a data set now that's that's an
ikrisab dataset
uh again the center that's based in
india
and at the bottom of this you see a
keyword cloud um as you did before
in this case the the the words here
are drawn from both aggravated
ontologies the earlier example i showed
you was agrabox
um and and where the ontologies
particularly common to play
even sometimes they're behind the scenes
they're not necessarily
part of this cloud but but they very
much play a role
in making data further discoverable say
to google data
so it's quite important in in in making
the data
fair not only within guardian but much
beyond that increasing the
the the discoverability of uh data more
widely data assets more widely
so this is my last slide i just want to
talk quickly about some of the
challenges
that the team has faced um the scio team
and in enriching in in
in using these kinds of approaches and
of course one of them is is
harmonization in the in in the
harvesting and harmonization step so
here for cgir particular particularly we
we do use a consistent metadata data
schema that's
um a sort of a an extension of dublin
core
um but there are differences in
interpretation of labels and even if the
metadata schema used by
our our uh partners who we who we
harvest from
maps to to to dublin core um it it is a
difficult proposition as has been
referred to in earlier presentations
i talked a little bit about deduping
records um so that can be sort of a
uh you know we have to be careful about
doing that as well
uh the quality and the richness of
metadata uh
uh is both of them are quite highly
variable so
so that you know for instance um for
for uh in some instances you might see
words
in some in other instances you see
something close to sentences or
paragraphs
in the keywords field which makes it a
difficult proposition to know how to
deal with
um and then of course there's uh in in
in some for some records
um the the metadata uh
is quite rich and in others it's it's
very poor there
there are you know just the most basic
metadata available so
there the text mining approaches that
are used by our algorithms
are become even more important with
automated enrichment comes as sort of a
pitfall as well so there's
the potential for misinterpretation uh
for instance
i i came across a a data set a spatial
a data set about spatial data and they
talked in the
abstract about grid cells but that was
being interpreted by our algorithms as
cells
and so when you clicked on the on the
cells in the in that
cloud in the of the keywords what you
got what you saw was a bunch of stuff on
organismal you know the biological
equivalent of cells which is not what
this was about at all
so so there's a danger there as well and
then the the the one
you know does one size fit fit all and
it doesn't typically because here we're
talking largely about um
a variety of scales all the way from the
genetic to the landscape
um and in terms of disciplines all the
way from the genomics
to or the omics types of disciplines uh
to socioeconomics
to spatial data and there uh you know
it's it's always a sort of a tussle
um and and compromises are involved
in terms of the the metadata and
enriching that of course has its own
special
challenges and pitfalls as you can
imagine so that's
um pretty much all i wanted to say i
wanted to give you a flavor of how we
approach this
at cgir and i'm happy to take questions
later on
thank you thank you mida
um excellent so we move to our last
um presentation um
[Music]
and this is uh it's going to be
delivered by laura
medjularo is the team leader of the land
portal foundation
and she's responsible for the overall
management implementation and expansion
of the land portal
i will be passing the slides on behalf
laura just let me know laura when uh
you want me to move thank you emma
can you hear me yes thank you so much
um thank you for this opportunity first
of all i just wanted to say that
introduce also my colleague carlo tejo
who created these slides with me and we
will be
presenting uh together uh
thank you so much so next slide please
let me introduce
uh quickly who we are the lamport
foundation is a small
dutch non-profit organization
we've been working over the last 10
years to address
the extreme fragmentation of land data
providing a free and open information
uh for for a rather small community so
the land sector
uh the land governance sector is a very
specialized
sector within the agricultural domain um
and according to it so they have very
special needs so according to land
researchers and practitioners
so access to land is key for nutrition
and food security and increases
investment agricultural productivity
improves people live food so so access
to land is at the heart
of this small specialized community i'm
not
um i mean our
numbers are much smaller than those of
my previous colleagues but i
just wanted to uh let you understand
what what
what audience and what community we are
serving so when it comes to access to
data and information
it's proved to be very close close
sector the vast majority of
land governance data remains closed
fragmented poorly organized with poor
metadata and
many times with no metadata at all so
they're representing
if you search for land information on
the web you you can find
only few information providers so this
means a very narrow range of
perspectives
and content to keep to be published in a
way that is not
doesn't facilitate discovery discovery
engagement and reuse
so because land is a cross-cutting
issue and very um politicized
so analyzing land governance often means
looking at not only different data types
but also diff across different domains
so
it also involves
looking at different data stakeholders
so not only academia
so research data but also the data
provided by governments um civil society
or private sector
um data providers so different
with different degrees of data
capabilities
so our response to this extreme
extreme fragmentation and accessibility
of information
is twofold so on one hand we develop
an archer a multilingual platform
lanportal.org
that hosts a wide range of
um organized country issuing data set
pages where we aggregate and pull
content data of different types such as
bibliographic
data statistical indicators
spatial layers we create a repository of
experts and sector organizations media
content
especially from southern countries and
on the other hand
we try to build capacity data capacity
in the sector and also um
a data infrastructure so in a few years
the lan port has become a leading online
destination for data and information in
the sector
so we have three main systems
we have a geoportal that aggregates
spatial layers
a drupal website that aggregates
bibliographic data a media content
and a triple store for statistical data
for the purpose of this presentation
we will mainly focus on the land library
that is a drupal
instance where we maintain and create a
repository
of land governance related resources
pulled from multiple sources
in which the metadata mapped to semantic
standards
so next slide please this is our
lan library so it includes again
for us this is a big number and 61
500 selected resources but i recognize
that is a very small number compared to
previous repositories but is
this content is either published
directly by our community of users or
ingested through automatic
importers most are metadata
but sometimes we we upload the the pdf
the resource as well
so as as you can see is is a very a
small
and repository that select content for a
specialized
community of uh experts speaking
different languages from different
geographies so we pull resources from
a number of different sources
and improve the quality of native
metadata
and the same time we also encourage
partners to
publish metadata and better metadata
so in our library we adopt a customized
version of the
meaningful bibliographic metadata m2b
to provide users even more
information about the the resources that
exist in them in the library so this
um custom adjustments to the
m2b um
include for instance making some fields
mandatory such as the
the subject field and
mainly because we also create um
a a semantic set of
controlled vocabulary on land which is
part of other vocab we'll explain in a
few minutes
so we also assure the quality of this
metadata by including license language
geographical focus that is very
important for our audience
and for the value of the metadata fields
we use
standard codes such as the the the
eso 300 100 3160 c's
one alpha three codes for countries or
the unm
49 code for areas and regions
and as i said before for the subjects
we use agrovoc and in particular
um a sub
schema of agrowork called lanvok is a
small
300 set of
keywords or concept highly relevant to
the small sector
that we serve and so we contributed
developing landmark and maintaining
landform within agroc up to my colleague
now that explains
the data flow thank you very much
so in the next slide
so here uh in this slide i want to show
you
how data flow when we import information
from some parties into the lan port
so at the beginning we have the sources
sources that could be very different
from mono generated
excel file that follows a structure that
is shared in the in the lamp portal
website
to adjacent respond from
cms as wordpress uh or
xml respond from a dspace for instance
the
dsps api so we have this
as the source in the b in the middle we
we have
what we call the importers that are
piece of software
that mapping the map to things
we need to map the fields itself so a
field in the source will be
filled in the in the lampportal
metadata it could be some of them
and also we need also to to map the
values
because we are using several closed
lists
in the ram portal and we need to do some
kind of mapping between the two
the two values and finally in order to
ingest this information into the lamp.
that is a drupal website
we use the fit important feature
and during this whole process during the
whole process
there are tasks of data correlation so
if we
we see that there is an issue with with
the metadata or with a value
we contact directly our partners our
the data providers in order to raise
this potential issue
something that is important to highlight
that it's in
in the land portal we are trying to not
uh host
pdfs we are not trying to host the
publications we are
always trying to point back to the
source
and we only try to collect the metadata
not the pdfs so in the next slide
we can see some of the challenge that we
are we are facing
as uh my previous colleagues mentioned i
think that is
more or less the same that
we have very different sources so
as as we need to deal with different uh
sources
um some common challenges arise
so the first thing is to find relevant
relevant information
because our sector is really small so
trying to find information is
is not easy after that it was
okay this source is is interesting i
have relevant
information so what can we do how many
documents
this source have so if there are
too many maybe we can go to a machine
approach
working with some kind of software uh
python importers or maybe we need just
to to fill
uh the metadata and spreadsheet and
ingest it
and uh well the cms is that
[Music]
the content management systems that are
behind
the organizations the data providers are
very different in terms of
of the cms itself or maybe it could be
an html page
and also the version and
working with different cms and different
versions
make us to change the approach
each time and also the type of
format the data format of the source
could be like
rtf csv xml
json files ris very different
also the metadata mapping we need to do
one by one
okay this field imagine that
in the sort we have um a dc
contributor maybe in our website
could be or should be a an author we
need to do this kind of mapping and also
the data values
um another challenge that we have
is the multilingualism mainly
for the data creation because we can
start more or less
some languages but other languages are
out of the scope and sometimes
you don't know if there is a problem or
not
in the in the quality of the data
last to mention is that we use a lambok
as for tagging the content and not only
for tagging the content we are
also using uh lamvok that is a subset
of a concept of aggro block also for
harvesting in order to find
relevant sources so trying to map
sometimes
uh the source to this lamborgh is a
challenge
and now i give back the floor to my
colleague laura next slide please
so to conclude uh we learned that
what we learned over the past 10 years
is this is a very
challenging sector because it's
absolutely
fragmented fragmented data information
is is highly fragmented
and enclosed in silas so what we usually
recommend to our data partners
is to to have an an openness default
mindset and follow
fur principle so the capacity
development is as important as
maintaining and creating
common open repositories we
recommend to use standards in data any
metadata
to show the data metadata model
um establish channel 4 for continued
feedback and collaboration with our
partners
is more a partnership rather than
serving uh uh kind of
an audience but one of the most
important lessons
that we learned over the past years is
that collaboration is key
so collaborating with like-minded
organizations like those that are
sitting in this panel
today in the sector is is very important
joining forces to improve accessibility
of scientific literature
promoting the use of standards spread
best practices
promote and build capacity development
and and also another key lesson is
building on what
already exists without reinventing
things like reusing existing semantic
vocabularies for instance
and build communities of practice around
uh
those standards to the help improving
constantly improving
and promoting them this this is very
important is one of the
most important lessons i wanted to share
thank you very much
thank you laura and thank you so much
carlos
so i think that we are and thank you to
all the panelists i think that you did a
great job
it's uh six to six
here in in the european eastern time i
presume it's 1206
in washington dc so uh thank you so much
to all of you so we kind of start now
what we call the questings and answers
um
i haven't seen too many questions from
the audience
um but i will encourage you once again
that if you have
any um any kind of
yeah question to to for any of the
panelists please
use the chat box and
we will answer as soon as possible in
the meantime
i have some questions for you for
all our panelists and i was
i would like to put them on the table
and perhaps
to have a kind of a round and to know a
little bit what
all of you think about um i mean
these these topics i think that in some
cases you already
mentioned uh how crucial to recommend
and and to promote good practices is um
are let's say in in our domain as much
as
it happens as well in other domains but
what recommendations specifically you
think that we could
provide to organizations and
to enhance this visibility of their
resources through the improvement of the
quality of metadata what kind of steps
would you suggest more specifically that
we could do
to help them or what you would recommend
to them
in laura you were very specific in your
presentation right now
talking about a specific community that
you are targeting
so maybe do you want to expand a little
bit more what you mentioned before
about this kind of recommendations that
you are preparing for for instance
workshops or
um publications videos
yes of course as i mentioned the
building capacities
um goes hand in hand with building the
the sector infrastructure
so on one hand we work with the the
agribook team
to develop landvoc as part of the
general infrastructure
and then on the other hand will build
capacity through
moocs workshops or tutorials for
people to improve their knowledge
management capacity with their data
management capacity so we encourage them
to you to to create metadata to enrich
their metadata to
expose their metadata in the right way
to use standards in their metadata
fields
um that's and again building a community
that supports those
best practices is is very important
um from from different uh sectors so in
in the landmark community of experts for
instance we
welcome um leaders from civil society
organizations or
a representative of government
organizations or researchers
from universities so all with different
needs and
slightly different perspectives but we
won core
idea in mind that the sharing data is
very important
to improve land governance thank you
thank you laura amita would you like to
add something about
lessons learned on these sites uh from
her experience a lot of experience with
researchers and cgir
yeah yes i can tell you
a few things um i'll keep my remarks
clean though
um so so i i like what laura said i mean
i think it's really important to work
um within the community uh a community
and across
communities so one of the things that
we're doing is is to work uh within
communities of practice
uh and that helps to train and build
capacity within our own communities of
practice in this case
uh it could be data managers and
information specialists across cgir
but more broadly even beyond cgir so so
anything that we do
uh will be open to to others as well
um part of this focuses around capacity
building as laura mentioned a lot of it
is also about culture change so with
when you're working with researchers
um you know the the i was going to
mention the third thing which is tools
and services but really the biggest
rub is the culture um and that's what
you have to change
um and and to do that there there are
multiple ways in which we we're trying
to do that one is to
to to build the capacity to to build the
the
tools um to to answer the question of
what's in this for me
that the researchers need to sort of
effectively understand and
and respond to um and basically to
incentivize
the the proper annotation and the proper
handling the proper management
of our data assets why you know more
broadly speaking
um that takes many forms it could be
through uh you know how researchers are
rewarded let's get away from the model
where
people are rewarded only for you know
high impact factor publications this is
a message we're consistently trying to
push out
um how are you managing your data how
fair is the data we've got metrics now
to
kind of you know put a quantitative
stamp on how fair data is so that you
can start to now incentivize it more
broadly through
um annual evaluations for instance off
researchers of scientists
um be you know putting in place rewards
having data sprints that that our
data managers and information
specialists organize on our pretty
routine level
uh hackathon you know pureathons they
call them data curatons and and data
sprints where
researchers are able to come in spend
two hours or half a day
with very much hands-on uh you know help
to make to annotate their data assets
better so these are all pieces that we
need to put in place
combined with the tools and the services
such as the fair workflows that i
mentioned earlier which will help
um researchers in the agricultural space
particularly annotate their data
consistently
and very easily uh the idea is to make
it easy and
and you know let let researchers uh you
know be able
to to do that that way so many different
approaches
i would say i see aaron agreeing with
all the things that you're saying
erin would you like to say something
else about that yes
um that's the incentivization just
trying to convince people
to produce better metadata is is huge
because when you're uploading data files
if you don't have good metadata you
don't know what that is and no one can
reuse it and a lot of times
researchers they're so strapped for time
that they don't it's an
afterthought metadata's an afterthought
and then at that point
once they get their publication they
they're just scrambling to go on to the
next thing and so we're trying to build
it into
the process so that it's maybe more from
the beginning
like with the usda first of all we are
now
um required to have data management
plans
so they have to start thinking about
where they're going to put their data
and how they're going to share their
data
and all of that what what they're going
to produce what standards they're going
to use
at the beginning before they even get
the grant and so
that is we're hoping that that helps to
increase
just they're thinking about it that
they're they're thinking about it
they're coming up with that plan and
that it's built into their culture it is
a culture change
and you know unless it's in
unfortunately in those cases unless it's
mandated a lot of people won't do it
because they
don't have the time and they look at
that metadata form
and then the other the other step is for
us to make it
more accessible for them so they see a
huge metadata form and they get
intimidated and we are also offering
webinars and and tutorials and
one-on-one sessions and group sessions
to help
educate people and take the take the
shock
out of it when they see that
right you can may add just one word i
what airing is saying about culture
is absolutely important so the the the
idea of
sharing data is absolutely an attitude
and we notice
that people for instance they don't
think about the license of their data
and if they don't put any license that's
that's close by default
so but they don't put the license just
because they don't think about it not
just
not because sometimes they don't want to
share the data so it's really
changing the attitude of how people
deal with data and they don't think
about
sharing a data management plan before
they start working on a publication when
they finish a publication they think
their job is
done and and they don't realize that if
they don't
share it they don't make it open then
it's not really useful right
37 whether you would like you had a
specific dislike about all these but i
don't know whether you would like to add
something more
yes i would like to add something i
really agree about
uh the reach the asking for rich
metadata and especially
to make that available but i want to
add something about the technology so i
think that in this sector we are
very late we are still talking about uh
sharing the data and making data
available while that should be given for
granted
tim berners-lee 20 years ago was talking
about
publishing your data make raw data
available and so over
now we live in the area of uh the
technology
so what we should really think is not
only sharing the data but it's
sharing the data in a way that machines
can do a better job with the data so for
example using standard metadata
properties of course allows the machine
to better understand what's going on
without using very sophisticated
algorithms that need training datasets
and
specialized id knowledge then for
example also relying on vocabularies
existing vocabularies or aligning your
vocabulary
with existing vocabularies can help of
course connecting
resources can help data discover you can
update a representation
so the usage of vocabulary is uri so
once there are alignments then
we solve a lot of issues with
understanding the meaning of the data
with the possibility to link things
together
uh and then when you publish the data
for example on a website
the possibility to annotate pages with
schema.org
and using metadata so that search
engines can understand
what's going on in your website or if
you have an api
like document your api in a machine
readable way or using tools like
swagger so overall i
understand that we have 20 years of
delay because
we still have to face with problems
related to
making that available while we should
address
the next step the next series of
problems like
making data available for machines so to
solve a lot of other issues that we have
now
right right carlos i don't know whether
you would i
like to to say something about what
febreze was mentioning i saw that you
were
listening very carefully or yes
um yeah just
i was thinking about uh we were talking
about a lot about reinventing the wheel
all the time that we don't reinvent the
wheel
but we're thinking more about not
tripping on the same stone
and we are facing the same challenge
the same different people in several
places
so maybe something that to think about
is to have a kind of session about what
are the
lesson learned and what are the
the the actually the the the
the issues that arises in in every kind
of integration
because i think that fabricio and i we
we get the same errors from different
places
um sometimes you have this lesson
learned somewhere
you you will overcome this
these issues faster
right so this brings me to another
question that is more about
a suggestion so because i see that
we all have the same problems in a very
similar way so i'm just
thinking what um what kind of next steps
we could take as leaders of
of of important information systems in
agricultural sciences
to join forces to to really uh
um work on um
together to to to to um
to let's say overcome with this this
these challenges or
there is any activity do you think that
we there is any kind of uh
um context where you think that we could
simply make sure that there is this
duplication that even
carlos is mentioning in another area but
in general that we are
finding ourselves in different areas
could be shared lessons learned sharing
standardization of data i'm so i would
have walked all over the place so
what makes me very happy since uh
eventually
i'm the aggravate manager and i'm
working as well with nalt
to map both vocabularies so this is very
very uh important at the moment but
there is any anything that you think
that we could um work together i know
that for instance
uh if i was working with laura in doing
capacity development activities we are
supporting
uh the alarm portal as much as we can
also
with inl we are working on this mapping
i was mentioning with nida
we are also working in some some areas
related to mapping ontologies in cir and
et cetera et cetera
this one of some of the areas but do you
have anything else in mind that you
could
you think that we could do together to
improve this situation
that we put on the table today i have a
thought about that and it actually
relates in part to something someone
just typed in the chat
about dealing with rigorous standards
and metadata standards for
different subject areas and that's one
challenge that we have we're dealing
with genomics data and life cycle
assessment data and
geospatial data and it's all ag related
but in the ag cross example that i
showed in my
in my slide may be finding ways to find
where the subject specific um people are
keeping their data
and finding ways to standardize it in
order to make it more findable but then
to point back
so that they don't have to necessarily
conform to one standard and i think
medha
mentioned this in her presentation that
we can't
it you can't make one one size fits all
it doesn't
and so what we should be doing is trying
to figure out
who's searching what are they trying to
accomplish and then
getting together and figuring out how we
can facilitate that so whether it's
using a standard vocabulary to integrate
into one platform that people can search
and then go off into their subject
specific
maybe something to something like that i
mean we do that to a lesser degree i
mean we're focusing on u.s
united states data usda data
specifically but
um some of you are aggregating what we
collect and so
if we can feed into that i would love to
know
what would make it easier as you're
taking in our data to make it more
discoverable you know on a larger
platform right
okay do you have
[Music]
any other comments mida falizio laura
carlos
i mean one of the things that occurs to
me is here we have you know some of the
pr
you know fairly some fairly important
platforms in in
agriculture um and repositories and we
could rope in a few others perhaps world
bank for instance in a and a couple of
other entities
uh but it would it would perhaps be
helpful to together
develop um a framework or a set of
principles that
that we stamp with with our presence
essentially with our organizational uh
presence
and and float out there as as sort of
guidelines
um along with attached tools that that
people can choose from it doesn't have
to be your tool or my tool we don't have
to choose among them but we
we make make it possible for people to
not only see what what
best practice really might be or is
really but but also how do i actually
make it simple for me you want me to do
this tell me how to do it and i'll do it
you know that that sort of approach
needs to be uh could could perhaps be
helpful
um the other thing i would say is you
know in terms of incentivization one of
the things that we're doing
um that that i'm trying to figure out
how
this group could work um together on is
one of the things we're trying to do is
show researchers what the value is
of well-described data what can data
science do for you
and so one of the you know one of the
sort of the small projects that the big
data platform funded through the
organized module
is uh you know answering the broad
question of you know is fertilizer
used really really um profitable
in africa we all go with the assumption
that it actually increases yields but
does it actually
uh translate to profit and if so where
and so this was done
using guardian uh they you know the
researchers a team of three
primary researchers found uh 200 data
sets in guardian
760 locations and they were able to put
you know
uh use machine learning over this kind
of data pool this these data points
um to derive some insight and and
actually found that it's not always
um you know even where yields are very
high profits can be very low because it
depends of course
as you might expect on on uh market
value of the
of the crop on on the price of
fertilizer etc so
being able to pool all of these data and
spatially
you know identify where where
fertilizer is useful it's one of the key
things that we you know that's that's a
key question
for for um african agriculture and and
we can do that
uh and and once researchers see this
kind of thing being done
they get really excited about it so can
we then uh you know with these growing
data pools
come up with these kinds of use cases
that would be very interesting i think
in terms of changing hearts and minds
right yeah
yeah well yep right sorry all right
oh no this uh this example is uh it's
very it's very nice and i think that
this is the last uh
step of the chain because as far as i
see now there are two
two two different groups so there are
the producers of the data
and as we are saying we cannot oblige
them to use a common standard a common
format
they produce the data they can produce
it what we can do as aggregators
and agress is doing already that but we
can always do it better
is to do capacity development with them
when we receive the data with
wrong metadata and in the wrong places
so for example there is the
alternative title and you find there the
journal title
you have to tell them that this is this
is not working
so this is the the first thing that we
can do
work with the producer of the data and
help them to produce something better
all the rest
is up to us so uh the harmonization of
the data the media enrichment and we
have to
to do an effort sometimes we're going to
do a joint effort because everybody has
their own way to to to be funded
so we are also guided by
what we find outside but what we could
do is to
[Music]
to work together to like recommendations
that we can use
uh that we can use all together when
it's time to urbanize the data when it's
time to
give some not truths but recommendations
to publish the data
and to make that available because then
at that point there is the third step
that meta was saying and
all this will help the usage of the data
to discover
to create new knowledge and to this to
discover new things
but as aggregators we have a
responsibility to guide the data
providers
and between us even if uh there can be
like uh
political and institutional problems to
to at least
write down some guidelines that we can
all follow
well we belong to a very small um
community so we always
we always had major
uh benefits from collaboration
collaborating with other
aggregators and within a wider
sector like the agriculture sector i
certainly welcome the idea of developing
common tools or guidelines facilitates
to facilitate interoperability and raise
awareness
and and to me is is also a matter of
making um i mean one of the incentives
for instance
in my opinion is really demonstrate what
the consequences of a closed data
environment
are what a close date environment will
look like and
why a more um interoperable
uh this environment is is than the more
democratic
so this is a kind of the um the argument
that we bring
to the table all the times is
making data visible interoperable means
making the data landscape more
democratic
and diverse we are almost
finishing the panel session but i just
realized that there is a question for
meta
that says can you say more about your
metrics for how fair
the data is
yeah so um i i saw that and i pulled up
uh i'm sharing my screen again just to
show you how we do this
um so so this is the the guardian
landing page guardian.bigdata.cgr.org
if you go to about guardian or if you do
a search
in guardian um every every resource
you'll see a fair metrics uh linked to
and and
you can go to sorry to analytics here
and when you go to analytics you see
something about
um you know fairness across particularly
across cgir
but you can go to view metrics here and
it tells you a little bit about how
we're actually scoring for fare and and
basically what that amounts to is that
we're using
um if i click on that download the
the the guide we've got a guide here a
step-by-step sort of blow-by-blow guide
on how you get to zero from zero to
level five
for bo for all of these things for f a i
and r
um so this is what we've tried to use in
in terms of how we score
uh it's built on the on the netherlands
uh archive for
its dance i can never remember what it
stands for it's somewhere here
permanent access to digital research
resources dance
roughly translated so we've used their
metrics to to develop these algorithms
and so each data asset in guardian is
scored
that way we're changing our our
interface so you'll see something like
this now
with a very large data management
toolkit and if you go to that
to that toolkit um at the very bottom
for instance you you'll see
you can browse them and so if you go to
data curation you'll see the fair data
guidelines here
and the fair data workflow uh will be
available soon as well there
in another couple of weeks thank you so
much meda
this brings us to the end of this
session
i would really like to thank to all the
panelists
for such a nice one hour and a half
i have really enjoyed to list listening
to all of you
and i hope that attendees also enjoyed
this
um this session as well as you have seen
this is just the beginning of something
else and we hope
that perhaps in another time we will uh
talk more about what we we are going to
do together
as we were putting on the table today so
thank you to everybody thank you as well
for the organizes of dc and i and
for giving to us this opportunity is
very