well i think today i'm uh trying to get some\h
work done on this farm gate i uh kind of started\h\h
looking at it the other day as to what needs to\h
get salvaged and you know what's gonna work going\h\h
forward with it do i even have enough pieces\h
to salvage and i think at this point there's\h\h
probably enough pieces left over where i can\h
fasten it together get it built the proper way
so i think we're gonna start working on that
well after going through all the material i\h
have more than enough for what i want to do\h\h
which worked out pretty nice i was a little bit\h
worried the truck hit the fence pretty hard so it\h\h
actually uh it split the original two gates into\h
four gates and uh so once i got a look at that\h\h
and got it all cut up um i i think i have enough\h
here to do the two small gates that i want to do\h\h
heck i might even be able to save some of this\h
stuff and uh maybe for some future projects or\h\h
something but we'll just have to wait and\h
see how that goes so for now i'm going to\h\h
focus on just making these two small gates um\h
the original gates i think were either eight\h\h
foot or ten foot i can't remember exactly but\h
uh these are going to be a little bit smaller\h\h
i think the overall dimension of each gate is\h
going to be about 45 inches or so so we'll get\h\h
cutting up and measuring on this stuff and start\h
figuring out where all the welds are going to be
well we made it to the halfway point uh\h
one's done so got one more to go but so\h\h
far it's going pretty good uh we'll get after\h
it and uh hopefully wrap this thing up soon
well i just spent 10 minutes looking for\h
my earplugs and uh they're around my neck\h\h
so that's good time well spent
let's talk about these welds i'm not a\h
professional welder i i don't have any formal\h\h
training and being a welder i had a few repairs\h
i wanted to do around here so i went on amazon\h\h
about 100 welder and uh watched a few\h
youtube videos these welds aren't going\h\h
in any museum anytime soon they don't\h
need to be perfect it's for a fence\h\h
as long as they hold together i'll\h
be happy so i encourage you if\h\h
you have something you want to fix around the\h
house or you want learn how to weld you know 100\h\h
isn't that much to spend to get started uh watch\h
some youtube videos there's a lot of guys on\h\h
here that know what they're talking about and uh\h
you too can do pretty crappy welds just like me
so