best for soil soil health practical
information hi i'm saskya a healthy soil
is good for the productivity and
qualitative crops we're here in Swift
abount we're just the preparations are
being taken to sow agreement or one of
the ways to make and keep a soil healthy
soil health is the ability of the soil
to cope with incoming diseases and pests
and keep their population levels
sufficiently low so that crops do not
suffer damage a healthy soil ecosystem
contains a rich soil biodiversity
sufficient amounts of soil organic
matter microorganisms nematodes
anthropods and earthworms key
microorganisms are bacteria fungi and
protozoa they are especially abundant in
the area next to the plant roots where
they interact in numerous ways soil
organic matter is the basis for
productive soils it allows for more
activity and diversity of life in the
soil which in turn stimulates soil
processes that contribute to healthy
crops soil microbes stimulated by
organic matter can suppress pathogenic
microorganisms liberate mineral
nutrients and improve the soil aggregate
stability the best practice to increase
soil organic matter is by adding already
stabilized organic matter such as
compost to the soil many agricultural
practices can help the soil ecosystem to
function optimal and to build up soil
health the more practices are combined
the greater is the potential effect on
soil health preventative practices such
as cover crops promote beneficial soil
life which in turn contributes to
healthy crops here we see a good example
of a combination of two best practices
cover crops and anaerobic soil
disinfestation asd
crops such as italian ryegrass can be
incorporated into the soil for example
to build up soil organic matter and to
improve the soil structure when combined
with anaerobic soil disinfestation the
soil environment is temporarily turned
anaerobic certain microorganisms are
stimulated to grow and under anaerobic
conditions they produce substances that
are suppressive or toxic for several
soil-borne pests and diseases in this
way cover crops cycle nutrients and
build up soil organic matter while the
soil gets disinfected through the asd
practice solarization is a similar
technique in solarization the soil is
covered with a plastic film to trap
solar radiation heating the soil to a
temperature that kills diseases and
pests in bio solarization the speed of
the process is increased by the
incorporation of organic amendments or
composts by understanding the soil
ecosystem and how practices above and
below ground effect them we can benefit
from their functions to increase soil
health
you