foreign
[Music]
hi welcome to another episode on this
Frosty morning we're already on year
four of pruning my apple trees my three
apple trees
now there's a few things I want to
mention before we get going because
these videos do tend to be fairly long
one is you don't have to watch the other
three episodes or parts necessarily it's
just that there's more examples there
plus you get to see the natural
progression over the years which is
pretty fun or if you want like I said
more examples then they're there for you
I'll put them up in the cards here
second is it's going to be pruned to all
of my trees are going to be pruned to a
modified central leader now I have a
video separately for that as well put it
up in the cards and I just go into much
more detail if I had to include that
here the video would just be far too
long and number three
if you mess up if you feel like you made
a wrong cut or whatever don't worry too
much about that it's a good thing about
trees and shrubs and things is that
they're alive and they keep growing so
you can always correct your mistake next
year as long as you don't completely
butcher it to death then you know have
it die on you as long as that doesn't
happen I think you'll be okay so that
said let's get to the first three all
right so this is the first tree that I'm
gonna be pruning
and you can start at one of two
places either you start in your main
scaffold
where you start at your top scaffold I'm
not too concerned with the top scaffold
I mean I have to select out some
branches
but overall I don't have to reduce a
height or anything
I'm pretty happy with it
so I'm going to start with the main
scaffold because that is just way too
many branches here I've definitely got
to simplify this down quite a bit
I also like to try and keep my bottom
branch
and the topmost branch which in this
case I would consider it to be this one
just so that there's plenty of space in
between each branch in the middle there
you get the only other consideration is
that with the lowest Branch you want to
make sure that you have plenty of trunk
you don't want it to be like all the way
on the bottom maybe like a third of the
way up or something
that should be good
so that spot right there is actually
quite nice
so this right here is my topmost branch
which is fine there's nothing really
wrong with it
this one however is not as great I just
don't like this weird vertical Branch
coming up so quickly after it starts
going because ideally you have it kind
of come out like a 45 degree angle and
then slowly
kind of arch up which this one isn't
really doing that either
kind of comes out kind of weird and then
it kind of goes down a little bit which
a lot of my branch on the street do that
but overall it just doesn't look as good
there's also this weird Jordan Branch
coming out
so I might as well just prune that off
first because it's
sticking your right in your eye
and then I'm going to prune this off
that Crow really wants to be heard
he'd like to ideally have a branch space
or Bud space in between each branch
and what I mean by that is essentially
just either if the if there was a bud
right here and it wasn't a branch I'd
like to have that in between
the next Branch down below or above it
so if I remove this one then I'd achieve
that goal
because I know be this space in between
these two main branches that I'm keeping
so start with that
when you're pruning you want to leave a
bit of your branch collar which is where
the branch thickens
don't damage that
leaving the branch collar will allow it
to heal over better so I'm going to
break my own rule pretty early on
already I'm gonna make an exception for
this one because I quite like it the
only thing I'm going to take off is the
part right here that's rubbing up
against the house and leave this
vertical one since it's at the tip I
don't mind it
on the next set of branches I already
pruned a branch off over here you can
just see the little
the little swelling the branch collar
right here so that's good there's
already space in between this one and
that one here there's only one thing I
want to change on this Branch here so
let me show you that this Branch it's
got this fairly weird Fork thing going
on I don't particularly like that I want
it to be focusing its growth on the
upper portion so I'm just going to
remove this lower portion and that's
pretty much all I'm going to do to that
again leave a little Branch the bench
collar there
just like so
and that'll do it for that Branch see
the guy up there
it's been there for hours
I think he's here to stay
it has been several hours now
because there were just far too many
interruptions
but it looks like it's died down a
little bit so uh let's keep going back
here is a branch node that I or a branch
that I removed last year but the note is
still there so there's a good spacing in
between these two branches here but as
you can already tell these two branches
are directly competing and so one of
them has to go I'd like to keep my
lowest Branch it's flowing out fairly
decently so I'm just gonna go with this
Branch here
uh that'll also free up this little area
in the middle here as well so let's just
remove that now
leaving that Branch caller intact
like that there's only a couple things
left to do so the first thing is you can
see that this branch is really long way
too long in fact
it's also kind of a fork I guess because
you got another one coming off here this
Branch this branch is fine curls up
quite nicely
well with this one I just wanna
bend it over so it effectively comes out
straight from the trunk
and I also want to prune it back because
it is so long to a breath to a bud at
least but in this case it looks like
it's a little fruit bud
that grows more upright so I can start
start to curve up
kind of like what's happened here but it
just happened too far down
and it also ended up drooping quite a
bit so I'm just going to tie it up for
this time around so first thing
pruning it to this butt here a fruit
spur it's not a vegetative bud so there
goes
the next two cuts are just to bring it
back in a little bit more and also just
to kind of remove weird branches because
you look at this one
so bizarre but it has a branch that kind
of grows up it's vegetative which is
good
like the fact that this is a fruit Bud
means it's not going to start curving up
as as much but we'll see what happens
with that
but this one is vegetative
so I'm just going to remove this lower
weird branch
all the way back
to that one there
and then the other one has a weird Fork
coming out if you remember a lot if
you've watched last year's video I
removed several of these another one
formed so I'm just going to remove this
one as well and it'll end up in a fruit
Bud which is not ideal I'd rather have
this be a vegetative bud but for now
this will do coming in on an angle there
and snip it off so that's looking
much more manageable now
the next thing I'm going to do is just
remove
kind of what I did down below but just
leave essentially a
Branch note or butt space in between so
like I'm going to remove this one is
this is the top right here
so I'm going to remove that one
to give the one back there space
I'm going to remove this one to give
this one up here space
because these are all fruit buds I'm not
really worried about leaving those
so I'm just going to leave those where
they're at
that Branch caller
the next one
I will just remove this one as well
because I have plenty of branches down
below if I ever need to replace it so
that's looking a lot better I am very
pleased with that
before we move on
there's a fruit Bud down below here
but there's a branch that comes out
right here that's trying to compete with
the main leader I don't want that so I'm
just going to remove that branch and try
not to damage the fruit bud that's right
beside it which is actually
a separate Branch so see if I can do
this without damaging up fruit Bud
beside it
all right there we go free Bud's still
intact
that looks a lot better
with the next treat there really isn't
that much that I've got to do
as far as the lower scaffold goes
because it's pretty much all done in
previous years
like for instance
this Branch here was removed last year
and then these two branches now have
plenty of space
there's a butt over here so this one has
plenty of space same thing with this one
and then there's a fruit bud I'm just
gonna let that do its thing
so nothing too crazy
honestly in the main scaffold the only
thing I want to do
is just pruning back this long squiggly
part it's just way too long
honestly I would like to remove it even
further than what I'm going to but for
now I'm just going to prune it back
probably
to this fruit butt over here
and we have a lot of other options I
thought about going back to this one
because this is also fruit bud so I will
lose a couple fruit buds
but that's okay I'm gonna prune it back
to here for now so here we go
that really just leaves the top scaffold
here and as you can see there's a lot of
branches so one of the first things that
I like to do is just identify which
branches you like the most
for instance for me
this Branch here I really like
it competes with the top which is that
Branch there that leader that's the
leader there
so getting branch that compete with it
will help keep it small or manageable I
suppose
same thing with this one I like that one
a lot as well
and then the one in the back it comes
out a little weird which I don't like
but of all the branches this one is a
pretty good one as well
and they all go their own
Direction I also really like this one
but um I'm probably gonna have to remove
it unfortunately because you can see
it's either this one or that one and I
like them both so that way you got to
make choices
the top scaffolds all that's left
and I'm going to first remove fairly
obvious branches that I know I want to
remove so for instance I have this
branch that is essentially the same as
this one but this one is just far
stronger and I like it a lot better
so I'm just going to remove that one
small one
leave the little Branch collar there
that can come off
so that leaves space for this larger one
here
and then I'm going to remove this small
one here because I don't need that
either
like so
which leaves space
for this one back here the next is that
fairly major Branch here
leave the branch collar intact
and snip now the other one I want to do
is this one here it's a vegetative
branch
so I'm just gonna
open that off and I'll leave this one
for now I'll leave
uh this one and that one it's not really
hurting anything so
those branches can stay
all right so the last thing on the
agenda for this tree is to Simply remove
the height a little bit on it because
it's it's fairly tall a little bit too
tall even for me
and this branch in particular kept
getting caught underneath the garage
door here so I'd really like to reduce
that
so let's start with that
now I'm going to remove them or prune
them down to these fruit buds here
so first
take it out of that
that means it probably won't get too
much taller than what they are
but it's all right and on here I kind of
want to keep them fairly equal so I've
got a bud
just right there which means I'm
essentially pruning off last year's
growth
and the whole Branch here is loaded with
fruit buds so that's kind of nice
just like that
I'm gonna prune it back to that one
there
I don't mind this being still the
tallest
and then lastly this one doesn't look
like it has fruit buds on it until quite
a bit lower down
um
I mean I kind of want to remove at least
a tip of it
so bring it down to the same Heights
maybe down to there
just a tip mostly all right so it's the
next day now yesterday I was just doing
the interruptions between the kids
playing it ended up riding for a while
and then there was also landscapers out
there with leaf blowers and things like
that just making way too much noise so I
had to count it yesterday but we're
gonna go back out there and finish up
that last tree all right so there it is
it is raining currently looks like it's
picking up a little bit actually
we should still be fine to finish it up
but we probably shouldn't dildo too long
all right so as far as the lower
scaffold there really isn't a whole lot
that I would change the only thing that
I did do is to the branch that I like is
I tied it up
so that
it comes up a little bit more and it
doesn't stick out so much
I may end up removing
this vertical Branch here maybe both not
sure yet
but yeah that's really the only thing I
would do to it
the other Branch I like as well
the only thing I don't like is how there
isn't a butt space or Branch note in
between these two branches that's a
little unfortunate but there isn't much
I can do about it yet I don't really
have a lot of options
so maybe a future years when some of
these develop I would change that out
and there's a lot of
fruit buds on here so I just kind of
want to leave that this year
yeah like I said next year that might
change so you're looking at the main
scaffold right now the top scaffold to
be exact and this right here that's my
leader which I like
this one beside it I also like
but then you notice
I kind of want to remove this one right
because you want to keep a space in
between every single Branch or butt
space Branch note in between every
single branch
but this one also happens to be
essentially the same as this one here
however this one has fruit buds all over
it and um it's just a better more
developed Branch than this one is
obviously this one is a lot smaller so
this one is definitely going to be
removed in favor of that one so let's
start with that
let's come in leaving our Branch collar
like so
and then the one below it
it's not bad
probably leave it the one that I don't
like however
is this main one it has a lot of fruit
buds you can see it has fruit buds all
over it it's kind of unfortunate but as
you can also see there is not really a
lot of space these branches are
extremely close together which I don't
really want so I'm going to remove this
one here gave you a little bit of a
better view of it but yeah as you can
see it's way too close together it
doesn't make sense to keep them both I
was going back and forth between keeping
this one or that one but I just really
like the way that this Branch arches as
compared to this one this one is kind of
weird and wonky you can't quite see it
it's just out of frame but it doesn't
flow as well
so I'm just going to remove that leaving
a branch collar again
now the next one you can see quite clear
clearly already is that these two
branches are essentially growing the
exact same way which means you just want
to ideally pick one or the other
so I'm just gonna pick this one here I
like that one better
so I'm just going to remove that right
at the branch collar again
there are a lot of branches that are
growing left as you can see here all
these Branch are growing left and that's
really one of the reasons why I was
trying to hold on to this one here
just because it's one of the few that
was going right
so hopefully in future something will
develop I do have this small little
Branch here that may end up becoming
that Branch I also like this one here
that's coming towards you but I really
just don't need these two here so I'm
going to remove those two in favor of
this larger one here
turn that off
prune the one beside it
so really the last thing that I would
like to do this tree I should just
reduce the height a little bit
now this to take this branch is an
example
this branch is two years old
uh the first year grew up to about here
and then the second year it grew the
remaining of that Branch there so all
these buds over here that you see are
fruit buds so this was two years ago
this was first Year's growth and then
the last little big group last year I'm
essentially just going to remove last
year's growth so if I take this Branch
as a guide
go to remove this to
right above that first food butt there
and then I'm gonna prune
the other ones to be kind of similar to
that size
so prune that one off
to a favorable
node there
same thing
with one beside it
it's gonna take the tip off
just like so so
and that will do it
all right so I'm happy with that
and this next growing season we'll see
what develops and see if I can maybe get
a branch growing that way somewhere
that'd be nice to kind of fill it out
although I guess that main scaffold
branch is actually filling that space
pretty well right now
but that'll be something that I'm going
to look for
next year
we'll get there when we get there
I feel like all these other buds in here
they're fine most of these are fruit
buds there are some vegetative ones I
may end up removing that you can
certainly if you want to
so anyway with that said
thank you all for watching
and I'll see you in the next one
foreign