in my youth we learned in school that it
takes 500 years to build an inch of
topsoil but there are people who are
doing it 500 times faster than that and
if these practices were adopted on a
global scale according to some estimates
it could offset all emissions we can
begin drawdown like right now but we'd
sacrifice agricultural productivity
right no actually these methods can be
as productive or more productive than
chemical based agriculture there's two
things though that they do require that
represent a profound shift in our
agricultural system and our entire
society the first is that they are more
labor-intensive in the United States
approximately 1% of the population is
directly engaged in farming that might
have to go up to 10% as it was in 1950
and maybe if you include gardens maybe
go up to 50% and the other is that in
regenerative agriculture what works in
one place may not work on another
continent or even in the next Valley
over the only way to make them work is
to be a patient attentive observer of
that particular land so it requires an
ongoing intimate relationship that is
unique between the human interacting
with that land and the land itself that
does not fit into an industrial model
the essence of industrialization is
standardization that's what makes it
efficient that's what allows a machine
to do it in order to have a truly
regenerative agricultural system we have
to undo that way of thinking and that's
another reason why we need more people
in close relationship to the land
you