bluetongue virus is transmitted to its
ruminant host almost entirely by biting
midges which we call curly coils so this
means it's a non contagious disease so
if you have an infected sheep which
shows clinical signs of blue tongue the
sheep next to it will not be infected by
the virus directly by passing on from
one sheep to the other the virus can
only transmit if the biological vector
Coleco despite images is around so the
virus and replicates in the insect and
eventually after a certain time period
it will reach the saliva gland and once
it has reached the saliva gland the next
time this now infected meat feeds on an
uninfected suitable mammalian host so in
the case of gluten again romulans sheep
cattle it can then transmit the virus
during that blood meal back into the
mammalian host and then the virus starts
its replication cycle in this host again
and this is a really intriguing
relationship because it doesn't function
as a mere needle transmission at all
there's more and more research for
examples that the saliva has a very
active role potentially in pathogen
transmission because these insects have
to salivate to stop blood correlation
and immune responses because if so
therefore live is come up surgical
active it could contains anticoagulants
because if they otherwise would try to
feed the blood would immediately clot
and then you can't take it up but by
having these bioactive molecules in
their saliva they can prevent this blood
clotting and they are able to take up a
blood meal because there it is a non
contagious transmission classical
methods we use like preventing contact
restricting animal movement although
they are still necessary they have a far
less in
act on a vector borne disease animal
movements are important to not dislocate
the virus throughout an entire country
so of course if you move the animal from
southern England to northern England you
could almost create a second outbreak
however on a local scale once the local
insect population is infected they will
say they will not stop you can restrict
herbs you can say excuse me you are now
on little interest rate so even if you
don't if you do have enemy movement
controls the moment that virus is in the
local insect population you have lost it
because it will still be able to be
transmitted those insects will still fly
and infect neighboring farms so this is
one of the challenges of dealing with a
vector borne transmitted pathogen and
this is why if your free country and
your fearing the incursion of a vector
borne disease it is so important to
catch it early because what you're
trying to do is find it and remove those
animals or or at least get them out of
being exposed to so many biting insects
before the local insect population is
completely infected the program
Institute has an insect er II where we
breed several insect species so
mosquitoes and some biting sized Moxa's
cats it runs and also Coulee coitus
biting images in our blue tongue
research which is mainly gluten
pathogenesis research or transmission
research or immune response and vaccine
research we do the vast majority of our
work with those mammalian hosts which
are really in which I in nature infected
and affected by this virus so we use
sheep goat and cattle because if you
carry out research in something as
complex as pathogenesis so where is this
virus going and how is it causing
disease or something like the immune
response which
is very species specific we fear that it
is an incredibly advantage to actually
be able to use the host which is
affected by this disease we would obtain
our study animals like sheep or goats or
cattle from a commercial farm these are
normal and farm animals and at the
moment they come into our isolation
units they are incredibly monitored so
depending on which type of study we do
we would treat them we would give them
painkillers the one questions which is
often raised when we talk about our work
and describe our work is could we do our
research without using animals so we do
a lot of work with primary cell cultures
where we just get blood or samples from
animals which which are put down any way
to establish primary cells to establish
organ cultures and we carry out
infection studies of these cells we even
we have a project where we also assess
the response of these cells to insect
saliva to already get an idea what is
going on what kind of cytokines are
being made how do they respond is
different when the virus is only says
with and without meat saliva so we have
developed a method to collect Mitch
saliva or making them making them spit
into a fill time we can wash off the
saliva so we have a really active
project to get our research to a level
as high as we can by not using animals
but there's only so fast we can go when
it comes to big questions like
transmission when it comes to big
question like is this vaccine safe is
this vaccine efficient how does the
enemy respond upon challenge we cannot
carry out this work without the use of
life and animals the vertebrate immune
system is way too complex that we could
ever
hope to replicate that fully in their
modern systems there's always going to
be a step where we need the animal
research because I just if you just
think of how for example an insect borne
virus is transmitted with insect blood
feeding in the skin the skin is one of
our is the biggest organ we have and is
one of the complicated the most
complicated organ we have and then you
have blood vessels bringing all these
cells and responding and then it gets
distributed to the entire body this
level of complexity would almost be
impossible to create in an artificial
situation and of all you can take it so
far and reduce the numbers which is the
alternative goal there will always be
questions where we need the whole
organism so currently the work we do on
gluten virus we use about twenty to
thirty animals a year occasionally when
there is an outbreak of bruton virus for
example in in a country where this has
never been or there is a strain which is
emerging which we don't know then there
is the potential to do like an emergency
study to be able to characterize the
pathogenesis of this virus and to foster
vaccine development for this particular
strength
there are several vaccines against
bluetongue virus and to understand why
we are still concerned about developing
other vaccines for gluten virus we need
to look a bit at this virus so the virus
has 27 serotypes so far we have
discovered at the moment but they keep
finding more and the problem we have is
it the protection or the immune response
upon either infection or vaccination is
serotype specific so what that means is
if you wax in it against the pt8 you're
cheap and your cow is only protected
against bt8
it is still susceptible to 26 other
gluten strengths so the vaccines which
are available are in Northern Europe
inactivated vaccines that is they're
safe and they are efficient and they
have been used successfully to for
example eradicate bluetongue virus 8
from the UK a few years ago but they are
only there monotypic so they will only
protect against the stream hence they
are fine in a situation where you combat
a single stream incursion it gets more
problematic when you're in a country
which has said those dreams of
bluetongue virus circling one big area
for the research is to try to find out
how can we get across ferrotype
protective vaccine because in countries
like India where bluetongue virus still
has a big impact on subsistence farmers
especially in the south they have 10 15
20 strains of operatin virus circling so
a lot of endemic countries use and
modified lights attenuated vaccines so
they have several strains of life virus
however it has been shown that they can
reach levels which makes them
transmissible so midges can actually
pick up the vaccine strain and then
testing some of them in British breeds
they also induce clinical signs so while
some indigenous breeds have clearly
avoid stress disease and do not get sick
to these vaccines anymore we did not use
them in northern Europe because we could
show that to certain preparations they
would still induce clinical disease in
in the country so then when we test for
antibodies we don't know does this
animal have antibodies because it got
vaccinated or does this animal have
antibodies because it was infected at
one point during their life so that
makes control very difficult and then
another area with inactivated vaccines
is although if they are applied
well in time their protect against the
challenge of the virus the immune
response is relatively slow so an animal
is protected or she probably after 3-4
weeks castle at the moment need to
dosages so that would mean probably six
weeks until they are protected so if you
think of an emergency vaccination where
the virus is already active you could
find yourself in a situation where that
induction of immune response isn't quick
enough developing better vaccine which
might be quicker might again shorten
that risk if you need to use a vaccine
preparation as an emergency response so
these are all drivers for improving the
vaccine although in a in a one strain
outbreak situation and applied well
before the virus really gets going the
current inactivated vaccine available
for gluten will protect your enemies and
and is a good is a good way of
protecting your enemies another very
important component of this virus which
is crucial to understand is that it is
segmented so its genome is arranged in
segments and what that means is if two
strains of bluetongue infect oneself
they can swap things a bit like
influenza okay so we create this virus
not only creates variation by mutation
it creates variation by changing genome
segments which we call reassortant the
immune response to this virus is
monotypic so it is specifically to the
zero type other characteristics however
our strain specific so we can have a
mild or moderate or virulent strain of
for example bt v1 so when we have a new
outbreak we buy serotypes have no clue
what this strain is going to do just
because it's a Vth strain
does not mean it will be a very long
string we have to monitor we have to see
and sometimes we even have to do an
element experiment to understand which
what kind of strain are we dealing with
is this a virulent strain it is a male
stream how quickly do we need to get a
vaccine out or if this is a mud stream
can we let this go and this can
obviously change very very quickly with
reassortant so you could have a mild
beat anyone strain circling and a
virulent
Vth strange circling and then they
infect the same enemy and suddenly they
swap this genome segment which is
responsible for the serotypes let's say
BT one but then the virulence is on
other segments and suddenly you have a
new btv one because your BT v8 strain
has now got that segment from BT one but
it has remained all the virulence of the
other segments which inside really maked
BT v8 but on the outside it has now
become meet anyone however it still does
mutate and it does mutate in this
segment this segment tool which encodes
for the outer coat protein which defines
the zero type and this is why we have 27
zero times but the strain landscape is
far more complex because it can chop and
change all the other segments and
therefore render a vaccination campaign
useless within the exchange of one
genomes
you