[Music]
traditionally pumpkins are one of our
favorite fall crops pumpkins are also a
crop that can encourage kids to start to
like gardening but one thing to keep in
mind when growing pumpkins is that here
in Wyoming we have a short growing
season so think about starting your
pumpkin seeds inside um just to get a
jump on so that you can have a nice
pumpkin pack match towards the end of
fall there are too many varieties of
pumpkins to name here now but know that
there are white orange striped and even
giant pumpkins that can grow well over
500 lb that all grow well here in
Wyoming as you can see here pumpkins
take up a lot of space so keep in mind
when planning out your garden space
where you want to have your pumpkins at
Beyond just making jck lards you can
also grow pumpkins to eat as well if
you're looking for any more information
on pumpkins contact your local extension
office and with the University of
Wyoming extension I'm Hannah Johnson and
you're watching from the ground
up