Oh
[Music]
in two villages in Zimbabwe school
attendance in recent years has been
steadily improving thanks to an IAEA FAO
project drought made it difficult for
farmers to generate enough income to
send their children to school for about
three consecutive years we get the poor
rains and do poor harvests so the
impoverished parents could not afford
school fees quite some time to support
farmers the IAEA helped the government
introduced a drip irrigation pilot
project that reduces water use by half
using isotopic techniques scientists
calculated the exact amount of water and
fertilizer needed for tomatoes and other
vegetables this allows farmers to save
both of these precious resources in a
routine or says result or film from tank
recovery Rio family pipe Yadira Numa
Numa pipe imitating bamboo yoga yoga
grinding is separation de pombal drip
irrigation is also more efficient
leading to more crops adding fertilizer
to the soil also increases the harvest
the situation with food security is
quite greatly improved
like for instance where the farmers used
to have a yield of says 5 tonnes per
hectare or a 6 tonnes per hectare now it
is almost trebled
that means more food for the children
and more money for their school I can
now manage to pay the school fees of my
children from the money I got from the
drip irrigation system
I also improved my my household and I
can also now buy food for my children I
feel happy because my parents bought
complete school uniform and stationery
for me and I expect to pass with flying
colours at
the end of the a with more crop per drop
the education of children in these areas
is safe for now this is a supported
project is also helping farmers
elsewhere in Africa
[Music]