are you ready to take your gardening to
the next level and start selling your
harvests but how do you turn your
backyard garden into a real business
what if I told you I've never worked on
a farm I've never owned a business and I
don't have a college degree yet I
managed to scale my gardening hobby into
a six-figure vegetable operation and in
this video I'll walk you through step by
step how I structured my small farm
business from choosing the right
business structure like an LLC and
getting the right licenses to tax
exemptions filing and insurance we're
covering everything you need to know to
transform your garden into a thriving
profitable business hey what's up
everybody welcome back to Chef's Harvest
Farm if you're new here I'm Chef Mikey
I'm a former executive chef turned Urban
Farmer I took my backyard gardening
Hobby and turned it into a thriving
smallscale vegetable operation I started
out selling at farmers markets but
eventually shifted to a wholesale model
supplying high quality organic
vegetables to some of the best chefs in
the greater Knoxville Tennessee area so
just like anyone starting out with no
experience I began gardening in simple
raised beds that I built out of wood and
filled the soil from Home
Depot at first it was just a fun hobby
but it didn't take long before I was
growing more food than we could eat
living on a busy road always thought
about setting up a Farm Stand to sell
extra produce but instead I started Ed
posting extra produce for sale on
Facebook my co-workers were my first
customers however my hobby wasn't cheap
I was spending about $300 a week on
supplies to grow produce once I reached
a certain level of production it became
clear that I needed to invest in
refrigeration wash pack equipment and
that's when I realized it was time to
take things more seriously and formal
legitimate
business at first I had no clue where to
start I began researching ing all the
forms and legal requirements for
starting a business which is
overwhelming that's when I came across a
company called Zen business they handle
all the paperwork for you file necessary
documents and keep your business
compliant year after year these services
do cost money but for a few hundred
dollar a year it took all the guest work
out and gave me piece of mind that my
business was operating legally you don't
technically need a business license in
Tennessee until you have over $10,000 in
sales but just to be safe I contacted my
county clerk they issued me a minimal
business license for businesses with
under $110,000 in Revenue it was an easy
and inexpensive way to make sure I was
covered because once I started attending
farmers markets they required me to have
a business license even if my yearly
Revenue was under
$10,000 the following year my Revenue
exceeded the $10,000 threshold and they
just switched me over to a standard
business license that first year I ended
up up claiming a $20,000 loss on my
taxes which turned into a huge tax
savings if I hadn't set up my LLC I
would have had to pay income tax on that
$20,000 from my day job but instead I
got it back as a tax return while I
didn't know much about forming a
business initially my background as an
executive chef for multi-million dollar
food and beverage operations gave me a
foundation in managing Financial records
bookkeeping and
operations those skills became inval
valuable is I transitioned my gardening
hobby into a legitimate scalable
business once I established my LLC and
got my business license I knew one of
the biggest advantages for Farmers like
me was qualifying for a tax exemption
and trust me you'll want to get this tax
exemption before you start making any
big purchases because it can save you a
ton of money the reason you won't have
to pay sales tax on products that are
directly used for growing crops like
seeds fertilizers and tools in Tennessee
all you need need to qualify for an
Agricultural tax exemption is $11,000 in
sales which if you're selling anything
should be pretty easy goal to hit but at
that point I hadn't filed for taxes for
my business yet so I didn't have any
sales on the books so I took a bit of a
leap of faith and I wrote a letter to
the IRS I explained that I was starting
a small farm and that I wanted to start
making tax deductible purchases to build
my business I mentioned that I was
selling extra produce to co-workers and
that I plan to attend Farmers Market
kids and sell to restaurants in the
future I also included a spreadsheet
with projected sales for the upcoming
year hoping that would help strengthen
my case to my surprise a few weeks later
I received a tax exemption in the mail
and since then I've consistently cleared
the $1,000 Mark in sales each year to
stay in compliance now a big question I
get is whether you need special
licensing to sell produce and in
Tennessee the answer is no not for
locally grown vegetables grown produce
and selling locally is considered low
risk for foodborn pathogens so there's
no additional licensing requirements
however if you start crossing state
lines things might change and if you
decide to sell meat dairy or eggs or add
animals like chickens you may need extra
licensing but for now as long as you're
just selling raw veggies you're good to
go I do have a greenhouse license which
allows me to legally sell rooted plants
typically this kind of Licensing costs
money but I qualified for an exemption
since my main form of Revenue comes from
vegetables not plants I simply had to
show them my books to prove that the
majority of my Revenue comes from
selling vegetables the greenhouse
license just helps me sell extra
seedlings at the farmers market when I
have them available also have a license
to grow cannabis although 99% of my
business Revenue comes from vegetables
the Cannabis is simply a passion project
but for most of you setting up your LLC
and getting your business license will
be all you need to get started started
legally now let's dive into how I manage
my taxes and accounting once I had my
LLC set up for my business and started
to grow one of the first things I did
was separate my business finances from
my personal finances I opened a business
bank account and credit cards which
really helped me keep things organized
at this point I was still working my
full-time job but I knew it was
important to keep track of my Farm's
revenue and expenses so I set up a
QuickBooks account to help manage
everything however I quickly realized
that QuickBooks wasn't quite what I
needed as a farmer I needed to be able
to categorize expenses for schedule F
form which is a requirement for Farmers
when filing taxes unfortunately
QuickBooks didn't allow me to do this
effectively so I had to look for an
alternative that's when I discovered
Farm raise and I highly recommend it to
any farmer who's just starting out or
looking to make tax filing easier Farm
ra is designed specifically for farmers
and everything is already set up with
schedule F categories which made
tracking expenses and revenue a lot
simpler it also sends out notices about
available grants and funding
opportunities which is a huge benefit
for anybody trying to scale their
operation if you're serious about
farming as a business Farm raay is a
game changer next I need an efficient
way to take payments especially for my
farmers market sales so I opened up a
square account square is free to sign up
for and they send you a free credit card
reader which I use when when I go to the
farmers market there are no monthly fees
Square just charges you a small fee when
you use a digital payment like a credit
card since I sell mostly to restaurants
now I only attend farmers markets
occasionally but it's still super
convenient way to take payments and keep
track of customer orders I also use my
Square account to run payroll my workers
can clock in and out on their phone and
at the end of the week I just press a
couple buttons and everyone gets paid it
takes care of all my payroll taxes and
compliance and it's sends everybody a W2
at the end of the year for my busino
business transactions with restaurants I
now only accept checks or wire transfer
so Square allows me to create and send
invoices to my customers for free and
they can pay me via check or wire
transfer once I get paid I simply Mark
those invoices as paid and square and I
don't incur any processing fees the
beauty of using Square and farm rais is
that everything's linked together every
time I use a credit card it
automatically goes into Farm ra account
and it's categorized properly and my
Square account is also synced to farm ra
so that all my Revenue automatically
gets pulled in and categorize the way I
need it to be for tax season by keeping
everything organized and linked together
I don't have to stress about missing out
on deductions or not having the right
records everything I need is right at my
fingertips making tax time so much less
stressful one of the most important
steps I took on my farm as I started to
grow was getting Insurance to protect my
business at first I didn't think much
about it I mean I was just gardening in
my backyard but as I started selling
produce and interacting with customers I
realized I needed to cover myself in
case anything unexpected happens I use
next insurance for my liability coverage
this includes product liability which
protects me in case anyone ever gets
sick from my produce and general
liability which covers accidents that
may happen either on the farm or off
site this just gives me peace of mind
known that I'm covered no matter where
or how I'm selling my vegetables on top
of that our homeowners insurance is
through Farm Bureau and it covers the
structures and equipment that I use on
the farm like my green houses and
tractor this is a great setup because it
protects not just my farm business but
also the assets tied to it if you're
just starting out I recommend looking
into liability insurance first It's
usually the most essential for small
farmers for example if you sell at a
farmers market or to restaurants product
liability insurance ensures you're
covered if someone claims they got sick
from something you sold and general
liability protects you from accidents
like if someone trips on your farm or if
something happens while you're out
delivering produce the good news
insurance for small farms is pretty
affordable my liability insurance costs
about $300 a year of course costs will
vary depending on your farm size and
location so it's worth shopping around
and getting quotes from different
providers I suggest starting with
companies like next especially if you're
looking for Farm specific policies and
if you have structures like green houses
or large equipment check with your
homeowners insurance provider they might
be able to bundle coverage for your farm
asset ultimately getting the right
insurance for your farm isn't just about
complying with legal requirements it's
about protecting everything you've built
and ensuring that one unexpected event
doesn't wipe it all out when I first
started gardening in my backyard scaling
up to a profitable business wasn't even
on my radar but over time as I started
selling extra produce I saw the
potential to grow into something bigger
scaling up didn't happen overnight it
was a process of making small
intentional Investments and reinvesting
profits back into the farm one of the
first major upgrades I made was building
a mobile walk-in cooler proper
Refrigeration was a game Cher it allowed
me to store larger quantities of produce
while maintaining the quality needed for
restaurant sales early on I also
realized the importance of staying
organized and thinking strategically I
focused on growing fewer crops at higher
volumes which streamlined my workflow
and reduced waste transitioning from
farmers markets to wholesale sales with
restaurants was another key step in
scaling up this shift not only saved me
time but also created a more predictable
and stable income stream but scaling up
isn't just about infrastructure or sales
it's about learning and adapting I
invested in tools like Farm raise for
bookkeeping and Square for invoicing
which helped me manage finances and keep
track of my growth I also took every
opportunity to learn whether through
networking watching videos or seeking
out resources to improve my processes
most importantly I stayed patient
farming is a long game and success
doesn't happen overnight there were
Seasons when I made mistakes lost crops
or faced unexpected challenges but I
kept pushing forward learning from those
experiences and making small
improvements year after year here if
you're trying to scale up your garden
into a business start small focus on
what's working build relationships with
your customers and reinvest in the tools
and infrastructure that will save you
time and improve your product quality
scaling up is about consistency
persistence in making thoughtful
decisions not overnight success