good afternoon everybody
my name is Eric sale I am a small fruit
entomologist
at University of Georgia and today I am
going to talk about insect management
for a commercial strawberry production
in today's talk we will
discuss season at the glass tests which
pests occur what kind of the a year for
strawberries then their management again
will take a season at a glance look at
their management options that we have
then I will get discuss a few select
tests in detail in terms of their
biology and management
at the end I will cover some aspects of
pollinator management which obviously
are important in Strawberry production
systems
so take when we look at a sort of a
season at a glance the pests of
strawberries starting with the
transplant
cut worms and aphids are important here
at this stage of strawberries and when
you will look at this season at a glass
Slide the leaf green leaf shows that
they are they feed on leaves
strawberry shows they feed on fruit or
flowers and this these sticks will show
that they feed on stems or branches of
strawberries so cut worms of course feed
on on stems as well as foliage if it's
they are sucking pests and they suck
primarily on the leaves going moving on
into winter it's sort of later part of
winter two spots spider mite they start
they all go all the way through
flowering into Fruit growth period
lead on on foliate of the strawberries
then trips also they feed on flowers for
the most part during flowering until uh
fruit initial fruit growth period as
well strawberry Clipper again feeds on
flowers and
sometimes smaller fruits
also if it's again are important this
time of the blueberry growing season
then we as we move on lady ligus bugs on
especially on their neutral strawberries
come into play at early through starting
with early fruit growth stage going all
the way to harvest then we during the
Harvest we have serious issues including
sap beetles
go on earworms and spotted ring
desophila spotted Wing discipla has
become more important for strawberries
recently than it has been in the past as
compared to some other Berry crops where
it has been key test ever since it was
detected in the mainland U.S
so now we when we look at a management
of those pests instead of a season at a
glance look
when we look at post planting fall to
early to midwinter crickets are
important we do have a couple options to
spray cut worms
recyclomine mites are important we do
have some miter side options fire ants
obviously we can use those baits that
are available here at this screen that I
am showing you now it comes directly
from South East small fruit Consortium
strawberry IPM guide
and a number of researchers from the
region that get together every year to
update this guide so this is one of the
best resources for you to learn about
Pest and disease management for
strawberries I highly recommend I'll
share I'll show you the main screen and
link to access that in the end
so and then two spider mites obviously
we have number of my decide options then
we move on to pre-harvest or Bloom time
late winter to early spring
aphids fire ants floor trips slugs and
the snails strawberry Clippers two
spotted spider mics these are major pest
insect pests or other pest issues of
strawberries and this slide does list
options that we have to control them
then we moved into the Harvest period
fire ants obviously still become uh
issue set beetles slugs and snails have
become serious issues if we don't manage
the moisture in the fields spotted
during the sofa obviously is is one of
the key pests tarnish plant bugs and
mites they are still mites can be
problem year round for strawberries
now I will get into you know this gives
you a season at a glass look but I will
show you a share with you a little bit
of
and details and some of the select tests
so one thing before we get into annual
plastic culture practices do limit many
pests of strawberries for example
strawberry root Vivo cyclamen mites they
do this particular system does help
minimize impact of those
those pests and also root nibbling
diseases
starting with the two-spotted spider
mite two spotted spider mites they're
it's very small little sort of difficult
to see without hand lens adults are
translucent greenish yellow to Rusty
brown or orange red in color they're
about a half millimeter long oval bodies
of those mites have two distinct dark
spots on E1 on each side
and which are which is sort of a
distinguished distinguishing feature to
separate these mites from other groups
this is actually accumulation of waste
products within the body that is visible
through their body wall
eggs are clear white and spherical newly
had larvae have only six legs compared
to the eight legs as they grow into
older nymphs and adults they develop all
uh four pairs of legs
uh two spider spider mites the rate of
development is highly variable and it is
uh dependent on temperature ranging from
5 to 20 days to complete their cycle
from egg to adult
so females basically they have about two
to four weeks lifespan and each female
can lay several hundred eggs during that
time which are enclosed in a fine silk
webbing eggs hatch in about three days
and then six-legged larvae emerge and
undergo through two more things
two modes to achieve than two nymphal
stages
and then adults emerge after the second
stage and then adults they obviously
restart the the whole process that whole
process can be completed within five to
twenty days depending on temperature and
other conditions
spider mite feeding on the the primarily
feed on undersides of the leaves and
sometimes the stems also they cause
initial stippling which is shown in the
picture on the bottom left on the screen
a set of a white spots
and eventually lead to chlorotic
yellowing
or some times it's called bronzing or
graying of the leaves and in severe
cases necrotic and the defoliation
necrosis and defoliation can occur when
populations are not controlled
Leaf deformities stunted growth Peril
Browning built and reduce the fluid
quality quantity and yield
quantity and quality are obviously the
outcomes these mites produce silky
webbing and leave behind skin castings
and feces that reduce plants as static
value and ability to for the synthesize
monitoring is is relatively easy in a
part that is up to 10 acre in in size
you need to collect only 10 mid-tier
leaflets per acre
and observe them under 10x hand lens if
the field is larger than 10 acres then
only five leaflets per acre would
suffice
the thresholds is if you have uh five
miles per leaflet early in the season
that maybe that may warrant application
of Mighty sides or if you have 10 mites
per leaflet during fruit and season then
that is when you need to make spray
applications to control them
there are a number of options that I
showed you in the season at a glass
slide as well acromide with the land
cane Mite nyalta these are effective
against all stages of Baron Savvy Zeal
they are effective against eggs and
juveniles
portal agreement again juveniles and
adults MP Horticultural oils these are
organic organically approved products
which can be used for organic production
and the predatory mites obviously are
the buyer control option if if you want
to go that route
the next pest the group that I will
discuss today is sat beetles
set me the speed on overripe fruit and
are attracted to the alcohol produced by
micro
microorganisms feeding on this rotten
fruit it can be problematic in Peach
Plum and apple production systems as
well at least three species of ripe
fruit feeding beetles are pests of
Southeastern strawberries
there are no thresholds developed for
set beetles in strawberries
at this point observe ripe fruit when
it's picking surface damage and
tunneling if a harvest is anticipated to
run long or if Beetle damage is
suspected bait buckets placed at the
edge of the field will attract small
adults adult beetles so that's that's
one way to control that and cultural
control is highly recommended for set
beetles
because there are registered chemicals
but those
chemicals can cause issues with the
during the Harvest we don't want to
leave too much residues in there we're
going to minimize the pesticide
application during that Harvest Time me
at buckets can also obviously serve as a
one cultural control strategy
trips now trips is another pest that has
recently been problematic in
some situations especially these chili
trips they are serious pests in Florida
and have been detected in Georgia as
well I'm not sure the status of Chile
trips in Alabama
but they are they have emerged as a
serious issues though both Larry and
adults feed on on strawberries Underside
the leaves they have piercing and second
pest uh mouth Parts they are originally
from Southeast Asia they have been
several times intercepted in at the
ports in in Florida
and have been established in Florida
since 2005 and in strawberries they have
become serious issue since 2015 and now
this is one of the key pests or one of
the major pests in Strawberry
systems in Florida
agility trips
they as I mentioned they have a piercing
sucking mouth bars and they feed on
underside of the leaves to some Jews and
that leads to darkening of the leaflet
and midriff as you see in this picture
on the left side of the screen
that can lead to Leaf curdling of the
strawberries and the image in the middle
shows that severe case scenarios
of just chili traps symptoms
and sometimes it also leads to bronzing
and cracking up the fruit and it's
extreme situation
several studies have been done in
Florida as I mentioned this issue in
particular is predominant in Florida so
lots of work has been done in Florida
and they have developed Management
Programs based on products here
[Music]
which is delegate a sale and ciazepir or
axel
these are effective products for for
management obviously broad spectrum
insecticides these are all three of
these products are reduced risk products
which is a better option to choose if if
there is a choice but they'll be
slightly more expensive likely then you
have broad spectrum choices like
bifantrin which will be
um
a relatively less effective but can be
used in some situations and there will
be less expensive option if you want to
go that route
then we also have some biorational
options that can be used for organic or
other reduced risk type systems
which include Azera and my control and
interestingly these and thermopathogenic
nematodes when they were applied two
times they provided really good results
so these options are also available for
organic Growers and also other systems
where reduced risk option is a desired
now let's get into spotted Wing discipla
which is a key pest in most of the berry
crops and is becoming increasingly
important for strawberry systems not
only in the Southeast but across the
country even in California it has
recently become serious issue in
Strawberry systems as well it was
originally discovered in stock
strawberries in California in 2008
to 2009 as you see on this screen sort
of an increase the spread of this in
invasive pest across the mainland U.S
2009 all West Coast in Florida
and then from that front on it just
quickly spread across the country in
2015 we just stopped monitoring it
because it was everywhere you looked
and spotted when the name comes from
these two dark spots on the uh exterior
margins of the male wings that's why
where the spotted Wing name comes from
and males can also be identified using
these two black columns as a feature on
the front legs
females of this species are uniquely
blessed with this very
sclerotized and serrated over Pastor
that they use to lay eggs in otherwise
healthy fruit larvae develop inside the
fruit
and start feeding
into the whole generation from larvae
from egg laying to adult emergence can
be completed in eight to ten days at 25
degrees Centigrade
which can happen faster if the
temperature is higher so this kind of
tells that this fly can go to several
Generations in one field season
over here is just images using
blueberries we generated this image of
how the fruit damage progresses starting
from over position to basically
broadening of the complete unmarketable
fruit is it takes about three to four
days beyond that is fruit is not
marketable
overall impact of this fly was estimated
to be 718 million dollars in the U.S it
was estimated in 2014 Plus in additional
management costs included about 120
million 129 million dollars which means
it's approximately a billion dollar pest
when you look at take all the crops into
account
starting with the monitoring initially
we have used these 32 ohms plastic cups
weighted with the yeast sugar slurry
which is a kind of a messy if you leave
it for a week it's become stinky and
more than that it becomes really stinky
and not easy to manage recently several
states were participated in these
studies
to develop these dry traps which is a
red sticky card embedded with these
commercially available lures and they
provided comfortable results and we are
recommending this now for monitoring of
swd these sticky red sticky card based
traps
we did monitoring for several years in
in Georgia blueberries and what we
noticed is that flies were active year
round they don't sleep during the winter
or slow down they just stick around
and what more interestingly but but you
can see in this slide is that numbers
were higher in the wooded areas nearby
than the field themselves for the most
part of the year
so it means there is a obviously
alternative host to plants that occur in
the wooded areas as you see in this
picture we have Carl Pines that are
mostly around the blueberry Orchards
here are other carbs including
strawberries but the understory is
filled with several other species and
when we looked within those
several species were identified where
swd females were able to lay eggs and
complete development in many of those
plants in the world so there's something
that we need to do to eliminate those to
those alternative hosts which will help
in the long term but
for now management is includes
biological control chemical control
behavioral and cultural control
biological control this being an
invasive species
biological control is is very
complicated a lot of work has been done
on classical bio control by large teams
of researchers from multiple
institutions after eight to ten years of
work finally we were able to get permits
of to release those exotic parastors
that we imported from native regions of
swd China and South Korea
and several states are now building up
the colonies to test to release those in
the field and see how they will help
control swd currently there is no bio
control in the field based on our native
Paris stones
all right so chemical control is the
primary means to control it I'm just
showing you this one slide which was the
first attempt to control swd back in
2012. you see very few options primarily
organophosphorus and pythroids with
spinosins
now look at this this is where we stand
right now we have lots of options
chemical options to control swd they
belong to several chemical classes which
means we have the option to do really
nice resistance management which is
highly recommended because resistance
has become a major issue in California
uh in in many cropping systems there we
haven't seen resistance in other states
yet but some states have started to show
initial signs of it so highly
recommended that Growers Implement
resistance management by rotating
products from one class to another
when you look at organic management
that's where we are in trouble because
entrust is the only one that has if good
efficacy but even that doesn't touch the
line of threshold of being good so it
means we need to add additional
non-chemical components to make sure we
are able to control a stability in
organic systems
here are some sample management
season-long management programs again
these are just a set of samples now we
have several chemical options that can
be included and in General weekly
applications are recommended in organic
systems we have to make some chemicals
don't have week-long residues we need to
go back after three days to make sure we
protect the fruit against this fly
when we have a sort of a decisions to
make for the whole season it is highly
recommended that you start with the
highest heaviest chemicals which means
the most effective chemicals as you see
here
infest light the intervention in the
second slide we started with low
efficacy product and still fly
populations sustained they did not
disappear however in the third picture
when you see here that a highly
effective product was used it knocked
the fly populations down and then you
can use low efficacy in mid-efficacy
product for the rest of the season to
maintain that low level of populations
which will not cause economic damage
all of the products obviously when we
talk about insecticides they do have
harmful effects against beneficial
insects so we need to keep that in mind
even organic products do have negative
effects on beneficial insects so we need
to always keep that in mind one thing we
can do to minimize the non-target
effects of those insecticides is to
spray
in the Dawn and dusk times when flies
ought active in the field themselves and
we can basically expose flies to direct
spray residues rather than spraying
other times of the day when they are not
active and then relying on their
exposure to the residues which may not
be as strong and may not be as effective
so recommending it is recommended to
spray during the Dawn and Dusk and the
other benefit is that less beneficials
are active during that time of the day
so that helps in in many ways
now moving on to behavioral control we
have tested uh several behavioral
control strategies the goal is to
develop attract and kill approach where
we have an attractant that can attract
flies away from the fruit and then we
have a toxic and mixed in it to kill
them by the residues
so this one technology that was
developed by iska
Technologies company based in California
we tested several years ago
and it did show some promise as you see
it reduced this it was 87 less fruit
infestation in than when this particular
product was applied which has an
attractive mix with insecticide and in
this case insecticide was spinocid
now the same company is developing these
new formulations which are even more
attractive however the difference is
that these new Farm TD formulation and
or formulations TD in particular is the
most effective and this is just by
itself attracted by itself is stored as
adjuvant
it is currently in EPA for a
constitution to be commercially
available hopefully this will be
available later this season or next year
this is sold as
ajimand itself and farmers will need to
mix insecticide of their choice with it
to use this as a check and kill too
other chemicals can be protect was
developed in Europe and several Labs we
tested it last year here in the U.S and
we found that even half weight of
interest can give us just as much
activity as Fuller rate of interest so
or even more in slightly more in some
cases so this is really good product
again currently in EPA to be considered
for registration as agile and hopefully
this will be available later this season
or next year
cultural controls again these are really
important the goal here is to modify the
environment to make the environment less
attractive for uh stability
swd flies are very sensitive to
temperature and humidity they don't like
high temperatures and they don't like
dry conditions so what can we do to
change modify the environment
so yes
in this case we can do okay so let me go
through one by one by one first starting
with exclusion that's one cultural
practice or a strategy that you can use
to cover the fruit production area or
berries themselves keep the flies out
this is one foolproof technology that
can use but it is expensive so uh
however some Farmers I have just talked
to they have repurposed their currently
used materials in part and in part they
got new materials to make it more
economically feasible but once you have
it installed it does work as a foolproof
technology to control swd to keep the
flies away
irrigation is you know most of the fruit
production does need the irrigation
system if you have the option use uh
drip irrigation as compared to the
overhead irrigation because drip
irrigation creates less humidity in the
canopy zones and that is that helps keep
the stability populations lower in the
fruiting Zone
mulching is another way to control swd
the principle here is that when flies
larvae are fully fed inside the fruit
they come out of the fruit and drop to
the ground to pupate if we have a black
beet mat or some Mulch on the ground to
prevent a lottery from getting into the
ground to prepare it they will get
toasted and killed on the surface that
again has been very useful
way to control the stability flies in
high pressure situations
pruning is is the other way to change
the canopy environment when you we do
heavy pruning but it does it allows more
light through the canopy into the
fruiting Zone where flies are likely to
you know spend most of the time to
infest food
and it does reduce humidity a little bit
so that slight increase in temperature
and decrease in humidity does lower fly
population in that zone to help with swd
control
Harvest frequency is again important if
you leave ripe fruit out in the field
for too long that is very attractive to
flies and flies will have more
opportunity to infest so remove the ripe
fruit as frequently as possible that
will minimize the risk of fruit
infestation by swd
sanitation is again extremely important
because ripe rotten fruit on the ground
is attractive for flies they will be
attracted from others surroundings into
the field if they have more of that
rotten fruit so keep the field clean any
ripe over ripe rotten fruit it must be
removed as soon as possible and you can
do deal with it two ways number one is
either
seal them in the plastic bags and leave
them for two to three days indirect Sun
that will kill all flies or you can bury
them at least two feet in in the ground
to make sure that larvae or pupils or
our flies don't come out again to become
source of infestation
last part is the post Harvest once you
have harvested fruit and you suspect
there may be infestation is always
possible to to control that or kill
those larvae if you can store the fruit
at 36 degrees
Fahrenheit for up to three days this
will allow more time
for you to market the fruit and also it
will kill majority of the Larry inside
inside the fruit
all right so when we talk about
strawberries pollinators are extremely
important and there is a very little
information about uh wild pollinators in
particular which are extremely important
for pollination in strawberries
so
let's double yield of course and quality
is increased with insect pollination
and what do you mean by pollinator
Health in in this system which is
currently one of the major issues and we
need to take care of it
couple things that can be you know part
of this whole concept of you know how do
we look at pollinator Health pesticide
use of course can negatively affect
pollinator Health if B densities do how
many bees do we have in the field and
Landscape what other sources uh these
bees can feed off of and then that
contributes to overall population and
their activity in the field that leads
to pollination
these are the key or general pollinators
that we anticipate the first one is
enemies of course and the other ones are
wild bees that play the key role in
pollination and Southeastern systems
so what we look for what uh is this kind
of a diagram shows you the red more red
means more negative for uh pesticide if
you know more negative for bees in
lighter color means better system so
first on the top left corner is you know
more pesticides and the top down lower
right corner is the least amount of
pesticides so that is the best one for
for bees bottom line
uh when you know they see an IPM is all
about making decisions and when to take
management action is based on
understanding of which pests are present
and if we need to identify those pests
how many of those pests are there what
type of injury are they causing and how
that injury translates into yield loss
we need to know that by active sampling
active monitoring of those pests and
once we know that then we can get into
making that management decisions
then what management tools are available
and what we can select to make sure that
we will control the past but also we
will not harm the beneficial insects or
other beneficial organisms in the field
that is extremely important component of
Pest Management
so now when it comes to management there
is a really important resource that I
mentioned earlier is the southeast
smallfield Consortium guide that is
developed and updated every year
for the whole region
it's available at
smallfruit.org if you go online
smallfruit.org you can find this guide
and and other small fruit guides as well
this is just the last excuse me this is
the last page of that guide which shows
you know in a one
page all chemicals that are available
and which pests they are effective and
what is the level of efficacy here you
know AE shows Excellence BG very good G
good and and those things are denoted
foreign
of the last a few of last pages at the
end of the guide so I highly recommend
you using this guide as a resource for
strawberry Pest Management it has really
valuable information another resource
that was recently relatively recently
created is in my IPM app it does have
information about strawberry diseases
and pests as well so you can download
that available for both
both apple and other devices Android
devices
foreign
Don Johnson and say uncle Lahiri Who
provided some of the slides that I
shared and also my lab my team and
sponsors that has sponsored our research
with that I'll take any questions if we
have some time