everyone this is Ross in today's video
we're gonna be doing a nice little
potato harvest for you guys what's nice
about harvesting potatoes now it's Jill
its July 20th we've actually been having
a really crazy crazy heatwave here in
Pennsylvania is that I want to focus on
my fall vegetables so one crop comes out
and another crop goes in and this is
kind of really the time to be thinking
about this stuff so if you're in my area
this is really when you need to get
something in the ground otherwise you
know it's gonna get too cold the
daylight hours are gonna really shorten
and you're not gonna reach that maturity
on different things that need a longer
season you know things like Brussels
sprouts as an example or even maybe
things like broccoli it could be quite
difficult for you to get things like
that or cabbages so what I'm doing here
is I'm actually gonna be taking all
these potatoes out we're gonna do the
harvest we're gonna clear this out and
then I'm gonna throw over top of this
compost and then I'm gonna direct seed
into this bed and then we're gonna throw
a row cover over top of it and the
reason for the row cover here I want to
show you this it's a good example is
that it really helps with white fly or
other insects any pests that are coming
in here and potentially attacking our
brassicas or other annuals that we put
in it's really important because in
order to grow brassicas at this time of
the year first off you need a heat
tolerant brassicas today the heat index
is over a hundred right so if it's
really really warm outside you need
something that's gonna not bolt but also
because it's so warm there's certain
insects around that are not normally
around in the fall or in the spring so
there's something called white fly at
least where I live and it comes in here
and really decimates a lot of the larger
brassicas if it really can proliferate
and it also really affects the seedlings
if you direct seed some stuff it gets
those really young seedlings and you're
kind of really off to a horrible start
because if you're damaging those first
few leaves on a seedling it really puts
that seedling far behind so it's
important I think to really have this
row cover on here so again we're gonna
clear this whole thing out
we're gonna stick to mostly in this
video just the potato harvest we can
talk about the variety here as we go
along and then we're gonna cover this
again with compost create ourselves a
nice little no dig bed even though we're
digging in this right now and then we
can really start thinking about either
direct seeding now or actually adding in
some different things like maybe some
garlic we can plant some garlic in here
we can plant some potatoes in here you
know we can plant onions as well so it's
all really up in the air but I want to
get some certain things in the ground
now get the row cover on and I think
this is a nice little transition from
one crop to the other so let me put you
guys down right now and then we can kind
of get into this potato harvest so what
I've been using actually is this this
betting fork I want to show you guys
this now I just got this at the store
and I probably could have found
something maybe a little cheaper and a
little better but this is really nice
for picking up material like hay and and
mulch and and wood chips so I got it
mostly for that but it's pretty good for
getting these potatoes out of the ground
which I didn't really expect them to be
that deep as they are but it seems like
they are and I got to get something in
the ground that's not gonna hopefully
decimate too much of the potatoes not
gonna damage the potatoes it's not gonna
we're gonna be able to get into the
ground it's really hard soil right here
this was not soil that I amended this
was not soil that I really have taken
care of at all this is this was grass
you know four or five months ago and
underneath it is this really heavy clay
so getting through this has been
definitely a challenge you can see
here's the remnants of the potato we
planted this is a variety by the way
called German butterball and
it is supposed to be the tastiest potato
there is it's supposed to be even
tastier than Yukon Gold so what I'm
doing is that we're gonna do a nice
little taste test I think later on I
don't have any Yukon Gold to compare but
we will know for sure based off of what
potatoes tasted like last year let's
pull this one up this harvest doesn't
look this one doesn't look too bad this
one looks a bit better than the other
one some much larger potatoes here
that's good to see oh they're nice and
what's nice about growing your own
potatoes guys one you can choose the
variety okay I mean that's that should
be obvious to us all
there's better varieties in every single
thing that we grow but also they're
really soft buttery
creamy potatoes with a skin that isn't
hard it hasn't been cured yet the skins
really really smooth so this is a really
good eating potato you know that's
really what it's all about is getting a
higher quality product then we can get
at the store and if we can't then what's
the point in my opinion now you can get
these potatoes like this you know you
can get them those really small potatoes
at the store they're usually like
multicolored they have like a blue one a
red one a yellow one
so that exists but yeah they're really
expensive and you can just get yourself
some seed potatoes and it's probably
more worth it at least so far we're
gonna really find out from this harvest
to see if it is indeed worth it but this
may take me quite a bit of time to get
through this entire harvest and I don't
really have the battery for it so let's
see here's some of the potatoes from
that particular plant as I get in by the
way deeper into the bed they're gonna be
more potatoes that's just gonna be a
fact because the potatoes on the edge of
the bed didn't perform well because of
our lawn guys and yeah you're probably
shaking your head long guys but they
really do more damage then they really
hurt more than they help from my opinion
I'm gonna bring you guys over now to a
different planting we had done some in
compost but what we had done has really
stuck the potato just on the top of the
soil like this and then cover that with
so much straw and that was it that's all
we did you can see actually this
potato's quite green so that's not good
this may be something we have to plant
rather than eat but uh let me take you
guys over here instead of putting some
of these guys on our hard clay I put
some in compost and I did the same
method where it's just directly on top
of this
however in fact I Madden even need this
fork because of how loose the soil is
right here so the soil should be looser
more nutritious etc etc everything
should be better ok well I still I'm
gonna need it because we pulled up the
plant but that's all we got and maybe we
could have waited a bit longer with some
of these alright here's some decent
potatoes most of them are like right on
the surface of the compost you can get
in here with your hands this is not bad
at all so you can see the difference
here you know look at this nice soil
compared to the other soil that I was
dealing with so I'm just digging around
in here seeing if there's anything else
in here and I bet you there is but I
don't know if I have the most time to
come in here and just start messing
around with that hi everyone so I want
to show you guys the harvest now we're
really like a few days after what we did
and kind of what we talked about earlier
in the video is getting this whole thing
set up you know the way we want it so
that we can direct seed some brassicas
in here so what we did is just very
simple we took out all the potatoes
really gave this a nice little bed prep
took out all the mulch all that straw
all the tops the potatoes we put that
underneath some of these grapevines here
then also we stuck it over here in a
pile for now because what we're gonna do
is take a lot of woodchips a lot of
mulch and we're gonna put down some
cardboard first underneath these apple
trees clear out a lot of these weeds man
we had just have so many weeds in here
it's been an area that I've neglected
all spring all summer and these apple
trees need it they need more MIDI more
assistance some of these guys don't look
really that great they're on dwarf fruit
stalks they just don't grow very quickly
I think they have weak root systems some
of them have been more susceptible to
things like aphids and other different
things and to be honest with you
I don't really want to grow many things
underneath these trees I think they're
very shallow rooted so we'll put down a
lot of mulch put down a lot of organic
material and that's gonna break down in
the compost over time and we're gonna
have healthier apple trees because of it
but unfortunately it's gonna take a few
years for that to happen but you can see
this is all really planned well and came
out well like this is really nice
soil we've down the just natural soil
conditioner I love this stuff this is
great for growing anything guys it's
half compost and the other half is a
pine bark and that stuff really helps
break down I think it gives a nice
little breakdown of nutrients a bit more
over time whereas you do have some
pieces now which if the soil is broken
down enough which sometimes it's not but
in most cases it is is that it is broken
down enough to really give a good result
in the first year that you use the soil
so for me it's a great for seeding into
it holds lots of water it looks a bit
dry on the surface but underneath it is
completely wet and then later today
because we've already seated this I've
seeded a whole bunch of different
brassicas some carrots different things
like that it's gonna rain about an inch
and a half this is gonna germinate so
well I have this other really about
sixty seventy percent of the bed I
haven't put anything in yet so we're
gonna think about what we can do inside
start some things indoors and then also
think about kind of what I want to do
with garlic next year maybe onions next
year even potatoes next year I'm kind of
debating here's our little potato
harvest by the way and it really is a
bit little I mean it's it's deathly more
potatoes than what I started out with
but not many of them are that big this
one's actually green right here but the
green ones and the larger ones I'm just
gonna replant them probably somewhere
and grow some potatoes next year
probably in a better location this area
doesn't get a whole lot of light also
this is not really the biggest area I
mean I started out with probably around
8 pounds of potatoes
I ordered 10
but I probably only used about eight and
this is a three foot but maybe I don't
know ten foot or twelve foot something
like that if it gets about twelve or
fourteen feet long
then you've got some areas in here
underneath the grapevines which really
don't get a whole lot of light I mean
the fact that I was able to get this
amount of potatoes this is definitely if
I had a guess I would say it's probably
close to 15 pounds maybe 20 pounds so we
maybe doubled what we originally put
into this but to be honest with you it's
probably not the best success and I have
to attribute that probably due to the
fact that this bed there's probably some
potatoes by the way still in here that
are gonna come up as volunteers next
year but I have a feeling that was
largely due to the fact that we probably
should have put down some nice compost
first some well draining soil nutritious
soil yeah that's gonna hold a lot of
water and then bury the potato just just
enough you know we don't have to bury it
too deep and then throw over even more
strong than we did I think the technique
in what I did was a lot less work than
what some people do with their potatoes
I mean potatoes are so easy in general
you literally just put them in the
ground and forget about them come back
90 120 days later and you dig them up I
mean it's so so simple
there's no care involved at all at least
where I live I mean you may have some
pests you may have to water them where
you guys live but for me I did nothing
so for me you know a completely carefree
crop I think it was worth it but would I
do this again for the amount of space
that these took up probably not it's
gonna largely depend on how good these
potatoes are and we talked about the
German butterball and how good German
butter balls supposed to be supposed to
be better than Yukon Gold like we said
earlier in this video when I filmed this
a couple days ago we'll see and also
we'll see you know when I talked about
the skin is that these are probably not
going to be the best baked potato but
they are gonna be the best for cooking
for frying them up in the pan
they're gonna be incredible you know we
could even make probably really good
ships out of them
I really recommend guys for those of you
don't know what Old Bay is invest in
some Old Bay okay
get yourself some potatoes slice them up
real nice and thin cover them with some
old bay a little bit of olive oil put
them in the oven for a really short time
you don't even have the temperature to
hot I think maybe I don't know the exact
temperature but I'm gonna say 300 350
something like that and then put them in
there for about 10 minutes see how they
come out they should start browning a
bit you want them really crispy you
don't want them burnt take them out you
can even sprinkle some more old bay on
at that point oh my god they're so good
so that's kind of it for this video guys
the last thing I want to mention is that
we did talk about I think this covering
here and maybe a different video maybe
we did it in this potato video I'm not
sure but this is really important for
this time of the year especially for
what we've seated a bunch of brassicas
not necessarily the carrots but we want
to protect these young seedlings from
insects some insects you can't really
even see them so it's really important I
think to get this this mesh on and you
know whatever else that I it that it is
that I put in this bed is certainly
excuse me certainly going to be covered
with mesh I have another mesh covering
that I have used on another bed earlier
in the year and we're gonna put this
down here on this one because these
seedlings guys if I get you a nice
closer look you know here's some of the
Brassica seedlings right in here and
they already got some holes in them
they've got some damage on them some
white little marks there that is from
the white fly so certainly on a large
variety of these you know crops that you
guys grow they're gonna have some insect
pressure largely some of them you can't
even most of them you can't even see so
you know I think it's a really good idea
but that is kind of the video here guys
I hope you enjoyed this little harvest
of the potatoes yeah I mean seriously
very easy to grow again I
have to depend on how good they are and
you know how much space I have next year
I'd rather grow a lot more melons I
think next year you know really let them
sprawl along the ground some of the
melons that I have over here doing
decent but a lot of them have been
killed off by the will and if I could
grow them on the ground and cover them
with mesh keep that cucumber beetle out
it's gonna be a phenomenal phenomenal
crop of melons so you know growing them
vertically I think really works but you
have to be on top of surround and
keeping that cucumber beetle away it
just can get a bit tricky here unless
you're growing them in a greenhouse so
anyway guys I want to thank you all for
watching this one if you enjoyed it you
know give us a nice little thumbs up
subscribe check us out on Facebook
Instagram and Twitter
check out the website as well we are
changing the website to a different host
actually not a different host with a
different name different domain so if
you guys are already subscribed to the
website you should continue to be
subscribed but if you haven't already
subscribed check out the blog it is
gonna be something special really
interesting trying to get a lot of
traffic flowing into that direction and
yeah we'll see you guys soon take care
it will see it for tomorrow's video take
care everyone