our presenters tonight in order are lisa
peterson 'if called assurance specialist
based at the central grasslands our EC
and Streeter Jerry stokka
livestock stewardship specialist and
extension veterinarian based in Fargo
Jana Block livestock systems specialist
base at the heading or re C John do
better livestock systems specialist
based at the north central
yeah Minot Carl hoppy livestock systems
specialist based at the Carrington RAC
and Miranda Meehan environmental
stewardship specialist based in Fargo
also with us tonight offering technical
support is Scott Swanson or electronic
media specialist based here in Fargo
again thank you for thank you all for
joining us and I'm going to turn this
webinar over to Lisa well good evening
thank you all for joining us our
speakers tonight all this as specialists
are dealing with many of the same winner
management issues and challenges that
you are and so please feel free to ask
questions I was asked to talk about
assessing cow and ball condition in
managing bolts in a tough winter
situation and so the first thing I'm
going to talk about is body condition
scoring this is a really nice three-step
system for body condition scoring first
I'd encourage you to look at the ribs of
the cow or the bull that's denoted by
number one on your screen if you can see
those last two ribs and that animal is
in a body condition score less than five
if those last two ribs are not visible
that animal is in a body condition score
five or greater next we would encourage
you to look at the spine that's denoted
by number two here on the cap Wow
if that spine is visible the animal is
in a body condition score of three or
less next look at the shape between the
hooks and the pins in the dairy industry
we call that area of the Theroux
if that animal
has a strong v-shape in that area that
animals in a body condition score - if
it's a strong V but a little more flat
that would be a body condition score 3 a
V shape would be a body condition score
4 and then as we move into a u-shape in
that area it would be a body condition
score 5 and as we move into a flatter
shape those move into body condition
scores six seven and eight in the United
States our beef body condition scores
range from a 1 to a 9 a body condition
score one is considered a callable that
is starved very emaciated and a body
condition score 9 is considered an
animal that is obese
so let's look at body condition scoring
we would like to see our animals in a
body condition score 5 to 7 a calving
time those are the two body condition
scores on the right side of the screen
here so we'd like our material cows to
be in a body condition score of 5 again
we are not able to see those last two
ribs the spine is not available it's not
visible
excuse me and the shape between the
hooks and the pins is in a strong
u-shape and so you can see that this cow
at the top on the right hand side is in
a body condition score 5 the cow below
her we cannot see those last two ribs
the spine is not visible in the shape
between her hooks and pins is very flat
and so she's in about a condition score
of 6 or greater now why did we talk
about this well for every body condition
score you lose you lose between 80 and
100 pounds of weight it takes a great
deal of energy and cost to get cows up
in that to increase body condition score
at calving or right before breeding and
so we really are concerned about body
condition score there's a lot of impact
on calf help calf health and calf
productivity along with cow productivity
we tend to forget about bowls when we
manage in the wintertime
and we certainly forget about looking at
our body condition scores of bulls so
these are two bowls the bowl on the left
is a body condition score five again
just like our cows we cannot see his
last two ribs we cannot see his spine
and that shape between his hooks and his
pins is the strong new shape so he's a
body condition score five the ball new
light is a yearling bull this bowl at a
sale time had a back fat of about a
quarter of an inch 2,600 and again as we
look at him you cannot see his last two
ribs his spines not available in this
area between his hooks and misses pins
is very flat and so he's going to be a
body condition score six or greater
so as we move into talking about balls
we have rows around to improve the our
herd but also to breed our cows right
and that's how we get back herd
improvement so let's talk about
spermatogenesis that's the fancy term
for semen development in those that take
61 days or about two months and so
anything that has happened in that
period of time will impact semen quality
and the ability to pass a breeding
soundness exam I always encourage people
to think of semen development as a
factory so anything that has happened
along that production in that line over
the past two months will reserve result
in the lemon in the semen production
system we certainly don't want any
women's when it comes time to breed cows
so what's the effect of body condition
score on semen quality and physically
normal Bulls Waldner embark they are out
of the vet school in Saskatoon at the
University of Saskatchewan looked at
body condition scores of bulls it
breeding sound this time exam time in a
time period from January to March which
is the green bars in April to June which
is the yellow bars we would ideally like
to see balls in the body condition score
of four or five or six at breeding time
and at turnout time and here's the
reason why you can see that the body
condition when we have those boys in
those body condition scores the
percentage of those Bulls the
satisfactory semen goes up significantly
higher so we range from anywhere being
60% satisfactory to 78% and a January to
March timeframe for semen checking to 80
percent almost 85% in that April's June
time frame
so what happens when we buy yelling
bowls or even two-year-old balls at the
local production sale typically those
bowls are a little heavier and
conditioned because we are trying to
optimize production we're trying to
optimize weight gain and marbling in
those bowls and so you can see here on
this screen that this shows a comparison
of bulls that were weighed at say a time
and then weighed again when they were
tested and they looked at the percentage
of balls that would pass braiding
soundness exam so in a short period of
time after that sale 74% to those bulls
has to semen semen test or breeding
soundness exam at that point in time is
those were losing about seven pounds a
day when you get out to about 43 to 85
days after that sale those bills are
losing still about two and a half to
three pounds a day but only half of them
pass the breeding soundness exam so the
take-home messages is that when we buy
these Bulls young bulls a yearling more
two-year-old bowl and take them home we
want to make sure that we are still
maintaining their quality of diet so
that we don't lose a lot of weight body
condition in fact so this year we are
going to see a lot of bowls what you're
likely going to see a lot of bulls with
scrotal frostbite and so what's that
impact on semen quality so in this slide
satisfactory semen quality is in the
green bar questionable semen quality is
in the yellow bar and unsatisfactory
semen quality is in the gray bar I want
you to look at the the boxes with the
red squares around them so they looked
at frostbite and they graded frostbite
by the number of scabs that were a penny
or larger or a penny and smaller severe
frostbite were those scat were those
Bulls that had one or more scabs on
their scrotum that were larger than a
penny slight was one or more that were
smaller so when we look at severe
frostbite in bowls that had breeding
soundness exams for example conducted it
from January to March zero men
those bowls had what we would consider
to be a satisfactory breeding soundness
exam somewhere around 30% had what we
would consider to be a questionable one
as we move down here to may in June you
can see that the percentage of bulls
that have satisfactory breeding
soundness exams or semen quality
increases significantly so the take-home
message is to protect the scrotum and
testicles from the cold
the easiest way most logical way to do
that is with some good wind break and
good bedding and so on the picture on
the left you can see that these bulls
are bedded with some nice straw and
there's some really nice natural wind
break through these trees this can also
be a man-made one break how weather that
happens to be stacks of bales or some of
these portable wind breaks as you can
see in Canada maybe they protect the
scrotum and testicles of boughs a little
bit different they utilized a Crown
Royal sac we know that that is maybe not
appropriate here and the easiest thing
to do
so in summary both should be in the body
condition score of 4 to 7 a pre breeding
to command it turn out we want those
boys to maintain condition through the
breeding season but we don't want them
to be too fast maintain young recently
purchased Bulls on a similar plane of
nutrition and diet as they were when
they were purchased and then slowly
stepped them down if you have not done
so check out the body condition scores
of your herd sires now ask someone who's
knowledgeable about cattle to check out
the body condition score of your herd
after bulls and cows to don't confuse
hair muscle and/or hey belly with a
condition and get help developing a
ration if you need to add some condition
this is really important in bills
because we don't want to get them too
fat and we don't want to step them up on
too hot of a diet
most of our County Extension offices
have software and rash and development
ability if you need some help
next we talked about this betting bills
and in fact betting cattle is really
important provide some windbreak
breeding soundness exams really
important we need to have our bills
tested within a month of breeding season
that gives us enough time to find those
if our bows happen to not test well but
it also is an appropriate amount of time
for them to have that breeding soundness
exam be accurate when you turn them out
don't save pennies to waste dollars by
skipping a breeding soundness again exam
most veterinarians charge 50 to $100 for
breeding soundness exam and while that
seems like a lot of money think about
this if your cows breed just 21 days
later because you're both failed a
breeding soundness exam that ends up
being some around 50 pounds of weaning
weight if calves sell for a dollar and a
half a pound that is $75 per head that
you have lost you could have paid for
that breeding soundness exam with just
one calf remember that that semen test
is only good for the day it was taken
and that semen development takes 60 days
and so with that thank you I wish you
the best of luck and as we move into
spring and next dr. Jerry stuck is going
to talk about managing calves that have
been chilled and pulled stress and
calves idea Lisa good to be with you
this evening I know that this is really
not a topic that it's all I'm enjoyable
to talk about we're gonna talk about it
anyway we've still got winter left and a
storm coming and I hope none of you have
to deal with cold stress calves but
we're gonna focus in for the next few
minutes on talking about how we handle
and how we deal with it and how we
recognize
well these are the three things we're
gonna discuss we're gonna talk about how
to recognize a calf and maybe in trouble
and I'm sure that's nothing new for
those of you in the audience you know
how to tell when calves aren't doing
well or doing right we're going to talk
about them in for intervention and then
maybe some things about what the
outcomes might be you know I noticed
some things that all of us are gonna
talk about betting and wind protection
come into play here and and yet the snow
months are talking about it does cause
us some issues it's supposed to be wet
snow and whenever we have those kind of
conditions the problem with moisture is
that it decreases the level of
insulation on an animal it's not just
the cows but it's those calves and those
those calves with not a lot of body
weight not a and a lot of surface area
they tend to suffer the most when it
gets to be these tough conditions so you
need to be doing what you can be out
there as often as you can during this
tough weather I know you're gonna
probably lose some sleep over the next
few days but being out there probably
saves you some calves and so think about
what your schedule is and if you can get
somebody to check calves for you during
the night time or even even the day
times you can get some sleep sure helps
barns through help and just a reminder
to keep them as clean as possible and
fresh bedding at this time of the year
um I just want to talk a little bit
about behavior of animals that are under
some stress and and cold stress and and
remember that cold stress can happen in
a lot of different outside temperatures
I mean the critical temperature for
calves is probably somewhere around 55
degrees so and all that means that is
when the temperature goes below that
they have to take in more energy to
maintain that body heat
we'd like 55 degrees now but calves can
handle it if they if they're able to get
up and nurse and the mother takes care
of them but the behavior that you need
to be aware of that they'll exhibit when
they're in cold stress is maybe standing
off by themselves and hunched up and and
of course you'll see that when there
can't get out of the wind but they also
can be just laying down even next to the
mother and you won't notice it and you
need to determine whether that calf is
nursed or not and sometimes I'll admit
it's hard to it's hard to determine that
but look at the otter do the teats look
dry and when it's moisture outside they
probably won't look dry they'll look wet
but is the hair on the utter dry or the
other quarters full a lot of things to
look for but if you're still wondering
you need to put your fingers and clean
fingers preferably in the mouth and see
if that mouth is cold if that mouth is
cold they have not nursed and you're
gonna have to intervene and and even
beyond that when you get a calf that's
cold and vocalising that is a really bad
clinical sign I sometimes use the term
five percent chance of survival so the
prognosis in a calf that's vocalizing is
really really poor we define hypothermia
and calves as anything below 98 degree
Fahrenheit rectal temperature you know
newborn calves should be somewhere in
that 90 902 we can actually have severe
hypothermia down to 86 degrees those
calves will definitely need to be
intervened I don't I don't I'm not
telling you need to run around with a
rectal thermometer I'm telling you that
you can probably identify those calves
that need help just by their behavior if
you have one that's fine but it's not
something you need to need to have to
identify calf that needs help
this is just a reminder that better days
are ahead we will get through this March
and we will have green grass and some of
you will have calves on green grass just
remember this doesn't these next two
days don't last forever just want to
make a couple of comments about this in
order for a calf to maintain its
maintain its core temperature and
maintain its life when it's cold out he
has to increase metabolic activity and
of course that happens when that calf
leaves the uterine environment that's
nice and warm and and safe and all the
shop know all the sudden he shoved out
into the the cold environment and so his
metabolic activity has to really jump
ahead and get on board there so
mentioned that the metabolic activity
will increase 5x over the resting phase
and I mean what calves end up doing is
they end up shivering and that helps
them to to generate heat and I've got a
comment in here below sharing its talks
about calving difficulty when a calf is
having trouble being born or the mothers
having trouble delivering that calf that
actually is a detriment to that calves
ability to withstand cold temperatures
because it messes with the metabolic
activity even a calf that's born
unassisted is going to have increased
cortisol and just a little bit of
cortisol allows that calf to better
utilize fat we're going to talk about
brown fat in just a little bit but also
the sugar stores the glycogen and
protein to create heat and what happens
in cold temperatures in addition to
increased metabolic activity when it's
cold out there's vasoconstriction in
other words the vessels will constrict
and you don't have that that blood flow
to the ears and feet and tail and that's
why when it gets really cold and you see
problems a result that's that's the
pieces of the anatomy that that get
affected the most just a little comment
on calving is just to back up what I
just mentioned about calving knees and
calves ability to withstand cold and get
up and nurse I'm answering something
about brown fat and we don't often think
about that you think
in terms of white fat while calves are
born with brown fat and and they have
the unique ability and it's gone after
just a short period of time but they
have an unique ability to use that fat
to keep warm and and calves that are
born to cows an adequate body condition
score back to what Lisa was talking
about those calves will have a little
better supply of brown fat that gets
them through the tough times and gets
them to get up and start nursing so it's
a big deal having cows and in adequate
body condition score especially cold
temperatures it's really important just
a couple comments about colostrum we'll
come back to this again in just a bit if
you think about a calf in thermo neutral
zone thermo neutral zone and I mentioned
this earlier but the mono thermo neutral
zone for calf's probably somewhere in
that 50 to 55 degree fahrenheit range
they need in order to maintain their
their heat source they need almost two
thirds of a gallon of colostrum milk
colostrum will different for cod a cow
and from from breed to breed and dairy
breeds and beef breeze but just there
kind of an idea of what those calves at
calves actually need and when that
temperature falls below that thermo
neutral zone then they actually need a
little bit more just to maintain their
their energy that they need for internal
body heat and remember that our beef
cattle do an amazing job of acclimating
to the cold when I talk about thermal
neutral zone I mean our cattle grow
longer hair they do lots of things to
acclimate to the cold if they didn't we
wouldn't be able to raise cattle out pop
doors I mean even in temperatures way
below zero if the sun is shining and
there's no win and they're laying
embedding those calves actually do
extremely well frostbite is one of the
one of the side effects of this cold
stress that you can have it can have
frostbite rot on the skin but a lot of
times what we see happen first is that
the tips of the years will freeze and
then they old necrosis and then they'll
fall off and that's okay those calves
will be okay if it's just the tips of
the years the one that becomes really
dangerous is when their feet freeze and
you'll notice you can notice this early
on perhaps when when you feel the feet
and they're just frozen solid and if you
don't notice that then those calves will
actually get up and move around and be
fine but after a day or so maybe about
48 hours those feet become swollen they
actually get a little what I call
squishy because there's edema fluid in
the tissues and and they're painful and
you can wait a while to see if somehow
there's a miracle that occurs and they
improve but they're most of the time
they're not going to be treatable at
those at that stage and those calves
will likely have to be put down
so how do we heat those calves up lots
of different ways lots of different
methods you know heaters floor heats and
blankets and hot boxes and I just want
you to think about this though because
when a calf is really hypothermic you
know I mentioned that 86 degree rectal
temperatures is extreme hypothermia it's
going to be hard to conduct enough heat
through the hide to raise that internal
body temperature so and in order to do
that really the calf has to also have
the ability to produce heat and that's
why in both of these instances those
calves need colostrum I know you're in a
hurry to get that calf formed up but
some time during that period when you're
warm and you you got to provide
colostrum because that allows calf that
calf to get some energy that it really
needs warm water is tends to be very
efficient at warming calves and some of
you may have bathtubs available
sometimes you need to carry them right
in the house and put them in the bathtub
100 degrees fahrenheit water and I'd be
like I'll just caution you a little bit
sometimes it's okay to warm those calves
up a little bit with dry heat first so
that it's not so much of a shock so
robbing and putting external heat on is
okay so you can start to raise some of
that temperature but the bathtub still
may be needed in those calves that are
extremely help affirming and also they
need colostrum yes this is my famous
picture of a calf in the bathtub and
that one actually did survive believe it
or not
um just a couple comments again on
colostrum itself fresh is the best some
is better than none and sometimes you
need to put that beef cow that doesn't
know that you're trying to help her in
the calf got to put up in ahead catch
and this is where you need some help you
need somebody to grab the tail any of
the bass and move it to a vertical
position so she won't kick so much and
put your head in that flank and milk the
nearest heat and then once they kind of
calm down you can kind of release some
pressure but that fresh colostrum is the
best energy source immune source that
those calves need frozen classrooms fine
I prefer if you harvest it from your own
herd I'm a little leery of taking frozen
claws from from other herds and from
dairy herds
there are colostrum substitutes on the
market today
and look at the label make sure they got
a minimum of hundred grams of
immunoglobulins that those calves need I
know always get questions about brandy
and whisky and 5-hour energy drinks
brandy and whisky I'm pretty sure are
designed for human consumption I'm not
sure about five hours I don't know of
any studies done on them so stick with
the things you know colostrum is the
best
I'm going to pass this over at this time
to Janna block our extension livestock
specialist out in heading her Janna you
take it away
all right thanks Jerry okay so I'm gonna
be visiting with you a little bit about
how to evaluate your nutrition program
and I know it's been a long haul for
many of us and still looking like we're
facing a little bit of winter so it's
important to be really critical and
evaluate what's going on with your
nutrition programs as we try to finish
out the rest of this winter and head
into spring so things that we need to
consider our obviously quality and
quantity of our base diet most the time
that's going to consist of forage so
don't be like the guy on this cartoon
here and let the whitetail show you
which are the best bales get your hay
inventory conducted and I'll talk about
an example of that shortly and also make
sure you get nutrient analysis conducted
so that you know exactly what you're
dealing with
obviously you have to know what
different types of production groups
that you have to take care of if you've
got some first-half heifers some old
thin cows mature cows or bulls those are
all going to have different requirements
and you're going to need to feed them
strategically based on your feed
resources most of you are calving now or
you have been for some time and so
that's going to impact requirements in
terms of when your cows gets peak
lactation which is approximately 60 days
after calving that's also going to
really kind of match up with our pasture
turnout dates in terms of when we have
to feed that high quality forage win
requirements out there at highest what's
the condition of our cow herd evaluate
body condition score and I'll talk about
a couple of other strategies to kind of
monitor nutrient status and then of
course your considerations are going to
always come back to the bottom line what
kind of costs are you looking at what
facilities and labor do you have
available and you might need to consider
some alternatives rather than just a
full feed hay diet okay so this chart
gives you just some rule of thumb for
estimating can take based on energy
content or a TD n total digestible
nutrients so as you can see here the low
quality
Raja's will have the least amount of
intake that's just due to bulk or
physical fill due to fiber content and
so our dry cows are going to be able to
eat around one at 1.8 percent of their
body weight of that low quality forage
lactating cows will increase the intake
of that and again intake will just
continue to increase as forage quality
increases and I have just an example of
down here on the bottom of comparing an
intake of a low quality forage @ 30.8
pounds to a high quality forage at 37.8
pounds so again that's where
understanding the quality of your forage
is helpful and this can be used when
you're looking at your hay inventory and
trying to figure out what the intake
should be on various forages based on
quality
so Jimmy kind of mentioned the lower
critical temperature so in beef cattle
that's just the temperature below which
they have to utilize energy to maintain
body heat and so in mature cattle we're
talking about 32 degrees with a dry
winter coat or 18 degrees with a heavy
dry winter coat and so as the
temperature starts to decline you can
see that feed intake will increase
energy for production is lost and the
maintenance requirement increases so we
can utilize the ambient temperature and
wind speed to calculate an effective
temperature and we use this effective
temperature to determine how much
additional energy those cattle are going
to require just to maintain body heat so
again a basic rule of thumb is to
increase T DT DN or energy by one
percent for every degree below the lower
critical temperature so if we have the
dry heavy winter coat that I talked
about in the previous slide our lower
critical temperature is 18 degrees so if
we have air temperature of zero in a
wind speed of 20 we're looking at an
effective temperature of minus 39 so we
take our lower critical temperature
minus our -39 and with those cows are
going to require 57% more energy so just
going through some nutrition
calculations here and I know I'm
throwing a lot of numbers at you I can
definitely get you copies of this slide
or you can print it from the webinar
later just showing you the relative
difference in how much energy is going
to be required by that cow just based on
that wind speed and temperature and so
if we were able to feed that cow then
not afford to that she's going to need
to meet her energy requirements she'd be
eating 3.6 percent of body weight that
might be possible in some feed black
diets that's still on the high side and
probably not possible with our forage
based diets so we have to find some
other ways to reduce maintenance
requirements and the amount of feed that
those cows are going to require so just
a couple ways that you can do that many
of you are probably already doing some
of these things need to think about
providing some higher quality forages or
grain or by-product feeds just more
energy-dense feeds
again forage will generate the most
amount of heat per unit but we can't get
in the forage into them based on that
really high energy requirement and it's
also difficult for cattle to utilize our
quality feeds when it's cold because
intake increases passage rate increases
and nutrient utilization will actually
decrease and so just providing the
higher quality feeds is a good idea at
that time separating off thin and young
cows seperate and feeding them
separately is a good idea if you have
facilities just to give them a little
more attention and again be strategic
about the cattle that you need to maybe
provide a little more nutrient-dense
feeds also Lisa mentioned that Gerry
mentioned it wind breaks and shelter are
really critical that's going to really
help reduce the effect of the windchill
and reduce that effective temperature if
natural shelter isn't available need to
get out there and provide some portable
wind brakes tires hay bales whatever
you've got a lot of you already probably
feed in late afternoon or early evening
if you can stand it I know a lot of
times it's hard for producers to kind of
wait to feed but basically what that
does is just kind of generates more heat
of fermentation later in the middle of
the night when those cattle me with most
and typically the temperatures at the
lowest wanted to just mention hay waste
most producers are utilizing round bales
and that's good for minimizing labor but
we do know that studies have shown that
waste is could be pretty high when
you're rolling out bales twenty to forty
five percent so you are in the situation
where you're having to unroll bales out
on feed ground it's a good idea to try
to limit access a one versus a four day
supply they've shown that is a waste is
reduced by twenty percent so obviously
if we're coming into a blizzard
situation and you feel like you need to
put a few days of feed out go ahead and
do that this is just thinking long term
over the entire feeding period providing
it one day at a time is probably your
best bet feeding on fresh ground if
possible is going to be important to
increase utilization and intake and then
obvious
defeating low-quality hey first and
trying to encourage them to consume all
that before they go to the high quality
feeds it's really difficult to put out
high quality feed and then kind of force
them to go back and consume that low
quality forage so we're thinking about
reducing waste a couple things come to
mind obviously using a bail processor so
basically that just functions to reduce
particle size increase passage rate and
then increase intake so it's a good way
to increase utilization of low to medium
quality forages disadvantages possibly
some increased costs due to labor fuel
investment in equipment you can also get
some leaf loss particularly on windy
days which we have a lot here in Norfolk
North Dakota so that's just a
consideration you can look at your
increased feed availability and
utilization versus the amount of cost
that it's going to take to get you there
hay feeders are certainly another option
they've been shown to really reduce
feeding losses it doesn't work in every
situation obviously but the cone feeder
with a waste panel at the bottom it's
definitely a consistent feeder that
results in the least amount of hay waste
so this just goes back to calculating
you know conducting a hay inventory and
calculating how much you're going to
need to get you through the rest of the
winter
again just a couple of examples here so
we need to know body weight of our cows
need to know the percent of body weight
as forage that they're consuming and
that's based on forage quality which you
get from your forage analysis and then
we're going to need to calculate in a
waist factor here to get pounds of
forage consumed per cow per day just
example 1400 pounds eating 2 and 1/2
percent of body weight I put in the
waist factor of 25 percent and so
they're gonna be eating red needy right
around 44 pounds per cow per day if we
have a 60 day feeding period to get
through hopefully we're gonna have green
forage available after that and so
that's the total amount of forage needed
per cow you also need to know your Bale
weights and your dry matter again that's
your nutrient analysis and so based on
our vale weight and a 90% dry matter
that's how much dry matter we have
will prevail so we end up right around
2.2 bales per cow and you could do a
quick estimation of this just based on
one bale per cow per month adding in a
little bit of extra like I said for
waste and this doesn't necessarily mean
that this is exactly how much each cow
needs I'm just gonna have to adjust
based on temperature condition forage
quality and all those other factors that
we've kind of talked about when you do
look at supplementing some low quality
forages it's important to know what your
goal is and how to most effectively meet
that goal and so if we're talking about
low quality forages that have less than
7% protein that's the point at which
ruminal fermentation could be limited
and so we need to look at providing a
high quality protein supplement
containing greater than 20% so we've got
alfalfa hay soybean meal distillers
grains the nice thing about cows is they
can be fed these every two to three days
because of their ability to recycle
nitrogen if you've got a forage with
greater than 7 percent protein might
need to look at supplying an energy
supplement and again that's going to be
based on the different requirements of
your various production groups and you
need to kind of look at whether you
choose a fibre versus a starch based
supplement so some of our fiber
supplements are soy hulls wheat myths
and distillers grains and our starches
are our feed grains corn barley and
other things like that so we know if we
feed too much starch on a forage based
diet it's gonna reduce digestibility and
intake of the forage and that's just
based on changes to microbial population
so there's some things you can do to
strategic and make sure that you're
meeting those needs effectively without
too much impact on the microbes just
when I quickly show you a feed cost
calculator this was developed jointly by
the North Dakota farm management
education program and NDSU Extension
this is just a simple Excel spreadsheet
and you can go in and customize all of
your feed stuffs and you can put in
weight we thought it was really
important to include your trucking cost
how many miles that you have to
incorporate when you're evaluating that
so you get a total tracking cost you can
go down here and nutrient content
and use your values from your feet
analysis and plug those in it'll
calculate your dry matter per ton your
new trip your energy and protein per ton
and what you end up with is dollar
amount per pound of nutrient and so
that's what we want you to use to
compare supplements when you're trying
to make those supplementation decisions
and just a couple additional
considerations before I turn it over to
John really important to not forget
about water we know that cold use is
going to increase metabolic water use
and so this time of year we don't think
about cow's water requirements as much
as we do in the heat of summer but they
still require adequate water for making
sure that we get good feed I jest in the
utilization and maintain performance and
health especially with lactating cows
so probably minimum a gallon 400 pounds
of body weight I know people have had a
huge amount of challenges this year I'm
just dealing with ice and the tanks so a
couple different options here for tanks
that maybe aren't next to an electric
source a propane stock tank heater
there's water circulators some of those
may result in some excess water flow and
so that can be a challenge but check
into different products that are
available out there and then another
thing is you just need to once we get
your forage analysis done your hay
inventory done want to take a look at
how that's performing in your cow herd
again evaluate that body condition score
and take a look at manure consistency
this pile here or there's not really a
lot of solid rating shows that that cows
getting a little bit of excess protein
here we have adequate protein but you
see some rings and again there's usually
a crater type appearance at the top of
the pile and then down here we get into
deficient protein
there's definitely very obvious rings
and usually this manure pile would be
very firm so that's just one other
option for evaluating the nutrient
status of your herd again I've known
I've thrown a lot at you tonight be sure
to contact me if you have questions or
put them in the chat box and I'm going
to go ahead and turn things over to John
do better and he's going to talk to you
about
in limited hey Thank You Jana welcome to
anybody who might have joined us on the
webinar up here in mine it we've had a
couple days a reprieve from the weeks
and weeks of bitter cold wind chills
which stressed a lot of things equipment
people a livestock and calves and
unfortunately I think we're all aware
that there's some more stuff coming to
North Dakota and some new challenges
with some blizzard conditions
it's truly amazing to me just how Hardy
our cattle are is these pictures kind of
illustrate they can cope with a lot when
we do our part to get them out of the
wind have a little back pad on them and
keep their rumen full so they generate
some heat of fermentation and have some
energy to deal with the wind chills and
the cold in the cases when we can't do
that for one reason or another we got
some cattle suffering from some lameness
or age it's pretty conceivable to have
cows lose three or four pounds a day in
a condition score within less than a
month of time we've talked about how
their energy needs go up with the cold
and the wind chill and along with that
their appetites go up the rate of
passage goes up they can eat more feed
and we a stock them and give them more
feed because it's absolutely necessary
what that does though is it puts us in a
position now that some things have
happened what we thought was an adequate
feed supply all sudden is starting to
look a little short and we've got some
instances of people running a little low
and concerned that their hay might not
get them to where they need to go how
that happens is just looking at what
we've had to do if we've been feeding 35
pounds of hay normally under more normal
weather and we've had weeks upon weeks
of extreme weather with minus 40 and 30
wind chills daily and we've had 50
pounds we've all sudden fed 40 percent
more hay over those two months that's
led us to a situation where we might
have to adapt some management to stretch
the aid that we still have we're not
there any worse close to grass for most
of us turnout might be in mid-may even
late May so we need to have a plan on
how we're going to get there one of the
things that we can do is we could
probably go out and try to find some
additional hay the reality of being able
to find it and the cost we might be able
to locate it
or is probably time to look at some
other alternatives most cases beating
some grain or concentrate feed and
limiting the hay somewhat might be an
option that we really have to consider
Lee sit consider I've got two rations in
this slide one for the last month of
gestation the one for the and one for
the first month of lactation as calving
is undergoing right now we know what a
cow needs for her energy needs and we
know we can supply that with medium to
better quality hay if we've had 40
pounds in late gestation or fed 45
pounds in early lactation if we don't
have that much hey we could restrict the
hay to probably 30 pounds feed 5 or 6
pounds of corn and with the bedding and
a little extra straw out there to help
her get content and fill up the room and
we could still meet her tdn or energy
needs if we happen to have a limited
supply hay but we're long on silage we
can adjust the ration as well to feed a
lower percent hey maybe a third hay
two-thirds or more silage and we can
mean her needs that way now I recognize
some people are a little careful about
how much silage a high-energy feed they
could feed a calving time bill concerned
about hi milk production to a young calf
who can't handle it the potential will
cause some digestive or scouring calves
but we can manage that by limiting that
to an appropriate level feeding grain is
a little different than feeding hay so
we got to take things a little slower
and understand that we got a potential
to cause some digestive problems if we
don't do it right for the most part it's
a new feed to cow it's a fast digesting
feed and it should be introduced into
the rash and fairly slowly we don't want
any cows to overeat too fast
create and acidotic rumen and might have
some consequences of bloat and Founder
and so forth
typically we also want to try to feed
these start to your grains at a low
percent of the ration just so we don't
interfere with the digestion of the
fiber that might be in the ration we
still get the value out of our forages
general that's feed
less than four 10% of body weight or in
the cows in this state that might be
four to six pounds for wheat and barley
we know cracking them breaking the seed
coats gonna create intensive
digestibility of those feeds and we also
like Janice said some of our rations may
be short of protein and maybe a grain
by-product which is typically higher in
protein may be more appropriate than
feeding just a straight grain as well as
when we feed these byproducts or a
higher grain ration they're high in
phosphorous low in calcium you might
want to consider that or check our
mineral to make sure we're not over
feeding phosphorus and under feeding
calcium and pick a mineral with the
right blender proportions of those two
but most importantly if we're gonna feed
a limit amount of grain to a herd of
cows we have to have a way of getting it
out there get distributed so we don't
have some cows eating excessive amounts
that some cows not getting enough so we
got to give each cow her fair share and
distribute the grain over a pretty wide
area for that to happen one of the
biggest challenges is how you do that
how you get four or five pounds of grain
to your cows you know timely matter and
everybody gets a share and it's hard to
handle grain if all you've got is a
loader tractor for most people who are
for people who are feeding a mixed
ration it's a feed bragging certainly
just weighing in the grain adding it to
the mix of forages and feeding it out
works very well some people are not
equipped with silage you're gonna feed
silage and so we've got some other
options with that and we could probably
get a cake feeder or kick box go out
there and put it all on the ground or we
can add an attachment to a you know a
bale process or some of them have
hoppers you can put 2030 bushels of corn
or grain in and top dress the Shred hay
feeding grain has also got some
challenges and that sometimes it's
pretty difficult with a large herd of
cattle to feed them in such a way that
we can actually minimize the waste you
know if we've got hard frozen ground dry
sod or compacted snow and ice
you know cows will do a pretty good job
of licking up grain off of those
surfaces however if we get some slush
and mud and deep snow
it won't work very well in those cases
we almost have to go to feeding these
things in some kind of a bunk system or
if we're feeding it on the sod or the
ground
certainly it's even better to feed small
piles that's with a trip hopper on your
feeding attachment so we put little
files over a roll rather than a
continuous very small shallow line of
grain certainly grain feeding is a
weight and stretch artery for a little
bit it's also something that we might be
kind of required to as hay by the hay
piles this diminishes and we just have
to stretch everything so we're gonna do
what it takes and I commend you for
being the Stockman you are and you know
taking care of these cattle under these
difficult conditions and now I'm gonna
turn it over to dr. Karl toppy and he's
gonna talk to us a little about where
maybe we can source some of these
additional treats
thank you John I know in our part of the
world here when has really been extended
cold and I hear you've been used up
pretty quickly this year and we're now
looking for other options to supplement
our cow herds so I'll turn the feeds are
certainly one of those things can be
used co-product feeds are moderate to
high in protein they're moderate to high
in energy content as well a couple of
things that poor quality forages straws
definitely need to have added to it so
Coke products work well as a supplement
or a partial replacement for a forage
space ration we're excitingly well for
low quality forages like straws or
Slough Hays or we've already used our
good quality feeds and
we need to add something to the poor
quality feeds co-products certainly are
something that Brooke held quite well
surprisingly North Dakota has many
co-products Mills crushes refineries and
processing plants across the state when
you get the other states they don't have
the number of opportunities that we have
in North Dakota now I recognize that
most of these crushes and mills and
processing plants are located in the
eastern part of the state which means
that we have ready access on our side
and western side of the state they have
the same access but they have freight
costs and EPA
just how much coke products do we
produce in North Dakota there's two
examples that I'll share of just how
much volume we produce our state mill
and elevator that's owned by the state
of North Dakota it's the largest single
durum wheat mill located in the world at
one location there's other companies
that are bigger but we actually have the
largest in one location at mills 90,000
bushels of wheat a day our durum into
flour semolina that means it produces a
co-product they mail out the starch the
co product the fiber and the proteins
are left over and that's called wheat
meds or wheat middlings and they produce
a hundred ton a day which is around 33
semi-loads just to give a feeling at 10
pounds per head per day they produce
enough feed to feed 20,000 head of
cattle uh daily North Dakota has 900
thousand head of cattle almost a million
head of cattle so you can see that 20%
of our of our cowards in North Dakota
could be fed just what would produce out
of this one particular mill it's a
high-quality feed of 18 percent crude
protein and 83 percent
even more production in co-product
feeders found in our ethanol
distilleries across North Dakota we have
five plants in North Dakota they produce
3,000 3,500 to 4,000 tons daily of
distillers grains that's on a dry matter
basis give them the cow inventory that
we have we could feed seven pounds of
distillers grace utilizes feed to every
cow every day or if we just looked at a
seventh month period we could feed
twelve pounds of distillers grains per
day there's that much product produced
in North Dakota 12 pounds of distillers
grains would really take the edge off of
how much hay is needed for our cow
ration not only that if you look at 30
percent good protein you're giving
almost three and a half pounds of crude
protein per cow per day which just is a
heck of a lot of protein to provide to a
cow but on a poor quality ration that
might be something at Cal certainly
needs this time of the year again it's
38 percent crude protein and eighty-six
EDM again high-quality feeds go products
there's two big issues that occur with
them and that's going to be the pricing
of it as well as the freight
freight costs can get to be pretty high
it's very competitive with other local
feeds when you look at the price of
these Co products but you have to
include the price of the freight Western
North Dakota certainly will have a
higher costs on our eastern part of
North Dakota it has to compete with our
other feats like grains Hays and other
available Co products but there are some
limitations on our products there are
some long-term stability issues with
some wheat meds tend to take moisture
out of the air and consequently mold
unless they've been put on the air floor
during the summertime the cellar screens
used to have abridging problems with it
you can still have things like
distillers excuse me wheat mids is very
light and fluffy unless it's pelleted
which increases density to foal and
makes it a lot easier to transport some
feeds like the wet corn gluten feed or
the wet distillers grains or beet
tailings or beet pulp all are high in
moisture and of course mold can become
an issue to calculate and cost per pound
a nutrient and easily be done it's just
a matter of taking the feed that you're
going to be using and taking the cost
per ton and dividing it by the energy
content of the feed so in this example I
used $90 ton wheat meds that has an 80
60 DM you do the math and all of a
sudden your cost per pound of protein
counted tdn or energy content is five
cents a pound if you need these tdn
values go to our NDSU a s 1182
alternative by-product feeds publication
that has a directory of of prices of tdn
values in the end the price of TD n
values
we have a bunch of co-products across
North Dakota in most parts they're all
low in starch and high in fiber and high
in protein feeds that are perfect for a
coward that's being fed a low for a low
quality forage in the milling process or
fermentation process most of the starch
is removed in these products and/or the
oil if it's a oil seed results going to
be something that's very high in fiber
and usually high in protein - and this
fiber I need to point out is very
digestible in the rumen diet distillers
grains are produced in five different
plants in North Dakota third senescent
all at Casselton Hank is in renewable
energy at Hank and Sutton Dakota spirit
AG ethanol spirit wood bluefin ethanol
at underwood as well as red trail energy
at Richardson it's a very popular feed
you can see some of the values over here
it's very palatable that that's an
understatement cows really go after the
sweet quite well it mixes well with
other feeds conditions the feed maybe
there's a limit to 30% of the diet this
is some of the sulfur issues that you
want to use there are ethanol plants and
other parts of the in South Dakota and
other states that can be trucked into
North Dakota too right now they've
raised the price of distillers grain so
it's still cost competitive but at $160
a ton it's no longer the cheapest feeds
out there that we can provide to our cow
herd wheat middlings is another option
there's five plants in North Dakota that
produces wheat meds
Dakota growers in Carrington Minot
milling in Minot iron in milling down at
Fairmont
of course North Dakota Mellon Alva that
we talked about in Grand Forks and to a
lesser extent the plant up in can do
some of these have already been their
source to supply has been booked out for
the year although at the mill and
elevator and Dakota growers availability
is still available an 80 or 90 dollars a
ton turns into a fairly competitive feed
corn gluten feed is created through the
process of a wet corn milling which is
the plant located on a Wahpeton North
Dakota at Cargill of course when corn
milling makes high fructose corn syrup
and the leftover product is 83% tdn 20%
protein very palatable it can be sold as
either dried or wet you need to contact
these people because usually
availability is was rather reduced
because they're sold out it's that
popular
it's very palatable soy hauls is a
product that we haven't had in North
Dakota unless we Freight it in for
Minnesota or South Dakota until the
recent several years now the ADM planted
Enderlin is producing soy hauls since
they're now crushing North Dakota
soybeans so high energy content feed
it's pelleted it's protein can range
from 8 to 13 percent so be sure to know
what your product is if you may not be
considered a protein source for your
feed but it certainly is a replacement
for for our feed I do have to point out
that it's usually high in calcium and
low in phosphorus most of our other co
products are always high in phosphorus
maybe triple x amount of phosphorus it
would be in green and of course calcium
is quite low a coin like John identified
adding extra calcium to co-product feeds
is always indicated
if you're located close enough to a beet
pulp plant or a sugar refinery like
American crystalline Hillsboro
drayton East Grand Forks or Crookston or
even min dak down at Wahpeton
they have a supply of beet pulp and
tailings that they usually at least
American crystal provides a no cost
other than trucking bar says you need to
be on the list to be able to get it and
if you have a trucker that hauls that
this is a product that works quite well
I think of it as a nice replacement for
silage if it's if you're feeding the wet
pulp or the wet retailing be sure to
know if the moisture content is quite
high so that's what limits trucking to
usually around a hundred miles away from
the plant before other sources of feed
get to be priced more competitive we do
have protein sources or crushes in North
Dakota canola meal is very popular if
that's all you need it's usually priced
competitive it's produced in Belva as
well as in Belem or West Fargo even up a
holic Minnesota these plants are
available linseed Mills crushed him in
Cargill and West Fargo on a sporadic
basis but it is available soybean meal
is priced very high and it works quite
well if you want to use soybean in your
ration that's produced down ADM and
envelope 46% crude protein the real
bargain on these particular protein
sources right now a sunflower meal so if
you're needing protein sunflower meal
could be a hundred and twenty dollars a
ton even less than that and it's
available out of Cargill and West Fargo
and it can be available out of northern
Sun and Android if you
need to have a list of co-products
boasts the phone numbers as well as a
recent price please go to our account
and research extensions on their
homepage on the internet and look for
livestock and then look for livestock
extension and then click on sources and
prices for selected Co products in North
Dakota and with that good luck in trying
to source extra feed for your cow herd
if you're running yourself short on hay
and can't find a there is a vast amount
of co products available in North Dakota
if you can find out what's available our
next speaker is going to be Miranda
Meehan she's our environmental livestock
environmental steward specialist and dr.
Meehan is here to talk to us about
pasture and range turnout issues
good evening so I'm gonna just change
paces a little bit here and talk about
as what we expect as we look forward to
a greener grass especially into some
strategies to help you plan for the 2019
grazing season one thing I want to keep
you all to keep in mind is that yes we
do have a lot of snow and there's a lot
of moisture in that snow but due to of
the timing of melt and in how things
melt a lot of that snow is going to be
run off and yes it's going to be great
for refilling some of our stock dams and
surface waters however that is not going
to be available there's not going to be
the principal source of responsible for
our forage production this year 80
percent of forage production in North
Dakota B comes from precipitation in May
and June so don't be making your grazing
management decisions based off of the
available precipitation snow that we
have right now so when we when I talk we
talk about preparing for a grazing
season and when should we be putting
those cattle out there I know a lot of
people use a calendar date the ideal way
to do this is to look at grazing
readiness based off a plant development
or you can estimate it using growing
degree days we do have a publication
that goes through that so I'm not going
to go in detail the simplest way is to
go out there look at plant development
or introduce pasture species such as
crested wheatgrass smooth round grass
meadow chrome that would be the three
leaf stage and so you just simply are
gonna count the leaves starting from the
bottom one two three and then for our
native species it would be the three and
a half leaf stage and why do we use this
as a rule of thumb it's important to be
looking at this and not crazy in our
class too early because grazing too
early can stress those plants out and
actually result in up to a sixty percent
decrease in your forage production for
the grazing season as a typical rule of
thumb we expect
our crested wheatgrass is already early
May our ohms smooth brown grass metal
grown grass being the most common
typically ready to graze in mid-may if
you have post contracts here peel and
that's typically stuff that's coming on
contract is typically somewhere called
intermediate wheat grasses and you can
expect that to be available in late May
and our native pastures typically aren't
ready until earliest is early June
depending if you're cool or warm season
dominated and that would be our full
season dominated pastures which are most
common across the state however I want
to keep him remind you and is that that
there's a lot of variability so we don't
want you want to be careful but just
looking at those states it varies across
the state some research that we've been
doing with with the extension agents
across the state shows a two week
variability between counties when
different species are available to graze
and also we have year to year
variability so just because that's the
gate you were able to start crazy last
year does not mean that that's when our
species are going to be available to
graze this year so the last two years I
have been recommending agents across the
state to monitor grazing readiness for
some of our common passion of these
species Chris wheatgrass smooth brown
grass and then our most common native
species would be Western week for us we
also have some what that green needle
grass but there's some challenges there
because it's a little bit more difficult
to identify early in the grazing season
in 2017 if we found that crested wheat
grass was a was ready to graze at that
three leaf stage around May fourth where
a broom was actually earlier at late
April April 24th where our Western wheat
grass wasn't avail wasn't at the three
and a half leaf stage until the end of
May almost Morial day
one of the reasons you'd be probably
wondering why is crested wheat grass
behind smooth grown grass when I said
that should be available to graze
earlier I don't know if you guys if you
remember that we warmed up pretty early
in 2017 but then we had a cold snap
later as things were starting to grow
and that said some of our grasses back
including the crusted me curse which was
further in development at that time I
did have to get a lot of pictures from
County agents where they were out there
monitoring and grazing readiness and
they had pictures of the grass was snow
looking at 2018 a crested wheat grass
was similar we were at May 11th and then
our smooth brown grass was actually two
weeks later at May 7th so typically
around where we would normally expect it
to be our Western grass was about the
same at that end of May May it May 20th
it was this year so one of the things
that we've seen here though we actually
seen a delay in some of the species
because of the drought to 2017 depending
on if those areas if pastures were
grazed hard they seen a decrease in in
productivity and a delay and grazing
readiness in some areas so I expected
something similar this year with we will
have a delay in our Gracie and readiness
because it's gonna there's a delay with
all the snow when our plants are going
to start growing and photosynthesizing
and her grounds going to take longer to
warm up how long that delay is going to
be I can't say right now we do plan on
working with the agents across the state
and monitoring again this year so
hopefully we can keep you up to date on
that as we move forward I know a lot of
you are probably it changed to get out
and get your cows out of lots and
especially the snow when it starts to
melt you're going to have a mess and
really like you want to get them out of
there you're also running hit short on
hay supplies so here there's some
strategies
you can look at you get them out there a
little earlier but while reducing that
the stress to those those pastures and
I'm talking about these and what I would
say the order preference so ideally if
you can looking at supplementing on hair
pastureland kasher again need it or we
those can graft species not native
specifically things like the domes and
your and your crested and then providing
them some additional forward if you
Forge if you still have it available are
supplementing with some of the other
products that Carl talked about the next
one thing to look at would be grazing
some of those domesticated grass
pastures then moving and if you don't
have that as option utilizing some of
your winter annuals for spring grazing
and Phil should be available early May
so things like triticale rye or winter
wheat if if you planted those last fall
then the next thing if those aren't
options for you would be evaluating what
you have for native native pastures
native rangelands we have a pretty big
issue across the state with kentucky
bluegrass invading our native rangelands
and and becoming dominant on a melon
long pasture especially eastern portion
of the state so if look at this picture
here this would be a patch or pasture
that's been taken over by a Kentucky
bluegrass so that would be a good option
if you're gonna graze native range if
you have a pasture looks like that
starting there actually could help
decrease your Kentucky bluegrass you're
using it early in the season and give
some your Nadeau's a competitive
advantage one thing is that this would
be very bowl of protein so you
definitely would need to supplement
protein in this situation and then
finally if if you have to graze native
pastures choosing one that's dominated
by cool season grasses and if you're not
sure about composition need some help
with the identification contact your
extension agent or your NRCS I'm sure
they'll be happy
and help you with that few other
considerations which we haven't talked
about yet is this is what especially
with this coming storm we're talking in
record level historic storms that we
need to be thinking about flooding if we
have a riparian passion that we usually
turn out in the spring
maybe avoiding that because it's going
to be a mess for one and you're gonna
have the decline in health but also that
that is gonna tear that pasture up and
may reduce its productivity in the long
run other thing is you know a lot of you
aren't thinking about drill right now
except for maybe those of you that were
impacted in 2018 but we do we did see
that keep that delay in grazing
readiness from those areas impacted by
the 2017 drought if they're a grazed
hard to be also seen decrease in
productivity this is a good example of
that delay in all over county last year
our Western B grass on in mid-may was at
the one and a half leaf stage compared
to the three and a half leaf stage early
May the year before and there's a pretty
significant it's probably hard to see in
these photos but there's a pretty
significant difference in the
productivity and the height of the
forage and those in those two pictures
and they actually seen that as it stayed
pretty stunted as it got to the three
and a half leaf stage there was an
isolated part of the state that did
experience drought in 2018 so if you
were in that area you also some of you
also had the experience don't in in 17
and so being cautious and maybe not
starting on pastures that you put extra
pressure on and those in those years so
they have a little extra time to recover
as always try not you know not over
grazing if you do put a little extra
pressure on a pasture make sure they're
you're allowing enough time for it to
recover from that extra prep pressure so
if you started
in a year starting in one of your native
pastures early in the grazing season
this year making sure that you don't
come back into that pasture again until
next fall if you need any help with some
thoughts or ideas on how increasing
management strategies contact me contact
your Extension agent or your NRCS and
they'll be glad to help you set up some
strategies there so with that I am gonna
turn it over back over to dr. Charlie
was he's gonna have some closing remarks
and then we can open it up for Question
and Answer all right Thank You Miranda
and thanks to all our presenters out
there we really appreciate that time
you've taken and our attendees out there
might notice that many of our
specialists are doing this from home and
so we want to thank you for the
opportunity to come into your homes
tonight and from ours to yours so this
is the question and answer time we have
a few questions as we go through these
if you have other questions please type
them in and so the first question X I'm
going to call on dr. stuck and the
question is can you feed a hyperthermic
calf colostrum
I've heard that a cap won't utilize the
classroom until its internal body temp
is increased and it will just sit in a
cat's stomach can cause blood is this
true yeah good question and I think when
we talk we were talking about the need
for colostrum no matter what method
you're warming the calf I think I did
say some time during that warming
process you need to get colostrum into
that calf because you won't have as much
success with warming the calf unless
that calf has been granted this is warm
colostrum so that actually helps a
little bit as well so it's just it's
every bit as important as you're warming
method whether it's a hotbox or or a
warm water bath I'm not telling you to
put in the colostrum before you start
warming the persuit process but at least
some time during that warming process
put claustrum into that calf and it'll
help it'll help that calf build his own
energy
in addition to what you're already
providing to warm that calf all right
thanks Jerry next one I think Miranda
I'm going to call on you what growth
stage should cows be turned out and I
think the growth stage is with what
growth stage should Cosby turned out on
winter annual pastures such as winter
rye so we want to turn it out at the
vegetative stage I would use the same
rule of thumb as we do for our
introduced grasses like the three latest
age with these if you manage it
correctly and don't don't graze it too
low you can actually take them off and
you'll get regrowth that you'll be able
to create again so managing the grazing
and one of the keys with these is a lot
of people are watching these pastures
they have a lot of other things going on
so getting them early enough so you can
get that wreath grilled because once you
head so you don't have that potential
for me girl and there's a serious
decline in quality too
alright thanks Miranda the next question
I have is well this is a toss-up I think
I'll call on dr. hoppy first but then
other panels can come in on that feeding
in late afternoon and early evening a
her this better for having I was told is
this true oh I'm not sure if it's better
for actually calving but if you're
looking for calving changing the time
frame which cattle calf throughout the
day feeding in the evening will tend the
delay calving until earlier in the
morning you'll end up having less night
time calvings if you're feeding late in
the afternoon or early evening actually
the opposite is true in sheep by feeding
them within four or five hours you'll
end up having more lambs to happen so
you don't you want to get away from
nighttime watches and sheep be sure to
feed them in the morning if you want to
get away from nighttime calving be sure
to feed the cattle at night or late
evening
all right thanks Carl we're at Wow hour
and 15 minutes we've been at this and
thank you very much
and all those attending one last call
for questions I'm going to call on the
presenters if there's any final comments
that anything has come up while you
watch you present things that you want
to make a point duck otherwise if
there's no questions cause you're a
little bit antsy
we shared the link where you can find
the feed cost comes later sure Carl if
you what we're going to do is at the end
of this session and you type in an email
so we should be able to email you we
have some other supporting documents
that we're going to send to all the
attendees that were tuned in tonight so
we'll be sending down so if there are
anything else put in a question box if
there's something else you want us to
send out but we will be sending out that
information let's see I'm trying going
down my checklist here I think we've
covered most everything any other
specialists have any final comments or
thoughts
dr. Charlie I just I guess I just tell
the audience still at this point that we
are available our phones are almost
always on and so you can get ahold of us
and if you have any more questions why
we were willing and able to help in any
any way we can and thanks Jerry anybody
else so I just want to close with thanks
dr. Charlie I was just gonna say 20 su
leads the University of Nebraska Omaha
48 to 39 with 1220 left in the second
half and that's to go to the big NC
double-a tournament thanks Lisa and
that's that's great okay so thanks good
for zooming with us tonight on behalf of
India extension we wish to wish you the
best over the next few days it doesn't
look like it's going to be very nice
weather out there if you have more
questions at a later date please contact
your local County based Extension agent
they can field your questions or they
can also get in touch with us they have
all our contact information
when this webinar concludes you should
be linked to a brief survey to leave
feedback for us we are very interested
in your experience this evening with us
in the use of this webinar technology
and we want to learn from you so if at
all possible please take a few minutes
and give us your feedback and so with
that I'm going to say thank you for your
time tonight and good night