hey hey what's up garden friends jeff
here how's everybody doing i hope you're
doing well
i am great kind of a rainy
drizzly day out here so doing things
from
under the umbrella the broken umbrellas
hopefully that'll provide the protection
needed to
do this thing and not destroy the camera
sitting out here with a whole bunch of
lovely plants on the table ones that i'm
really excited to talk about
really common plants ones that i do get
questions about
fairly often the and amanda villas
diplodenia mandevillas both of them are
fantastic plants they make great annuals
they're really good perennials where
they can be perennial
i love these plants for their beautiful
glossy green
foliage their abundance of flowers these
plants will flower
and flower and flower they just keep
growing and
they're very low fuss they don't need an
awful lot
they don't need deadheading fertilizing
should be minimal with them the
pollinators
love these plants and they can be used
as fillers spillers climbers
lots and lots and lots of versatility
with how the plants can be utilized you
would think that because they're
pretty easy and simple to grow that that
means this should be a short video
there's not a tent to say about them
and that might be the case i'm going to
go over the quick care for people who
don't want like a long video and
don't need a ton of details about the
plants they just know what to do with
them i'll do the quick care
shortly here and then it just go over
like the differences between mandevillas
diplodinius
some tips for care and just go a little
bit more in depth about
some of the nuances propagation leaf
drop yellowing
those sorts of things let's hit that
quick care for starters diplodinias and
mandevillas carrie's gonna be pretty
much
identical for these two plants we'll
talk about why later
they're typically regarded as hardy
zones nine and up some sources will say
zone ten they don't like
cold weather and frost so if you have
frost and colds
probably not gonna be a perennial for
you maybe they will be go over that a
little bit more in depth later
but for part to full sun they are sun
lovers but in areas with really dry air
some afternoon shade might be a good
idea just to help avoid the foliage
getting kind of burnt up and crispy
they like their soil to stay
consistently moist but if you let the
top inch to two inches of soil dry out
between waterings that's usually okay
once these are established if you're
growing them in the ground they can be
very drought tolerant they aren't going
to be as demanding for
watering if you have them in the ground
versus in a pot gonna need to water them
more if they're in a pot personally i
don't do a ton when it comes to
fertilizing these plants too much
nitrogen can inhibit flowering so i just
make sure that there's a good continuous
release fertilizer with them when i pop
them up
and then usually i'll repeat that maybe
three months later mid-summer
give them just a little bit more of the
top dressing size is really variable
with these plants that's a hard one to
talk about
generally the diplodinies are going to
be smaller with more rounded habit the
mandevilla the vines those are going to
vine up to 10 feet if not more like they
can find more than that just depends on
which type you're growing because there
are a lot of different cultivars out
there
these are plants that don't particularly
mind being pop-bound
i really only re-pop these plants when
it gets to a point where i've noticed
that when i water them
they're not really responding to being
watered when it's difficult to keep them
hydrated that's when it's time to repot
or if you notice roots growing off the
top and bottom of the pot that's another
good way to tell
sap can cause skin irritation so maybe
wear gloves the toxicity on them is
considered
low but can cause problems so keep it
away from curious mouths just to be safe
there it is fun easy plants that's like
essentially everything you need to know
about growing them they're not too fussy
what's the difference between a
mandevilla and a diplodynia i have
all of them here in front not all there
are tons of different diplodinius and
mandevillas
but i have diplodynia and mandevilla
here on the table
diplodinias tend to have more of a
mounded growth habit to them
so if you put them up against something
you can train them to climb but they're
not going to climb very much
whereas amanda villa like over here see
nice big mandevilla that's a vine they
are going to climb and climb and climb
they come in all different colors and
leaf shapes like you can see this
mandevilla in the back is the more
classic mandevilla
has much much much larger leaves on it
and larger flowers they don't flower
quite as prolifically as the other ones
that have the smaller flowers like i
just showed
but their leaves are so cool i really
like both of them
this one right here i believe is an
alice dupont but i'm not positive which
is just
a classic form of mandavilla that's been
around for a long time
this other one i think it just said like
pink
i don't know what kind it is it's a pink
mandevilla and then
over here i absolutely love
this one that's back here where's its
tag i can show you the tag that is the
sun parasol
apricot which is like only kind of in
focus this particular
one the flowers start off this fun
peachy
or apricot like color it's a very light
light pinkish orange and then they fade
to a kind of a creamy
light yellow color i enjoy that a lot
because you get multiple colors on one
plant there's no such thing as an
ugly mandevilla or diplodinia they're
all beautiful plants the mandevillas
also will often times have larger
flowers on them like you see back here
with alice dupont
that's not always as true anymore though
because there's so many cultivars that
have come out that have that like you
see the flowers
right here on this manda villa are
essentially identical
to this diplodonia right here see that
they're basically the same flower the
leaves are even pretty similar
too they're native to central america
and i believe parts of northern
south america so those are the main
differences some difference in flower
size depending on the cultivar but it's
mostly mandevillas or vines whereas
diplodinias are more like
little shrubs all diplodinias are in the
mandevilla
family and that's why they care on them
is basically the same there will be some
differences because
well one's a vine and sometimes you have
to take some different things into
consideration with vines like if you
have them planted up against the wall
you don't want afternoon sun on them
because they could get baked they could
get kind of crispy
particularly with the ones like the
amabilis types or the
alice dupont that have those really big
leaves sometimes in the afternoon sun
that can be an issue if there's a big
reflective surface nearby or right
behind them
and then with the diplodinius sometimes
their growth can end up being
somewhat stringy it'll look like it
wants to vine you can either cut that
off to encourage the plant to keep
staying bushy
or you can go ahead and put a support
behind it and let it do a little bit of
vining but again it's not going to be
anything like
on the actual mandevillas those are
going to vine far far
far more aggressively than a diplodynia
some diplodinius have been hybridized
and cultivated well enough that like
they
hopefully won't even do that they'll
just maintain their bushy shape they're
plants that do appreciate the warmth
they like get pretty toasty when
temperatures drop below 45 degrees
fahrenheit
i try and make sure to cut back on the
watering i'm much more cautious with the
amount of moisture around their roots
because they're going to be more prone
to rotting if it's cool and if they're
damp
too much fertilizer too much nitrogen
can inhibit their flowering
it can also sometimes cause some
discoloration on the foliage though i'll
go over a leaf drop in yellow and leaves
and all that
here in a moment less sun is also going
to mean
less flowers so they can go part to full
sun
but the more sun they get the more
they're going to flower depending on
where you live
afternoon sun might be a bit much for
them so just keep an eye out i generally
prefer these
get some filtered sun in the afternoon
and just bright direct sun in the
morning time but my yard there's a lot
of
pavement and brick and lots of
reflective surfaces so that's why
sometimes i have issues with scorching
i see these planted out as annuals all
over the place where i live and they get
bright bright bright direct sun all day
long
and they're totally fine so it's gonna
be somewhat region specific that's why i
said you just kind of have to evaluate
your area
i already mentioned they don't need to
be repotted very often they kind of like
to be root bound but one thing to keep
in mind with them
particularly with the mandevilla the
vine more than the diplodynia
is to be cautious about right where that
root or not the root right where the
stem
comes to the soil when you're repotting
the plant it's a good idea to keep that
really well supported when you re-pop
these when you pull this out from its
can
if there's too much disturbance in this
area and in the root zone in general
they're going to be far more prone to
leaf drop to dropping some leaves and
throw in a fit when they get repotted so
it is helpful
with these vines to try and disturb the
roots as little as possible
when repotting them if the roots are
wrapped and twisted
root bound then you might want to go
ahead and give them a little tickle and
try and loosen that up and just break up
that circling habit
but you don't have to go too
aggressively with it just lightly try
and loosen it up and that's only if it's
really really like hardcore
wrapped in a circle would i do that
otherwise i try my best to just
maintain whatever root shape is there
plop it into a new pot with maybe
a couple of inches of extra space on the
outside diameter
refill with an all-purpose potting mix
that is generally fine for them
they aren't nutrient hog so they do okay
with that water them in and they're good
to go
and a little bit of continuous sweet
fertilizer they appreciate that i
already talked about that the
diplodonius and mandevillas
oh hello camera both of them do
propagate very easily
m cuttings from green growth put some
breeding hormone on it pop it into a
moist soil
and they should take off or you can take
the growth and wear it onto
a fresh soil that maintains moisture cut
a little notch in there maybe use a
rooting hormone
and bury where you made that cut and
that should take root and the plant will
take off from there and you can sever it
and
keep it going that way that way you
don't have to risk losing the cutting
it'll just keep getting some nutrient
from the plant while
getting rooted really simple to do but a
lot of these are
trademarked and owned because they've
been cultivated
always put a lot of hard work and time
into coming up with their own varieties
of diplodonia's mandevillas so
it's a good idea to check the legality
behind doing that if you want to
propagate them
particularly for resale right like
somebody else owns it so gotta be
careful there i've never had many pest
issues with diplodonia's or mandavillas
but they
can't be prone to just the commonpass
aphids whiteflies
uh smealybug i haven't heard much about
scale comment down below
and let us know what problems you've had
with them if any
i really i haven't had any issues that i
can think of as far as pests are
concerned with them even when i've taken
them in the house for the winter time
still they generally just kept on going
the mealybugs and everything else
usually stay away from them however i
have a lot of plants
so that could just mean that i have
other plants around that the mealybugs
favor
so that so my experience there doesn't
really mean anything like i said comment
down below so we can all learn together
from that one
the main things they had to ask about
with them is leaf drop or yellowing
their cold hardiness and overwintering
indoors beef trap is a complicated one
there can be a lot of different causes
for it so i'm just going to
run through all the different
possibilities the different things that
could be causing them to
drop their leaves for starters there's
root rot which would typically mean the
plant has been over
watered or just the roots have been
overly disturbed that can cause
leaf drop and yellowing as well over
watering will cause yellowing
correct or inconsistent fertilizing and
watering that can also cause yellowing
and also just excessive fertilizer that
can cause issues with the foliage and
the flowering as well
cold temperatures that's another
possibility extreme changes in
temperature if you have them indoors
they're near a draft that could be a
problem this is really big for leaf drop
and leaf yellow wings there are a lot of
different
causes that could be going on there's
the process of eliminations figuring
that one out when growing them indoors i
make sure that these get
as much sun as possible like basically
all day long so a south
south fest facing window i'm probably
keeping them a foot or two away from the
window
especially in winter if it's really cool
and drafty and i don't water them
at all the same during winter as i do
during the summer
i just give them a little drink maybe
like every 10 days or so
just let it go through the pot about
once and i let the top two
to sometimes even four inches maybe up
to 50 of the soil
dry out it's one of those things you
kind of have to watch the plant they'll
get a little bit wilty and let you know
when they need to be watered
and then you can kind of learn the
routine and the habit of the plant and
how often you'll
need to water it it'll get a little bit
more leggy and kind of funky looking
when you have them in the house
if you have really long winters like i
do but when i bring them back outside
give them a cut back and get them into
the sun and they
pop right back out and look wonderful as
far as overwintering them is concerned
oh i'm almost out of memory
i'm going to go through this really fast
as far as overwintering them is
concerned
they don't like frost they don't like
cold temperatures it's why they're hardy
zone 9 or 10 and up
but if you have really short winters
like maybe just a month or so
you can usually mulch about the first
foot or so of stem coming out of the
ground
and then when the heat returns pull that
back and sometimes the growth will come
back out of there i know people who have
had these in zone 8 like 8b
and they've returned for them okay
that's it lovely beautiful plants
comment down below what's your
experience with mandevillas and
diplodinias let us know i love talking
to everybody
do you have favorite colors favorite
varieties what do you use them for i
love them for the hummingbirds i like to
have them all over the place they're
just all around just excellent plants
they're beautiful
fun and easy to grow all right hope
everybody's doing well having a great
day and a great life and everything just
going beautifully for you
and of course as always and most
importantly everybody
keep on growing bye
[Music]
you