hi this is Stacy from the adviser I'm
very excited today because we have
sander veny here today and he is an
amazing individual he has a really
amazing story to tell and he right now
um he he was going to go and become a
veterinarian back in the day and he
found his true purpose in life and he's
going to share that purpose with you and
how he took his purpose and made it into
a reality and so sander tell everybody a
little about yourself and what you do
thank you Stacy yes so when I when I was
younger I've always had a deep love for
animals so it wasn't a surprise to me or
my parents like that I wanted to do
something with animals growing up that
was always a North star for me so then I
wasn't sure if it was farming veterinary
medicine and and as soon as there was
any sort of doubts my parents like you
got to go explore veterinary medicine
make sure that like that you go down
that road first
because it farming is tough so you can't
have any doubts in your mind when when
things start getting tough in farming
and uh when you have bad days stuff like
that you can't live a life with regret
and what ifs and stuff like that so I
went to the veterinary medicine route I
went to University of wealth and I did
everything that I need to do to get my
application ready and instead of sending
it in I changed my mind I came home to
the dairy farm instead so then that was
2010 when I graduated
and basically
we farmed together my parents for four
or five years and then 2015 we moved our
our cows into a new Dairy facility which
was very exciting because I found it
endlessly frustrating in our old dairy
facility because that Barn was built in
in
1987 and they didn't really know much
about how a barn should be built for a
cow to thrive and they didn't they
didn't Thrive so it was endlessly
frustrating for me being as passionate
about animals as I am so when they
we moved the over to the new barn the
cows thrived they did better they they
produced more milk they they lived
longer they had better body condition
they seemed happier like it was it was
amazing but right around that same time
as the cow's Health improved ironically
my own
health um took a hit and my hormones
crashed and I had to look around like
what am I doing wrong what am I missing
why all of a sudden now is at the age of
25 has my testosterone crashed to
nothing basically to like 9-year-old man
levels and then I started looking around
and I was questioning everything I was
questioning the Health Care system
because I was bouncing around from
Doctor to doctor and no way was able to
figure out what was that actually wrong
I had doctors telling me that I need to
just accept my condition and move on
stop trying to look for things that I
can change or improve or things like
that it's just I just need to accept it
and and move on with my life and
naturally I wasn't willing to do that
but then it took me about six years
though to finally figure out enough
things where I was able to improve my
own health to the point where my
hormones
returned and um and then but that same
time I was questioning my life I was
also questioning the way we farmed and
as I was looking for ways that I could
improve the lives of our farm animals
and do things better and going down that
rabbit hole is what led me to regener
culture is uh it's a lot a lot of the
goals are aligned when it comes to
trying to improve animal welfare and the
the goals of regenerative agriculture
and and getting the cows back outside in
the environment where they can have a
positive impact on the environment and
so where we are now is like I I have my
commercial dairy farm which I still have
lots of plans lots of dreams of
transitioning that to regenerative
agriculture as well but in the meantime
I'm trying to build that customer base
and I have the pasture turkeys that I
have on our pasture that fall behind our
Grass Pad beef is kind of mimics the the
ways that the the massive herds of Bison
used to roam North America and then
there'd be Birds fallowing behind there
and they complement each other really
well which is a common theme in regener
of Agriculture where you're kind of
treating your farm like an ecosystem and
it's a lot of give and take and and and
uh a lot of complimentary traits between
the different animals and and the goals
of uh of producing food on your
farm you know I I don't think people
realize how common um you know problems
with hormones um how many people go
through it how many people go through
low testosterone or low progesterone or
they have low estrogen or their estrogen
is too high and people are really
imbalanced in our society and it does it
could start at any age when people think
about um low testosterone they
immediately associated with later in
life but it's not really true like I
started having problems with my test
testosterone at age 39 and I didn't even
know what was going on I just started
getting symptoms out of the blue and you
know I went to the doctor and my doctor
was the same as yours you know just you
know didn't have an answer yeah just
take birth control you'll be fine and
I'm like I'm not taking birth control
you know and then later on I I went to
other doctors that were more natural and
you know and they you know did test and
they figured out what was going on but a
lot of it you know in our society people
don't realize what a lot of it has to do
too with the foods we eat you know in
America cuz you know especially you know
a lot of foods are injected with
hormones and you know nowadays you see
children at the age of eight starting to
develop breasts and starting to go
through menstruation at an early age
because they're injecting you know
they're injecting the chickens with
hormones and they're injecting certain
animals with hormones and and they're
injecting you know cows with hormones
and those hormones are going into your
body and they're changing in the whole
chemistry of your body and you know and
like we discussed before you know
everybody's body is different we all
come from different DNA so you know for
some people going through you know low
testosterone at a at a young age is can
be normal and it does it can happen at
any age you know and that's what people
have to be aware of and you know
problems like you know low liido or
erectile dysfunction is so common in our
society worldwide it's just not talked
about but you know as we were discussing
before you were talking about
regenerative egg and you were talking
about how the different foods and how
you know eating certain foods and and
how to take care of the animals and and
take care of your bodies can play such a
huge role can you explain a little bit
more about agre AG um
regenerative a you know and explain to
people what it is and how it could have
such an impact on your health
very simply regenerative agiculture is
just farming in a way that maximizes
soil health and that's in contrast to
just trying to maximize profits or
maximize
efficiency but if you take that like a a
layer deeper a little more complex what
you're really trying to do is you're
trying to create a thriving ecosystem of
microorganisms in the soil and it's a
you have when it done properly you have
a a very complex food chain of these
microorganisms you have your bacteria
you have your fungus you have protozoa
Nemos arthropods and it's a real it's a
crazy amount of biomass underneath the
soil that we don't even realize is there
but when you have that and it's done
correctly what you what the plant then
can do is that it can excrete a sugar
into the soil and trade those sugars for
nutrients so then you don't need the
synthetic fertilizers because the plant
can ask for nutrients from the
microorganism in the soil and they'll go
out and they'll mine these nutrients
from the rocks and from the silt and
sand and then they'll they'll trade
those and then they'll be able to for
the sugars that so that the
microorganisms can Thrive that that's
their food source and it's
um and like what's really important in
this whole system like a keystone
species is the micro risal fungi which
is basically a long filament that
actually embeds into the root of the
plant and reaches out into the soil and
transports these nutrients and these
sugars and
um what actually happens is is when
we're when we use these synthetic
fertilizers or we use things like large
equipment to drive over our land these
fungus are the first to die off they're
very sensitive so we have to be careful
with how we treat our land but
then what we can do is is we we we
follow these five principles of soil
Health which are very important because
you can if you follow these five
principles then you you you don't have
this negative impact on the soil and you
don't you don't kill all this diversity
in your soil because if you don't have
that diversity you end up being addicted
to synthetic fertilizers there's really
no other way to grow crops because
without this this uh relationship
between the microorganisms and the
plant the plant can't get the nutrients
without fertilizer and it's not just the
fertilizer and the nutrients that the
plant is missing it's missing the
defense chemicals from all the all the
the the insects and stuff like that so
then if it doesn't have these defense
chemicals from these healthy insects
will then becomes vulnerable for pests
and then you end up spraying with
pesticides and it's the same story with
weeds if you don't have the diversity
not only of the microorganism but also
just the the plants that are are living
in the soil you it's the one of the main
downsides of these monocrops is that
you're missing that diversity it's
missing in the soil and the nature
doesn't like that monocrop so then
that's when the weeds come in you start
spraying for weeds and then and it's
it's a a vicious cycle really and yeah
it's a hard thing to break free from and
when you're following five these five
principles which is like you need the
biodiversity you need to minimize the
impact that you have on your soil you
have to have armor on the soil in the
form of plants or pasture or whatever
else and you need to have living roots
in the soil all year around and the last
thing is you need animal impact and if
you have those five things you can have
that diversity where you you can break
free from that addiction and then you
can have that beautiful relationship
between these microorganisms and the
plants and it's not just oh now I don't
need synthetic fertilizer it's it's it's
a much you end up with a much more
nutrient dense food because you can
never fertilize for absolutely
everything that the every micronutrient
that the plant wants and needs that it
can find in the soil you can never
fertilize from all those tiny
micronutrients so like you end up with
much like with food that has less
nutrients in it for that reason so it's
it's it's a it's a beautiful system and
the end result as as a nutrient healthy
nutrient-dense
food you know it's it's pretty amazing
because it it seems like when you do
regenerative you know agriculture it
seems like you're for one you're balanc
in your gut because you're you're you
know you have the good bacteria the bad
bacteria you have the healthy soil and
you're you're you know that helps your
digestive system work which entail helps
everything it helps you know because gut
health is really related to everything
including your brain and you know the
fogginess the way we think our Clarity
you know overall health and that's one
of the components that it seems like it
really helps and you know CU When you
think about it you know if when if you
if once you start adding those
pesticides and those weeds and all those
toxins into your body your body doesn't
know what to do with them so it stores
them and it stores it in our body and
what happens is is that our body you
know our our our organs become sluggish
it affects the way you know we feel it
you know it could cause illness you know
after after so long and people are going
to the doctors they don't understand why
they don't feel good and it all has to
do with the root cause of how the food
is made how it's grown how it's taken
care of and people are getting sick all
over you know the United States and and
I don't know what the regulations are in
other countries but for the United
States there's so many illnesses and and
illnesses the percentages have grown and
grown and grown and so many people
you know have realized that a lot of it
has to do with gut health leaky gut
syndrome not having enough of you know
good bacteria versus bad bacteria and it
all has to do with a lot of the way we
take care of ourselves we take care of
the food that we're growing and it's
it's really you know it's really hurting
our society it's you know we talked
about you know our hormones and we
talked about you know gut health and and
and illnesses and it's really it all
draws back to really we need to have
concern of how we are growing our food
and really how you know what we're doing
because it's affecting our society as a
whole and it's really it's it's
destroying the healths of people you
know Nationwide and and and any other
countries that are doing similar
things absolutely and and like there
you're right there there's a um a huge
issue with autoimmunity in our day and
age today and
a lot of it comes back to the food we
eat but also like a lifestyle of
Sanitation where we're obsessed with um
putting alcohol in our hands and
cleaning everything making everything
perfectly clean disinfected and and um
and it starts with the food and like the
soil because like the soil we Farm it in
a way typically with commercial
agriculture where it's it's almost a
sanitary soil there's bacteria but
there's such there so so devoid of life
it's almost like a sanitized growing
environment and then it's this those
this lack of diversity comes up through
the food chain so the plants don't have
a healthy microbiome on it as well so
then it's like because there's not the
microbiome there's a void there so then
there's as soon as you have something
growing some coli or some some sort of
unhealthy bacteria it'll explode in
population because there's not the
competition of the healthy BAC the
healthy microorgan orms on that food so
then it becomes even more important that
we sanitize our food so like yeah it's
and and like like people talk about too
like how it's important like you eat
your food dirty food and stuff like that
with some dirt on it so you have those
those microorganisms but like it's not
that simple because you got to make sure
it's the right dirt it's the dirt with
the healthy diversity the healthy
ecosystem of microorganisms in it and
then and then we can like fix the whole
the not only the food system with the
with the microbiome and but also just
like our our our culture of Sanitation
because like it's it's incredibly
important because if you look at our
body we are more bacteria than we are
human we vessels for carrying this this
diverse population of of bacteria in our
Po in in our in our body so we have to
be careful too with like a lot of these
pesticides and and and herbicides or
sprays that we put on our food or or
sanitize our hands with or whatever else
is like it might not affect our human
cells but like it could very well be
affecting our microbiome and and issues
yeah you know and and they they've come
out with you know information about you
know everyone with you know hand
sanitized especially during covid and
everybody's using it but you know too
much hand San hand sanitizer is not good
for you you know it's really we the
germs are good for you you know people
don't realize it but we need germs we
need to grow you know our antibodies we
need we need you know just like when
they say take a probiotic you should be
taking a Prebiotic too because good
bacteria versus bad bacteria you need
both you need both in your body and you
know people don't realize that and then
you know in America we have you know
chickens are getting shot up with
nitrate and they getting shot up with
all these different you know chemicals
and things and and you know we as a
society really need to try to go more
the pure route like you were talking
about regenerative egg and and be able
to have a cleaner you know way of living
because if we don't we're we're going to
our our country healthwise is going to
be destroyed it's already you see stats
of of how much you know PE illnesses
have gone up in so many different
categories and the question is why you
know and you know our society is not
looking at what they're putting in their
bodies and we were talking about before
the show you really need to treat your
body as a temple and maybe you can
expand on that explain to people why it
is so important that we just don't throw
things in our mouths and we just don't
take anything that we see over the
counter you know but we we treat our
body as a
temple yeah it's something that uh I
believe in very strongly is because like
you you gota look after your meat bag is
how I like to think about it because
like it's it it it makes you more
effective at everything you do in life
makes makes me a better dad a better
husband it makes me a better farmer
gives me more energy more clarity and
thought allows me to dream of of
directions I want to take my life like
like with with more Elites and make an
impact on agriculture and improve animal
welfare and and and and also like move
bring the the movement of regenerate
agriculture forward like it all that
health is is absolutely critical to uh
just to be
ourselves but like 100% ourselves not
just
walking through life and and and waking
up and and hitting the snooze button and
going through life as as a zombie and
just hit being on repeat like it's it's
absolutely critical yeah and like and
the food that we eat is a big part of
that it's um it's we almost gota like
it's it's we gota go back to eating a a
simpler diet kind of it's like it's not
all these complex ingredients and
packages stuff like that it's like it's
just your one ingredient and and uh and
and that's real food and then the Step
Beyond that is like the food that you
eat that's simple it's just one
ingredient is just your Whole Foods it's
nothing packaged A Step Beyond that then
is like okay now that I've made that
massive leap away from processed
foods the next step is okay now the food
that I'm eating is that top quality food
is that also food that's raised in a way
that makes it it's it's nutrient dense
it's healthy and it has it's not only
healthy but it's it's improves welfare
or and improves the environment like it
it's it's a it's treated in a way that
is that is is is healthy for the whole
ecosystem as us as a whole and our
planet as a whole oh 100% I I agree with
you totally and and and it you know it's
a lifestyle change it's not just
something you're going to do temporarily
and then you know okay you know like
just like people go on these fad diets
yeah after a while they get sick of
doing it and they go back to their old
way of living it's something that you
have to incorporate into your life and
and and stay consistent you know I don't
think of you know I don't look at it as
as a things as a diet I don't look at
things as you know this is the way it
has to be I I call it a lifestyle change
do you want to be healthy do you want to
feel good do you want to prevent illness
from occurring do you want to sustain
your illness that you have right now do
you want to keep it at a level where you
could be productive and happy you know
do you want to be a ble to live life the
way you you've always dreamt of being do
you want to have goals in the future and
be able to reach those goals well people
don't realize it but it all stems back
on how we take care of ourselves and
what we put in our bodies and it's so
important that people realize that every
little thing whether it's a supplement a
vitamin you know the food that we eat
you know whether it being natural or
processed you have to really think about
what am I putting in my body and how is
that going to affect me
and you know and and make it so natural
that you do it so consistently that you
don't even have to think about it
anymore it's just you you're just doing
it you're just doing it you know and I
think people have to really seriously
think about that how is it affecting
their life people have stomach issues
and they and they're not digesting food
well and they're going to a gastrologist
and I'm having all these problems oh
what are you eating well I had a pizza
yesterday and then I you know in the
morning I had a bowl of cereal and had
like you know you know this enormous
amount of sugar in it you know and and
you know people don't get it but we
really have to focus where we're getting
our foods and what we're putting in our
mouths and and think about the more
natural way of living and how that could
benefit us in the long run I think what
are your feelings about that I yeah I
completely agree and we have to be
careful that we're not trapped by normal
like all the normal ranges for your
blood all the normal diet that can't be
what's causing you that's that's a
normal diet for you to be eating but you
know what it's also normal to die at the
age of 60 75 80 from a cardiovascular
disease cancer and all these chronic
diseases that um are arguably
preventable with a healthy lifestyle and
exercise and a healthy diet and like you
gota almost beware of normal because if
you really look at what normal is that's
not a happy road to walk down I don't
want to start losing vitality by the age
of 65 because that's retirement age and
it's normal to have a sore body and an
achy body and a and and be incapable of
doing the things that I want to do with
my life now and it's it's normal to now
take a step back and no longer have Big
Dreams because that that's what normally
happens like beware of normal and and it
starts with every single day with your
daily choices like are you eating the
with the normal diet that's leading
people down this road this that this
unhappy Road really are you making the
normal choices that's going to lead you
down that road as well or should you now
do an overhaul of your pantry and have
instead of your your packaged food for
snacks you have some piece of fruit or
something like that like has some
healthy habits and it all comes back to
habits yes and like it it becomes easy
Once you these you form these healthy
habits these the these things that
become normal for your your new life
where you're cooking your own food
you're buying food from the perimeter of
the grocery store and like you're having
simple snacks that are just one
ingredient there's nothing in a package
and you don't stop and and buy that take
out because it's convenient it's like
it's now normal that oh I can just fast
like you can fast and not eat for a
couple days and and you'll be fine it's
crazy and and and like you don't have to
stop as soon as you have a hunger pay
you can you can drive and you can wait
till you come home you can have a piece
of of fruit and then you can cook
something up that's healthy right these
are all habits that you can form and
then like you said it's not a diet it's
a lifestyle it's it's a way of life
where you it's in in where you do this
long term for the rest of your life and
then so you can go down a road that's
abnormal that's abnormally amazing
abnormally healthy with lots of
Vitality yes and it's so true and you
know it's it's all it's all mental how
you know what we put in our head and how
we react to things is how we feel if you
start taking care of your body and
you're and you start feeling good you're
in your head you're going to feel young
you know and that in itself because
we're all Connected Mind Body and Soul
it's all connected so if you're taking
care of your body you're feeling good
you're feeling young you know and it's
in your head I feel great I feel like a
30-year old you could be 65 but you feel
like you're 30 you're going to act like
you're 30 you know dream then too you're
going to keep making Dreams yeah if your
body feels good your mind feels clear
then you can keep having those Big
Dreams even when you're 65 when you're
normal to be retiring like you could
have Big Dreams still you can you could
strive for an amazing life exactly life
does not end because the the quote
unquote you know in our normal society
you retire at 65 well that means you
know life is over you have to sit on a
couch and you know watch soap propers
all day no you know it's all how you
perceive it you know it's how you take
care of yourself it's what you put in
your mind it's you know you could change
the way you think the way you live the
way you everything you know all by you
know creating that healthy lifestyle now
you know I want to just tap into you
know talking about the harmone issues
because I feel like it's such a huge
issue you know especially in the United
States and all over because I've spoken
with people that are just not from the
United States all over the world that
have had these issues have contacted me
you know having you know low
testosterone having low progesterone
having low libido and and going through
erectile dysfunction and they just don't
know what to do and you know you see on
the counters like a lot of times you'll
go into food stores or you'll go into
you knowes and you'll see tons and tons
of bottles you know all you know boost
your testosterone do this you know great
muscles and blah blah blah blah and you
know and all this stuff and all these
promises you know but it you know there
are there are you know a lot of these
things are not good for you and when you
when you know our whole body is run by
hormones so you have to be very careful
just like we talked about treating your
body like a temple when you play around
with hormones you have to be really
really careful you know I I want to a
functional medicine doctor you went to a
natural path you know we we were
monitored by a profess professional I
know that I had to take consistent blood
tests and you know they had to make sure
everything was leveled properly and
because you know what if you have too
much of something it could throw your
whole body off in many ways and you know
I don't know how you feel but when you
went to the Natural path that was the
finally you know everybody else told you
don't worry about it just live with it
you know suck it up you know but what
was the turning point when you went to
that that natural path that helped you
you know get your life back in that area
of your
life the real thing that the naturopath
gave me was optimism because everywhere
else I spoke with it was it was just
hormone therapy hormone replacement
therapy and and there was never any T of
Lifestyle it was just these are the
drugs that you should take and you
should accept that and move on and and
the the unique thing about the naturop
path is like they they said I asked them
like this is what what I'm dealing with
this is what the doctors tell me do you
think I could fix this and they were the
the only people that said yeah you could
you could totally I I they saw a road to
recovery and like it gave me a glimmer
of hope when I wasn't really getting
much of that from anywhere else so and
they help me with like with like a
little more concrete things too like I
had digestive issues and along with dig
digestive issues is is I had a B12
deficiency because you I couldn't absorb
those B vitamins from my food yeah so
took some B12 for a short period of time
and that helped a little bit um and then
they also like pointed out to me like
hey these are probably the foods that
you're are reacting to you can try avoid
these certain foods that are causing you
to to flare up your immune system and
have this inflammation throughout your
body and I tried that too and and it
definitely helped and then uh I it just
got me down walking down that path and I
started reassessing everything as far as
health like my sleep habits like I was
definitely um I grew up in a household
of of of three brothers and um and and
no sisters and and and a hardworking dad
so it's like it was a real the
environment of just like go get it and
work hard and and um to H the
consequences kind of thing like you're
now go fight for the for the future that
you want to have like I was all for it
like that that mindset came naturally to
me as the way I grew up you that grit
and that hard work and push through and
tired doesn't matter I can I can handle
it kind of thing and um and that's just
it it came so naturally to me and I
think that's part of the reason why I
struggled I didn't have this opposing
Force this whole other part of my
personality wasn't
being wasn't being developed to the same
degree as the hard part of my of my
personality the softer side of myself I
I was not developing to the same same
degree and and that's a real inflection
point in my life when I when I got sick
is like what am I missing and then
that's when I started looking at these
Sofer sides of my personality and
surprisingly enough exercise for me was
part of that because it felt like a form
of self-expression yeah exercise before
because I had a physical job any sort of
exercise was a waste of energy that
could be energy that could put to
getting work done physical work like
taking the time to to really focus on
myself and like and like improve my my
my movement pattern so that I wouldn't
have all these achy joints my body hurt
and like all my joints hurt I couldn't
walk without pain anymore I couldn't
even run at all anymore it was so
restricting all this pain that I was
constantly trying to force my through
force myself through my day through all
this pain and discomfort and just tired
and brain fog and and it's it's just
like it it's it's tough because it's not
one simple feeling or one simple
diagnosis or one simple
issue that you're having it's like you
said the hormones they affect your whole
body so it's it's a long list of
insignificant symptoms that add up to
like I feel like an old man yeah and
have my energy levels like my immune
system is not working I had warts in my
thumb and like I tried treating it it
wouldn't go away it would just spread
right and then so like yeah I I was
focusing all I was trying a lot of
different things things that really
helped was like really improving my diet
simplifying my diet get eating those
whole foods and uh getting enough meat
in my diet made a difference too because
I got sick the the vegan movement was
massive and it seems hypocritical as a
Dairy Farmer to try the vegan diet but I
was desperate I was willing to try
anything so I did and and there's things
that uh did
improve with with like my diet did
improve to some degrees because I had a
lot of the whole plant foods but I
really started feeling much more
Vitality when I I started adding a lot
of those animal products back in and and
eating a lot of meat and a lot of dairy
raw dairy because I'm one of the few
people in Canada that can have raw dairy
because I produce it myself it's legal
for me to consume it and because like
the the pasteurized more processed Dairy
I was reacting to right it was it the
thing that was triggering my immune
system but I can drink liters and liters
of raw milk without issues so that's
added that back to my diet and that
really helped as well as well as fasting
my
hormones never returned for six years
straight and and it's frustrating
because I was I constantly was building
these healthy habits and my hormones
haven't returned yet and it's
almost can be tough to keep going when
you're in that place but it's like when
you're sick you almost have to push your
body to the extreme and and to to allow
it the permission to to relax and
recover and allow you to bring your
hormones back but like for me is like
the last
triggering moment that allowed my body
to relax was I did a prolonged fast the
first one I ever did after that it was
it was two and a half to three days
something like that I'm never really too
picky dogmatic about it or too strict
but it's like two and a half three a
that and after that my hormones improved
they came back and I wasn't taking
hormones anymore
and it never gets old being healthy like
because like you can you can have all
sorts of Dreams in your life but like as
soon as you get sick you only have one
so like it's such a a weight lifted off
my shoulder
and uh to to be healthy again you know I
it's it's it's wonderful once you start
feeling better again because I I went
from you know being so young and feeling
so old I couldn't even get myself out of
bed I was so fatigued and I I couldn't
focus my moods were all over the board
everything was changing about me and you
know it was amazing because like you
know there are so many tests out there
now they got DNA tests they got hair
tests they have certain food you knowest
test where they could tell you you know
what foods you can eat what foods you
can have moderately and what foods you
need to stay away from because your body
might not be agreeing with certain foods
but you're not having a physical
reaction you know you're not getting
bumps or a rash but you're you're
getting all these symptoms inside and
you don't understand why but your body
is not agreeing with the foods that
you're putting in your body and you know
I I did for me personally I did hormone
therapy and then they tested all my
vitamins and they tested all my um you
know what I was lacking and they put me
on certain supplements and they put me
on certain vitamins that I was deficient
in and I also started to do different
supplements that rejuvenated the cells
in your body and because the old the
older you get and when you start to go
into like the par menopause and you
start to slow down your libido your body
is not the same anymore and your cell
production is is slower everything is
starting to get deficient and you know I
was taking pomegranate I was taking the
the you know both both extract and and
the and the and the pomegranate itself
and that helped with the Rejuvenation of
of cells and and a lot of other little
things and just eating certain foods and
like you said sleep people don't realize
it but sleep is a huge factor and so is
stress learning how to cope with stress
and I love how you brought up about
exercise because exercise is not just
about you know gaining muscle strength
you know you could let out a lot of
steam and you can and it makes you feel
good about yourself and it really can
help you you know it makes you feel good
about yourself you get less you know it
takes that stress level down and you
start to feel more focused and it it
also gives you a good you know um view
of the day like wow I accomplished this
I got this done I feel good you know and
you know it puts you on a different
pathway of of mentally thinking so you
know I think exercise and and and sleep
are two major factors because I I
started to make sure that I got I
Incorporated enough as sleep and some
people don't even realize it but when
they're going through this stuff a lot
of people suffer from insomnia so then
you know there's different ways that you
could focus on to try to help with
insomnia that are natural that are out
there as well but sleep is important you
need those eight hours of sleep and and
just a little bit of exercise and
walking around a lake or just you know
going outside and taking a walk down the
road things like that is is all you need
you don't have to be like w lifting you
know 60 lb weights and you know going on
the exercise bike for an hour and a half
you could be doing simple things and
they could have a huge impact on your
body so I think it's like you know I
learned what my body needed and I
learned what my body didn't want and
once I started staying away from what my
body didn't want and I started
incorporating everything that I needed I
started feeling the change was that
something similar you know that that you
felt as well yeah for me it's the same
but different like it's uh like I was
saying before like like the path with
the natural path like it's uh they told
me the B12 they told me the foods I
needed to avoid and those things helped
a lot um but eventually the B12 didn't
make much of a difference anymore as I
was trying to like had less inflammation
and stuff like that and the things that
made the biggest impact on my health was
just the very simple things like like
like the sleep like and my sleep's not
perfect now I got four young boys and
they keep up hours the day and night and
um but it's it's I have enough other
healthy habits I think that now I I'm
able to handle a little bit of uh lack
of sleep but I prioritize my sleep
whenever I can and I I have the Naps
when I need to and um and I'm getting
through with with not as much sleep as I
would like but like for me the big
things was just like and and there's
clues in your life as far as what to
focus on
um for example like the things that you
dread the most quite often that's a hint
like why do I dread that for example
like when I was in in the depth of of of
uh of feeling like an old man like I was
almost fearful of being cold which is a
problem because I live in Canada it gets
pretty cold
yeah I I dreaded getting out of the
shower and it's like my bi is often cold
I have um in my family there's a a long
line of of rhinos like where you're your
blood circulation shuts off in your
extremities and it gets a little bit
cold then it gets extremely cold because
the blood circulation is shut off
painful and and uh you can have all
sorts of damage to to your to to your
skin and stuff like that with a lack of
blood flow but like that's something I
struggle with constantly and it got to
the point I almost had symptoms of
anxiety around going outside and and and
and doing the work that I need to do on
a daily basis so I started doing cold
showers and believe me the amount of
stress that I felt getting that water is
is insane but I stuck with it and like I
learned so much about my body in the
meantime not only did I get healthier
and and um because like the the benefits
that people often talk about like I
Revitalize the mitochondria in my body
because the mitochondria are the heat
producing parts of your
cells and like and like like they
produce heat and energy so I had more
energy throughout my whole day because
of it but like also things like once you
get into that cold water you have to try
to control your your stress response
control your breathing and I was never
really aware of my breathing before
right and and so like when I took what I
learned trying to get into the cold
water and to to what stressed breathing
felt like and how to control that and
now what relax breathing feels like I
started noticing I'm just working just
do my normal work throughout the day I'm
I'm stress breathing for no reason right
to your body that's stress yeah it's
throughout your whole day just the way
you're breathing you got to breathe into
your through your diaphragm into your
belly and I was breathing up in my chest
constantly just shallow breathing and
that's signaling to my body that that
we're in a stressful situation when I
wasn't I was just going about through my
daily routine and and like so that was a
huge hint like why I'm so fearful and
and almost anxious of the cold it's like
that's a Direction needed to go and that
made a massive difference bigger almost
than a lot of other things and then like
in fasting I was like it I never it
never occurred to me as I especially
when I was younger but like growing up
and like I'm I'm six feet tall I had
huge grow Spurs I couldn't do without
food I need to grow and and fuel my body
kind of thing and like and then later on
in life I gotta feel the work I got to
do I got a physical
job it never occurred to me to do it
fast but when I did like I said that was
a triggering event that brought my
hormones back and and not only that it's
surprisingly easy and later on I I
listen to other people about fasting you
take some salt while you're fasting it
curbs your hunger and it keeps your
strength up so I can do a physical job I
can pick Stones all day fasted as long
as I have enough salt if I start feeling
shaky and weak I consume a little extra
salt and I'm good to go again like it's
and it's like the power that you feel
realizing that you control over your
diet because if you're out traveling
whatever else that you you know I can go
two three days without food no problem
right so I don't have to eat this
Convenient Food that's around at the
airports or wherever else or or or at a
party something like that and you're
feeling some H things like you can you
can wait you won't die yeah exact yeah
there like there's really much focusing
on simple things and looking at my own
life for hints of what I should focus on
first but like the really the simple
things like eating the Whole Foods
getting some doing some some some
exercise it doesn't have to be crazy
like you said like the most important
thing about exercise is doing it
consistently so just do what you love
and for me more like the like the the
animal type movement stuff like that
just felt freeing for some reason and it
wasn't in a masculine way it was much
more in a softer way that just the
self-expression only in an artistic way
but for me it built my body it got me
strong it was easy for me to stay
consistent and is a lot of healthy body
move movements which applied really well
to my physical job surprisingly enough
to um all the critics especially my
father out there seeing me do exercising
saying like why you wasting all your
energy because like allow me to learn
how to move properly move at least less
joint pain less body aches and things
like that so then yeah it made a made
that made a really big difference too
and all these all these habits that that
I focus on one at a time then you make a
habit around it becomes becomes easy and
normal to do those things on a day day
to-day basis and now you maintain those
habits becomes much easier so like
building those habits and and then uh
for me like the the final straw was was
the
fast that's great you know what when you
brought up the breathing I you know that
is so important like when I started to
learn how to do slow breathing and I
took some lessons and they taught you
how to control your stress how to
control your body through breathing wow
what a difference it made you know you
can be anywhere you can be anywhere and
if you are conscious of the way you're
breathing you can change the way you
feel you can change the way your mind is
thinking you can change the way your
body is feeling just by the way you're
breathing you know people have done like
you know I've showed people how to do
methods of of relaxation breathing and
as they're sitting in their seats at
work when they're all stressed out and
you know it's amazing how impactful it's
so important to know how to breathe CU
most people don't pay attention but if
we're in a stressful situation or if
we're not feeling well we should focus
on our breathing I think and really
learn the right way to breathe and
that's something people should look into
I think what do you
feel yeah it's it's always like if you
told me that 10 years ago I thought that
sounds hokey I'm not gonna worry about
that like it made a big difference in in
uh in the the average stress I felt
throughout the day just and it's not
just like yes you you got your breathing
and like being able to focus on that but
it's just like the the awareness of what
relax breathing feels like and what
stress breathing feels like that was
massive for me just having that
awareness yeah and like so like for me
that was the biggest impact I got from
cold exposure is just the self-awareness
of what stressed feels like and what
relaxed feels like yeah it's I don't I
don't naturally have that much
self-awareness I'm not really very
naturally very self-critical and and is
good some bad things to that like I'm
not really I don't I don't feel the
impact of of uh of pure pressure the
same way some other people do but like
yeah it the downside like I I I could be
horribly stressed and have no
idea that that awareness made a big
difference and and just yeah like being
aware and then being able to change your
breathing because you practiced relax
breathing and just be able to switch
over and like for me too like other
things like that I I learned that
techniques that I also use during those
stressful cold uh periods is like I
would smile even though like I'm I'm
struggling I would just force a big
smile on my face and it's like it's
hilarious some of the research that are
out there people just putting pencils in
their mouth which kind of f forces a
smile and like you feel better like it
it works yeah like you wouldn't think so
and especially people especially like
myself are just like go getters it's
like yeah like I don't got time for that
kind of hokey stuff but it's
like it does it it makes it makes a
difference
it makes a difference and I feel like
you know I hear people use that excuse I
don't have time I don't have time but we
do have time you know all you need is
five minutes of the day 10 minutes of
the day somewhere if you can spare 15
even better but all you need is a few
minutes here and there and just little
tweaks can make such a big difference in
your life something better than nothing
and then what I always tell myself is
that it's never a lack of time that's
your issue for not making this change
it's a lack of priorities like how
important is it maybe you got to
something in your life that's very
important to you like you got a wedding
coming up and you want to get a healthy
body or like you have your your kids or
your grandkids or or or a massive dream
that you might have like chasing your
dreams or creating that business like
and like that's that's that's a real
thing for me I'm trying to improve the
lives of farm animals like it's like you
gota tie these little habits that you
say I should add this to my life I don't
got time or but it's not that at all
it's a lack of priorities like what can
I give up like I don't golf anymore
don't play video games forever but like
it's like it's like things that you can
give up or like or you look on your
phone it it gives you a a number every
so often of the average amount of time
you spend on on your phone screen day
like cut that in half and you can have
hours more time exactly exactly you know
I you hit it right on the nose it's
really just an excuse because you don't
prioritize what's important in your life
and you have to really think about
what's important to you you know what do
you really how do you really want to
feel how do you really want to look how
do you really you know when you wake up
in the morning you look in the mirror
are you happy with who you see are you
happy with the way you feel and then you
got to start just stop making excuses
and just make little you know prioritize
your time just a little better and all
you need is just a few minutes and
miracles could happen it's not going to
happen right away of course you know but
baby steps you know that's part of the
problems because usually the things that
we need to give up give us immediate
gratification and the things that we're
trying to add in requires that delayed
gratification but those but that that
that delayed gratification the impact is
massive so like that's the problem so
you got you got have a lot of
self-control in your life to to make
that happen but if you if you stick to
it it it pays back for sure oh it
definitely does it definitely does now
if you had to give a couple takeaways
before we go what are some important
factors that you want people to realize
from this whole conversation because we
tapped into a lot of important things
and we you gave such such great advice
today thank you so much for all the
great advice you gave but if you had to
like sum it up what are some things that
you just want the audience to realize
from this
conversation big big picture is yes you
need to look after your body look after
yourself to make yourself more effective
at everything you do
and I think just just thinking now like
if you are in that place where you're
sick your body has an amazing capacity
to heal and I think that that is I think
maybe the the biggest takeaways like
your body can heal if you get out of the
way and stop feeding it junk and
stop Doom scrolling and stop sitting on
the couch like these simple habits that
you hear is is not rocket signs every
basically everybody know knows what you
got to do to be healthy like you got to
sleep enough you got to exercise just a
little bit it doesn't have to be a whole
lot it's just start that habit eat your
Whole Foods stay on the prim and the
grocery store and then like and then
from like once you get those those those
core habits in place like those those
simple things in your life then you can
really go into the weed with it and then
you can like you can really focus on
like the quality of the food I'm eating
is is it regenera raised do I know the
farmer and stuff like that can I get
more in touch with the food I'm eating
and like really respect your food and
stuff like that like you can keep going
down those roads with exercise too and
like and like meditation and like you
can keep it's endless the way you can go
but just start with those those few
simple habits that can make a massive
massive difference oh yeah for sure and
I gotta I got to be a testimony to what
you just said because I did those things
and my my health and even my mentality
did did a whole turnaround so everything
you just said is so true 100% true now
before we go can you tell everybody your
website where they can find you and some
of the services that you offer
absolutely yeah uh my my farm is moral
eats um m o rat ts.com is our website
and what we're trying to do with this
business is like I'm trying to improve
the lives of fire animals through supply
and demand supply and demand is so so
powerful
and uh it's it's a bigger and more
powerful way to make an impact than
writing those comments on social media
and stuff like that or or or anything
else really supply and demand is so
powerful and getting your voice heard so
like that's what we're trying to do with
moral eats and the best way to get in
contact is like through our through our
website you go and you sign up to our
email list that's our favorite way to
contact people and educate people and
keep them up to dat of what we're trying
to do with more Elites and and our
mission of improving the lives of firan
an and furthering regenerative
agriculture because like the thing
beautiful thing about email is like I
don't have to rely on the algorithm to
put my my my information in front of you
it's like it's in your inbox either you
delete it or you read it yeah so there
so it's like but then beyond that oh and
like and if you live in Ontario where is
where we Farm like we will if you sign
up to our email list you get that chance
to to win free a free meat box and and a
sampler box of like of everything that
we have we have have our our our
pastured turkeys our grass-fed beef we
have pastured pork we have uh wild and
sustainably Source wild seafood and we
try to get like a whole smorgus Board of
of of products especially animal
products because we're trying to improve
the lives of farm animals and hopefully
in the near future you'll find some
dairy products in there with some calf
of foot Dairy which is just cows that
are allowed dairy cows are allowed to
raise their own calf and and and have
that be a massive step forward too
towards Animal Welfare Improv Animal
Welfare so like we have we got big plans
in the future Big Dreams but like beyond
that you can you can find us on on
Instagram and Facebook as as more Elites
or uh on Tik Tok and and YouTube as uh
just my name sander Vance
D wow this has been amazing thank you so
much sander for coming on the show today
and sharing all this valuable
information I think you really you know
explain through all the things that you
share today how important it is to you
know really focus on what we put in our
bodies how we take care of our overall
health you know and really about putting
oursel on a pedestal because it's time
that people show each other not just
show other people but show themselves
some self-love because really you know
without taking care of yourself you'll
never be able to take care of the people
around you so you really have to focus
on number one and then you could focus
on whatever else is important in your
life but you know health is so important
and it really goes down to what how
we're treating our bodies and what we're
putting in our bodies and you know and
it's so important that we really like we
talked about create that healthy
lifestyle you know and make it you know
break those bad habits and start
creating those good habits and just
making it a part of our lives so you
you've you've provided us with a a a
wealth of information today and I thank
you so much for coming on the show it's
been a pleasure thanks for the
opportunity oh you're very welcome you
have a great day you to