as organic farmers we're like the
Lifeboat of the planet I mean it's kind
of a big deal and I it's I'm really
passionate about that because we're
doing this really hard work Matthew was
explaining like we're literally hand
shoveling compost like so many noil
farmers are wheelbarrowing their compost
onto their land and like literally
shoveling we're like the Earth core and
Engineers we're laying all this organic
matter down and the huge benefits are
being brought to the planet as far as
climate change you know as far as
habitat for beneficials we learned that
you know you add fertility to the soil
and you take care of the soil Health you
grow bigger plants and that means that
the plants are taking up more carbon out
of the
atmosphere and fixing it into their
bodies which is exactly what all the
green energy folks are telling us is
what we need to do right is to to to
sequester more carbon