of the entomology graduate student
organization I'd like to introduce dr.
David Pimentel first I want to thank all
the organizations that helped co-sponsor
dr. Pimentel visit including the ISU
lectures program the graduate college
the pesticide management and the
Environment Program the Leopold Center
for sustainable agriculture within the
Leopold Center the IPM that's integrated
pest management issued team the
bioethics program and the Center for
agricultural and rural development lots
of organizations we couldn't have done
it without all of them and this wide
range of organizations reflects dr.
Pimentel his wide range of interests to
describe dr. Pimentel to you I have to
start by describing his scientific
credentials which are pretty extensive
he's currently a professor of entomology
which is the study of insects at Cornell
University 50% of his appointment is in
the department of entomology
to accommodate his wide range of
interests the other 50% of his
appointment is as a professor at large
of Agricultural Sciences including such
things as energy use soil erosion this
is the only such appointment at Cornell
so someone with a unusually wide breadth
of interests he served as the chairman
of the animala G department at Cornell
for six years he has authored over 400
scientific and technical papers
including having written two books and
having helped edit another 14 books so
in other words this is someone who is
really excelled in pretty much all the
ways in which scientists measure success
but that's not the main reason why the
entomology graduate student organization
invited him to speak tonight what really
distinguishes dr. Pimentel is his
willingness to take risks
and what I mean by that is his
willingness to take public stands on
controversial issues this is something
that not a lot of scientists will do
it's it's not necessarily the safest
road to professional recognition but
it's something that dr. Pimentel has
done consistently by his example dr.
Pimentel shows us that scientists have a
special responsibility to educate the
public because it's you the public
that's going to have to make the
decisions about where the balance lies
between the costs and the benefits of
pesticide use and we're very pleased to
have dr. Pimentel here tonight to give
you some of the information that you're
going to need to make those decisions
this topic tonight will be economic and
ecological benefits of sustainable
agriculture
thank you again for a very kind
introduction
I hope I'll live up to it I'm going to
take one aspect of sustainable
agriculture for emphasis and that's on
the subject of pest control and I will
have a few other things in there but I
think it well illustrates some of the
problems we have the challenges and also
some of the opportunities we have to
change the system and make agriculture
environmentally sound and I'm going to
try to keep this to about 45 minutes so
that we can have some time for questions
I will be using slides to illustrate the
points that I hope to make if you could
turn those on then I put these this
first slide on to emphasize one point
that we have I think we can make out
with I think the side lights on it but
anyway it's that we one major problem
and challenge that we have is trying to
provide food for a rapidly growing
population and is that the one this
doesn't seem to work
can you either we're disconnected or did
you change it or I did okay anyway the
world population is 5.5 billion and
where we add a quarter of a million
people to the earth every 24 hours a
quarter of a million that have to be fed
and we already have a problem in feeding
the numbers that we already have 1.6
billion humans are malnourished on Earth
today with 2 billion living in poverty
but even the u.s. did
I do that a you did you did all right
thank you I'll rely on you now the
United States in 1850 had 23 million
people or less than the population of
New York State today in 1990 we went to
250 million and my must admit that my
number of 20 year 2070 is incorrect that
ought to be because the world population
says I made this the u.s. population so
I made this slide during the last three
years has increased its well do both due
to immigration and rate of reproduction
in the u.s. is now 1.1 percent per year
and so that should read now year 2050
that we will have a half a billion
humans in the United States assuming
they don't increase further next slide
now our goal accosted in is to produce
high-quality food in the US and
elsewhere to feed people and the next
slide a few people appreciate the fact
that the average American consumes 1,500
pounds of food per year and I've got the
calories in the so for three-quarters of
a ton of food per person per year in the
US and the next slide we should be
eating only about a thousand pounds of
food per year and this shows you where
that excess is going that's part of our
national strategic petroleum reserve
next slide now to focus a little bit on
on some of the pests and they do cause
an enormous loss to our food system not
only in the US but worldwide next slide
although they're attractive I suppose
sitting in your corn it's not a great
benefit if you want to save that corn
next slide worldwide there are about
67,000 pests that tried that che
share our food and that doesn't include
the rodents or the mammals and the birds
and the plant pathogens obviously
dominate the system next slide now to
try to control these pests and limit
their destruction of our food enormous
amounts of pesticide are used next slide
2.5 million tons worldwide and the u.s.
uses about a half a million tons
pesticide in one way that we waste
pesticide is the way we apply the
material for example by aircraft if
you're spraying and I want to emphasize
now this is under ideal conditions and
very seldom do they apply pesticides
from aircraft fly under ideal conditions
only fifty percent gets into the target
area I'm not talking to the target pests
of the crop I'm talking in the target
area and the new technology that's being
adopted in aircraft application is
called ulv are also low volume and in
those cases only twenty five percent
gets into the target area and so the
rest of this goes drifting off into our
environment to cause problems that I'm
going to talk about in a moment next
slide now the actual amount of pesticide
that reaches target pests is less than
one tenth of one percent which means the
rest of it is again in our environment
although a lot of this is in the target
area but is still in our environment of
course some of that will move out of the
target area in addition next slide now
in general pesticides do have a benefit
we in the u.s. spend 4.1 billion dollars
annually in pesticides and it's
estimated we save about 16 billion
dollars in crops thus for every dollar
invested we get about four dollars in
return but I
I emphasize now that does not include
however the public health and
environmental costs of using pesticides
these are the direct benefits and do not
include any of the costs social or
environmental that are involved in using
pesticides and I'm going to get into
that issue in a moment next slide now in
the US we lose in other words despite
the use of the 500,000 kilos the
pesticide that we use we lose 37% of all
potential production to insects diseases
and weeds and incidentally the world
figure is 35% now the reason in part we
use a large quantities of pesticide but
still lose on average slightly more than
the world is the difference in cosmetic
standards for example a lot of the
fruits and vegetables that you see on
the Guatemalan market or in India would
not be saleable in the US so this is all
based on saleable products and this is
in part why our losses are slightly
higher than the average in the world
next slide now some interesting data
that indicates some of the problems that
we're having and mismanage when I term
it is the crop losses due to insects and
these are USDA data in 1945 before we
started using the new synthetic
insecticides we were losing about seven
percent of our crops to insects and
today am i standing in the way of this
projector the law all right let me stand
over a little bit you can still hear me
okay all right they
sighs in 1945 when we we did not use any
synthetic insecticide that's when we
started and we were losing 7% of our
crops to insects in 1992 after
insecticide use it increased tenfold
crop losses according to the US
Department of Agriculture now 13 percent
in other words nearly a two-fold
increase in crop losses due to insects
with a tenfold increase in insecticide
use now you might say how the hell could
that happen well the reason is for the
most part changes in agricultural
technology some changes in cosmetic
standards and their pesticide resistance
and a few other problems next slide and
destruction of natural enemies and and
so forth the next slide also illustrates
a little bit better using corn as an
example related to the agricultural
changes in agricultural technology in
1945 for example almost zero insecticide
was used in in corn production and today
corn is the largest user of insecticides
in the nation VDOT cotton about 4 years
ago now next slide when we started with
1945 most of the corn was grown in
rotation and we didn't have a problem
with the corn rootworm complex of
insects and today about half the corn
has grown in rotation and half is not
next slide and now with corn being the
largest user of insecticides there's
been over a thousand fold increase in
insecticide use in corn production in
the US and again going back to you
da next slide the data that corn losses
to insects according to the USDA have
gone from 3.5 percent to 12 percent with
a thousandfold increase in insecticide
use and it's primarily due to a change
in agricultural technology that is
moving away from crop rotations next
slide
now our land is extremely important to
us and I wish I could have spent some
time on the on the soil degradation and
soil erosion problem but I'll leave that
for a another time but land is extreme
next slide if you people appreciate the
fact that 99% of the world's food comes
from the land less than 1% comes from
the oceans and freshwater aquatic
systems and so we should be very
concerned about the our soils and the
degradation of these soils by erosion
and various other means including
highway construction urbanization and so
forth
and you'd appreciate the problem in part
that during a 30-year period from 1945
in 1975 of just agricultural land from
highways and urbanization we blacktopped
over the equivalent area larger than the
state of Ohio
that's just highways and urbanization
and if you took all the areas that would
blacktop over over that period it would
be both Ohio and Pennsylvania but the
agricultural land alone was greater than
the state of Ohio next slide now when we
do apply pesticides as I mentioned by
aircraft and especially if they're near
housing areas and so forth you do have
the serious drift problem and the impact
of pesticides on the public is
significant next slide is world data
from w-h-o the total number of human
pesticide poisonings worldwide is or
about a million with 20,000 deaths in
the u.s. we also have a problem next
slide the human pesticide poisoning
sixty seven thousand it's more than
sixty seven thousand each year twenty
seven deaths and the estimated cancer
associated with pesticides aprox list
about ten thousand per year so it is a
significant public health problem in the
u.s. not as severe in the rest of the
world but certainly it's it's it's
important next slide now we also when we
use pesticide in particular insecticides
we do destroy some of the natural
enemies and this costs us money the next
slide gives an estimate of the cost to
the nation that's us in the destruction
of natural enemies estimated to be five
hundred and twenty million or about a
half a billion dollars next slide and
then pesticide resistance these are
world figures about five hundred and
four species of insects that are
resistant and well close to 900 total
species pests that have become resistant
and this is a very important problem in
the US as elsewhere in the world next
slide nope I guess I didn't have that
number but anyway the estimated cost of
resistance in the United States is 1.4
billion dollars annually John and this
is due to the extra pesticides as to
treatments increased crop losses due to
the resistance problem it's certainly a
major environmental
problem and then of course pesticides do
get into streams and lakes and destroy
fish and this is totally an under
estimate but it would be somewhere in
the neighborhood of thirty million the
realistic figure is probably three or
four times that next slide and then when
we do use insecticides in particular
honey bees and wild bees are killed and
that is a cost to the April culturalist
and it's also a cost to agriculture from
the point of view of reduced pollination
wild bees and honey bees are important
to pollinating about thirty billion
dollars worth of agricultural crops
annually and a conservative estimate is
that the impact of pesticides on tame or
honeybees and wild bees is about over
three hundred million dollars annually
next slide and then some other
interesting effects that you can get
when you're using pesticides is using if
you use an herbicide for example 2 4 D
on a crop such as corn that it creates
other pest problems that is it may help
control the weeds but you do create some
other pest problems and these are data
on corn showing that with 2 4 d it
recommended dosages that the corn leaf
aphid population was nearly three times
on the treated corn that is treated with
herbicide than on the untreated and
another next slide the corn borers for
example were significantly more abundant
on the treated corn that is with 2 4 d
then the untreated and furthermore these
corn borers grew 33% larger on the 2 4 d
corn and produced 33% more eggs than the
corn borers
the untreated corn and we also checked
it out on to diseases corn leaf blight
and corn smut disease and both was
significantly increased
well actually the corn lost its
resistance the southern corn leaf blight
when we exposed it to 240 and the corn
smut disease was 5 times larger on the
treated corn those are the only
organisms we looked at but it does show
you the significance of the interaction
of some of these pesticides in the
impact on pests next slide I'll skip
that's in part some of the changes that
we observe and then birds Osprey and
various other birds that do become
exposed to pesticides next slide the
estimate is that pesticides are causing
about two billion dollars worth of
damage to birds using a very
conservative estimate that I explained
to if you liked it some time next slide
and then groundwater and well water
contamination and I understand that it's
a serious problem here in Iowa also it's
estimated that if we did an adequate job
of monitoring well water and groundwater
for pesticides that it would cost a
nation 1.3 billion dollars annually I
remember that's strictly monitoring it's
not doing anything about the problem
next slide and then of course pesticides
do reduce species diversity and it's
estimated worldwide that it's not used
just due to pesticides but due to all
the factors such as removal of forests
that we're losing about 150 species per
day due to our various changes that
humans are causing next slide now the
total environmental cost
of using pesticides back to the United
States we estimate to be at least eight
billion or another way to put it more
than eight billion dollars annually so
it is a significant cost now pesticides
still are benefi benefits in terms of
economics if you factor that in on the
cost benefit originally I told you that
you get $4 returned for dollar invested
well if you would factor even this 8
billion now I realize that this is a
conservative figure this 8 billion but
if you factor it in it still turns out
that pesticides are a net benefit for
the nation
now I'd learn a turn next slide to what
we can do in managing our pest control
technology to improve it and hopefully
make it more profitable next slide and
the basic principles that I have it
related to sustainable agriculture is
that we make maximum use of our
biological resources and to minimize our
energy inputs in the system in other
words actually minimizing our management
of these resources next slide and
related to sustainable agriculture in a
study that one study that we made it
does take more labor especially if
you're going to make use of livestock
manure and the recycling in the system
and that is one major problem in the
u.s. is that we're not making effective
use of that manure is polluting our
water polluting our surface waters and
wasting a very valuable resource next
slide and we can confuse consumers
particular model situation related to
corn we were able to buy some a being
selective of the tractors
and the equipment that we had reduced
the total fuel input from 115 litres per
hectare to 70 major well about 40%
reduction in fuel inputs next slide and
then our actual corn yield in this
particular system we are actually able
to increase the yield in the sustainable
system we were using a crop rotation
system here and so that we were able to
get a higher yield and with no
insecticide being used in this
particular system next slide now as far
as energy goes we were able to in fact
reduce the total energy inputs by 1/2
that is from seven point eight million
kilocalories per hectare to 3.7 million
Killa Killa calories per hectare reduce
soil erosion from 20 tons per hectare to
one and obviously reduce the water
runoff and reduce the amount of
pesticide being used in this particular
system next slide
now dollar-wise it was also the cost of
production were reduced from five
hundred and twenty three dollars per
hectare to three hundred and fifty two
dollars per hectare and that does
include the additional labor xx sorry 20
percent more labor that we had in that
system
next slide now related to pesticides for
countries if you include on a character
Ontario in Canada as a country I have
made the decision to reduce pesticide
use by 50 percent and Denmark was the
first country to do that and sweden ii
and sweden in 1992 or last year it
already achieved their 50 percent
reduction in pesticide use and this year
they've implemented another program to
another 50% reduction in pesticide use
well what we did at Cornell was to make
a study I think there's 40 different
crops and all of the non chemical
technologies that exist and then examine
aren't asked well two questions could we
in the United States implement a program
to reduce pesticide use by 50 percent
and how much would it cost and that's
what technologies we already have
available similar to course that Sweden
or Denmark or Netherlands are
implementing next slide well skip next
one now what one of the things we want
to do a course in your trying to reduce
pesticide use is make better use of your
natural enemies such as this a fat lion
that you see here next slide
and that makes making judicious use of
pesticides this is the potato beetle and
using crop rotations and short season
potatoes anyway there are a lot of
different technologies that we can use
to deal with some of these serious pests
next slide and I'm not talking about
total elimination of pesticides I'm
talking about reducing the amounts that
are that have to be used through
implementation of non chemical controls
through the judicious use of pesticides
and crop rotations are a benefit not
only to insect control but diseases and
weeds and obviously help reduce soil
erosion and soil degradation next slide
and then because one weapon that we have
in pest control against insects is using
some of the diseases that affect them on
the slide here you see
the the one on your left the caterpillar
on your left is a healthy cabbage looper
the cabbage looper on your right is one
of the whitish one is full of virus
crystals and these virus crystals have
looked like pure crystals under the
microscope and that animal is totally
packed with virus crystals and it's a
highly pathogenic virus if you take two
caterpillars well such as the next slide
24 hours later this is the cat l and if
you just take two caterpillars like that
and you mix them in a hundred gallons of
water and spread it over an acre of land
you can kill 98% of the cabbage loopers
that are present there so it's a very
effective highly pathogenic organism
unfortunately even though every one of
us in this room was eaten the virus in
our coleslaw or lettuce and so forth and
not affected us or at least not that we
know APA is still not approved the use
of this virus yet next slide now there
are a lot of and I'm not going to go
through all the loads that's just a list
of some of the non chemical controls
that are available to us that we can use
and implement to reduce pesticide use
and you can't there isn't any one of
them that is perfect and what we should
be doing is being very selective and
using those that are most appropriate
and I guess that what Professor Pedigo
said is very appropriate there is no
silver bullet for pest control and we
ought to be using a combinations
depending on the particular situation
the pest and the environment the crop
and and so forth next
slide but it does illustrate the
complexity that we're dealing with and
this is a shot in Kansas that the lake
professor painter provided me showing
you wheat on the right here the
susceptible to the hessian fly and we on
your left that is resistant to the
hessian fly and so this is one more
technology that is available to us and
can be used effectively depending on the
crop depending on the pests and so forth
next slide now I'll skip that one the
next one that's well anyway I know what
the what I hope to be my last slide is
that that we could achieve a 50%
reduction in pesticide use in the United
States you can turn the lights on and
without a reduction in yield without a
change in cosmetic standards and that we
could do this with an increase in food
prices of only 0.6% now what I also
emphasize that this calculation of a
point six percent increase in food costs
implementing a 50% reduction in
pesticide use does not include the
benefits of public health of reducing
pesticides on public health or reducing
pesticides on the environment if you
take into consideration those benefits
Aventa costs I in general there should
be a net benefit to society by reducing
pesticide use by 50 percent and it can
be done as a
one country has already achieved their
50% reduction in three others are unwell
on their way to achieving this 50%
reduction so this is not something that
is pie in the sky I'd be happy to answer
questions very well I guess we got quite
a bit of time no way good
any comments a question I what are two
bits of information in Central America
where we were working on cotton because
the I was going to say the workers were
careless I should really put it the
other way around that is that the
managers of these firms were very
careless they sprayed these workers
while they were in there in the field
they allowed to fit their field workers
to go into the field to pick cotton or
weed right after the fields have been
treated and so that they were getting
wet with the pesticide in there that of
course we don't do in the US but even in
the US right after DDT was banned and
there was an increase in paradigm and
several of these other more toxic
materials there was about a three-fold
increase in the number of deaths in the
u.s. now one has to say if we were
careful there shouldn't be these deaths
because we know how to handle it safely
and so forth but of course accidents do
do happen and in Central America we also
would know how to handle it but it's not
being done and I'm not just blaming
Central America there is the curse
that's where I mentioned Central America
only because we worked there for a while
yes
and of course you know that has problems
because I know I'm sweet in some of
these other countries some of these
toxic materials and so that's there's no
good way for we were using the same
materials or reducing the materials to
achieve really amount of the frequency
and so forth is still there it's just
that yeah materials more active with
appeared oh that there was a reduction
when in corn we haven't talked to the
pyrethroids so really you know it's not
sure
yeah yeah that's a that's a good point
and by rejoyce have their problems in
viola yes to make the shift yeah you
couldn't do it overnight well I'd say in
general sustainable agriculture is more
knowledge intensive so it takes more
knowledge now to do that of course it
means that you've got the training
people to use this new knowledge in new
approaches and that would take time to
achieve a sweet knitted in five years
some of the other countries are have
plans to do it in about 10 years but
it's not substituting alternative
technologies but chemicals will take
training ten dollars yes
there would be no increase fertilizer
use know we didn't decrease to fertilize
the use in that sustainable system that
we had there through use uh well first
of all keeping the soil in place that is
preventing 20 tons of soil being lost
from the land you know each ton of soil
has about four kilos of nitrogen plus
other nutrients but making use of
livestock manure in that particular
system not did cost us in labor of
course to do that but as far as reducing
the pesticide no there was no impact on
the fertilizer I would say we on corn
there was decreased energy but I
wouldn't want to say that for all the
other crops because we now know we have
to really look at that crop by crop in
general I would guess that it it
wouldn't increase the amount of energy
but I wouldn't want to say that a
decrease in either at this at this
moment yes
the question here is Sweden and Denmark
appear to be progressive and will we
ever in the United States achieve this
type of a change I think we will but if
I look for the DD banning DD T is the
model decision then I would say it takes
us 10 years after Sweden to get to the
point where we will make a similar
decision but I think the climate is
certainly coming and remember this
change in Sweden and Denmark did not
come from agriculture or entomologist it
came from the politicians listening to
the people now already in the United
States and the survey by Food and Drug
Administration I didn't know there was
97 and 96 percent some of that vicinity
all the public are concerned about
pesticides in their food today growing
concern in the credibility of EPA has
dropped significantly
yes and so there is this climate and
pressure to trying to do something about
it in and certainly once we see the
success of Sweden and Denmark and Norway
- although they haven't passed
legislation that they certainly well on
their way and the Netherlands and the
province of Ontario incidentally in
Ontario the specialist who's in charge
of reducing as implementing the program
to reduce pesticide use
I thought the farmers would be resistant
to this and he talked about opposite he
said the Pirates are highly supportive
of this whole program to reduce
pesticide use and he said the three
reasons one pesticides cost of money -
they're the ones that are applying these
toxic materials and they're being
exposed their families being exposed and
three they also have a concern about the
environment I must admit I didn't expect
this talk about all three not just the
last one but they're really highly
supportive of this program out there I
don't know about Sweden and Denmark well
it never asked a question there someone
else had a question yes sir
herbicides insecticides and punishment
right and then the actual reduction that
we look at paper in achieving this
reduction we could achieve the greatest
reduction in herbicides second and
insecticides and lease fungicides
and you know price supports is playing a
very important role in reducing crop
rotation and it's also played a very
important role in separating livestock
production from integrated with grain
production and so there's a whole array
and the marketing orders as far as
changing cosmetic standards not that
that's important in the brain so much
but there's been a whole array of
factors that the government I'm talking
about federal government has played a
very important role in encouraging soil
erosion and cryogen fertilizer use and
encouraging pesticide use and so one
first step would be to get the damn
government straightened out and
supportive of sustainable agriculture in
reducing our reliance on chemicals and
that would be the very first step and
let me yellow and indicate in I think we
could go beyond a 50% reduction if you
will allow changes in the price supports
and deficiency payments and marketing
orders and you'll also allow this to use
pesticides at dosages that are effective
instead of using the label dosages on
the pan and I indicated
mentioned this afternoon I have one of
my past students in Galway he's working
with true and he is demonstrated clearly
that in using certain insecticides that
using one-fifth or one-tenth the dosage
is on the label he can get more
effective control and I want to imply
more effective control because he's a
lot he can save the natural enemies and
make use of them in the pest control
system so now if you'll let me do some
research and determine the appropriate
dosages we could go further than that
reduction if you will allow me all those
changes combat extent his marketing
price apart and getting the proper
dosage I think we could go to a
seven-year