hey there backyard Farmers want fresh
eggs and feather friends today we're
counting down the top five chicken
breeds perfect for your home Garden at
number five is the coachin these fluffy
Giants are gentle and cold hearty making
them coup Superstars number four is the
Rhode Island red these productive hens
lay tons of brown eggs and are known for
their friendly temperament coming in at
number three the ostr these black
beauties are prolific egg layers and
fantastic forgers in your garden number
two is The Bard Plymouth Rock This Dual
Purpose breed lays a good amount of egg
and is a cal addition to your coup and
our number one breed is the buff
orpington these dosel chickens are
perfect for beginners laying lovely
brown eggs and are total Charmers that's
it let me know in the comments which
breed you'd love to add to your flock