do you know what an agronomist does
agronomists are plant and soil
scientists
who conduct experiments to find better
ways to manage our farms
most agronomists work outdoors from time
to time and you'd need to be prepared to
get your hands dirty
you'll be working alongside farmers
researching ways to boost crops control
pests and weeds and protect the
environment
this means you'll need to collect
samples perform experiments advise
farmers about the ways they can improve
their work
and you'll also be working with others
to increase sustainable farming
practices
agronomists need to be interested in
science and farming and you'll also need
to be able to communicate well with
others
so you can share your findings as an
agronomist you'll need to be able to
visit farms
although you may not need to live in a
rural location you don't have to go to
university to become an agronomist
but you will probably need a vocational
or tafe qualification to get started
most agronomists work full-time during
normal business hours and around one in
four agronomists are women
it's a small industry but it's growing
fast and there's lots of demand for new
agronomists
if you're interested in science and
farming see if you can find work
experience or part-time work on a farm
or take on a farm job such as fruit
picking over the holidays
it'll help you work out if agriculture
is the right place for you want to find
out more
head to study work grow for all the
details