greenhouses and high tunnels are
attractive because they allow us to grow
plants that may struggle if we tried to
grow them outdoors and it can extend the
growing season about a month on each end
some of the considerations to make when
choosing the high tunnel or Greenhouse
structure for your backyard would be the
plants that you want to grow and the
material that you want to build your
structure with in this case we have a
poly film cover over the top of this
High tunnel and we have polycarbonate
sides or ends to the high tunnel and of
course glass is another option
polycarbonate and film materials might
be less expensive but they have a
limited lifespan of maybe five to seven
years another consideration would be
venting and Cooling in the summer when
it's really warm outside it's extremely
hot on the inside of the structure which
can stress the plants so
a door sides that roll up or even a vent
installed in the top of the structure
will help let that hot air escape the
University of Wyoming has Publications
on high tunnel and Greenhouse structures
from the University of Wyoming extension
this is Chris hilgert and you're
watching from the ground up
foreign