tractor has broke down so anyway want to
see what we got going on check out the
[Music]
video so guys the burn pile is burned
down good so far we got good hot coal so
uh as soon as I get the tractor going be
real easy to get this back going and we
have obviously put a big Den in this but
I got no go on
that so let me tell you what happened
and it's kind of a series of events it
I've got two issues so first of all U
and I'm going to include this in on the
end screens when we get to the end of
this video a while back I've got a video
it's called I messed up and I'm
surprised I didn't that it didn't break
everything then but I'm convinced it did
like 80% of the damage so what happened
was I and again I'll show you the video
when I was hooking up my grandpa I
accidentally just for forgot to put in
the Locking pins I did the hydraulic
lines and anyway I just dropped off the
grapple it pulled all the hydraulic
lines very tight I think it did a lot of
damage to them but they did not rupture
so I've been working I don't know last
two weeks contined to use the grapple
well anyway over the weekend it finally
um it finally gave up The Ghost and I
had a ruper I was shooting uh as I was
picking up this stuff and moving it over
to the burn pile all of a sudden I
started shooting a stream out of one of
the hydraulic lines about 2 or 3 ft up
in the air so I immediately shut down uh
went to investigate real you know I knew
immediately what was going on but I
disconnected the hydraulic lines cuz I
did not want to lose any more fluid and
lo and behold when I went to crank back
up battery was dead as a door knob even
though I had been sitting here running
it for hours so uh I know just the
battery over time this this tractor is
over 6 years old now and uh you know
it's time for Batteries they you see if
you get over 5 years you count your
blessings right so anyway guys first
thing on the list is I'm going to walk
you guys through uh putting a
replacement battery in here now I've
already pulled the battery but no uh no
big deal for you guys not to see that
coming out obviously we're going to do
the reverse process and as we go I'll
tell you guys a bunch of stuff I've
learned along the way so you know me
guys let's get busy all right so
obviously my tractor is a
3032e um and on pretty much all these
versions of tractors the battery is
located up in the front and so um this
right here just sets in a in a a holder
and it's real easy you can just lift
this up and move this over and this
right here just lifts up and comes out
of the way and I'm going to set this
over to the side and the the um battery
goes right down here in the bottom and
it's got a special way that it mounts in
now now uh one thing I want to share
with you and you know you guys can make
decisions for yourself on how to do this
but this is a 22 Series battery and if
you go to like Advanced Auto now you can
see I've got this was a John Deere I
actually went to the Tractor place to
get this and I'll explain why uh first
of all if you go to like uh and I'm not
knocking the advanced Autos or the Auto
Zones uh they have a battery that's
pretty close to the same size but the
one thing their batteries don't have is
this little protrusion out on the side
with this hole indention and so you have
to make a decision do you want to get a
a little bit cheaper battery that does
not have this and then this is what's
used to lock the battery on the tractor
in place or you can do one without this
and you got to figure out another way to
strap it down and hold it into place cuz
it been up on the front of the motor and
it is near the radiator and the uh
intercoolers for the for the hydraulic
fluid you don't want the battery moving
around in and bouncing in and breaking
you know you just will have another
thing to get tore up so then I played
the numbers game uh the batteries at the
Advanced Auto that's in the 22 series
are AutoZone they're all about the same
they were anywhere from $110 to
$115 I could get this battery which is a
factory replacement from John Deere and
this was just like 140 bucks so for 20
or 30 bucks more uh was it worth it to
me it was because my time I did want to
have to take time to reinvent how to
strap this down and so uh I just went
ahead and got it I was there it was
available and it was the exact thing I
needed so I got it you guys obviously
more welcome to make up your mind on how
you want to do the fix but that's the
reason why so anyway that's the battery
and now let me uh start getting things
laid out and I'll show you how we get
this in place and by the way while we're
here these are the straps that hold down
and this is why this is so important
is this strap the way it goes and let me
get the camera here so you can see it it
this battery I mean this bolt sits right
up in that little Groove and that's
what's going to keep it from moving back
and forth so anyway again the decision
is Ys on how you want to play it but
anyway let's get this in and get my girl
going all right guys so I'm just going
to ease this on down in
here like
[Music]
so
up and get it set in
place and make sure I'm left and right
from where these holes
are all right and then as I was stating
there's one hole to the left one hole to
the right and this is where the
challenge comes in a little bit because
that has a nut on the back side and you
got to reach around so hopefully my long
arms are long
enough they sure don't make this easy to
get
to from
[Music]
here there we
go that's that
side this right here is the hard Parts
just trying to stretch around and get to
the
bolts I've got an extension on the upper
end holding it in place and I'm screwed
that in so now I've got them started all
I've got to do is just snug them
up like I said this is the fun part but
it's not too awful
[Music]
bad all right one side done one side to
go so now you just pull up the tabs and
pull the tops
off and obviously you want to make sure
black to black or black to negative and
red to
positive and obviously if I was at my
house I would have much better selection
of tools but this is called in the field
repair and you make out with what you
got so it might be a little
slower but we're going to get
it so you just snug these
[Music]
up and hopefully here in a minute we're
going to be ready to fire this bad boy
up
so if you've been watching any of my
videos recent you know that it's
extremely dry here and uh you also know
that it's just been Dusty Dusty and boy
if that doesn't show the tail of it
right there with how dirty and dusty
everything is underneath when we get
home it'll definitely be time for a
cleaning and replacing filters cuz I'm
at my fall servicing anyway and uh just
time for a good clean up good
servicing all right so as you saw I just
set the tray back in place and set this
on top all right guys here's the moment
of truth let's see oh we got all kinds
of Lights that's a major Improvement and
here we
go yeah baby well guys I owe y'all an
apology you know when this video started
I was going to be doing two repairs well
in the middle of me working
uh something happened which I absolutely
loved I got some surprise visitors that
kind of interrupted my work so I never
got around to recording the second part
of the repair I'm sure I'm getting ready
to show you what what happened and uh
I'm sure you guys will forgive me when
you see why get out of my way I'm coming
through there she
goes and Sissy's chasing her here she
comes com s and there she
goes you're the best Papa in the world
well thank you are you coming
through see you later I at your house
now wiing with two swings there you
go now don't you think you a little too
big for that one hi I'm set going a baby
[Music]
swing here let's face
hi
hello
byebye see
you crazy well guys the tractor's back
running great I also did a little bit
more excavator time and this pile is
just endless and keeps going and keeps
going and keeps going so what we're
doing is just reaching in pulling this
stuff out get getting it to where we can
work with it cutting off what wood we
can burn and we'll continue working try
to get the stumps burun down as well for
now uh everything's back in action and
working great and uh I'll catch you on
the next one cuz you know here at
project next one there is always one
more we'll see you on the next
one