When people come to the extension office asking
about pesticides, they oftentimes have questions
about the effectiveness or availability of
organic pesticide options.
Now, there are many options available that
are considered or labeled as organic and are
certified for organic production.
Despite the fact that a product may be labelled
as organic, it’s still important that we
take the proper precautions and use the appropriate
PPE, or personal protective equipment.
And this means, at a minimum, we should have
a long-sleeved shirt, long pants, shoes, socks,
chemical resistant gloves, and preferably
eye protection as well.
It’s also important to remember that these
products can also be toxic to beneficial insects,
such as our pollinators, if used incorrectly.
So, it’s still very important that we open
the label, take the time to read it, and familiarize
yourself with the product, and understand
how to safely use that product.
Due to a limited availability, there’s not
always going to be an organic option for every
pest, so you may have to get creative or look
at other control measures in some cases.
Even if a product is listed as organic, it’s
still important that when using that product
that we take the proper precautions and treat
that as a chemical.
This has been Caleb Carter with the University
of Wyoming Extension, and you’re watching
“From the Ground Up.”