Hello and welcome everybody to our
Commlands one tile challenge. This is
going to be episode 16. Um we went ahead
and fast forwarded a little bit to April
and
well well that that that caused some
more problems for us.
Um we we will have to uh look into how
we're going to solve our issues moving
forward. um especially with mowing our
grass. But if you haven't yet,
definitely look down in the description
and check out some of the other content
creators that are doing this challenge
with us. They are doing awesome. Great
bunch of creators. Definitely worth
checking out their videos. If you've
enjoyed what we've uh done so far on the
series, consider smashing that like
button and hitting the
subscribe. But without further ado,
let's go ahead and get into the rest of
the video. All right. Oh, it sold 50
chickens. So, we got 250 bucks for it.
But, I mean, that doesn't really cost a
whole uh cover a whole lot.
Um, wow. So, they they produced a whole
another pallet worth of eggs. Nice,
nice, nice, nice, nice. We're going to
have to worry about where we're going to
put all our eggs pretty soon. All right,
but we got four more pallets of lettuce
ready to
go. So, yeah, we're definitely running
out of storage area pretty quickly.
Um, but we do want to go ahead
And honestly, I think I'm just going to
keep the time down at
three. That way, we we have plenty of
time to work in a month instead of
keeping it on five.
Um, get our mower out. So, we're going
to go ahead and Oh, wow. I did not
expect the trees to pop up so quick.
Oh,
[Music]
we I I did not expect to see any kind of
growth visually for a
while. Oh man.
Um that's I mean great. Uh we we have
trees, but that means we can't get the
harvester into that other
field if we did throw down plant uh
beans. So, I thought we were going to
have a little bit more time. Let's go
take a look at that field. Uh we'll
we'll try and get a cut on that one
first.
Um but yeah, I was definitely not
expecting that.
Maybe we can get in
between all them all the
trees. Yeah, that might be an issue when
they get a little bit bigger to try and
get into that other field. I mean, we
still have that open wall on the other
side,
but
yeah, this is going to be even a pain
just to cut.
Um, but we might have shot ourselves in
the foot by putting a crop down
here. Yep, cuz I can't even just bounce
off the
tree, man.
Well, I wonder if we can go in from the
side and
just don't want to get too close. I
think this might actually be our best
direction to go ahead and
cut. That means I'll
get a pass in one direction and a pass
in another.
We don't have a whole lot of room to
turn around down
there. So, we'll take a look to
see. We probably should be closer to the
trees over
here. Yep. And that's
about about where we'll be able to get
without running into our
crops. Yeah.
You
know, don't think I thought this one
through. Might have to look at maybe
getting a skinnier mower just to go
ahead and get in here.
Um,
man. All right. Well, in the
meantime, we'll go ahead and cut our
grass
field. I was not expecting for
those kind of mistakes to be
there.
So, it
happens. But we are going to go ahead
and cut our
grass.
And so that'll limit our income quite a
bit cuz I'm not going to be able to cut
in
between any of the grass besides what we
have. But in the same turn, that means
we're going to have trees a whole lot
sooner than I thought we were going to
also. So that's good thing. It's both a
blessing and a curse.
But I am excited to have the
treats. My tractor running away without
me cuz I hit the wrong
button. All
right. Back it up a little bit.
All
right. Yeah.
So, I'm glad that
uh we're able
to get the trees up a little bit.
Um, not
[Music]
sure. Not sure what we really want to do
about all that.
Um, I think our lines disappeared on
where we want to cut, but I think I can
just run along the edge of this and be
just fine if I keep my back tire along
the
edge. But yeah, so was not expecting
for those trees to sprout up.
Not this soon.
Anyway, so I think what we're going to
need to look at is a mower that can get
in between those. That way we can still
Well, we're going to need more than just
a mower, aren't
we? We're probably
need We only got
16,000,
man. All
right. So, I'm going to go
ahead. We're going to look at our
options real quick. See what what can be
done. And we'll decide what we should
do. Uh let me set this mower off
real can't mow
backwards. These are all 20,000 and they
still stick out a ways afterward.
[Music]
Huh. Unless I just mow in reverse, but
don't think we're going to be able to do
anything with that grass for a little
while.
Okay, I might
uh search the modhub
uh off camera and take a look at what we
can do cuz I really don't want to lose
that profit down there cuz that's going
to be a ton of money. I mean, not a ton,
but a decent It's a decent sized field,
so I I assuming we'd probably at least
get 10 grand off of it every
cut if we converted it to silage. So, I
mean, we get a little about 20 grand off
of this one when we cut
it. So, that is unfortunate.
Well, I mean, I don't think that one's
nearly as big as this, but
yeah, he's five, six
grand ladder. We need
to That's actually pretty decent spacing
on those trees, at least at the moment.
Um, I'm trying to think. Trying to
think. So, we might possibly
start cutting some of those trees out
while the others
grow.
Um, just
to try and get a little bit of
wood going.
I mean, I might give them a little bit
more of a growth
stage. That also allows us
to continue to get
wood if we throw down a lumber
mill. Oh, we forgot to drop the the bar.
What are you doing, donkey? What are you
doing?
Yeah, I'm just going to circle the
wagon and we'll drop back in right
here. All right, there we go. Yeah, I
think what we might do is go ahead and
look
into how much it is going to be to put
down our sawmill
production. And then
once maybe once the trees hit one more
growth stage, we'll start chopping a few
of them
down. And
then from there, we will be able
to kind of weed out and replant as we
need. No, I lowered that. Oh, I lowered
it once and then raised it back up
because I got off track.
Okay.
Yep. So, I think we'll take a look into
that once we get this mode. Um, so I am
going to go ahead and jump into mowing
this. I know since we didn't get it
fertilized, we're going to we're going
to take a hit on how much we're actually
getting off of it. If you can look down
in
the bottom corner where the map is, you
can see our yield is
changing from that nice dark green that
we were getting to a lighter green
because of
the fact that this field needs both lime
and fertilizer.
But it happens
and we
are going to go ahead and get this mode
and we'll catch back up to
you. All right, so we just finished up
mowing here, but I think we might have
figured out a solution to our mow
problems.
Um,
now it is going to cost us a little bit
more
money,
but we should be able to earn that bag
off of the first
cut. So, I think we're going to run up
to the
shop. We got a friend over there eating
our grass.
All right. But yeah, so I think if we
run up to the shop, we might be able to
get a mower small enough to go in
between the
trees.
Um,
but the only other question is, are we
going to be able to get the wagon in
between the trees to pick up the grass
that we
mow? Um, that's going to be another
one. But let's let's
let's get up here.
Uh, you guys are running in a little
late to work.
I've noticed that uh the traffic on here
is very very much uh based around the
hour. At least maybe that's just when I
come to the shop and see the traffic.
But all
right,
so we're going to go into mowers here
and went ahead and added a couple of
mods. So, this one is an option, uh, the
iMac, but it only has a 1.8 working
width. So, I'm not sure if that's what
we want to go with, especially since
this lizard mower here has a 3.4 working
with, which is almost what we're we're
currently working with. Um, but it goes
directly behind the
tractor and it can go 3 km faster than
the iMac. So, I think this might be what
we go
with.
Um, you know what? We're going to go
ahead and buy it. Uh, does it cost us
anything to change the
color? Let's
see. Cuz
No. Okay. Awesome. So, we can change the
color as we feel the need to. Um, what
color are we
feeling? You know what? It'll kind of
Oh, no. That's way too bright.
[Music]
Um, you know what? We'll just keep it
with the classic red. But all right. So,
we'll buy that.
Now I guess our other option if we
can't
get that might actually be pretty close
to width of those trees.
um about the width in between those
trees. And once it gets bigger, uh we
probably should have went with the
smaller one, but decisions were made.
So, we will probably face that problem
when we get around to it. Granted, when
they get bigger, I'm planning on
thinning them
out,
but
should Let's see. How close are we going
to be? Oh, yeah. Now we're going to be
great. Okay,
so that being
said, what do our lines
Oh, yep. We're going to be doing this
one by hand. That is some funky looking
lines. Yep.
So, I'm not sure why, but
yeah. All right. But yeah, it our other
option is Okay. And it looks like we
might be able to get right up next to
the
trees and get that median in
between. But if we can't
uh get our
uh our forge wagon in between here, I
guess what we could probably do is push
all of it with the bucket.
And
uh this is going to be a pain, but we
could push it all with a bucket and get
it down that
way. So, I think we'll go ahead and
finish off this strip
here. Uh just to make it easier to turn
around and then we should be fine to go
ahead and mow this. Now, that'll allow
us to
uh at least make some money on this
field.
Uh why these trees are
growing. But yeah, and then we should be
able to fit just fine in between here
because this is our narrowest
section. If I could just drive straight
because these trees were planted in a
straight line. I just have to be able to
uh mow in a straight line. All right,
but yeah. So, this is our narrow section
and we fit just fine at the moment. So,
that's not going to be a bad
thing. But
now, but now we're going to run into the
issue of being able to either a
fertilize to keep
our score up a little bit on precision
farming as I know since I didn't
fertilize the land
uh or our
other grass
field last time before
cutting. Oh, whoa. What just happened to
that
tree? Does this delete trees as
well? Um
[Music]
Um, I'm going to go ahead and turn real
mower off on
that. I don't want to be losing trees
like
that. I mean, I want to be able to cut
the grass,
but that tree had a lot more potential
than than that little bit of grass that
we cut right
there. All right. Yeah. So, we'll get
this cut and then we will see if we
can't end up
uh and see what issues we're going to
get with
uh picking it up the grass. But yeah, so
we
will skip you guys ahead until we get
this mowed and then we will see you guys
once I get
back. All right, guys. So, we just
finished mowing this.
um did kind of a
uh weaving pattern between the trees to
try and get a little bit more cuz even
after we turned off the real mower, we
still ended up cutting down a tree
somehow. I'm not sure why, but that was
not in the mod description on this that
it does remove stumps or any kind of uh
tree deletion.
So, little weird about
that, but we are going to go ahead
and we're going to go ahead and wind row
at least this field and then we'll pull
out the
uh porch
harvester
to see if we can't get a
uh decent amount of grass picked. up
between the two
fields.
Now, one of the things I did say earlier
is that our pH and
our fertilization was bad on these
fields. Uh, which it is. Um, well, yeah.
Yeah, our pH is non-existent in spots,
so that's not very good. I mean,
granted, back here it's fine, but if we
look at our pH map, it's not looking
pretty at all. Um, at least on this
field. So, we are going to need I think
last time it was three bags of
uh
lime to get that done.
Uh, so we will have to get I say bags,
but pallets of
lime to get that all
situated.
Um, and we're going to have to get that
down today. Now, as far as spraying, we
might be able to save that
until next month. That way, it realizes
that grass is
here.
Um, this if we do it this month, why
shortly after it's harvested, it's going
to lose its mind and we're going to end
up putting down way too much fertilizer.
Now, if we do wait till next month, we
might be able to afford the pulse
modulation and throw that on
there. But that'll definitely be dipping
into our profits from the silage in
order to do
so, which isn't necessarily a bad thing
because we do want that for the future
anyway.
just to help us out as far
as saving a little bit of money on
fertilizer.
So, wouldn't be a bad thing to go ahead
and get that. At least I believe that's
what it'll what it'll be.
um that or we might uh sell a couple
more pallets of
lettuce as we are getting four pallet
around four pallets a month which that's
a lot of lettuce.
Um and we'll see where that puts us. It
might put us right there at being able
to do
it. Well, actually, what we have eight
pallets sitting there cuz we skipped a
month. So, yeah, we might we might go
ahead and sell our uh lettuce off and
put pulse the pulse modulation, but
that's uh that'll mean that we can't
um do lime and fertilizer. We can't
afford that. So, yeah. Yeah, I think
what we'll do is we'll save our money
this
month and go ahead and
uh put down the
lime and then next month we should be
able to
afford the pulse modulation as well as
um our liquid
fur and get that thrown down. Now, for
this other field, we're we're still
going to have to use
our dry fertilizer to fertilize the
grass over
there, just because we're not going to
be able to get the sprayer in between
those trees at all.
But we should be able to run probably
every
other lane in between the trees and get
fertilizer spread out there. It's not
going to be
as evenly distributed as far as the
nitrogen values go, but it should still
take care of the task of getting our
nitrogen up as far as our field. Okay.
So
yeah. Yeah, it is not looking pretty for
us. So if we don't get our values up
nitrogen
wise, we're missing out on a lot of our
bonus that we get from
uh precision
farming. I think I probably should have
done a second headland down there before
starting the down and backs. So, I think
when we get down there, I'll do a second
headland on the bottom and
then we
will finish window rowing this and
then I will bring you back once we
uh are picking up the other field just
so you can see how that's going to work
out. But yeah, so we will see you once
we get done with that.
All right. So, we finished wind rowing
uh on the field up there. Now, we do
want to check to see how well this is
going to fit in between the trees. So, I
wanted to go ahead and bring you guys
back in for that.
Um that way you guys can see whether or
not our problem was solved as far as
picking it up. At least for the little
bit. It looks like we will clear the
branches.
Um, and hopefully these trees only get
taller and the branches don't get
lower. I mean, that's how nature works,
right? Is
uh things grow
up.
But yeah, and see this is where we
deleted the other tree by accident. So
that's why I left a lot of grass around
each tree is I did not want to risk
bumping into the trees and making them
disappear.
So thankfully it was only two trees that
we lost, but that's still two trees that
we lost and the potential of our
wood cuz right now each of these trees
um yeah each tree at the moment is 350
lers of wood.
So,
but it does look like this is working
for
now and we are almost done picking up
this field.
Although, if it is only going to
be, it looks like it might
be two trailers worth of grass off this
little
bit. It might not even be worth risking
losing the trees to go ahead and
mow,
but we'll have to see.
Yep. It looks like it might be two
trailers worth.
Uh, see if I can sneak out this
way. Now, if they get bigger, it might
it might still be worth
it.
Um, but yeah.
I
really really don't like losing profit
like that though. So I think what we're
going to do because I don't want to run
over our
crops. Just definitely want to avoid the
crop destruction. I think I'm going to
use the bunker up here and go ahead and
fill that.
Um, so we'll have 12 pallets next next
episode of Lettuce at about $1,000 a
pallet. That'll
uh be 12,000 in lettuce. So that that
won't be too terribly bad.
Um, plus whatever we're going to get off
the silage. So, you're looking
about possibly making we'll say
30,000 next month.
Um,
possibly.
Now, that being
said, in order to put down our
uh lumber
mill, so that's going to be
about I think 12,000 10 or 12,000 to go
ahead and put down the lumber mill that
we want.
Um it was one of the only ones that I
found that will do the prefab walls
um and still be a decent size to fit on
our farm.
So, I think that's the one we're going
to end up going
with. Uh, and then it's another 30,000
for
our
concrete plant.
So, we will have to save up for that as
well as the
[Music]
additional 40,000 to get our
um sprayer where we want it. So, I'm not
sure which one we're going to do first.
I
know if we can make about 40,000 every
couple of months, that'll be great.
But I am so like I'm still on the fence
on which one we should do first. Should
we should we go ahead
and get the lumber
rolling or should we go ahead and get
our sprayer situated the way we need it
to be? I think we might end up getting
the sprayer done
first just
because that's going to be something
that's going to be a little bit more
useful in the
future. Or well, actually, no, they're
all going to be pretty useful.
Um, at least getting the sprayers. uh
fixed with uh pulse
modulation. Um and
then possibly around planting season.
Oh, and we are full. Okay. So, yeah, a
little bit over two trailers. So, it
might still be worth it to mow.
Um if they grow up a little bit bigger,
hopefully we're not going to run the
risk of deleting the tree just because
we simply bumped it with a mower.
Uh we're going to have 3 months before
that grass is ready to mow again. So
we'd be looking at mowing again in
July.
So that's going to
be good little ways
away and maybe be able to get another
growth stage out of these trees before
that cut.
I don't think I am going to go ahead and
mow those just yet. I might
save that for next
episode if I decide to cut it even at
all.
Uh now
cows. Cows is another thing that we
wanted to invest in.
Now, we don't currently have enough
money to deal with cows
either. We have what we need to feed
them, but the cow pin itself and then
buying the cows is quite pricey.
And unless we just stick with a super
small
pin and maybe fit only 20 cows, I'm not
sure how good 20 cows is going to be as
far as milk production. I think we are
producing way more food than 20 cows can
eat. And that would just leave us for
the most part with that secondary grove
of trees just sitting over there cuz one
of the
uh one of the cowpens that I installed
is a lot smaller.
Um it's about the size of the chicken
coupe and it can fit about 20 cows in
it.
And then there's another one from that
mod that
uh it's still
a it doesn't have a pasture, so we can't
really
extend how much there is. It pretty much
only relies on the food that we give it.
So, no meadow
grazing. And it holds 40
cows. And so that that might be an
option. And then we just continue to
grow trees over
there in the grass over there.
But I I
mean 40 cows is still 40
cows. So that might be the way forward
is just go ahead and forego the
pin for cow for
uh taking the 40 cows and producing milk
already.
Now, that is something that we would
possibly be able to afford. Let's let's
go ahead and take a look why we're
dumping.
Um, all right. So, yeah, what I was
talking about here
is But it's a breeding barn, so milk
production wouldn't
happen, man.
H I don't
think What about this one? So, this
would be 36,000, which is right in our
price
range. I know I don't have it at the
moment, but we'll be able to put that
down right over here.
Still want to give us a little bit of
space to get in and
out of our
silo and then space to get up to our
[Music]
house. That's
tough. So, we would have to almost put
it right up against the trees right
there and we'd still be able to go in.
So, what about this one? Okay, that's
about the same
size that has. So, for an
extra
$3500, we can get five extra cows in
there.
H. And that would actually allow us to
have Yeah, that that's not even worth
it.
Um, that'd be 50
cows or
40,000. And of course buying the cows as
well. But yeah, I didn't even think that
these
were. Yep. Okay.
Um, and I'm not sure
if I do have
a mod on here to
add milk. Oh, but it's 30,000. Okay.
Yeah, I
think I think it'd be worth it just to
go ahead and buy the one that allows for
uh
milk and versus buying that
extension. So, I'm not
thinking unless we just buy
calves and then add the extension in a
little bit later once they're raised up
a little bit.
But I was thinking even if we just buy
10 cows, 10 adult
cows, that
would that would help us out
milkwise a lot
more than just selling the silage
outright.
So that is something to think
about that. Do we want to go with
buffalo the water buffalo or do we want
to go with cows? I know buffalo milk
sells for a ton more but the cows
themselves produce a ton more milk than
what buffalo
does.
Hm. A lot of decisions to make around
this farm. So, we're definitely going to
be looking at those in the future.
But I am going to go ahead and get this
all picked up
and we'll get it
compacted and we will see you guys once
I am done with that so we can spread
some lime out on this
field. Right. So we will see you all
then. All right. So, we just finished
compacting our silage. So, get that
covered.
Um, and
then we'll get our roller put
away. I almost think we should put the
roller clear in the back. So, we don't
use it nearly as much as we do the
mower.
So, I think that's going to be what
we're going to want to
do.
So, get this put away and then we will
grab our fertilizer spreader. I think it
should be empty. And probably our pallet
forks and go get some lime.
Uh hopefully we
can get all the lime we
need quick, fast, and in a hurry. And
then we'll get
that thrown down.
Um not sure with
this. No, it
took
four I want to say four pallets of lime
last time we did this
field, but that was also with the old uh
spreader. So, we will want to probably
take a look at
that. Actually, I think what we'll do is
so I
know our trailer
is probably going to be needed. So, I
think we'll take
our spreader down to the other end of
the
farm so we can start as soon as we get
down
there. And then we will grab our trailer
and bring that up with us
to the shop to go ahead and purchase our
lime.
Um
although
h we need four pallets, don't we?
So, I wonder even if we go ahead and
uh that's probably not going to be a
good place for that. Yeah. So, we'll go
ahead and place this down
here. I wonder if we take our box
instead of the whole
trailer, will that be something that
will be
useful? as we don't quite have a
hole.
Uh yeah, we don't have
a whole bucket of stones at the moment.
So, we can just pile that there.
Um, but can
we just trying to
see is there a way
to open
it? So if I lower
it is there going to
be X? Nope.
Okay. But there is tension belts. So,
what we can do is we will Oh, pick that
back up real quick. Turn off that. We'll
grab our pallet forks and we'll run up
to the shop and grab our lime. We should
be able to fit two in the back and use
that as a counterwe
uh and have the other two on our forks.
I think that's what we can do and get
that
done. And uh if I
can. Yeah. Okay. So, we are going to go
ahead and drop off our
bucket. We'll need that next month when
we go to sell our
silage. Did get a little over 170. Why
is
that? Okay. What did
I Ah,
okay. So, up and
down. Oh,
okay. Good to know. We can lower the uh
tailgate on it.
Nice. Okay, so we're going to go ahead
and run and grab
our lime that we're going to need. I
believe four pallets should be fine for
this
field, but we
will definitely see and
hope. Four pallets is
What?
$1,800. So, we can afford it at the
moment. If we're only putting lime down
every three cuts on the field, that's
not too terribly
bad. I know it would increase
our yield a little bit more if we threw
it down
every every cut,
but that's
just I don't think that's going to be
costefficient uh compared
to what the difference is in yield.
So, we
will lower this
down and disconnect it. And then run to
the shop real quick. I don't get stuck
on the pallet forks tripping over them.
And we will grab some lime.
Okay. So, we
need four pallets of lime. Yep.
$1,800.
Okay. So, we should be able to get two
in the back. Granted, we're going to
have to grab them one at a
time. And
then then we can have those just readily
available to load
into our fertilizer
spreader. I don't think I got that in
the right place. There we go. All
right. And is it being ready? Well,
honestly, we might be able to fit all
four of them in here. And then we just
have all of them ready to go right next
to
it. Now, not sure how
heavy or what that's going to do to our
tractor trying to lift that much and
take it down, but I think we should be
fine. I don't think we're going to tip
backwards. Can I
Maybe push it. Yeah. Oh well. Well,
yeah. So, we'll get this all loaded and
we'll get down there and I will see you
guys once we are down with the
lime. All right. So, we brought the lime
down. I did go ahead and just bring it
on the forks just to save a little bit
of time there.
Um, so we're going to go ahead and get
this filled
up. Uh, we do want to go ahead and make
sure uh that we are running into our
market, but we want to go ahead and set
up
our our
lines and then we'll build this up.
Should be about 1,000 lers if I remember
correctly. Yep. Okay. Awesome.
And then we will hop into the field.
Spread out some
lime. I do want to get a running start
on
this just because it seems
to prevent getting those deep blue areas
as much as long as we are driving
already.
So definitely making the field look a
whole lot better
limewise. But that's
already half a pallet gone right
there. All right.
So, we are definitely going to end up
using a lot more lime than I initially
predicted. Hey, at least it used the
same pallet twice.
Okay, but I think getting a running
start on distributing the lime is the
way I want to go.
Um, that way we're not piling lime up at
the
start. But I guess I let our field get
so bad limewise that it just cost us one
pallet to do the
first first pass on the
field. Just not the greatest.
Um, so we're gonna end
up probably having to get another two
pallets, I
think.
Um, yeah, I think I will jump ahead and
I will let you guys know how many more
pallets we had to buy. If you would
like, please drop a guess down in the
comments and see how many pallets of
lime this field is going to take and I
will let you know once we get back. All
right, so we just finished lying the
field. I'm not sure why there's that red
line right there in the middle,
but not a whole lot we can do about
that. um ones on the border, I'm pretty
sure, just because that grass right
there is not mowed and so we couldn't
get the lime down. So, I did go ahead
and buy another four pallets.
Um
and yeah, so we used about five and a
half pallets
total to lime the field.
So, not as efficient
as our spreader that we had before, but
honestly, it kind of saves us a little
bit of time um to do this. So, now that
all the lying is done, we are going to
go ahead and get everything put away.
We're going to
get Yeah, we're going to put the mower
away. We're going to put the fertilizer
spreader away.
Um, and then yeah, we should be able to
see you guys
next in the next month and we should be
able
to put down some liquid fertilizer. We
definitely should be able to
afford once we sell off our lettuce and
silage again, should be able to afford
to upgrade
our sprayer a little bit.
um in order to put that uh pulse
modulation on it.
So, that's what our goals are moving
forward is to go ahead and get our our
sprayer upgraded for the fertilizer. And
then we will look at doing
uh the weeding upgrade a little bit
later on in the season, probably when we
get closer
to planting down crops again.
But yeah, I think I will leave the Oh, I
need the pallet forks. So, we'll go
ahead and grab our lime and bring that
up and put that in the
shed in case it rains.
And then
we Yeah, we'll get everything put
away. But definitely thank you all for
joining us. If you like the video,
please smash that like button. Um, and
consider hitting the subscribe button if
you've enjoyed the content I've put out
on this series so far. Uh, it definitely
is
appreciated. Feel free to drop any
comments in the box down below. I do try
to answer all the comments that I can.
Um, I do enjoy talking with you guys.
[Music]
So, until next time, peace.