hey uh my name is Jim Horman and we're
going to talk about the biology of soil
competion we've had a few problems here
this morning but I understand this may
go off at noon so I'm going to speed it
up just a little bit you know when we
talk about ideal soil composition uh
roughly 50% of the the soil is what we
call solid material about 45% of that is
the mineral portion and in an ideal soil
we have about 5% organic matter a lot of
farmers don't know this but uh as much
as 50% of the soil can actually be PO
space however when we compact the soil
uh a lot of times we don't have that
much so let's take a look at a compacted
soil look at some different bulk
densities if you look at an uncultivated
undisturbed wood lot typically the bulk
density is anywhere from one to 1.2
grams per a centimeter cubed and and
what we're looking at is we're looking
at the weight uh uh and basically the
weight over a volume of of soil and so
that would be ideal if we had 1.2 gram
per centimeter cubed that would be an
ideal soil we have
about 50% uh Poe space in that but as we
get into cultivated Clays and cultivated
Sandy loms you'll notice that the bulk
density increases and that means we have
less room for air and water to move and
so if you look on my right hand side
there at the bottom once we reach a bulk
density of 1.6 grams per cimeter cubed
it starts to become root limiting that's
somewhere around 250 pounds per square
inch we get up to 1.8 and then the roots
are totally restricted and you can't you
uh The Roots can't get through there so
that's real important on a lot of our
soils we're actually uh limiting the
roots and how deep they can go so let's
take a look at at what is typical in our
soils we generally talk about the plow
layer and this may be anywhere from 7 to
8 to 9 Ines deep
and you'll notice that we have as we
light as we plow that soil uh the buk
density goes down it's like around 1.4
and then we reach this limiting layer
there about seven eight nine inches deep
where it's very hard for the roots to
get through the soil we've seen this in
almost all the soils that we've we've
looked at uh there's a a limiting layer
there and a lot of times especially on
corn Roots they'll go off at a right
hand angle also on soybeans so what
we're doing with the cover crops and the
noil as we're trying to break up these
compaction zones the very fine Roots can
get through uh ples of weakness and they
can uh decrease that bulk density so
that uh uh our main crop the green crops
can get deeper into the soil to get
moisture and also nutrients soil organic
matter if you look at some of the
characteristics why we want to increase
soil organic matter contact look at the
bulk density of soil organic matter it's
about 6 compared to say 1.45
somewhere in that range for where we
have a tiled soil so soil organic matter
has less density in the soil has more
room and more space for air and water
storage and here's an important
characteristic every pound of so organic
matter can hold 18 to 20 pounds of water
that's why we like to say that s organic
matter acts like a
sponge and here's a a picture of that
you can see the little black areas in
there if you look at s organ matter uh
it's it's not nearly as dense the color
tends to be light to dark brown and it
has room to store water and also to
store uh nutrients you also notice that
the surface area is is quite large so
that allows uh water to get trapped uh
in between those particles it also gives
structure to our soils when we looked at
a compacted soil uh the density could be
between 1.6 to
1.8 compacted soils kind of have have a
much higher density less room for air
and water storage they tend to act like
roads or Road payment they a lot of
times result in flash floods it was
interesting this year we had a drought
we had a couple of onein rains but the
majority of that water ran off the soil
surface even though the soil was
extremely dry it's because we turn that
soil into Road payment I like to say we
turn it in whenever you do excessively
till the soil you turn it into a road
payment we've all probably seen a farmer
maybe your neighbor really till the soil
what happens when they till it and get
it very fine as soon as it rains it
turns into concrete and so dense soils
also have less microbial life and that's
really important for nutrient management
here's an electron microscope of some of
the clay minerals this is where the the
water and the nutrients can be trapped
generally um this clay mineral will put
in organic film around there and the
nutrients get trapped in between the
soil organic matter and and the minerals
that are in the
soil three soil compaction factors we
all know that heavy equipment uh due to
its weight will compact the soil but did
you know that rain and gravity will also
compact the soil we can have
rainfall uh when it comes down it can
reach a terminal velocity of 35 miles
hour and almost looks like a any uh
nuclear explosion when it goes off so
that can move Soil and Water but it also
tends to have a compacting factor is
there a visual way to measure soil
compaction and actually you can go on
your farm and you can probably see this
uh if you look at a fence row and look
at the elevation difference between your
field and where that fence row is we've
measured this in Ohio some said that
this was due to wind others said that uh
uh a lot of the soil had eroded and uh
had piled up in a wind R but actually
we've measured this on the Le side of a
uh woods and we saw anywhere from a 6 to
9 inch elevation difference if 50% of
that is void space that equals an
additional three to four and a half
inches of additional water that we could
store uh in that soil if you really want
to see this if you've got a a wooded
area you can see the difference here in
northwest Ohio
uh a lot of times the woods is uh the
woods that we had were actually uh very
low and uh that's where the water stood
now often the water is standing on the
Headlands uh and we can see water
standing there it's because that soil is
much more compacted here's the water
available uh the available water
capacity of soil organic matter that
first inch of additional soil organic
matter can gain you anywhere from one to
almost two Ines of additional water if
we get it up to 5 in or 5% soil organic
matter you can see we're gaining on a
sandy soil 2.5 on a Cy Loom four inches
and on a Cy clay Loom three inches of
additional water so it starts off at one
to two inches of water per foot of soil
and after we get up to about 5% organic
matter we're down to about a half
2.8 uh inches of additional water for
for every 1% organic matter that we're
adding to that soil this is extremely
important in dry weather or in climates
that don't have uh a lot of uh uh
rainfall here's what happens we've
talked about this where we've got a
compacted or killed soil it tends to set
up like the road where we have good
vegetation throughout the the year we
increase that por space so it slows down
the water runoff and it increases water
infiltration here's what happens if we
speed up or double the velocity of
water the relationship is two to the six
power for every time you double the
velocity of water this tells you how
many more nutrients that that water can
carry the faster the water flows the
more energy it has so if I go from one
to two mile per hour I can carry 64
times more nutrients if I get up to 16
to 32 mile per hour in a flowing stream
I can carry a thousand times more
nutrients with that water so what we're
trying to do now is we're trying to slow
the water down so that it drops its load
keeps the nutrients in the soil rather
than running off we have a lot of
problems with hypoxia and nutrification
hypoxia is too much nitrogen and
phosphorus getting into uh the Gulf of
Mexico nutrification is mainly where
we've got too much phosphorus causing a
lot of uh algae
wounds for water uptake if you're
looking at where the roots absorb most
of the uh water it's in that top half if
you look at each one of these lines is
about six inches so 40% of the water uh
by that plant is absorbed within the top
six inches the next six inches will
absorb about 30% so 70% of the of the
water is absorbed in the top foot this
kind of explains why corn can actually
do quite well with maybe only 8 to nine
inches of rooting depth before the roots
start going off a right hand angle it
actually has almost 70% of the water but
if we can get those roots to go a little
bit deeper especially in a dry year we
can gain another 20 to to as much as 30%
more water as we get into that subsoil
same thing goes for nutrient extraction
exact same relationship 40 30 20 and 10
and you can see the depths there so the
same
relationship also when we look at a soil
there's a big difference between no tail
with the cover crop where we have live
plants notice the temperature difference
it's about 87 to 85 degrees over here
where we have conventional and maybe we
have started to try to do no till you'll
see that there's at least a 20 to maybe
as much as a 30 uh degree increase in
the temperatures this year when we had a
drought here in Ohio we measure soil
temperatures up around 130 to as high as
140 degrees Fahrenheit and what impact
does that have notice here the soil
bacteria start to die at 140 degrees
Fahrenheit we get our best moisture
somewhere where the soil is around 70 to
95 degrees once it gets over 95 notice
we're only using at 100 degrees
Fahrenheit 15% of the moisture is used
for growth 85% of the moisture is lost
through evaporation and transpiration so
if we can keep that soil covered with
live plants and keep a nice layer of
residue on there we can conserve
moisture and that's the key thing that I
wanted to talk to you about also for hot
dry Summers how much more water do we
need when the temperature goes up at 75
degrees Fahrenheit we need about one
inch of water per week raise that by 10
degrees we need two inches raise that by
another 10 inches and now we're up to
four inches of water a week so your
water requirements double for every 10
Dee increase in temperature heat and
drought together they're linked together
they quickly increase yield losses in
your soil this information came from Dr
elwin Taylor out of Iowa if we look at
the soil and look what's going on when
we do subsoil tillage where we ex add an
extremely large amount of oxygen into
the soil it acts like a furnace almost
like a wood stove you might say adding
oxygen to the soil actually causes the
soil organic matter to go up into the
atmosphere so we start to lose soil
organic matters and the more aggressive
your tillage the more soil organic
matter losses you're having matter of
fact in the last uh 15 25 years once
tillage starts you'll see that you will
lose uh as much as 50% organic matter in
some places we've seen as much as
6% losses in soil organic matter notice
though that once we started doing
permanent side and adding
we can start to add organic matter back
to that soil but you notice that we
didn't reach the same level you might
want to think about that why didn't we
get back up to where we were and the
answer to that is quite simple it has to
do with the amount of roots and how tall
we let that grass grow we tend on our
permanent sides will cut off uh the top
growth top growth is related to root
growth the more root growth you have the
more healthy that plant is the more
organic matter you're going to add to
your soil matter of fact most of the
organic matter in the soil comes from
the roots as much as 65 to 70% of the
organic matter comes from Roots so the
more Roots we get into the soil the
higher Are soil organic matter levels
let's talk a little bit about compaction
here's the typical tire and you'll
notice as you're putting weight on that
soil the forces are down and then what
actually happens is the soil uh moves to
the side and we'll actually get uh kind
of a lip there around that r you'll see
that the soil is actually forced uh
upward and so what happens then if we
take say a disc and we try to take that
lip off and we try to fill in that hole
you always notice when when this happens
that you never quite fill it in and why
is that because we're losing the void
space when you break up the soil and you
lose all your soil structure you have
less room for air and water and so what
we're doing is we're breaking this soil
down and the mineral portion uh is very
solid very dense and so what we need to
do is now lift it up uh and keep it in
shape we need to have better soil
structure and one of the ways we can do
that is with a root you might see this
root here it's expanding the soil where
that uh man is pointing you'll notice
that when this big oil seed radish these
can get as big as your leg and get
anywhere from three to four feet deep in
the soil although mostly the tuber is at
the soil surface but it does is as it
goes down and it expands it's forcing
the soil down forcing it to the side and
it's physically lifting it and so what
Roots actually do is they actually
compact the soil but they reate uh
reorientate the uh clay particles and
then what they do is they form
Aggregates so we're going to take some
of the polysaccarides and the exodites
that come from these roots and we're
going to form uh nice aggregates which
will um give us some structure back to
our soil so that our soil
doesn't collapse on us and it's not
quite as
dense here's what the bacteria do 90% of
the bacteria are linked to the clay uh
40 to 60% of the soil microbial biomass
is associated with this clay and that's
how we form something called a ma a
microaggregate and what we do is we take
these microaggregates which are less
than 250 microns and we're going to form
macroaggregates now if you want to know
what a macroaggregate looks like when
you go home just take your shovel in
your lawn dig up some soil uh in your
lawn and then Shake uh the the turf a
little bit and you'll see these what I'd
say p siiz small pieces almost the size
of a small piece of gravel little pads
those are the macroaggregates that are
forming so what we're doing is we're
allowing that soil to start to set up so
it has more structure so it has more
room for air and water and and by that
by doing that we can store more uh air
and water in that soil and it's less
dense and one of the key uh uh fungus
that we have in the soil are these
micral fungus they actually infect 80
percent of our plants and they give off
something called gloman or glomulin some
people call it that's what gives us some
of the uh glycoproteins and and some of
the it's a structure that helps to
cement soil together to form these U
macroaggregates and here's what microp
fungus look like you'll notice on the
top we have this brown uh root the um
the fungus are actually either white or
yellow and in a handful of soil we can
have as much as 20 to 25 miles of these
filaments going into the soil what these
fungus do is they bring back water
nitrogen and phosphorus to the plant in
exchange the plant is going to feed that
micro risia some of its carbohydrates as
much as 25 to 40% of the total
carbohydrate reserves in the root go to
feed these fungus if they're available
it's a very beneficial relationship and
then when these fungus die they give off
U the this glomulin that's inside their
cell structure it's kind of sticky it's
kind of like a glue that helps to glue
our soils together so we want to keep
these micro risia healthy they need to
have live plants ear round in order to
do that killage and excess fertilizer
tend to kill off the micro rizio fungus
and here's what happens this shows that
sticky substance being surrounded it
surrounds uh those soil particles and
that's what gives us those nice
macroaggregates that we were talking
about building soil structures like
building a house uh it starts with other
nature we've our Carpenter is our plants
and we're going to start with this sand
silt and Clay the roots are kind of like
how we would frame up a house um some of
the nails and the lag screws uh this
humus is very hard very tough It's been
around for hundreds thousands of years
it's been broken down so it sticks
around but what we're really uh lacking
in the soil is some of that gluman or
some of that active carbon some of the
polysaccharides are missing the nitrogen
offer also act like braces and then that
surface residue that's kind of like the
roof on your house so here's a picture
of a house and see how we start let's
take a look at how we build this out we
start off with the foundation we add the
wood and so look around the room where
you're maybe you're sitting at notice
that there's a lot of space in in a
building like this or in a house the
reason we have that is because the wood
or the soil organic matter in the soil
is giving structure and the nitrogen and
the sulfur are acting like bra
and now we've got room for air and water
to move the black screws i' like to say
is how soil organic matter attaches to
the clay particles and a lot of times
we'll have phosphorus we'll have some
other uh nutrients in between there that
will give uh that'll attach that clay
particle and that organic matter
together the humus again is like nails
and then this glomulin kind of acts like
the glue or house wrap it helps to
insulate this house and then the roof uh
is is uh uh helps to keep on a roof on a
house will help to keep out water what's
interesting in the soil the roof
actually acts to help keep out too much
oxygen imagine what would happen if we
had a tornado come through on your house
and every other year took your roof off
we get too much water in there and that
water would start to rot out uh the the
wood and pretty soon this whole house
would cave in in the soil if we get rid
of the residue we get too much oxygen
into the soil and it burns up the soil
organic matter and the whole house
starts to Compact and starts to Decay
and everything falls in it works the
exact same way uh in the soil too much
oxygen uh oxygen and carbon dioxide are
um uh opposed to each other when one
increases the other decreases so carbon
dioxide is heavier than the oxygen so
they're inversely related so if we get a
heavy rain where we have a
microaggregate you're not going to get
as much water infiltration and a lot of
the water will run off one of the things
that farmers have talked to me about is
saying you know I've been in noil for
five or 10 years and some farmers will
say that my soils are cold and wet other
Farmers who've been in noil will say my
soils are warm and moist so which one is
right actually let's take a look at this
probably when you started into noil did
you get rid of of all the soil
compaction and so that's probably one of
the reasons why our soils are cold
compacted soils hold more moisture so
coming out of the winter we're going to
have water which holds the cold it hold
the cold and the Heat and so your soils
will tend to be wet and they'll also
tend to be cold as you start to get into
no till and you start to break up that
soil and get more macro pores to get the
water to drain from your soils that soil
will start to warm up quicker matter of
fact you've probably seen this in your
own home window panes a lot of times are
triple uh double or triple and they use
air as an insulation so now when you
start going let's say you've been in
notel for one to two years we're
starting to get more residue at the
surface what is the color of residue
when it breaks down it actually turns
black and does black surfaces warm up
the soil or do they cause it to get
colder they tend to draw Heat
and so they'll actually help to warm up
the soil so as we get more residue on
top the soil your soils will start to
warm up and then as you get a thick
layer residue a lot of farmers think
that this is not a good thing but it
actually is what happens is think about
a compost pile if I have one to two
inches of residue on my soil surface
what happens in the middle of that
compost pile there's biological activity
and that will actually warm up the soil
most farmers who are doing doing no till
with cover crops are fighting to keep
residue they have so much microbial
activity and so many earthworms they're
are actually fighting to keep the
residue rather than trying to break it
up if you're having a hard time with
residue if it's causing problems to your
tires we see a lot of that here in Ohio
chances are that you don't have a lot of
microbial activity or a lot of Earth
wors in your soil and you need to make
it get your soil more healthy here's
where we're measuring soil compaction we
can actually do this uh in the field and
we're finding out that right next to
that route uh the soil compaction levels
uh decrease by as much as 30% why do our
soils compact well look at your crop
rotation typically we uh at least here
in Ohio we're drilling most of our
soybeans drilled soybeans are planted
very close together they have a very
poor root system I would rather see
soybeans planted in 15inch rows or
spaced a little wider apart they have a
much healthier root system and they can
help to break up some of this soil
compaction also if you look at corn it
has a very thick root and it tends to be
limited by the plow layer we saw that in
Minnesota last year we visited Minnesota
their plow layer was down there about
eight inches deep that's where they
plowed every year those roots could not
get through them even though they had
beautiful soils they were only reaching
about 125 to 140 bushel corn y that's
some of the prettiest soils I've ever
seen dark rich black but the soil was
compacted so that was limiting their
yields what percentage of the time do we
have live Roots typically in a corn
soybean rotation only maybe four months
out of the year maybe as much as five
months about onethird of the time if we
can add a cover crop to that we can
greatly increase the amount of soil
organic matter that we have in the soil
and one of the things that people have
asked me is why does no tail really have
more live Roots than conventional
pillage the answer is not really it's
not until you add the cover crop that we
start to gain soil organic matter so
what's missing in noil is those live
Roots soil compaction is a biological
problem it's related to a lack of living
Roots uh in the soil so I've got about
15 minutes left let's start looking at
some things that we can do to get rid of
this soil compaction so if we're looking
at subsoiling here's some research that
was done uh in Ohio subsoiling yield
gains or losses if you have conventional
tillage
with subsoiling we found out that the
corn yield gained about one to three
bushel or about 3% about a 3 percentage
increase on soybean yields it was just a
little bit more we gained anywhere from
two to five bushels or about a 10% yield
increase what happened when we had
long-term noil it actually went the
other way by the same amount our corn
yield loss we lost anywhere from one to
three bushel or about 3% so being uh
yield losses were around
10% so what does subsoiling do if we're
comparing subsoiling versus covered
crops uh the subsoiler what does it do
it gives you immediate change in soil
structure is down as deep as what you're
going to subsoil it if you're going down
eight inches deep however those changes
are not permanent and it actually leads
to Greater Reliance on tillage in the
future because we're losing that soil
organic matter it will increase
infiltration in that top 18 Ines because
you're fluffing up the soil it leaves
the soil susceptible to compaction later
the first trip across that field you're
going to compact that soil 80% of that
soil will Rec compact almost immediately
with the first
trip what can cover crops do well the
change is a little bit slower but it's a
little deeper we can go three feet deep
or even deeper with really deep rooted
cover crops and fil uh increases the
infiltration but it may take a little
bit of time generally cover crop Roots
can go through about one foot of soil of
compacted soils per year so if you have
a very heavily compacted soil it may
take a little bit of a Time think about
your grain carts and your uh uh your uh
combines a typical combine's going to
compact that soil 18 inches deep about
26 tons of of uh compaction for axle
load it'll compact it down to8 inches
deep one of the things that cover crops
do is they protect the soil from erosion
they add nutrients in organic matter
they tie up the nutrients they fit into
a continuous noil system they really
make the noil work much better and they
help to protect against soil conection
if you want to think about this just
imagine if you had two bricks and you
put a sponge in between them what
happens is as you add organic matter if
you were to compress the those bricks
them bricks would come back apart the
sponge helps to uh alleviate some of
that compaction it doesn't allow those
bricks to get too close together so if
you're imagine These Bricks bricks are
made out of clay they have a negative
charge if we take these two bricks and
we get rid of the organic matter now
you've put a positive ion in between
there something like calcium or potash
that's going to set that uh those two
bricks up and it's going to set up like
a brick wall that's what happens I like
to call it cement mix that's what
happens when we till the soil
excessively we need that organic matter
in there to con cushion the
soil here's some of the soil resistance
and here's the rankings and we'll start
from the bottom I'm going to go back
subsoiling deep RI full surface tillage
you're adding a lot of oxygen into that
soil it will help you but the problem is
it's a short-term solution we can mboard
plow or chisel plow and then when we
finally uh will create a fine um seed
bed but the problem is again the more
you disturb the soil the more organic
matter you're losing is and so you're
going to be dependent on that system
year after year after year we can
subsoil with white Spanx uh space Shanks
and that will help so we're not doing
quite as much disturbance we can get
into strip till where we only K up just
a
small portion of the field and then we
leave the rest of the field untouched
and that will help we can do shallow
tillage things like the airway and the
Phoenix hero a lot of people call this
vertical tillage the problem with this
is now we've changed our compaction
layer we've seen this time and time
again as we do the shallow tillage your
your compaction layer rather than being
8 to nine inches deep now may be only
two three four inches deep however far
that you go down the bottom of that tool
creates a compacted Zone we can do
intermittent uh intermittent not till
which is tillage every other year
typically in a corn soybean rotation
they might till the soybeans and then go
to Corn because the corn has such a
thick root it really benefits from
having well a rated soils or we can
start to go to continuous noow tail
where we get light residue on the soil
again now we're building up that organic
matter we'll have less compaction we get
more residue that's bever with no cover
crop once we add the cover crop now
we're starting to cushion that soil and
then the best situation is where we have
continuous noow till cover crop and
control traffic now we're limiting uh
that zone that we're compacting to a
very small portion of the field and if
we do that year after year uh now we can
make uh our soils much healthier and
have a lot less compaction how to
establish cover crops uh add diversity
to your soils you can reduce your crop
maturities basically on corn we're
looking at a shorter maturity if you can
reduce that by 5 to seven days that will
really help you we can also grow
soybeans grow an earlier maturing
soybean one of the key points uh is we
need to give that cover crop time to uh
establish before winter sets in most
cover crops need anywhere from 60 to 90
days of growth and so one of the ways we
can do that is we can intercede we can
either fly it on or broadcast it a lot
of our Farmers uh are now um investing
in these Highway applic
they have a 90 foot boom on them and
they're using an air seeder with drop-
down tubes that they'll go in between
the corn and they can seed cover crops
uh into their corn or even into their
soybeans and get them started and then
when they harvest them a lot of times
these cover crops may be two three
inches tall starting to grow that gives
them a head start going into winter when
you let that cover crop grow longer in
the spring and intercede uh our next
crop into it we'd like to do this with
uh soy beans we'll use cereal Rye we'll
let that cereal Rye grow in the fall let
it grow in the
spring uh in Ohio we have a problem with
excess moisture so if we let it grow it
uh through respiration it will allow a
lot of that uh uh through transpiration
it will allow a lot of that water to uh
uh get out of the soil by by putting it
up into the atmosphere so we can
actually get onto our Fields anywhere
from seven to 10 days earlier we let the
cereal Rye grow up plant our soybeans
into it let the soybeans come up then
kill the cereal Rye if we kill the
cereal ride too early it'll lay down and
then if we have some uh wet weather that
soil will stay real sticky and then it
may not dry out till uh late June or
even July so what we like to do is let
it grow up either drill or plant our
soybeans or uh into that cereal Rye it
will not uh hair as much and it won't
tend to bind uh as much and so it's much
easier to do that we can also use
legumes uh things like uh winter peas or
um crimson clover and we'll plant those
with oil seed radish and do that before
corn and that's been very very
successful we've seen as much as six to
eight bushel yield increases on our
soybeans and with our corn uh uh varies
quite a bit depending on how good your
soil structure is but we're seeing uh 10
15 bushel sometimes even more yield
increases by doing this practice here's
some of the best cover crops to fight
soil compaction grasses have a very
fibrous root system I'm a real big fan
of soron sedan grass uh you can let your
sorum sedan grass grow a little bit uh
in Ohio we tend to plant it after wheat
our wheat we have winter wheat so our
wheat will come off in July we plant the
Sorghum sedan grass if you can let that
sorum sedan grass get about 3 feet tall
and either Harvest it in some cases guys
don't have livestock so they'll just mow
it off when you mow sorum sedan grass
you get anywhere from five to nine times
more Roots being grown and so it really
tillers out and it's all about roots in
the soil that really helps to keep your
soil really gives good soil structure to
your soil annual Ry grass is another
really good one it can be a little
harder to manage cereal Ryan oats can
also be used uh very fine Roots they can
find those Plains of weaknesses they can
really help you with soil compaction
they also go uh fairly deep in the soil
anual white grass will go five to six
feet deep uh unless there's H water or
limiting layer seral Rye tends to go
about 30 to 36 inches in uh similar
numbers for oats we can also use Z
brascas things like the oil seed radish
or the turnips oil seed radish
especially the some of the uh uh daon
varieties such as um um tillage radish
or the groundhouse radish they get a
fairly good size root system they're
white they're very sweet the earthworms
absolutely love them and uh they do a
very good job in loosening up soil
matter of fact if you're going to plant
oil seed radish never plant them by
themselves on a hill with greater than a
3% slope we've actually seen some of the
uh soil on these slopes start to move
with if you get a heavy rainfall we like
to um plant them with another grass or
plant them with another legume uh to get
more roots and to have more biomaster
for legumes uh you want a large root
Network hary vet cow peas red clover and
winter peas are some of the ones that
we're using that gives you the
relationship if you've got a problem
with surface compaction buckweed is
excellent and also filia that's a new uh
one that came out of France uh they work
quite well buckweed is very beneficial
for insects and it also helps if you
have low phosphorus uh it has a lot of
organic acids in it so it will release
phosphorus into the soil so if we're
looking at U and I'm I'm getting low on
time so I'm going to go through this
fairly quickly I've got about six more
slides if you look at the New Concept
that we're looking at we're calling it
Eco faring or ecological farming we're
trying to keep uh the soil covered with
live plants year round again if you only
have plants out there four
month side of the year you only have
about a third as much fuel and energy
going into that soil the plants give
energy to the microbes and the microbes
keep those nutrients recycling it also
improves your soil if we can keep those
year round we've got 100% of the fuel
and energy going into that soil here's
what happens under conventional tillage
you have a smaller microbial population
we've got this brown combine Rusty
combine you notice we have a lot of
carbon dioxide going up into the
atmosphere here where we have the
eco-farming we're not disturbing the
soil we have a much larger microbial
population and they're going to keep
more nitrogen and phosphorus recycling
in the soil and here's the relationship
every 1% organic matter can give you as
much as
$850 of nutrients that's going to tie up
per year a th000 pounds of nitrogen and
roughly 100 pounds of phosphorus poach
and sulfur that adds up to about $850
for every 1% soil organic matter how do
we lose these well when we do tillage
you'll see these whirlwinds there that's
the carbon dioxide going on and you'll
notice that we we can't tie up as much
of the uh nitrogen and the phosphorus
because we have less organic matter in
the soil uh anywhere from 50 to 75% of
the phosphorus is tied up organically
and right around 90% of the nitrogen is
tied up in an organic form here where
we're doing the eco-farming we're
carrying those nutrients forward these
plants that are alive in the winter even
though the soil may be cold uh it's much
warmer down below it be around 50
degrees there they can uh below the
frost line they can actually take up
nutrients all winter long and they're
turning that into H soil organic matter
something that will turn into here's
what happens when U we do too much
tillage tillage to the soil microbes is
like the worst hurricane the worst Earth
Quake worst Force fire and the worst
tornado all wrapped up into one event it
really disturbs them they don't like to
have uh this disturbance you'll have a
much healthier microbial population if
you uh uh stop doing the tillage and
where do we lose these nutrients most of
them are lost in the winter they're lost
to the air and the water because we
don't have plant roofs there to absorb
them so a lot of times in late winter
early spring with the snow melt a lot of
the nutrients are lost here where we
have the Eco farming we're keeping those
nutrients tied up and we're carrying
them forward to the next crop finally in
summary I think I might uh might have a
minute or two for uh questions soil
compaction is related to the biology of
the soil and how the soil was managed
organic matter and microbes influence
soil compaction if you have cold no till
soils it's probably a result of soil
compaction and poor soil structure if
you can add cover crops and no tilt to
that system you'll actually uh improve
your your soils and they should be warm
and moist that's an ideal place to plant
corn and soybeans active living roots
and the microbes are acting and working
together to improve your soil structure
that equals this ecological farming that
we're really promoting notel Plus cover
crops so I think I have maybe a minute
to go we may get cut off any questions
I did that pretty quick that's about as
fast as I've done that so uh if we get
cut off that's
fine all right well sorry for some of
the technical problems we had and delays
but uh hope you guys enjoy your
conference can somebody tell me about
how many people we have
there 230 well great I wish I could be
with you
but okay I'll see if I can answer
it
hello how do we get cover crops to grow
all year I is that what you're talking
about okay one of the one of the
benefits as you go a little further
further north is especially serial Rye
it originated in uh the mountains of
China those roots are active all year
round even though they may not be
growing snow actually protects a lot of
our cover crops you may have a much more
beneficial growth to some of these cover
crops what's really detrimental to cover
crops is the wind and so if you can
protect that um that the crown of these
cover crops and keep some residue over
there even though it looks like they're
not doing you may not see a whole lot of
top growth they can do a lot of benefit
from just the roots growing down through
the soil serial Rye is a a really good
one uh after corn uh probably in South
Dakota I mean it grows uh up into Canada
so that's probably one of your best
ones other
questions oh well good
sure we can do
that okay
in a dry spring yes there can be um and
what you want to do is if you have a dry
spring and you see that it's that you're
going to go into a drought you want to
conserve moisture uh what you want to do
is you want to build your organic matter
but you don't want to hurt that next
crop so and it's hard to predict this
but if you see that the soil is is
excessively dry and you're getting a lot
of uh transpiration going on you can
kill that cover crop early you guys
don't have as much problem here in Ohio
we have seven out of 10 years it's wet
and so we're trying to dry out our soils
you probably need to manage your soils a
little differently you might want to
kill that cover crop uh uh early and in
order to conserve moisture and then
plant into it uh when the conditions are
right but uh it should make the soil
much more mellow uh that's at least what
we've seen here Ohio especially when
we're using these oil seed radish we
used to worry about we'd have too big of
a hole there but you'll also find and I
didn't tell you this covered crops will
give you more moisture because you're
going to trap more snow uh we've seen
this time and time again if you put up
it's almost like a a snow fence it it
traps the snow on the soil so it's not
blowing across your fields and you'll
actually gain some uh moisture by having
a a cover crop that's maybe a couple
inches tall it'll trap that snow there
and you'll gain uh basically what you're
losing all the recent uh information
that's come out says that cover crops uh
are really adding uh water to the soil
and even though we're losing some from
transpiration if we see that that's a
problem just kill them
early does that make sense
oh well I I I'll tell you a quick one
until we get cut off here a story from
Nebraska we had some guys this idea of
phow soils that's the stupidest idea we
ever come up that's my personal opinion
I'm just going to tell you that uh in
Nebraska some guys started doing noil
long-term noil with cover crops they
found out that they were they were using
two feet of irrigation per year they
reduced it down to six in
per year by going to Noel and cover
crops the reason being is they were
trapping more snow and they were adding
organic matter to their soil so now they
can store more uh more water remember
that that chart that I give you was the
inches of water per foot of soil so if
you can get these cover crops to go very
deep into the soil and add a couple
percentage points of organic matter to
each foot of soil you can greatly
increase your water storage capacity and
then if you have that residue on the
surface you're not going to have as much
heat you're not going to have as much uh
evaporation going on you're going to
store a lot more water in your soil rain
makes grain but that also uh going along
with that uh ex uh more water holding
capacity in your soil is going to equal
higher
yields uh I wish I could be with you
folks but uh I've got another meeting
here in Ohio yet ton night that I have
to do so uh thank you for inviting me
it's been a
pleasure thank you