[Music]
hey it's Matt from McGee farms and got a
couple Amazon packages in this week and
was going to open them up kind of uh
show them off a little bit and then as
we get them set up kind of show you how
they work
out uh ordered these the other day you
know we've got our new pfal pin that
we're setting up and also we got our
chicken house and I was looking in to
try to get some kind of a solar lighting
set up and uh I'd seen these a buddy of
mine actually got these and I'll put a
link to them uh on the on the notes for
the description for the for this video
but uh they're small solar lights
they've got a little thing to hang a
buddy of mine uses these in his tent
sometimes and he's had real good luck
with them they're cheap so I figure well
why not try them out so opening them up
looking
through like I said the lights look
pretty uh
pretty nice kind of impressed with
them the only thing I'm not overly crazy
about is the solar panel doesn't really
have a way to mount it it looks like uh
I don't know if this is like a sticky
thing where you just kind of peel and
stick I don't know how well you know
that's really going to hold up over time
but again these were super cheap so you
know if if they don't work out I'm not
out that much money but you just have a
small solar
panel hook up with a uh uh looks like a
c connector maybe uh like a phone C
connector and it came as a two pack so I
ended up with with two of
them two of these
and two little remote controls I don't
know how uh how much I'm going to be
using the remote controls I've got some
other solar lights at the house with the
remote control and I don't think I've
ever put batteries in
it but I don't know maybe this might be
nice for uh you know setting them up and
if I want to turn them on or off from
the house it does have a setting on here
though for where it'll be super bright
for 30 minutes not quite so bright for 2
hours all the way out to like an 8 hour
setting and my thinking is uh twofold
one
as far as uh leaving some lights on
it'll maybe help them uh you know if we
have Predator problems I'm working on
the Predator problems right now uh and
hopefully uh by the time they become a
problem next spring they won't be a
problem but also as we get
into where they're not laying as many
eggs because of the uh the less daylight
you know this might be a way if uh we're
wanting more eggs we can do that so I'm
going to get these set up today and I
will uh make a video once we get them in
there and kind of show you how they're
working and then after I'm sure it's
going to take all day to charge them but
if they're working at night we'll go out
and take a look at how they're working
tonight it's Matt with McGee
farms hope you enjoyed this video hope
you enjoy all the videos if you like it
please consider giving us a thumbs up
down there at the bottom leaving some
comments or subscribing to the channel
it's always appreciated and it helps
Channel till next time have a great
day