first of all let's get the matter of
introductions out of the way if you
don't Bob garsten Charlie Thomas here
goes this is Bob Bart
if you see him again this winter you
won't be wearing a hat fan either and
here's John Thomas who's constant
attention to growing and processing seed
corn is your crop insurance for next
year the result of this partnership is
an institution dedicated to the
production of superior seed corn the
largest and most modern plant in
existence more than a hundred thousand
bushels of pioneer hybrid seed were
dried sorted graded and bagged here this
year
the warehouse 300 feet long and with the
capacity of more than 40,000 bushels was
recently built to accommodate the
increasing volume and how and why it's
useful put more money in your pocket but
before we see what has been done with
hybrid corn let's take a look at a field
of open pollinated corn I think you'll
recognize maybe we can refresh your
memory about the faults and the flaws of
open pollinated pause
anywhere in the Corn Belt fields of open
pollinated corn greets the eye this one
isn't a bad feel in fact it's pretty
good but it won't bear close inspection
garstin Thomas have thousands of
visitors every fall to insist upon
seeing the difference between open
pollinated corns and pioneer hi-bred
corn
nor worse than the average field yet
there's a decided lack of stiffness here
which is notably present in the hybrid
fields your to visit later you will
observe a general lack of stiffness and
style looks like the cows had been in
the corn
there's an appearance of sagginess due
mostly to fall in stocks stocks that
break before the ears mature caused
champion dropping ears not sound corn
and not conducive to large yields
the stocks upon which these ears were
produced went down early with resultant
rottenness of the ear limber stocks are
easily blown down that are difficult to
pick either by hand or by machine when
the wind is accompanied by rain the
Fallen stock attempts to come up again
and in so doing forms a gooseneck
another reason for stocks falling is a
poor weak root system a typical fault of
open-pollinated corn later you will
contrast this root with the heavy
pioneer hi-bred root the lack of
uniformity in pint of ears of open
pollinated corn slows down picking
materially for this reason corn picking
contests are practically always held in
high bred fields where the contestants
show to the greatest advantage the
uneven position of ears seen here does
not permit rapid or efficient husky
another fault of open pollinated corn is
the fact that the ears themselves drop
off so easily on windy days a mechanical
corn picker can't pick up these ears a
human corn picker doesn't like to
after the corn picker has been through
the open pollinated field the job of
picking up fallen ears yet remains this
extra task is wholly unnecessary in the
pioneer hi-bred fields which you'll soon
see 10% of the corn was left on the
ground too much to leave but a lot of
work to get and here's what you finally
do get on uniform size shape and quality
for the lack of uniformity and bigger in
the field that we've just looked at is
that you don't know which pollen grain
pollinated each separate pound in other
words you don't know who the daddy was
no one would be so foolish as to try to
improve livestock without selecting the
finest sire the reason you get a
prize-winning bull or a good boar is
because some breeder has selected his
grandparents with the greatest of care
now let's take a look at a field of
pioneer hybrid corn where we do know the
father from the grandfather in fact we
know all of the ancestry for ten
generations back the cloud gets larger
you know what they say about building a
better mousetrap this is daily routine
during harvest time at the Garston
Thomas plant in Coon Rapids where
visitors are welcome seeing is believing
here's an example of what pioneer hybrid
seed corn will do for you
there's an ear on every stock the ears
are at a uniform height and the stops
are standing up stiff straight and
strong and the ears will bear plenty of
inspection to again the uniformity of
height is extremely noticeable product
of two adjacent hills three emphasizes
the uniformity of the ears for size type
and quality they're a noonday meal for
any horse pioneer produces corn of real
quality it's good feed and it markets at
top prices what all of you who've
marveled at hundred bushels per acre
yields you're now seeing one hundred and
ten bushels to the acre what do you
think of this neighborhood of healthy
ears called the Gold Coast by one
visitor 110 bushels to the acre means
eighty eight hundred pounds of ear corn
it takes sturdy stops to hold up this
kind of a crop how beautifully they
stand we can even see angle risers
crosswise through the corn field
take a look down that aisle a pathway to
prosperity
and what's more the ears don't fall off
when the wind blows remember how easily
they fell in the other field smoke that
one in your pipe mister
corne can't stand up without a root
system either go ahead and pull it out
it can be done but it takes plenty of
help these roots go down where the
plants will endorse your arm they oughta
produce corn
they've had plenty of opportunity to
absorb a lot of nourishment from the
soil and they did produce a lot of corn
roots tell a lot of the story of pioneer
hi-bred corn which one of these two
loops do you think has the best chance
to get down where the moisture and plant
food are which one will hold the stock
the straightest a pioneer hi-bred root
is four times as large the mechanical
Quantic are also gets a real chance to
do a good job in hybrid corn sooner or
later all farmers will be using the corn
thicker the heavy root system sturdy
straight stops and strong shanks of
Pioneer hybrids are well adapted to
mechanical foreign thinking
this is corn raising reduced to a
science in a few minutes that wagon will
be back full of corn from four rows
seventy rods long
when picking coin by hand or
mechanically
how convenient it is to find the ear at
a uniform height on every stop there
aren't two inches difference in the
height of ears just to show that these
individual hills aren't unusual for this
pioneer field
let's pick three consecutive hills how
uniform they are in height how nicely
they break out
and what fun to pick these Golden Ears
and man what up prophet three adjacent
hills nine big fine quality ears harder
to hold them to husk over here the corn
pickers already made one round seventy
rods long and here's the tape
hold on there old boy over then we can't
blame you at that they'd never believe
you back home if you didn't have some
corn to back it up and over in the
corner of the field the loaded wagons
are dumped the coin elevated onto
waiting trucks and headed for the
processing plant in one day three men
with a corn picker have picked 2,000
bushels from 19 acres of land and loaded
it onto the truck again we repeat corn
raising reduced to a science and saw the
town it goes and while we string along
behind
let's glance at the field that was
picked with the sturdy straight pollen
rows left standing the corn from these
pollen rows is never used for seed but
is later picked and fair
back at the Platte our cargo potential
seedcorn gets ready to face its Judgment
Day
it looks mighty fine out there in the
fields and it would be excellent in any
grain market or feedlot but it must
undergo many severe and exacting
processes before it becomes pioneer
hybrid seed corn the quality hybrid
truckload after truckload of carefully
bred corn is hauled from farms of nine
counties in the vicinity of the garstin
Thomas plant corn that has been brand
and grown under vigilant supervision of
pioneer experts the crowds of visitors
are always interested in studying the
many reasons for pioneer supremacist
good substantial businessman beans all
interested in learning why pioneer can
afford to extend its famous replanting
agreement to all purchasers to find out
why pioneer can back up performance with
an agreement that makes this hybrid seed
as good as a gilt-edged bomb
ah Niagara of golden well pours over the
top and down the conveyor belt into the
large bins beneath cream-of-the-crop
disscourn but still only embryo seed
until it has been processed thoroughly
to fulfill the rigid requirements
pioneers are max only 60% of these tears
are good enough to become pioneer hybrid
seed pod
the rest will be fed on Bob Darcy and
Charlie Thomas's farms in the sorting
plant another chef leaves another comes
on duty and the ear corn faces its first
acid test three shifts a day 230 men to
a ship just a cross-section of a large
number of men whose skill and hard work
makes possible a hybrid like pioneer
approximately 8,000 bushels are handled
in the sorting back each day only one
variety is inspected at one time to
insure against any mistake in
classifying each ear is individually
examined every damage channel is removed
all off-site beers are discarded and
only the choice corn is dropped in the
Box foresee inferior or light ears are
rejected no farmer ever started his own
seed with greater care
from the hundreds of skilled workmen
farm minded young men from Nebraska
Missouri Iowa and Kansas emerged the
checkers those links hide inspectors who
reexamine every ear and every kernel to
make sure there has been no oversight
the words are famous and handy check and
double-check this careful sorting and
restarting is another reason why pioneer
corn grows uniformly and vigorously
uniformity is elemental in quality
hybrid corn it took many seasons of
breeding to get ears like these they
still have a long hard path to go but so
far they have proved beyond doubt to
have quality and breeding the choice
corn that survives this series of
inspections is conveyed directly from
the sordid piles by way of a conveyor
belt system which transports it to the
root of the large frying bins and fence
into the cribs below
portable dryers along the side of the
cribs force hot air through the corn six
oil burning front Swift fans driven by
60 horsepower motors maintain a constant
temperature of 110 degrees just like a
hot wind off the Kansas wheat fields the
constant hot air pressure reduces the
moisture content to 12% and assures
splendid germination later guarding the
seed against possible danger from cold
weather
the corn now sorted checked and dried
and already over some top hurdles
proceeds on its way up the ladder of
success to the corn Shelley at full
capacity these chalets can shell 1,000
bushels an hour
on the top floor of the grading plan the
sorted dried and shelled corn starts its
homestretch trip through the main plant
the postgraduate course and processing
that adds finishing touches to a truly
great scene for several sets of sodding
drums separate the large kernels from
the small kernels and the pea we in fact
circles are removed
breeders on the floor below divide the
large round from the large flat and the
small round from the small flat making
for kernel sizes accurate grading
permits accurate planting which means
uniform stands
this mercury treated superior seed corn
has finished the long race and is now
worthy of the name pioneer finally
receiving the award of merit the
familiar trademark of Pioneer hybrid
seed corn every sack has been stamped to
show the kernel size and variety the
particular variety being sac today
happens to be another pioneer champion a
banner Trophy winner in the Iowa State
yield tests a masterpiece in scientific
seed selection sealed by sowing the bag
contains genuine pioneer hybrid seed
corn the real McCoy a perfect seed that
has successfully withstood the many
tests and processes this seal is for the
customer's protection when Pioneer corn
is sealed in the bag
your next year's banner crop is as good
as in the bag - it's bred and selected
to produce prize years seven different
varieties each adapted to a particular
area each one students of varying
climatic conditions are stored in the
three large Garston Thomas warehouses
until delivery
can there be any wonder with generations
of breeding and the painstaking
processing that each kernel of Pioneer
corn receives by the famous pioneer
replanting agreement can be offered with
the purchase of each bushel of corn this
replanting agreement ensures that if for
any reason including worm damage and
floods you have to replant pioneer
hybrid corn the seed for replanting is
free pioneer first oldest and largest
producer of commercial hybrids can give
you this assurance only because it's
time-tested results every
all the guesswork from corn growing when
you buy pioneer you'll get more for your
money it costs a dollar an acre more to
plant pioneer hybrid seed and normally
it increases the yield around 14 bushels
or seven dollars in other words it Nets
you six dollars an acre more profits and
now I want to thank you for your
interest many of you have seen our
processing plant and visited our seed
fields and can vouch for everything
you've seen here today and more - for
the rest we've tried to bring them out
into mow hammer to show you how pioneer
hybrid corn is produced and what it will
do for you next year we trust you to
join those thousands who know that
pioneer the quality hybrid is the surest
way to happy harvest