Whether you contact your local Extension
Office for a problem in your yard or
garden or you're working with a new
landscaper on a landscape project, one
of the first recommendations is going to
be to have a soil test done.
Once you've taken the samples they'll
send back description of what they find
in those soil tests. Those soil tests will
give you your basic pH, the electrical
conductivity, whether you have lime in
your soils, soil texture, and give you
some basic information about nutrients
and organic matter.
One of the things that your soil test
will tell you is that you have high
salts or electrical conductivity in your
soil, and in Wyoming most of our pH tends
to be high in the alkaline range.
The organic matter is something that you
do have a lot of control in and if your
organic matter is low we would recommend
that you use compost manure, anything
that was plant material to amend your
soil. And then it will give you
information on the nutrient levels in
your soil. Nitrate is really important
for plant growth
Phosphorus is important for root growth.
Potassium is going to be really
important for the overall health of the
plants in your garden.
If you need help in determining what
those soil sample results mean you can
have a copy sent to your local Extension
office for details on your soil sample.
I'm Donna Hoffman from the University of
Wyoming Extension and this is
From the Ground Up