all right time for another little video
showing you some of my uh issues with
the 750 grain drill
normally when i put the the main seating
rate on um i can
have no problems but when it comes to
cover crops where there's a small amount
of seeds per acre going down in terms of
weight
i have to really adjust these
seed cups
which are
this width here on the row which will go
in and out
depending on how i move this lever
and when it gets too narrow the seeds
start to pile up and they don't flow
um easily so gear what deer does they
sell a kit
half speed gears
which is consists of two gears
and crucially for for my purposes
the part number changes by serial number
and
i bought
this set which one of the two gears is
fine
for my serial number but apparently i
needed
this gear 300.
um which you can see there's a hole
there i don't know if it's going to show
up but a roll pin goes through that
where it slips on the shaft
this gear is in place of that spur gear
um
and then we're going to go over here and
i'll show you
the issue that gear the larger gear goes
on top on the left
and then the smaller gear that i just
showed you goes on in place of this one
down here
and
the issue becomes trying to get that
gear on and off there's a roll pin that
goes through it and you've got to be
able to knock it
sideways
to get at that shaft because the
shaft comes through
right here on the end
and the roll pin goes through that shaft
so the roll pin is perpendicular to the
shaft
the issue is
how do i get a punch in there to deal
with that and then the other issue
was
i don't know if you can see but i
modified this cover
it's a little tab i welded there
normally this sits
right down in here
but
in order to get that gear out
this one you have to pull it straight
out it won't come out because the space
between the shaft and the side was so
small you can't get the gear out without
cutting this
so this is all by way of saying this was
the difficulty i faced when trying to
switch
right before i planted and drilled the
cover crop
had no problems with the wheat with the
normal size gearing but when i wanted to
try to use
the smaller gears not only did i have
the wrong part but to put that part on
and off
just be i want to say a nightmare but
trying to get in there and then you have
to get new roll pins every time and
you're pounding on it
and there's got to be a better way so
that's what i'm trying to come up with
some kind of little press
to press that roll pin out
um
in order to go to the the smaller gear
the different gear when i have to really
dial the uh the rate down and
essentially what this these half speed
gears do
instead of having let's say
a half inch slit or a quarter inch slit
in this seed cup
you could you could double that size
that width of that seed cup because the
gears are only turning at half the speed
it lets you flow flow a little bit
better and you get more sensitive
because i was down here
on this scale at like
seven or eight
when it goes up to 60 and
it's not very sensitive there's a lot of
slop in it and and it's just very very
um it was a challenge so i'm hoping this
video kind of makes sense
um but it's something i want to work on
in addition there's
various wear parts on this drill that
are going to need replacing the gauge
wheels
the
openers the seat openers
there's various parts with the seed
boots that need to be replaced as well
and and that'll all happen
at this point next spring before we use
it to drill
uh the peas
so uh thanks for watching
um try not to get too jerky here but uh
it's a it's a it's a really good drill
it's worked well for me but it just it
just needs some attention to work even
better
thanks for watching and we will see on
the next one bye