[Music]
[Applause]
hello I'm Jimmy Whit I'm the president
of the Alabama fruit and vegetable
growers association I'd like to take
this opportunity to thank all of our
conference exhibitors and sponsors from
our
2014 uh conference we had a six
educational sessions and over 300
different uh attendees at our conference
[Music]
I'm Doug Chapman I'm a regional
Extension agent with the Alabama
Cooperative Extension system uh work on
the commercial horiculture team and I'd
like to tell you a little bit about the
workshops that will be held at the
Alabama fruit and vegetable Growers
annual conference and trade show in
February we'll have a fruit tree
grafting Workshop we'll have a vegetable
grafting Workshop we'll have a high
tunnel Workshop a marketing workshop and
a beekeeping workshop and these are all
hand Zone workshops uh it's where you uh
actually get to do something that you're
interested in and we look forward to
having you in Auburn and uh we'll try to
make you as welcome as we
[Music]
can I'm a regional Extension agent with
uh corporative extension work in
commercial Horticulture I'd like to
invite you to the 2015 Alabama fruit and
vegetable Growers Association conference
in Auburn this year and would love for
you to come lots of educational sessions
uh lots of speakers uh some from out
throughout the southeast cover a wide
range of topics and it's just part of
what you would get from uh coming to
this conference uh another thing that
you'll benefit from is interacting with
other Growers uh and a trade show and
also we'll have some some workshops so
if you're growing uh if you're a
producer now or if you're thinking about
uh being a producer I think this would
be uh very beneficial to
[Music]
you I'd like to invite all of our
sponsors anyone who wants to become a
sponsor or sponsor an event at the uh at
the meeting uh invitees you to uh become
an exhibitor if you have products or or
services that you would like to offer
someone in uh in this field uh I also
like to invite you to become a member
and you can find a lot of this
information on our website at AFV ga.
aces.edu um we'll also have a uh a form
there where you can enroll or or
register online for the conference this
next year or you can do it uh by paper
also uh you can Al also visit us on
Facebook uh from more information
[Music]