intro hey there fellow farmers and
agricultural
enthusiasts Welcome to our video on
maintaining your combine
harvester have you ever wondered how to
keep your combine running smoothly all
season long well you're in the right
place today we're going to walk you
through a step-by-step guide on combine
maintenance proper upkeep is crucial for
Optimal Performance and longevity of
your
machine so let's dive in and learn how
to keep your combine in top sh shape
main content first up let's talk about
the importance of combine
maintenance regular upkeep can
significantly extend the life of your
machine it helps prevent unexpected
breakdowns during crucial Harvest times
proper maintenance also ensures better
fuel efficiency and crop
quality now let's move on to our pre-
Harvest
checklist before the harvest season
begins inspect your combine thoroughly
check the engine oil and coolant levels
examine belts and chains for proper
tension and wear inspect the cutting
platform including knives and
guards don't forget to look at the
threshing mechanism and cleaning shoe
clean out any debris from the previous
season test all lights and safety
equipment moving on to daily maintenance
tasks during harvest season start each
day by greasing all fittings as per the
manufacturer's
recommendations check fluid levels
including engine oil hydraulic oil and
coolant inspect belts and chains for
proper tension clean the radiator and
other cooling
components empty the rock trap if your
combine has one check tire pressure and
adjust if
necessary clean the grain tank and
unloading augur at the end of each day
take time for some additional care clean
off any crop residue from the machine
check for any loose or missing
bolts inspect the header for damage or
wear look for any oil leaks and address
them
promptly now let's discuss post Harvest
care once the Harvest is complete give
your combine a thorough cleaning remove
all crop residue to prevent rust and
rodent damage change all fluids and
filters as recommended by the
manufacturer lubricate all necessary
points touch up any paint chips to
prevent rust store the combine in a dry
covered area if possible if storing
outside use a quality tarp to protect it
from the
elements let's move on to
troubleshooting common issues if you're
experiencing uneven cutting check the
sickle sections and guards for
inconsistent threshing adjust the
concave clearance and rotor speed if you
notice grain loss inspect the sves and
adjust the fan speed for engine problems
check fuel filters and lines for
contamination if you're having hydraulic
issues look for leaks and check fluid
levels remember always consult your
operator's manual for Specific
Instructions if you're unsure about any
maintenance task don't hesitate to
contact a professional outro and there
you have it folks a comprehensive guide
to maintaining your combine
harvester by following these steps
you'll keep your machine running
smoothly all season long
do you have any combine maintenance tips
to share leave them in the comments
below don't forget to like this video
And subscribe to our channel for more
farming tips thanks for watching and
happy harvesting