Now, I just want to show you my
strawberry patch because if you guys
have followed me or if you've actually
come to me because you saw my strawberry
planting video, then you'll know that we
planted these strawberries uh about 3
months ago and they are doing
wonderfully. So, as you can see, these
strawberries are doing quite well. You
can see all these beautiful, beautiful
strawberries right there. You can see
all these wonderful runners here and
even the unripe strawberries right
there. And these guys are loving life.
These guys are producing well. They are
happy and they are busting at the seams
here with all the produce.
Now, if your strawberries are not
looking like mine here, there's a couple
of things that you can do that are going
to perk them up that's going to make
them produce better and going to make
them grow the most luxurious
strawberries you've ever had, the
sweetest strawberries you ever had. Now,
the first thing we're going to do to
help our strawberries out is we are
going to fertilize. Now, right over here
is the video on where I planted these
strawberries, the fertilizer I used and
why we did that. Because strawberries
are a very finicky kind of plant. They
really like to have a lower pH soil and
they will suffer if they don't. So,
we're going to add that fertilizer in
there that's got those components that
lower that pH, and that's going to help
them grow big, nice, firm, juicy
strawberries and is going to help your
plants look like
these. The other thing is is
strawberries like to have a very, very
loose, lomy soil, and they don't like
wet feet. Just like a tomato, they want
that soil to drain away fast, but they
still want to have moist soil, not wet
soil.
So, in order to take care of that, I
have added straw.
Now, the straw is going to help keep the
moisture into the soil, but it's also
going to allow that soil to drain and
kind of maintain that that kind of happy
medium, which is going to help these
plants grow and do well. Now, the first
problem we run into is especially with
straw is most of the straw you're going
to buy is going to have seed in it. I've
kind of found a way that we can keep the
straw but actually separate out the
seed. And what I found is is if you take
a five gallallon bucket or actually I
used a large like almost like a big wash
tub, you take that straw and actually
for for this because I knew I had a
bunch of plants that I needed to fit
that that straw in around. I didn't want
these super long pieces of straw. I
actually cut it up and then washed it in
that bucket. Got about a half a bucket
of water, put that straw into it that I
chopped up and moved it around to
release those seeds and make them fall
to the bottom. Then I pulled, you know,
I took handfuls out as I was washing it
and then placed it in my beds around my
strawberries. And I'm going to tell you
that it worked wonderful. But I will
tell you when you pour that water out,
pay attention where you pour it out at
because there's going to be a lot of
seeds in the bottom of it. The other
thing that helps is as you're washing
this straw, that straw is picking up
water and it's going to retain that
water. So when you put it down now,
you've got a moist layer of straw on top
of your of your bed and it is going to
start leeching moisture down into the
bed, but it's not going to get it to
where it's actually wet and it's going
to be harmful to these plants. Now,
dealing with straw and covering our beds
or even if you're using
mulch, we run into a a sort of an issue
with the fact of we have
runners. Now, with runners, runners are
a wonderful thing. These are where our
strawberry plants actually send out long
leads. And wherever that long lead will
touch the ground, it will actually set
down roots and create a whole another
strawberry plant, which is wonderful for
you guys who have a whole bed and you
have room in between those strawberries
and so forth. But for guys like me and
I've got this I mean really I've got it
over full of these strawberries that
whenever you have these leaders going
out. You don't necessarily want them
here. So a technique that I've come up
with and something that I think is going
to help a lot of you if you don't have
room in your beds or if you've got straw
which is going to keep those runners
from contacting the ground. Here's
something you can do in order to save
your runners and be able to move them
somewhere else or it will allow you to
transplant those into your bed, but
maybe not where the plant wants to put
them down. So, what we're going to do
is we are actually going to take a
little 4x4
pot of soil and we're going to set this
in our bed.
And what that's going to allow us to do
is
take these runners like this. We can
bring them over to where that that
runner is and see right here where it
makes this little bend. That's where
it's going to send out a root. And all
we've got to do is give that thing a
little
shove and cover it with a little bit of
soil. We have to move it over here
because unfortunately this leader is
going to go where it wants to
go and you're going to bury it.
That is all you're going to
do. Now, as you can see, I've already
got some here that are down in there and
are trying to make roots. Now, as you
can see, this one is actually continuing
on. Well, I don't want this to continue
on. I want it to stop. So, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to pinch that
off, and I'm going to stop that runner
from continuing on. And this is going to
be the end of it. And so whenever this
actually takes root, you'll start to see
this start to die
back. Once this dies back, we can clip
this
off. We can take that plant out and we
can put that wherever we want.
Strawberries are what I like to call a
family and friends plant. And that means
that number one, if you plant them and
you give them the nutrition and they are
happy plants, they're going to do two
things. They're going to give you enough
strawberries that you're going to be
able to share with your family and
friends. And number two, they're going
to send out enough runners to where
you're going to have enough extra plants
to give to family and
friends. And you might even have enough
that if you want to, you can sort of. So
these plant are going to give back what
you put into them. If you give them love
and care and all the nutrition they
want, they will reward you with fruit
and with new
plants. Now, keep in mind, these new
plants that are being
made are the replacements for the other
plants that are going to stop producing
and slow down and are going to die
eventually because strawberries have a
very limited lifespan. And you need
those new plants in order to replace the
older plants. going to stop producing.
So, we need to keep that in mind
whenever we're, you know, maybe we're uh
getting our pots and we're getting these
other runners that we're we're making
into plants and we're giving those
away. You might want to hold back a
couple for yourself so that in a in a
few years or in maybe the next year if
you've had them in the ground quite a
while that you can start replacing those
plants that are not making fruit
anymore. Now, another care tip that I
can give you guys is strawberry plants
are going to have leaves that die off.
Here's a perfect example. That leaf down
there had died off. Here's another one
that has died
off. And the reason that that's going to
happen is because you are going to have
these plants are going to get huge.
They're going to go get a lot of green
on top of them and some of the
under some of the the leaves that are
under the
plant are going to
die. Now, typically
this is going to provide a natural mulch
for your
strawberries. But if you have mulch or
straw or hay underneath these
strawberries, you don't necessarily need
that natural mulch. You can leave them
there. It's not going to hurt
anything. But if you, you know, you
don't want to look at it, it's not going
to hurt to pull those off.
and get rid of
them. You just kind of give them a nice
little tug and they come off. Now, I
will say that some people told me that I
should never plant this many
strawberries in one
bed. And you know, that may be right for
some people, but I live down here in
Texas to where it's extremely hot most
of the time. And if you plant your
strawberries this way, you have to be
kind of mindful of where you live at
because of if these are in an area to
where it is you have a lot of moisture
in in the air that is not going to dry
off quickly, you can deal with wilt and
mold and mildew and those kinds of
things on your strawberry plants. You'll
get gray mold on your strawberries,
things like that.
But down here in Texas to where we're in
I mean we're already in the 80s in April
and these the moisture on these plants
is going to dry very very quickly. It's
not going to stick around. There's not
going to be enough of a a chance for any
kind of mold or wilt to set in. So me
planting them this close together means
that I maximize my space to get more
strawberries out of a smaller space. And
frankly, I had the plants, so I didn't
want to, you know, I wanted to plant as
many as I could in order to have the
most production that I could get.
There's plenty of nutrition in the bed
to carry these things over. I put the
straw down to help retain the moisture.
And as you can see, these plants are not
suffering by any means. Now, if you look
at the planting instructions whenever
you get them, they're going to tell you
to plant them about a foot apart. And
the rows need to be about a foot and a
half apart that you need to heal them
and all these other things. And yes,
that is a perfectly good description of
how commercial farmers and commercial
growers grow these plants because they
need to have room in between these rows
to get people down through
there in order to pick them. And also,
they won't want them so close together
that they have to hunt and find for
strawberries. They want them to be right
out in the open. Now, this the way these
are planted is kind of like a treasure
hunt. Every day I come out here, I sift
through and I push all the plants out of
the way and look at everything because
I'm hunting for strawberries. Now, a lot
of times I've kind of scoped them out. I
know where they're at. But I can do that
because I'm a small home gardener. I'm
dealing with, you know, 40, 50 plants
here at most. And I can just go through
and pick them out. No big deal. I'm not
worried about time production and I'm
not I'm not looking at efficiency
whenever it comes to picking
strawberries. So, if you have a
different idea or a different reason why
you think that these plants are supposed
to be spaced that far apart, put it down
in the comments. Let me know. School me,
educate me. I may be a gardener who's
been doing it for years, but I don't
know absolutely everything. And I am
always willing to listen to and have
someone tell me something that they I
might not know already. So, hope you
found these tips and this information
very, very helpful to help you you grow
bigger and better strawberries. And if
it was, I'd ask you to go down below and
subscribe to me and, you know, hit that
bell notification, hit that icon to, you
know, that way you can find out whenever
I put out new videos and you can be the
first to watch them. So, guys, as
always, I thank you for joining me
today. I ask you to pray over your
family, pray over your garden, and have
a great