[Music]
foreign
program is based on agreements for
sustainable agricultural practices so on
one side the farm commits to series of
management practices that benefit nature
and on the other side of the agreement
government in recognition of this
commitment that benefits society as a
whole will help the farmers in various
ways one of our lines of action is
providing training and consulting
services on sustainable Farm practices
and farm management
we know that education is a motive for
change but we also know that farmers and
land workers are extremely busy so we
try and choose topics of special
interests such as those that are around
increasing agricultural productivity and
reducing production costs
aware of the implications of working in
agriculture and livestock we organize
training sessions during one or two days
where farmers can pick and choose the
workshops of Interest so they don't have
to attend all of the sessions
we tried to organize training when there
is lease workload in the agricultural
sector and we always prioritize an
informal space and time where producers
Educators and other stakeholders can
chat with each other and exchange
valuable experiences
one of the activities that we organize
is the Agriculture and environment
seminar you could say that we have been
organizing it historically because we
have already organized 15 editions it is
an annual event where we share inspiring
stories from within the agricultural
sector the key point is that the
speakers share their direct life
experience so they share their success
but also the mistakes they have made and
the lessons that they have learned from
it
we also organized technical workshops
that include theory and practice in the
same day
they cover various topics such as
natural pest control soil fertility
directed grazing or wind manures
during these workshops we go into the
detail on how to implement the practices
shown on the farms
finally a point we believe is key when
it comes to moving from Theory to
practice is accompanying the farmer in
their first steps when implementing
these new practices
this is why we have invested in personal
post Workshop consultations on farms
basically from the participants those
firms who decide to implement the learn
practice can opt into an accompanying
consultation that can help them put it
into action and resolve any questions
when they pop up during this process
this would conclude the short summary of
activities we do in training and
Consulting work in custadia this is just
one of the routes we take as we also
take action by providing services and
materials Product Promotion and also
working with the general public through
volunteering and Environmental Education
and other activities that we will
explain in the following videos
foreign
[Music]