there are a few facilities around that
have utilized it
but it's fairly new for beef bracken
county extension agent for agriculture
and natural resources david appleman
used to be a full-time dairy farmer but
he left the dairy business
25 years ago and applies his farming
knowledge
as an extension agent today kind of
kind of my favorite here but when his
adult children
wanted to get into a beef cow calf
operation
breeding for genetics and quality that
presented a problem
we did not have any facilities at all we
were just open pasture
and so we knew being employed off the
farm we had limited time
and so we wanted a facility
that allowed for easy management
and then we wanted to optimize animal
performance
and animal comfort as well
appleman visited the university of
kentucky's dairy farm
where there was a compost bedded pack
barn for cow comfort
which the dairy cows seemed to enjoy
appleman got the idea the concept could
work for beef cows
when it comes to animal rest that's
something we've forgotten about we don't
focus on
and we really have to keep in mind that
if animals are in muddy conditions
they're going to be standing for
many more hours than normal and you take
six eight hours of additional standing
just because it's muddy
i think that's where the real stress is
coming on all these beef animals
30 to 35 cows in their fall calves
spend the winter months in this compost
bedded pack bark
they stay out of the mud are fed hay and
grain in this feeding area
where appleman said they can control the
amount of hay loss
the resting or loafing area is this
bedding of sawdust
where cows can lay free of mud and gets
raked twice a day to keep the area fresh
appleman said it is a safe way to manage
his herd
while making visual contact every day
we think about our farm population and
we do
see our producers getting older and
still working off the farm so they're
coming home at night
it's dark it's muddy they're taking the
tractor out in the field going through
gates
and you know among animals that are
pushing and shoving to get to the feed
and while the cows spend the winter
months
indoors it gives appleman's pastures
a chance to recover and be ready for
another grazing season
when the cows and calves return to the
pasture
in the spring from the university of
kentucky
college of agriculture food and
environment i'm jeff franklin