[Music]
[Applause]
what if I told you I built this entire
farm with the help of tens of thousands
of dollars in federal grants money you
don't have to pay back I also secured
tens of thousands of dollars in interest
free loans with up to 21 months to pay
back with no interest about 5 years ago
I turned my Suburban backyard into a
thriving profitable vegetable farm and
in today's video I'm going to show you
exactly how I funded it and how you can
too hey what's up everybody welcome back
to the Garden if you're new to the
channel I'm Chef Mikey I'm a former
executive chef turned Urban Farmer and
this is my backyard that's my house
right up there when we bought this
property we had no plans to start a
commercial vegetable operation we just
wanted a small piece of land to grow our
own food I was working a full-time job
and gardening on the weekends but I
quickly realized I was spending about
$300 a week on my gardening hobby to
offset costs I started selling some of
my extra produce at work that's when I
decided to form an LLC so I could write
off my expenses at first I funded
everything out of pocket with money from
my job I'd sell extra veggies to
co-workers and reinvest every dollar I
made back into the garden I even went as
far as making posts on Facebook for
produce for sale stating that all money
will go towards my Greenhouse funds this
made it more fun for my friends to
purchase from me because they knew what
the money was going towards and they
could watch it all evolve as I posted
updates and they could see the green
houses being built on social media I
built my first three green hous
using 0% interest credit cards with 12
to 21 months to pay them off these cards
even gave statement credits like $900 if
you spend $3,000 in the first 90 days
which essentially gave me a $900
discount on my green houses it's
important to note that these are
business credit cards that have high
limits and large statement credits and
they're not typically available to
individuals understand you must first
form a business to qualify for these
types of credit cards and for these
large purchases to be tax deductible for
me I have a single member LLC I also
have an agricultural tax exemption so I
do not pay sales tax on these large
purchases I would highly recommend
forming an actual business and getting a
tax exemption before you start making
infrastructure purchases otherwise
you're just giving away free money to
the government for no good reason it
should also be noted that I had the cash
on hand to pay for these purchases with
a solid plan on how is going to pay back
the debt before I acred any interest
typically one shoulder season crop can
pay the entire balance of one of these
high tunnels that I bought but if
anything were to go wrong you need to
have a way to get yourself out of debt
by no means am I recommending that
anyone buy a high tunnel on a credit
card if you don't already have the cash
on hand I simply leveraged my
outstanding credit score to get the $900
statement credit and 21 months of
Interest free payments so I could keep
my cash on hand for working capital but
if I got myself in a jam with the
payments I had the cash to pay it off
but when I quit my job and relied solely
on the farm to pay my bills it became
too risky to put up my own money I had
savings but I didn't want to drain them
I remembered a YouTube video I'd seen
about nrcs high tunnel grants I tried to
Google information about how to get a
high tunnel from the nrcs and it's not
as easy to find the information I was
looking for deep down at felt like a
high tunnel Grant was probably not
something a guy like me would qualify
for since I was just farming on a
quarter acre in my Suburban backyard I
didn't think they'd take me seriously
but after I did some digging on the
internet I found an email address and I
sent an email to ask how I would go
about applying for a high tunnel Grant
the next day a lady from the USDA and
the nrcs came out and talked to me at my
farm she was super impressed with what I
had accomplished on my own she also
helped me apply for for an irrigation
Grant low tunnel Grant and a grant to
install water lines from the main line
directly into the garden for more
efficient irrigation hookups but it's
not as simple as just filling out an
online form and getting a check USDA has
lots of paperwork and the processes can
take time after the lady left that day
it took about a year before I ever heard
from her again I just kind of rote it
off and I ended up purchasing my next
high tunnel out of
pocket but then out of the blue I got a
phone call from the USDA to tell me I've
been approved for a high tunnel with
irrigation low tunnel and to have the
water line installed it was a total of
around $112,000 on that first round of
funding my patients paid off once I was
approved I ordered my fourth farmer
friend caterpillar tunnel and got it
installed right away I also created an
efficient low tunnel system using 10-ft
pieces of electrical conduit that I bent
into Hoops using a 4ft hoop Bender that
I bought from Johnny selected seeds I
bought a pool cover roller and a thft
roll of agrion 50 I designed an
efficient low tunnel system so I can
efficiently protect my garden from Frost
with only minutes of work rather than
hours like it took me before the low
tunnel Grant was like 1,500 bucks for
300 Square ft which was a ton of money
to cover 300 ft of garden space so I
spent all the money on enough materials
to cover my entire Garden so when they
came to to look at it they asked why did
you do more than 300 Square ft I told
them you gave me way too much money for
300 Square ft so I just went ahead and
spent it all so I could cover my whole
garden they said okay well I'll get you
more money since you covered more than
the planned amount but I don't think I
can get you more than 2500 bucks I said
I'll take it and they sent me a deposit
for even more money than we planned also
my Garden's on an 8% slope but the nrcs
standards state that they will not pay
for a high tunnel on more than a 5%
grade they told me I would need to get
it graded before I built my high tunnel
I looked at them and I said absolutely
not no one's driving any type of heavy
machinery in my garden that would be a
complete deal breaker and i' just pay
for it out of pocket if that's the case
I explained to them that I spent years
building up my soil using no till
practices and always keeping the soil
covered with compost and wood chip
mulches having any type of heavy
machinery back here do far more damage
than it would improvements I showed them
how I constructed my previous three High
tunnels by digging trenches in between
them so water flows away from the garden
and I lined The Trenches with wood chip
mulch to eliminate any potential for
erosion due to runoff from the high
tunnels and after a little back and
forth they finally agreed with me that
it would do far more damage than it
would good to have the land graded and
they allowed an exception for me to
build the high tunnel on an 8% grade I
just share this with you so you can
understand that it's okay to challenge
their standards as long as you can give
them reasons which make practical sense
as to why their protocol might not make
sense for your context what I've learned
is everything is a caseby casee
situation and exceptions can be made but
it's important to know that grants like
this aren't a free handout they're
funding programs you'll need to purchase
the equipment build the infrastructure
yourself and once you've completed the
project the nrcs will reimburse you a
set amount per square foot for example
when I was approved for a high tunnel
Grant they didn't just hand me a
greenhouse I had to pay for it up front
and build it myself but they reimbursed
me for the entire cost after I finished
building it they typically pay by the
square foot for example it doesn't
matter if you spend $1,000 on your high
tunnel or $100,000 on your high tunnel
they will just pay you around $3 to5 per
square foot so it might not always cover
the entire cost but it'll at least cover
some of the cost depending on what size
and additional features you might have
like automated rollup sides or heaters I
went the lowtech route and bought
Farmers friend caterpillar tunnels it
not only covered the entire cost but
even a little extra I think I made like
a hundred bucks for building mine after
it was all said and
done they also paid for the irrigation
in the high tunnel they don't ever seem
to care about how much money I spend or
don't spend they just pay out the same
same amount either way it's either by
the linear foot for water infrastructure
or by the square foot for everything
else one thing to keep in mind is the
usca doesn't make the process as easy as
possible because they want to make sure
that you're serious about fulfilling
your commitment otherwise there would be
lots of people applying to get free high
tunnel grants they're not actually
capable of falling through with the
obligation once you've completed the
project and met their standards the
reimbursement comes through and it's a
huge boost for your farm bottom line and
gives you the resources to expand more
quickly than if you were funding
everything on your own by using grants
for my high tunnels low tunnels and drip
irrigation I was able to create a more
efficient profitable operation and once
I had these systems in place I could use
the extra Capital to reinvest in my
business hire help and expand even
further applying for the grants isn't
easy there's no online application the
paperwork's extensive and the funding is
competitive each county has a limited
pool of funds however being an Urban
Farmer in Knoxville Tennessee gave me an
edge unlike agriculturally dense areas
there aren't many farms in the city
fewer applications means there's less
competition so if you're an Urban Farmer
like me you might find it easier to
receive this type of funding than
someone in a more competitive area
completing the projects immediately and
meeting their standards not only ensured
I got reimbursed quickly but also made
made me a standout example of how these
grants can work the nrcs was so
impressed that they've invited me to
join their subcommittee to the board of
directors for their Urban agriculture
initiative to help other Farmers achieve
similar success a pretty cool
achievement for someone who's never
worked on a farm in my life but I didn't
stop there I started asking more
questions there's codes on the bottoms
of these papers what are those how do I
get more do you have any other grants
well it turns out they do and I
qualified this year I received another
high tunnel Grant grants for mulching
and cover cropping where they pay me
$6,000 a year for the next 5 years to
implement cover crops and mulching
that's
$35,000 just for doing what I already do
and another several thousand to turn my
sidey yard into a pollinator habitat
we'll be building the next high tunnel
this month and we've already tarped the
area for the pollinator habitat which
will be planted next spr spring I'll be
sure to share all the projects with you
as we get them completed receiving these
grants at my homebased property allowed
me to reinvest and expand when I gained
access to lease land on a friend's
property I had the capital to develop
without any Financial strain I've now
applied for the same grants on the
leased property and given my track
record and connections within the USDA
and the nrcs I'm optimistic about
getting approved these grants will help
take my farming operation to the next
level so you might be wondering how can
you get these grants for your farmer
Garden well the first things first
there's no easy online form the process
can be a bit intimidating because
there's lots of paperwork involved but
don't let that scare you off the first
step is walk right into the local USDA
or nrcs office don't call don't email go
in person and start talking to the
person at the front desk they might not
be immediately available but showing up
in person will really get their
attention anyone can send an email but
very few people make the effort to walk
in and ask questions face to face that's
how you'll get noticed once you're there
you'll schedule a visit with an nrcs
representative this person will assess
your farm or garden and talk to you
about your goals and help you determine
which grants you qualify for now when
they come out to your operation make
sure everything looks clean and
organized the last thing you want them
to see is a messy Farm you want them to
see a professional operation that they'd
like to invest in this about building
trust and credibility and don't be
afraid to ask questions many of the
people who work for the USDA and the
nrcs might not even know about some of
these grants a lot of them are fresh out
of college and learning the ropes
themselves I asked about codes I saw in
the paperwork grants I'd never heard of
they didn't know what those grants were
at first but they went out of their way
to find out and that's how I secured the
cover cropping and pollinator habitat
ATT grants so ask those questions even
if it feels like you're pushing the
limit if they don't know they'll find
out for you and if you think it's a long
shot ask anyways the worst thing they
can do is say no and you're in the same
position you were in before but the best
case scenario you might get funding for
something you never imagined for example
I asked for funding to install 20,000
gallons of rainwater catchment and they
said not in this round but maybe in the
future it wasn't a flat out no it's just
a not this time pal but whatever I I
didn't care if they said no because what
if they said yes so if you're thinking
about starting your own Market Garden or
you're already in the game I got plenty
more videos on my channel to help you
with everything from starting your farm
to making it profitable so good luck
with your Grant applications and I'll
see y'all in the next one thanks y'all