what is the fastest way to level up your
hourglass for Guardians of Fortune to be
honest this has been a mystery to me
since hourglass pvp's launch back in
season 8. but thanks to fellow content
creator toxy Sinclair's latest video we
have a new strategy in town that is
exactly what we're going to be doing in
this video copying um I mean taking
inspiration from an amazing video which
you should all check out in the
description of this video and practicing
it on my own terms I mean that wasn't
the intention of one of my streams
twitch.tv Mystic but when things got
interesting I decided it was worth a
shot in today's adventure
so what is the strategy we aren't going
to go the conventional route here and
dive below the waves to match make
instead we're gonna let the people
invade our servers
why would anyone do this if you may ask
well it's so that we can take advantage
of one of the most forgotten features
that season 8 brought us the treasure
grade
you see toxy discovered that regular old
Merchant Commodities boost faction grade
and as you can imagine farming
Commodities from Outpost Outpost is not
too difficult of a task
there is only one problem though in
order to purchase Commodities you need
to be a representative of the merchant
Alliance and with the fast queue times
on EU servers this could become a
problem as we would want to end up with
grade 5 faction stash but also grade 5
Athena Emissary which requires at least
two fights to achieve
again I didn't originally plan on doing
this method but after my second fight
well
thank you
[ __ ] you're a streamer
huh
mistakes
your butt blank's friend Birch plank oh
right you actually do holy shh
[Music]
oh I'm gonna get stolen Commodities
let's go wait I actually kind of want
this
things changed
so there I was faced with a decision do
I risk my streak and go for toxic
strategy or call it quits and sell
as you can imagine from the title of
this video there was no quitting we was
going for the faction champion after
purchasing Commodities I re-raised
Athena Emissary in the case of evasion
however I happen to notice a grade 5
merch in Emissary and for sure knew this
was going to be the key to getting grade
5 faction stash
am I supposed to feel bad I
he left okay
the thing is people I I need I need his
supplies I need his loot
you know pirating is just
you know it is where you make it right
after sinking the ship and starting to
board on the treasure we had done it we
had successfully reached grade five but
just as that happened well we were
invaded
I knew this would happen
right we're grade five Let's uh let's
vacate
foreign
how does this dude have legendary Sea
Dog chat
I think he's an average tdmr
we sank our third ship of the day and
decided to travel over to plunder
Outpost as this is the closest Outpost
nearby where we could sell all of our
loot without complications here would be
where we would wait in preparation for
our fourth and Final Fight for faction
Champion we waited for a lot longer than
expected as the server seemed to be full
so after removing one AFK Sloop later
and waiting for our next battle well
let's just say it's not how I was
expecting to reach faction champion
break has gone so
okay and now
I'm able to vote so
is there someone on the island
[Music]
yes
okay right trap here we go
okay they didn't bother turning so
there's now a thought of the Damned on
the server
okay
where did they go
I think
is he trying to sell to the force adapt
no I don't
Fort Rudder maybe maybe it was meant to
be what what the hell is that
oh man
oh man I don't like this
all right let's see how much rep we got
come on let's see the wrap
bro I got a whole lot a whole level for
that
whole level
try I got a whole level
this isn't exactly how I pictured my
last battle going and was contemplating
continuing this streak however I decided
against this as I fought a fortune
spawned on the server meaning that the
likelihood of invasion was very slim due
to the players not leaving our Waters
however after all of the fighting the
reputation gained by reaching faction
Champion while at grade 5 seemed to be
worth it that is if you're lucky enough
to consistently be invaded
been feeling
see what rewards we get I don't think
you get anything extra for having ending
with a grade five
okay so let's see let's see the wrap
the whole level basically
in conclusion do I recommend giving this
a try sure but it's a very
circumstantial and requires a lot of
luck once again thank you toxy for
making your video on this strategy
without your inspiration I would have
never thought to give this a try so
people make sure to check out this video
in the description and show some love
but until the next adventure make sure
to leave a like comment and subscribe
and I will see you guys in the next one
are you ready to level up your gaming
experience to new heights well look no
further because Apex gaming PCs have
decided to continue the partnership with
the channel bringing you the best top of
the line machines for all purposes and
guess what they are offering an
exclusive deal just for our viewers
choose from any of the high performance
rigs whether you're a Casual Gamer or
hardcore Enthusiast they've got the
perfect machine for you and right now
they are offering an amazing 12 discount
on all purchases using our special code
mistakes they offer customizable options
so you can tailor your rig to your exact
specifications whether you're into
Competitive Gaming streaming or
immersive single player experiences Apex
gaming PCs has got you covered don't
miss out on this incredible opportunity
to grab your own top of the line gaming
machine at an unbeatable price so what
are you waiting for head over to the
link at the top of the description or
the pinned comment and use code mistakes
to get that 12 discount elevate your
gaming experience with Apex gaming PCs
trust me you won't regret it