[Music]
hello ladies from thailand today today's
video is going to be an unboxing
unboxing of a couple of solar-powered
devices
i'm convinced that solar power is the
way to go now i've tried a few things
with regard to solar
and i think that the small items are
probably the way to go so today i'm
gonna unbox two items that i think it'll
be very useful in the future
and the first one is let's have a look
i ordered these from lazada and they
came today very very fast
only three days for delivery
now
i've already done a few
solar things i've got solar-powered
light flood lights
around the house
and they'll last for 10 or 12 hours i'm
very very impressed for the price of
what they are
and this
is
obviously a solar panel
and a light fitting
comes with the remote control as well
[Applause]
so this is the light fitting
that i've got and the reason why i
bought this
is because
you can easily change the batteries in
these now there's pictures here of the
flood lights that i've put around the
house they're a little bit more
difficult to change the batteries once
they need to be
changed because eventually the batteries
will stop recharging and you need to
replace them
so i'm going to do
a breakdown of this and see what how it
works and how it fits together
and um
i think you'll be impressed
and the battery is already in there so
we'll have a lot
for being able to replace the battery
once it's it's worn out and it's past
its usefulness
[Applause]
i was hitting safety in there so
as far as being able to get access to
the battery and replace it
it's also simple very very simple for
diy installation and that's all i'm
dealing with is diy installation and
those people that can actually do it
themselves
so i'll put it back together now and
we'll
see it when it's working
two screws that's all it takes to be
able to put it back together again
plastic housing so waterproof and a
remote control
which
helps everything along
so i'm sort of impressed it's
it's a cheap light fitting
but we'll get some ideas to how good it
is
once we plug it in
so
the solar panel
which charges it up
well again
i intend to extend
the
sort of paddle lead because it's never
long enough to be able to
to put it where you need to put it to be
able to put the light up
and
i'm going to use these lights for
outside that's what i'm intending to use
them for so
we'll be able to put these onto the roof
or in some position where
it will
be able to charge everything up so the
lead really isn't that long maybe it's a
couple of meters long so what we're
going to do
i'm going to put it in the sun
for now
and then
see how it charges up and see how good
it charges it up
because as it comes now it's probably
uncharged
so let's put this in the sun and see
what we can do with it
so let's put the light in this sun
see if we can get it charged up
so
hopefully that should charge that up
okay that's the first one
unboxing done of what it is
the light fit in
some batteries some screws some raw
plugs
i say we'll deal with that when we come
to fit it up
i don't really know where i'm gonna put
it yet but
it will go somewhere
and the second thing that i've got
um now we use this particular item all
the time in the house
we have air conditioning but my wife
doesn't like air conditioning so i
let bought show you
in the box well packed
and
so let's see what we've got
it is a
[Applause]
solar powered
fan
as i said this comes with
it's a 16 inch
fan which is what this the same size
that we use already but electric
and
the idea is with this is to see how
much the battery lasts for for
because we use the fan nearly all day
and we certainly use the fan on the
nighttime in the bedroom
so we're going to see
how long it lasts for even if we just be
able to use it during the day it's some
sort of saving of electricity
now that's the size of the panel
to charge the battery that comes with it
now i'll leave some prices as to what i
paid
for these towards the end of the video
so you can see exactly how much i
appeared for these things
and there's a 16 inch
fan
so here we go we're going to put it all
together
now the idea is this is because i like
playing around with the electrics and
things like that
is that
if this
sort of
[Music]
brakes with the with the
i don't expect it to last very long
because it wasn't expensive
but the idea is
if the controls break
we
have 12 volt fan which can be controlled
by the solar panels i've got now i've
got some bigger solar panels
now
for those people who watched my programs
before with regard to solar i had an
inverter which was
linked up to the to the grid system but
unfortunately the gardener came around
one day
and the pebble dashed the
the panel and and smashed all the glass
on top of the solar panel
and also there was a lightning storm and
i think that blew up the diodes within
the
inverter
so it wasn't worth replacing the
inverter but i'm still a fan of solar
panels and solar power is why i bought
this because i want to see if this gives
a return
a quicker return than
buying another solar panel and inverter
so i'm going to put all this lot
together
[Music]
[Applause]
so let's go and plug it in and see what
it does
see if we can get it charged up
so again just got a phone charger
dc
charger
so let's go and see what it does
and let's do the same with
the fan
put that in the sun and let's see if we
can
charge later's working
it's working
from the sun
it's been a week now since i bought this
this solar panel
and light fitting and what do i think of
it
if you watch this video here you'll
actually see how easy it was to fit to
the roof without actually not fussing in
it to the the tiles on the roof
it's easy to do took less than 10
minutes to do and the results
i'm not overly impressed now this light
here only lasts for babies eight hours
when it's fully charged up as these ones
here last for the full 12 hours or so it
might have something to do with the size
of the battery i don't really know but
they give an impressive light out for
the eight hours that the
that they're lit for but
i'd want them to be up for 10 or 12
hours it gets dark here in thailand
about six o'clock in the evening and it
gets late again six o'clock in the
morning so they need to be on for at
least 12 hours for my
um
likability of it but eight hours it's
better than nothing at all isn't it i
suppose and it's free so eight hours
it's not too bad for the price uh 450
baht i think there were so less than 10
pounds
and it's free once it done so it's not
too bad
so what about this the fan the solar
panel fan
now again if you look at the box here it
says three hours on fast speed um now
again i've had it a week and i've had
the solar panel going out in the
sunshine for
all day and it's fully charged up with
the solar panel the best i can get out
of it is two hours i can get three hours
if the solar panel is in the sun
whilst it's being operated during the
day so with the battery and the solar
panel you can get three hours but it
doesn't say that the instructions are
any of the literature that comes with it
so again a little bit disappointing on
the evening time that's what we're going
to use it for
two hours at the very very most and
again on the box it says up to eight
hours on on slow speed
now
impossible doesn't give you the full
eight hours so
again a little bit disappointing with
that but for a thousand or just over a
thousand baht what could you expect
maybe as if i put a little bit bigger
battery in it but i've got other ideas
out how i can adapt this fan so it can
be used with my bigger solar panels but
this is all
in the future with regard to solar
panels i'm a big fan of solar power and
i will make the solar power work in this
house whilst i'm here so from this
retired and living the dream in thailand
until the next video bye for now