the snow pusher or the snow plow which
one's better
which one do you need guys how we doing
welcome to good works tractors today
we're talking about a topic that is
something i'm asked
all the time especially this time of
year the snow pusher versus the snow
plow let's go over those strengths and
weaknesses yes
each of them have strengths and
weaknesses we'll give you price points
what they're good for construction
design all that good stuff
if you'd be so kind i'd love to get a
thumbs up from you and if you haven't
done so yet hit that subscribe button
right underneath the video
to get more informational videos like
this one here if you're in the market
for a tractor an attachment an accessory
or maybe a whole package
check out that description below all
sorts of helpful links down there or
head on over to goodworkstractors.com
let's get to it let's talk about price
for a minute here in most situations
the snow pusher is going to end up being
a little bit cheaper than a snow plow
however that can vary and i do actually
have a very price competitive snow plow
here
from tar river it's available in 60 72
84 and 96 inch sizes
or widths there for compact tractors
this one that you see here on a kubota
l6060
is gonna be an 84 inch variant you can
also get a 96 inch for this machine
that'll be a good fit for it as well
over here on the 4066r you're going to
see an hla 2500 series
72 inch wide snow pusher some options to
consider that will affect pricing
on the snow pusher there's not going to
be any hydraulic options so nothing to
worry about there
on a snow plow however you can get that
set up with a manual angle
or an optional hydraulic angle for an
additional cost that is also going to
require additional hydraulic
capabilities on your tractor as well so
keep that in mind
the cost can really start to add up if
your tractor isn't already equipped with
those additional hydraulics
on a snow pusher some considerations to
take into mind are going to be something
like a back drag right here you can get
it with or without the back drag
and if you're going to get a back drag
you can add on a replaceable edge if you
want to make it a replaceable steel
rubber uhmw you have a lot of options
there to consider but
keep that in mind with or without and
then your edges as well are going to
drive the cost
now i love these tar river snow plows
they are
well built i did a comparison last year
comparing a tar river snow plow versus
the frontier snow plow for example
and the amount of steel that is in the
structure back here that's behind the
actual pushing blade itself
is just incredible there's way more
material here than what's on a lot of
other snow plows
and when you're plowing along you want
to have the weight to get the momentum
going
and you also want to have that rigidity
that structure there that strength
to allow you to go through whatever you
need to do to get the job done if we
take a closer look right here you're
going to see
two beefy trip springs one on either
side here that are just very substantial
in case you do hit a lip or an edge
and you need to have that release right
there that's what that's going to be for
you'll also see you have a skid shoe
down here with shims that are adjustable
one on the other side as well you're
also going to have mounts one right here
and one tucked underneath here to add on
a hydraulic cylinder if you want to
it comes standard in the piece of
equipment now i love these hla snow
pushers as well for a lot of reasons
i've gone into a lot of depth about it
they really stand apart from what else
is on the market today
including the huge background that's on
here this big black piece of steel right
here actually entirely closes off the
top of the
snow pusher on the smaller models once
you get to a 2500 series
you're still going to have roughly a 13
inch piece of steel right here that is
way more substantial than the
competition which is typically a three
or four inch piece of steel
to grab and accumulate all that snow in
there on the inside you're going to see
there's no cross braces in here at all
you have a double panel sidewall
construction
that also welds right into a radius back
on here so that radius back helps
propel the snow forward keep it rolling
forward so it doesn't stick there
nothing wants to get trapped more of the
snow is going to be released with this
design
some other great features included are
going to be adjustable skid shoes so you
can adjust them up and down if you want
to get just above that plowing surface
and not
scrape your gravel off the driveway you
can also add on a replaceable cutting
edge if you want to to the back
drag and of course the frame that
attaches to your tractor whether it's a
john deere quick attach it could be a
skid steer quick attach it could be a
global
we can even get custom mounts if you
even have a pinned on bucket all of
those frames are going to be bolted onto
the back of the snow pusher that way
if you end up with a different piece of
equipment down the road you don't have
to buy an entirely new snow pusher
just get a new frame bolt it up and away
you go so let's talk about requirements
what's needed
for you besides having the piece of
equipment here whether it's the plow
or the pusher well with a snow pusher it
really doesn't get any
easier because all you have to do is
hook it up take your bucket off all
right
take your bucket off or your forks or
your grapple connect
to the front end of your loader the snow
pusher and away you go over here
on the snow plow you do the same thing
all right if you have a manual angle
take your bucket off your forks all you
do is hook it up if you're going to have
a manual angle
again at that point you are going to
have to hop off the tractor anytime you
want to adjust the angle this way
adjust it that way you got to pull a
couple pins out you know rotate it
around put the pins back in and lock it
in place
however if you do have the optional
hydraulic angling kit that you can
add onto this system right here you can
plug it in if you have the hydraulics on
your tractor
and then you can operate everything
right up there from your operator
station
for me though i love simplicity and that
ranks really high on my priority list
and so that's where i
really appreciate the simplicity of the
hla snow pusher or snow pushers in
general
there's nothing else to worry about no
angling anything no hydraulics no
electric
you just put it on there and away you go
let's talk about how this equipment
carries the load
so over on a snow pusher as you're
collecting and accumulating snow
it's basically doing it in an even
amount you know dispersing it all
throughout here and capturing it
you know wherever it falls but it's just
going to accumulate in there and trap in
there evenly
now if you think about a snow plow
whether it's a big old one or a small
one
you have your plow angled you're never
really using your plow perfectly
straight on so
the load is constantly sweeping to one
side and when you have your load
sticking out as far as it is like this
it's going to be a lot more difficult to
try to steer your machine when you have
a load especially on lighter machines on
smaller machines your
your subcompacts and your smaller
compacts that don't have a lot of weight
when that snow is constantly pushing to
one side and you're having to combat
that
by steering this way and the front end
of your tractor is
sometimes wanting to lift up because of
the amount of snow is pushing so you're
already a little bit limited on traction
to begin with and you're compounding
that
by having that off center load and one
other thing to keep in consideration is
the fact that
you know your plow phase here on the
pusher is sitting closer to the loader
arm so
it's closer to your machine it's going
to allow you to maintain better control
as you can see over on the plow right
here your plow face is significantly
further away from your
the base of your loader arms here so
what that does is it makes it a little
bit harder to control a little bit
harder to steer
and get leverage with your machine now
keep in mind we're talking about
loader mounted plows you can get frame
mounted plows for certain machines
but for me that defeats the entire
purpose while you have a loader on there
most of us that have loaders on our
tractors need to be able to use them
year round and so if you get a frame
mounted plow that means you have to
remove your loader and then install all
the hardware and the quick attach system
and everything else to use the plow
so getting something for your loader is
going to be a lot more effective for
most of us that we have to use
a grapple in the wintertime or a bale
sphere or a bucket or pallet forks or
something else along those lines
let's talk about the types of snowfall
that these attachments can handle and
that's going to be pretty easy pretty
much
everything that you can throw at it
whether it's a small amount just an inch
or two that you want to clean up so it
doesn't turn into an icy mess
or if you have 12 18 inches i know some
of you guys just got 30 or 40 inches
any piece of snow removal equipment is
going to struggle with that so you're
just making do if you get a monster
mega storm you know that's 30 or 40
inches of snow you're just doing what
you can
to keep up it doesn't matter if it's the
light fluffy stuff it could be the wet
heavy stuff
these hunks of steel right here are
going to take that snow and move it
wherever you want to
one of the great features about this
backdrag is the fact that if you have a
big building like this or it could be a
garage or it could be a retaining wall
even
some place where you can't push snow
whether it's a pusher or a plow
you can go up to that surface there rock
this whole piece of equipment forward
like you're going to dump your bucket
out
and then this right here becomes your
scraping edge or your plow edge and you
can go up to that
that wall or that face and pull the snow
away
it's going to be all trapped inside this
box there so it's very easy to do and
very efficient to do
one of the big questions i'm asked is i
have a long drive what do you recommend
or i have a big parking lot or i have a
big landing area
or maybe i have both what do you
recommend as the right piece of
equipment for me
if we take everything we've learned so
far from the strengths and the
weaknesses of each one of these pieces
of equipment
my money goes to the snow pusher however
you got to make your own decision
if you have a long drive all right say
six or 800 foot
i sell both okay i sell pushers and
plows plows i guess are
more common right they've been around
longer you see a lot more of them out
there
so that's kind of where people tend to
gravitate towards it doesn't mean it's
the right solution for everybody
let me give you an example i've been in
a few locations even my current place
where i live right now where i've used a
snow plow
on the front of a garden tractor if you
have an unrelenting winter
where the snow just keeps coming guess
what you can only plow so often to the
side
before you're gonna have to stack it
somewhere anyway otherwise your
driveway's gonna continuously close in
on you and get narrower and narrower
because
that plow's not gonna go ahead and just
keep dumping it over the top
there's just nowhere for it to go so at
some point
and you're better off doing this early
on is pushing that snow back
periodically
in sections off the driveway to the
locations that you can even if you have
a 600 foot plus long driveway
you're going to have these same problems
versus if you have a 25 foot long
driveway you have to have some place to
put the snow
and that's where doing so with a snow
pusher can be more effective
than doing so with a snow plow and so
basically with a pusher or a plow even
on a long driveway
you still have to push that snow
straight you're going to have windrows
with either piece of equipment
and so where that efficiency comes into
place is with something like a pusher
here
that makes cleaning up collecting those
windrows a lot more efficient
with a plow it's windrow after windrow
after windrow i deal with it all the
time when i use a plow at my house
because that snow never is trapped by
the far end of the plow it's going to
constantly spill over you have to go
back through and make one more cleanup
pass if you want to
however smaller volumes of snow that
windrows normally are
they're captured right inside this box
here on a pusher so you collect it
you move it where you want to you stack
it up and it's done
and again bear in mind with smaller
machines maybe not so much once you get
to an l6060 or into your utility tractor
but those lighter machines are going to
have a challenge
steering while you're pushing all that
snow with a snow plow so if you can
keep that load centered with a snow
pusher it could make your life a little
bit more enjoyable as you go through the
winter time
now for talking about larger areas maybe
it's a lot like what i have here at the
shop
maybe it's at home you've got a garage
here maybe an extra garage or a barn or
just a big landing area
snow pushers really are the tool to use
they're going to be a lot more efficient
at trapping that snow
minimizing the amount of passes you get
the job done a lot quicker with a piece
of equipment like this
now as you might be able to tell i'm a
snow pusher guy i just really love them
and again for me it's all about
simplicity and you can't beat that with
a snow pusher
however no matter what i choose to sell
or recommend to folks i want it to be a
good value
above and beyond everything else so the
tar river snow plows
the hla snow pushers they just have that
great combination of features
price and quality that you just can't
find with anything else that's out there
so i hope you found this video helpful
it gave you some good food for thought
to help you make your decision if you're
going back and forth i know it's a big
decision that a lot of folks are
trying to figure out on their own and
this gives you some insight a different
perspective maybe to think about
it would really help me out if you
consider giving me a thumbs up and maybe
even leave a comment down below
also consider hitting that subscribe
button if you'd like to see more helpful
tractor videos
and make sure you read through that
description below we have all sorts of
helpful links down there
as you might be able to tell we sell
tractors and attachments to and also
work with other manufacturers where you
can get five percent off with code gwt
well until next time stay safe we'll see
you soon
all right let's get going all done for
the day
we gotta pack up first rolls