good afternoon everyone my name is Julie
Garden Robinson and I'm your host for
today's field to Fork webinar this is
brought to you by North Dakota State
University extension this is actually
the ninth year we've done the series and
we're really glad you've been joining us
maybe this is your first time or maybe
you've been to all of the webinars so
far we have archived all of the webinars
from previous years and the link is on
our field of fork webinar page and I
want to give a special Welcome to our
watch parties welcome
everyone we also are providing a
certificate of attendance on our website
and it is posted with the recording
which will come out in a couple days the
next slide shows the upcoming
webinars so you can take a look we hope
you join us for these as
well the next slide shows the webinar
controls and because of our large number
of participants we invite you to post
your questions and comments in the chat
let's practice finding and using the
chat box some of you already did you can
ignore the Q&A box we're not going to
use that we're going to have you put
your questions for harleen in the chat
box so type your city and state where
you are right
now the next slide provides an
acknowledgement so as you work on
putting your city and state in I have a
special request this program is
sponsored in part with grant funding
from the usda's Agricultural Marketing
service through the North Dakota
Department of Agriculture actually and I
will ask all of you to complete the
short online survey that will be emailed
right after today's webinar and as a
thank you we are continuing to provide
prizes to the lucky winners of the
random drawings so be sure to include
your complete
address and by the way you will need to
scroll down to today's date and
speaker's name because we're combining
our data from 2023 and 2024 so the 2023
dates are listed first so scroll down a
little bit and click on that button that
corresponds to the 2024
date and with that our next slide is a
welcome to today's webinar and our
speaker I'd like to tell you a little
bit about Dr harleen hatterman Valente
she was born in northeast Nebraska and
raised on a crop and Animal Farm she
came to NDSU in 2000 as an assistant
professor in the high value crops
project so she has spent more time in
North Dakota than Nebraska she has
conducted research on approximately 20
different different crops but aliam
crops have been most predominant during
her 23 plus years at NDSU and I have a
beautiful blooming bulb behind me right
now that's quite fragrant so I'm looking
forward to Spring and some of the bulbs
that pop up so welcome harleen and I'll
you can take it
away okay so that is wonderful so today
um the the topic is how to grow garlic
and aliums and I only have about 45
minutes so I'm not going to touch on a
lot of
aliums um uh because there are way too
many that uh it would take days to go
and discuss them all uh but so today I'm
just going to talk about three of them
uh garlic dry bulb onions and leaks and
those are the big three that we can
really grow quite well here in North
Dakota so with that I'm going to start
with a little bit about um garlic well
first I'll just talk about the the genus
alium it is one of the largest flowering
plant groups in the amarillis family and
that's what Julie was talking about she
probably has an amarillis that is what
its common name is uh bulb flowering
right now the family name is actually
amarilla
daier um and this consists of hundreds
of wild and cultivated scented bulbus
herbs and the three that I have talked
about are um well known there's there's
also a lot of chives for example is
another one but there's even herbaceous
ornamentals that um grow quite well in
North Dakota that um Chinese garlic for
one and ornamental onion uh that uh grow
quite well and prolifically as
herbaceous ornamentals but today we're
going to talk about more of the culinary
ones and and to start with um garlic you
know it can be used for a whole bunch of
different things um I have a graduate
student that is looking at uh the
cultivars and some of the information
that I'm going to provide is from his
trial to give you an idea of which Cult
of Art do better in North Dakota than um
other places but I also have a graduate
student that is looking at aliums for
their um Health
attributes uh we know garlic has a lot
of Health attributes and I'll talk about
that in a little bit but she's looking
at um how some of these other aliums
leaks um green
onions um dry ball bulb onions and boy
now I lost my thought on the third one
um it'll come to me probably when I get
to the end but she's looking at more of
the health attributes and that's because
a lot of these
uh aliums have these
bioactive components in garlic it's
alisin and Alin and actually Alin is the
precursor to Al sin so um most of the um
the health attributes has to do with
this sulfur compound of alisin which is
the most predominant in garlic but
garlic also has a g
glutamine sorry a mouthful and
polyphenolics and we've been looking in
collaboration with um Dr Kalita Shetty
on um just
the the health benefits of the
polyphenolics um with type 2 diabetes so
um cidra's whole research is looking at
um the four aliums for
that um as far as uh the amount of
production of garlic the United Nations
food and agricultural assoc organization
has uh estimated that on an annual basis
there's about 11 million tons of garlic
produced and that's just on 2.5 million
Acres um that's worldwide that isn't the
United States actually in the United
States we import a lot of our garlic and
that's because of the uses and
effectiveness of it treating uh many
different Cancers and diseases and so
the consumption has
increased faster than actually the
production has increased so in the
United States especially we're really
importing quite a bit of um forgot to
start up my little thing well I'll look
at time make sure I don't run
over um importing much of the garlic so
now let's go in a little bit get started
on the production and
management um garlic grows best in a a
welld drained Sandy clay LOM soil so a
little bit heavier soil and actually we
have a study where we're um trying to
see how these cultivars compare um at
our horiculture research site which is
more of a Sandy LOM and comparison to on
campus here where we're in the Red River
Valley we have a clay soil uh and so
we're we're testing that uh we planted
those last fall and we'll hopefully have
some results come this uh kind of late
July um period when we
Harvest um soil pH is best around 6 to
6.8 uh but I know we have a little bit
higher um pH out at the Horticulture
research Farm it's more of a 72 maybe
7.4 and we haven't had any problems um
with that so um one nice thing about
garlic is it it's it's a very uh
adaptable plant in most
cases as far as nutrition you know we
want to overall apply between 70 and 125
pounds of nitrogen 150 lbs of um
phosphorus and a excuse me about 100
pounds of potassium now that will depend
on your soil test and what previous crop
you had a and uh so um but it's also
important that we don't put all that
nitrogen down at F at one time we really
want to spoon feed the
nitrogen um and so that should be split
into approximately 25 lbs before
planting and then side dress around 20
lb every 3 weeks and then we want to
make sure we stop four to six weeks
before Harvest um because we really want
that plant not to keep trying to grow
and produce it has to um you know it
it's a rather long season the way it is
we need that dry down we have to go and
cure those uh um B um bulbs and and and
it also helps if you shut that off so
that you don't it in the preservation
otherwise uh your bulbs will deteriorate
quicker if we keep on fertilizing right
to the end um as far as irrigation I
think drip irrigation works the best
with drip irrigation you can avoid some
of those uh Leaf diseases that um all
aliums can get uh and uh with drip
irrigation then it's easy enough to um
put on about an inch a week if it's
getting um towards the end and the
plants are bigger you might need to go
and put two two inches a week when it's
um some of those hot days especi like
last year we had June weather no July
weather was in June so it was really
really hot we had a number of 100 degree
days days um and aliam in general do not
really like those hot days so it's best
that we do whatever we can to go and and
help them through those kind of
periods now there are three different
types of garlic you have your um
elephant garlic uh softnet um garlic and
hardnet garlic we in in the northern
part
um do best with hard neck
cultivars and um
so and but there's a lot of there's also
then subgroups but hard neck by far are
are the only ones that we grow in North
Dakota so when do we get started well
we're past that time already we needed
to do that this last fall approximately
6 to eight weeks before that ground
freezes um and we actually have another
study where we're looking at you know
what is the optimum time because there
hasn't been any research on that for um
garlic and and so I'd rather have us do
some trial and air and figure out when's
the best time uh to have um to go and uh
transplant your cloves of garlic
um than to have someone else go and and
trial around and find out um that
through more air than um anything else
um spacing your rose spacing should be
anywhere from 12 to um 36 in or 1 to 3
feet and then um between the cloves you
want somewhere between 3 and 6 in they
kind of like to be kind of close
together but you need to go and give
them enough room so that um they aren't
pushing against each other and deforming
each other so depth um is 3 to 4 in deep
and and so you see the picture and in
which they've just kind of marked out
the row then they'll go and cover that
with soil you can do that or you can go
and just actually if you have a well
tilled soil you can probably just push
them down to that depth another way of
looking at it is that the top of the
clove has to be twice the depth of the
clove height so if your clove was about
1 and2 in uh tall then you want 3 in um
above that tip of that
clove of course um we need to mulch in
this uh climate that we have actually
one time I was growing some and um I
thought well the previous year generally
we have plenty of snow and I said oh
they'll be fine I won't have to go and
and get some straw and mulch them and
sure enough that was the fall that we
had the really cold weather before we
got the insulation from the snow and so
the following
spring um most of them did not emerge uh
they in fact they just because of that
cold injury they just rotted in the soil
so you want four to six inches of
straw and the nice thing about that is
uh you know having that
straw through the winter protecting it
um you can then leave it there and it
provides uh wheat control not allowing a
lot of those annual weat needs to get
enough sunlight to go and germinate so
it it it provides weed control as well
and that is always a a good thing um
because there's not a lot of way um easy
ways to go and for weed control usually
it's by hand weeding uh the roots are
rather shallow and you really don't want
to go and disturb the roots so um uh the
mainly it's been hand weeding for for
especially for a homeowner I think if we
were to have a big commercial grower
then they would have put down their um
pre-emergence herbicide um way before uh
the uh garlic or the weeds
emerged so let's go on okay more on the
production and management so um garlic
will flour and these uh that flowering
stem is called escape and that must be
removed because if you don't remove that
and you allow the garlic to flour then
it's taking away nutrition from that
bulb and those cloves and putting it
towards that flour stock and that flour
so you you remove the Scapes and they
can be consumed or you if you have a
farmers market you can sell them you can
make them into a whole bunch of
different things I'm sure Julie has um
all kinds of recipes for Scapes uh
anything from a pesto to um just a pan
uh frying them could be done um and so
when you do that then the next sequence
of what happens is it's time to go and
harvest and you're going to go and
harvest the them when there's about six
brown leaves or 60% of those leaves turn
brown I should say um
unlike well they do like onions they'll
actually that stem will Kink over uh but
you generally want to do that before you
don't want to wait that long because
then that plant is also
overmature and especially if you're
going to go and try to you utilize any
of those cloves to plant the following
year or if you want some long storage um
they're going to have poor quality so
when 60% of the leaves turn brown uh you
can either go and try to um pull and
twist but I really think the best thing
is to have a like the picture shows have
some kind of a fork or shovel or
something to help dig those because I
have gone and um thought I could just
pull them out and um no I'm missing part
of the the bulb so um I just try to I
use a shovel and help to help dig them
up well after that um just like other
aliums that you want to um maybe store
or even if you were going to use them um
shortly you need to do some curing and
uh it's best if you avoid trying to cure
these outside in full sun because a lot
of times you can have problems with Suns
scold on those so um
indoor at a temperature around 75 80°
Fahrenheit and you can see as a picture
they have them in these little netted
bags so that they can have some air
circulation uh and then well actually
after one to two weeks then you cut off
the stems and you can then continue to
store them this
way um and if you do in those kind of
situations then they'll be able to go
and be stored for one to two weeks if
you want longer storage you need to have
them at a refrigerated temperature with
relatively low um relative humidity and
then you can go and and store them
um if you're a lot of garlic growers
will go and um use their own cloves for
next uh for the planting in the fall um
and if you're going to do that you have
to make sure that you um store those
cloves that you're going to use for your
seed at around 50° fahit with that
relatively low um relative
humidity if you don't if you go at
temperatures less than 5050 that hastens
the breaking of dorcy so you're going to
end up uh maybe having a longer shoot
and it's really going I mean you don't
want that shoot really above ground um
in the fall so you're trying to plant it
so that it gets a start but you don't
want it above ground um and it's going
to be difficult to do that when if it
breaks dorcy early
likewise if you go and uh store them at
a much warmer temperature greater than
65 that actually will go and delay the
sprouting and thus I'm going to also
throw things out of whack because you
really want to have those come up in the
spring because they don't do really well
in really hot hot
temperatures that what um and so if you
have that earlier emerg in the spring
they'll get mature and you won't have to
worry about
that see you on my time
okay
so um now I'm going to just talk a
little bit about some of the cultivar or
the cultivar trial that Stephen is doing
and so he's looked at these 29 cultivars
and you'll see that some of them say
2021 and have the same name and and
that's because we're actually TR um
using the
seed seed I guess the clothes that that
we planted in 2021 seeing if there are
certain cultivars that do better that um
are more adapted to our um environmental
conditions that would work better for
someone who who is trying to go and use
their own seed and continue to use their
own seed or maybe sell um
garlic and so that's why those say
2021 um as far as then results so this
is the the results that Steph Got U from
2023 and he at initially he was looking
at uh the number of leaves that are
produced because um more Leaf production
ction just means there's more
photosynthates that go into that bulb so
help that bulb um get larger and of
course that's what we want and when you
look at this this is 30 and 45 uh days
after they emerged from the soil and we
see here that you know we have a a
number of them that are doing well both
uh they are producing around six leaves
um at 30 days and at 45 days they're
right up around N9
days um one in particular went from only
producing about five leaves um at 30
days and really shot up the leaf
production that was Yukon Ukrainian red
um and by um 45 days it was up to nine
leaves when we looked at um then 60 and
80 Days after emergence um the order
hasn't really changed too much uh there
was you know they really didn't go and
do a lot of lot more growth except for
like Ukrainian red it um did quite well
in that um it can you know continued to
produce some leaves so that by 60 days
it was at um 11 and just a little bit
higher at 80 Days in in comparison to a
lot of these others that stayed around
that
Nine area another one that was the
Deerfield purple
2021 cloves and it again jumped up from
having around nine to right up there to
uh 10 10 and a half
leaves
so there was then a number of the that
just you know they after 45 days they
really didn't change much in in their
Leaf
production oops there we go as far as
average scape length what we were seeing
is that you know
um the ones that were producing more
Scapes or longer Scapes generally are
more adapted to the environmental
conditions that we have here in North
Dakota um our best was Dakota white but
statistically because these other
letters also have an A or these other
cultivars also have an A associated with
them there was no statistical
differences in uh the average scape
length for those
cultivars when we look at average scape
weight again we had a few more so um
there's a number of those that went and
didn't have the longest skape length but
they were probably thicker thus they had
uh similar weights and you can see uh
those seven right there that were um for
average scape
weight now this um average bulb diameter
um again I I should have probably
earlier talked about what the scale is
here this is in millimeters but really
the what I'm trying to get across is you
can see how uh the diameter went from
these which were all statistically the
same having the largest diameter to
those that had um were statist
statistically the same for having a
rather small diameter bulbs
and that then when we look at average
bulb weight which a lot of times um is
is how they're sold uh we see here that
we had three of them that had um the
that had the heaviest weight um German
White had by far the the heaviest weight
but Georgian fire and music were
statistically the same for weights
in opposition to that we we now know
that um or pretty sure we'll find out
with our second year of data um this
year when we Harvest but we have a a
pretty good idea that uh
um purple white spring chestnut red
Yugoslavian Ukrainian red which is kind
of unique well um that was 2021 spay
Deerfield German red and Italian Lola
can canono um really had now most of
those had smaller bulbs but they also
had very small weight for um for
um
garlic so in conclusion the average
number of leaves um was similar for all
these cultivars and until about 60 days
after they emerged from the ground and
then after that then Ukrainian red
really took off and it produced the
highest number of leaves however that
wasn't
associated with um with bulb diameter or
bulb weight for that
cultivar um when we're talking about
Scapes Dakota white and German white
produced the longest and heaviest scapes
respectively while this Italian Lio Kono
uh and white spring did not even produce
Scapes when we're talking about um the
bulbs then there was numerous cultivars
that produced bulbs that had a diameter
of approximately 2.4 2 and2 in but only
German White had the bulbs that weighed
over 2.5
o and so by far
was the
superior cultivar that we tested and we
tried to find every cultivar around um
that was available in the US through
numerous uh uh Garden Supply cataloges
and so um so German white appeared to be
the most adapted to the North Dakota
environmental conditions well um there
was two that um were the least and were
would not be worth the time to go and
put into your
garden okay so now we're going to go and
move on to onion basics in a little bit
I'm going to probably have to hurry up
on this with onions um so Garlic's a
perennial and if you didn't go and
harvest your garlic it would come up
again um and but that would would not go
and and behoove you to go and and
because it's not ornamental looking at
all um a and so uh it also would then
that all of those cloves would try to
come in that one Bunch which would also
defeat the purpose of growing garlic but
onions on the other hand they're a
banial and so they need two years before
they
flower which is important to know for
for some aspects of why you have
flowering um so they also have a these
concentric swollen Leaf bases and that
the the leaves emerge from the center so
the oldest Leaf is here the newest Leaf
is going to come from there and bulbing
is is determined by the photo period and
temperature and that's important because
the bulb size and the rate of bulb
development depends on the size of that
plant when bulbing starts so you have a
larger plant when it starts and you have
good temperatures um then you'll have um
really a good
siiz onion bulb that you will
harvest so some of um a little bit of
information on you know these various
veget vegetables that have storage
organs and how they respond to photo
period so we have some that are
classified as day neutral they don't
care what you know how long a day is or
how short the day is and that's carrots
beets turnips and radishes so they're
classified as day neutral you plant them
and when they get you know as they
mature that storage organ will get
bigger however onions and garlic are
long day and and so they that is
triggered by um their flowering or their
storage their bulbing is actually
triggered by long days there are some
exceptions but it's still considered a
long day and I'll talk to you a little
bit about that um on the other hand we
have short day um vegetables potato Poes
sweet potatoes yams and cassavas that
actually the the
tubers um start to form in response to
short days so just a little bit of more
um information than maybe you wanted to
know there are different onion types but
I'm thinking I'm going to run out of
time and so I'm going to kind of just
pass over this um because really
um you're going to
order what's available in in a uh or
what's available in the store or through
a catalog and that's already been kind
of um they've kind of tested these
cultivars for various
areas other classifications include um
skin color of course you've probably
seen that in the store where you can buy
Reds whites or yellow um according to
the mildness or pungent
pungency um the yellows that we are
accustomed to Growing for storage are
much more pungent and um and usually the
ones that do not store well are much
more milder in taste um they can be
categorized also according to their
shapes now here's where you know I said
they're a long day for that for the
bulbing but within that um they this is
so crazy you know they'll still go and
say you have short day intermediate day
and long days but they're all long days
because you can see um the short day
ones for bulbing is 12 to 13 hours of
day length the intermediate need 13 to
14 hours and the long days need 14 to 16
hours before they start to
bulb and you um you know those short and
intermediate ones are are really for uh
I I'd
say probably Kansas on down and and the
short ones are texus Florida
area Okay sets versus seed you
um really sets have higher Vig ger a and
in especially in less favorable spring
conditions so they're going to take off
quicker um they also provide a more
consistent sta stand establishment but
with that they're you're they're more
expensive in comparison to seed if you
bought a dozen sets versus 12 seeds it's
there's quite a difference there uh
another thing about the sets is they're
earlier at maturing and they require a
shorter growing season because with the
sets you generally already have um four
to five leaves in that set and so you
see this picture here and um the sets
you can see are so much further ahead of
the
seed in North Dakota um commercially we
generally
uh plant uh just because of the cost of
of the sets and um since I don't think
anyone's going to be doing this and this
is available in the handouts I'm just
going to go and and kind of just go over
um pass through this but you know
Growers that are commercially growing
onions they're going to try to plant as
early as possible and they do it in
these double rows as you can see in the
picture because onions they kind of like
to be by each other and do much better
and they're really wimpy getting out of
out of the ground so they need as much
help as
possible um some will do transplants but
to go and get um put through transplants
you need to start those 8 to nine weeks
in a greenhouse or indoor with adequate
lighting um and you have to really um be
careful that you don't
um have any vernalization occur and
that's also true with those sets uh the
and I think I I'll go over that in a
little bit the sets are next Um this can
be costly at one time the
Growers uh were the there are some
Growers that use actually transplants
because you have they're already growing
some other vegetables and they have a
vegetable transplanter and so this works
out quite well this also goes and gets
them a a very early
Market um because the transplants will
be um just as early as sets so they you
can get an earlier market and thus um
get a better price or they'll do it for
those late maturing Spanish types in
more of these uh more northern
states as far as
sets if you're going to um use sets you
want to have them be less than a half
inch in
diameter uh if you happen to go and have
a few of those that are larger usually
what they're what you can do is just use
those for green onions and the reason
I'm saying this is because um if they're
larger than that/ inch
diameter they've been put into a cooler
and ship to wherever for these garden
centers or box stores to go and sell and
if they have if they're larger than that
half inch diameter they probably have
gone through the juvenile stage and thus
can be
vernalized to think they should flour so
those larger ones are going to probably
uh go and flower on you which is
something that you don't want with
onion so
spacing um we kind of talked about that
weed
control uh in commercial it's um very
rigorous onion are just like garlic
they're just don't ever canopy so weed
control is really really important but
you know all the aliums have a very
fibrous shallow root system so you you
have to really be careful um so if
you're pulling weeds you don't allow
those weeds to get really really large
because you'll if that are growing next
to the um onions because that will
actually um go and cause some injury and
they may just kind of stop their growth
for a while uh which know in our short
growing season is is important not to
have anything that uh slows things
down um so watering you can see what
that is fertility again just kind of
like um The Garlic you want to more
spoon feed the nitrogen you don't want
to go and give too much up front and you
don't want to go too long um with um
fertilizing uh the the onion either uh
generally you want to stop by July uh in
your fertilization because if you go
much uh go past you know into August um
then you end up with onions that have
really thick necks
and those tend to be soft when they cure
and you end to end up getting a lot of
disease
problems with that bulb rots because of
that large neck that stays soft
longer okay so we kind of talked about
um bulbing uh and I think I mentioned
that um it's controlled in onions um by
that long day so location is important I
said it was um day length and
temperature so this is why um it's
really important that we have the right
kinds of cultivars those long day ones
um anything really above uh
Kansas this would be for long day um
when we're going through that just
because of the
daylength and so here's a little uh
table that kind of talks about you know
how our days get
longer and you can see here by
um June 7th we have you know we're
almost to 16 hours so if we didn't go
and plant if we were going to go by seed
um and we didn't get that planted until
May you know they'd come up and they'd
almost by that time be triggered into
wanting to bulb and they wouldn't have
hardly any they'd have just two leaves
um and thus we'd end up with very small
diameter
onions here's another way of looking at
it um so here's our day daylight and
then we have uh our Dawn and here's our
Dusk and you can see how that changes
then when we get for daylight savings
time and then in the fall again but you
know June 20th then is our longest day H
where we have day length from um almost
5:00 in the morning to
10:00 um at night so this is uh why I
feel June is just the most fabulous
month in the year in North Dakota oops
okay getting almost oh I got to hurry so
why do my onions flour I think I've
talked about this um
repeatedly uh and so um I'm going to go
on to leaks because I only have a few
more three more slides so growing leaks
it really they're really pretty easy uh
but they need a rather a real long time
to to mature um they're rather slow
growing and and so um most leaks need
120 to 150 days so you need to start
them from seed indoors and then you
transplant them early spring you can to
go and you really want to to have this
stock long and white this one's not
really quite there I I mean they didn't
have uh they didn't have these buried
very long to do that you can either go
and throw keep throwing soil up or you
can plant them in a furl and then slowly
fill in as that plant grows larger and
larger um they the water is about the
same as onion and garlic
uh but they can Toler and actually onion
and garlic can tolerate cold too
um the problem is is um that you
know what you can go what happens here
is now different because you have this
bulb only in onion and garlic you're you
know you harvest end of July first part
of August so I mean you can't even get
to the cold temperatures there but with
leaks because they're tolerant of cold
you can actually let them and delay your
Harvest or maybe just pick them as you
need them um after that first Frost
because a lot of times here in North
Dakota we'll get that first Frost and
then we have a month of really rather
nice weather so the fact that they can
tolerate that cold you can have fresh
leaks for quite some time after that
first Frost so start them indoors
February March you transplant them when
they're 10 to 15 weeks old you don't
want to wait too much uh longer than
that because then um they'll go through
some kind of transplant shock and if you
go less than 10 weeks old um they're
just going to be so small very difficult
to handle before you transplant them you
want to acclimate them to the outside so
about a week where you have them in kind
of a protected area where they aren't
just getting wind whipped all over the
place but they're starting to adjust to
the
outdoor breezes more and um a lot more
sunlight so acclimate them for about a
week and then when we have um average
daytime temperature of 45 degrees or
above you can go and Transplant them
um and I think you know you need you
can't because two weeks ago we had above
45 for a few days you just don't go and
do that um in North Dakota because all
of a sudden we can have a blizzard again
and so you know you want to wait until
uh 30-year average is above 45° for your
location planting pretty much the same
as uh the others and we fertilize so
depending on on the cultivar you can
have some shorter ones that are mature
when that stem diameter the stem
diameter is a half an inch and the
larger ones you want to wait until
that's about an inch in
diameter and then you again I would dig
these uh instead of trying to pull
because they have quite a root system
and I just pulling many times you're
just going to pull off that bottom part
so um one other thing is try to
thoroughly clean before you use because
know if you're filling that soil in from
that furl you might get some soil down
into those leaves and you can eat both
the green leaves and this white stem
that had turns white because of the soil
around it and so with that uh just a
little bit over sorry Julie that's great
well thank you so much we have a number
of questions so I'll quickly go through
these um first two questions one's about
hard neck and the other's about soft
neck so why are hard neck varieties of
garlic best in North
Dakota um I I think they're they're
harder so they you know with that straw
covering they just uh do better
and then we have a question asking about
southern varieties I'll call them Zone
Seven are soft neck varieties of garlic
better for I guess warmer
climates probably um they they actually
store a lot longer than hard neck so if
you can
um see and that also depends so soft
neck have more cloves in a bulb than
hard necks so if you want you know if
you're in zone seven I would think maybe
you would go with the Elephant Garlic
um also
I uh soft neck are a little bit more
milder than the hard
necks but um but I I don't I've never
lived well no I have never lived in zone
s so I better not better not go and um
talk to somebody who's an extension
specialist in zone seven I'd say that's
a that's a good
answer uh what could you expect if you
plant garlic in the
spring okay so there are places that
planted in the spring but um the fact
that it doesn't you're going to have to
give it you know they require those
chill weeks so you're going to have it
in your refrigerator so it accumulates
those chills and and then they just
never get as big so if you want larger
bulbs then plant them in the
fall uh couple of questions about Scapes
how do you remove the Scapes do you cut
them off yes just cut them off and make
sure you cut them off before that um you
can see the flower it's a little H it's
like a candy kiss you want to get it
before it gets much bigger and
definitely before it opens um to go I
could have darn it I should have put a
picture of that I could have done that I
never thought about that so and then a
question about garlic leaves versus
Garlic
Scapes okay what's the difference
um the scape will
be round and the leaves are more
flattened Hollow flattened
leaves um and it will come up through
the
center and and so um it'll be and then
it'll start to form what is that flower
head and when that starts to form that's
when you can cut it off and you'll just
cut it as close to the uh plant as
possible to the bottom to of the plant
and I I will tell everyone that on our
field of fork resources page if you go
to garlic we have a garlic from garden
to table that was first written by a
previous horiculture specialist in me so
you can also check that we have a lot of
recipes there
too um here's another question I want to
leave garlic in the ground around my
property will it
naturalize you know I suppose but it's
going to be these little clumps
and then if you if you want something
like that then go with the garlic chives
herbaceous
ornamental uh because they they're very
naturalized they're an herbaceous
ornamental uh and much more set up to I
mean they actually have a a really
unique pretty humble flower so yeah I
would go with ornamental onions or
ornamental chives or garlic chives
they're have different names like that
um common names but they aliums that are
herbaceous ornamentals that are much
more naturalized for a situation
very good um the next person asks why
people would want to grow
shallots that was the fourth one I
couldn't think of thank you for coming
up with shallot um and they're they're a
m a much more
milder um onion and they can be
grown uh but we haven't been able to
there was only one of the four cultivars
that cidra um used that actually had a
sizable they're much smaller but you
know some recipes just call for shallots
because they want that much more milder
they don't want that pungency of of the
onion uh next question when do you pick
winter
onions I'm not really too familiar with
winter onions
and so that's okay we can go on to the
next one that's a question for your
local horiculture specialist if you're
from another state uh if leaks are
planted two to six inches apart in a row
can you not have the row six inches
apart I'm working in raised beds and
it's the same true for garlic and
onions so the difficulty with a raised
bed you know so when with leaks you know
you want to you want to have that stock
that is white so you keep throwing soil
what we did was we made furls and if
it's really if you have six inch rows
where you going to put that soil for
your furls to go and slowly fill it in
we had these Mounds on each side of the
row that we then slowly filled it in to
go and get you know you're hoping to get
68 Ines of of soil covering that so
that's the whole part with leaks that
would make uh in a raised bed having
them so close together is unless you you
know didn't care to have that much white
and you want it to just have lot more
green leaves um if you don't go and put
that soil there then you know your Leaf
your Leaf base is going to be right
close to the you're not going to get
much of the bulb
part with it but with um onions you know
we generally put them about 4 Ines apart
because we're trying our aim is a 4 in
diameter onion so if you have them
closer together then they're going to
start to compete and can actually um
cause some deformity in the shape of the
bulb let alone um probably compete more
for nutrients and and water as
well
so next question what are some common
insect pests that will feed on onions in
a hom Garden
setting well there is the onion maggot
that will affect the
seed and and that's the
biggest I guess
insect um that is a problem um
otherwise there you know you don't have
caterpillars or anything like that
chomping on
them uh but um yeah the and but there
are some Leaf spots and then of course
um some
bacteria that if you have bruising that
can cause problems but you know the
biggest problem is you know if you
fertilize too much and you get those
with onions especially you get those
larger necks that stay soft and they
don't dry down so fast then you have a
various fungi that get in and start
causing neck rot
problems all right so we'll take two
more questions here can you eat onions
that have
flowered oh yes you can you can eat them
um it's just you know that plant when
it's flowering it's diverting a lot of
those um carbohydrates that it's
producing from
photosynthesis to that flour so your
bulb's going to be smaller and it's not
going to store very long so
all right so last question we'll take
for today uh can you eat garlic chives
they're not just ornamental
right um
so I've never I well I I suppose
anything could be edible unless it's
poisonous correct you but um garlic
chives versus chives now see there's
chives
which you would eat the the hollow
leaves and um and then garlic chives is
just the ornamental aliam
species um and it got that common name
because the leaves are flat like garlic
um but it's a different species and
it it never hoods cloves it just stays
as like a little green
onion so um I've never eaten them I've
never had the desire but I don't you
know I would stick with the the known
stuff I'm sure you could eat them but I
don't think there's going to be much
flavor to them okay well that's all the
time we have today thank you so much
harlene we really appreciate all your
expertise and seeing the latest research
that probably isn't even so you were the
first all of you to see some of that
research so thank you very much and we
hope to see you next week I'm your
presenter next week so um thank you
again for joining us and please fill out
the survey that will be in your inboxes
in a couple minutes so thank you
everyone