[Music]
well hey everybody peace and blessings
to everyone so today I'm going to give
you guys the update on how the garden is
doing also on today I am going to plant
the seed potatoes so I need to hear up
and get them going um before we're past
that Mark so it's the middle of February
here in San Antonio and I want to go
ahead and get these seed potatoes
planted um so this is a seed potato
Harvest
blend uh it has like the purple potatoes
the yellow potatoes and the red so we're
going to go ahead and get these planted
and I'm going to give you an update on
how everything else has been growing on
in the garden all right so everything is
going along pretty good we have some
cabbages over here that are really
forming um the oregano it's been
thriving it with stod the the winter U
when we had a little Frost our th plant
is growing back also the Mexican mint is
growing back and we have cilantro uh we
also have a little parsley that's
peeking through over there unfortunately
our basil died but it was expected so
we're not too sad about that over here
we have more cabbin look at these
cabbages they are growing and really
fing I have to get out here and treat
them again because you as you can see
you have the little bugs that's kind of
wearing them out also we have broccoli
look at the broccoli is
growing the broccoli is coming through
so I'm excited we have a lot of broccoli
heads that are growing also over here we
have the brussel sprouts that are
growing as well you can look down in
there these are brussels sprout plants
um uh we have some more over here and
then we have more broccoli that's
growing so I'm excited about the
broccoli all right and so over here we
have more
cabbages um we have some radishes that
I'm going to harvest today because they
have been in here too long I think I've
let them I've let them get too big so uh
but the spinach is doing well look at
that spinach the spinach is doing very
well we have some more cabbage over
here um we have some
lettuce and we have some carrots so
everything has been growing pretty good
now over here we have a we have some
beets that are growing um we have
our turnup greens so I am going to
harvest some turnips today if you look
down in there we have quite a few of
these turnup greens that are they're
ready they can be harvested if you look
there this is like a a
trio so I'm going to harvest some and
then plant some more seeds the only
thing I don't like is the turnips are
pretty good but big but the leaves we
didn't really get a lot of leav growth
but had to get out here and treat it
because these bugs are really eating
them up and so here go the collge
they're growing and then we have some
Swiss short over there so if
anybody I have idea what I can put
down
for these
greens um what can stop these you know
the bugs that are eating them up please
let me know all right so I'm going to
plant the potatoes over here in these
two boxes and then I put some uh
compost um dirt that I already had I put
it in here and then I'm just going to
mix it with some miracle Grill and some
other top saw dirt that I have all right
going to put the dirt in here
this is just some pot and so it's not
that
expensive I feel this
well since these are
full I am just going to
put so let see we
hold all
right so this looks like a red
one so I'm going to
put that down there and cover it
up another
one right
there put this one over
here I'm not putting them too far down
but just down
enough I don't no I'm not supposed to
put which way I supposed to
putant there a
hole I'm going put the
roots that one right
there we have another
one right
here this
here
and them up so I have one
more so I'm thinking about the this one
I'm just going to put this one in
another
box
and go from
there all right so I have another box
this is the biggest one I can find it's
a little smaller than the H or to but
it's going to
work go ahead and
put this side in
here so this almost fills this box up so
I'm going to add some of the
[Applause]
put the too there
all right so here's the tuer I'm going
put this one right here in the middle
cover it
up and then I'm going to water so what
I'm also going to do I'll probably get
another bag up there just to feel these
all the way up to the
top I'm go ahead and
under M estim the
water coming all the way over here
so once they store gr I just use
the get the water in from
now do this hopefully it doesn't miss
the box so I wonder should I put a
plastic EG in here anyway
oh we're going to see it's going to be
TR the Box start
breaking think that should
little but oh
well we going to go from here and see
how
yeah all right so I got the potatoes
done so next thing I'm going to do um
probably tomorrow I have some seedlings
I'm going to go ahead and start
indoors um so um you know when the
spring kick in so still got a little
time but I'm going to go ahead and start
them indoors so I can transplant them um
in six weeks so thank you guys for
watching my um Gardon Channel God bless
you eat what you grow and have a
growthful day
[Music]