I started my journey actually at South
Dakota State University and ended up
getting a degree in botany because I
like to study of plants then I spent
about 20 years with the USDA and most of
it was ARS and doing research I was the
technician under the research around the
Cheyenne I was born in Brookings South
Dakota and so we focused on no-till
mainly diverse rotations and how they
impact crops and then that transitioned
into a lot of cover crop research well
ahead of the popularity I think we're
seeing with cover crops especially in
South Dakota
the agronomist for Olsen custom farms
now I'm based out of Hendricks Minnesota
but we've have farms in in South Dakota
as well before I got to the farm they
had acquired a small seed business and
so they started raising some certified
oats and spring wheat with me joining
the farm we had other crops like
sunflowers and then of course corn
soybeans a little bit of alfalfa hay and
then they have forages that are devoted
to the to the feedlot operation and so
one of the the first opportunities that
I've seen joining Olson custom farms was
to stretch our rotation out to take that
power diversity and make it work for us
because it's free it just involves more
management but that's what I'm that the
farm for is to help with that management
and execute those cropping plans so now
we're trying to move from not just corn
soybeans but rather a corn soybean small
grain a cereal crop right now that's old
spring wheat or winter rye so now we've
got this diverse set of situation where
the corn sees a different previous crop
but also a different moisture balance in
the soil the community that we set up
for it in the soil with the cover crops
I look for many benefits to come out of
it it's a little too early to tell but
since I come from research and I've seen
it be successful I'm pretty confident
that we can be successful
and like any management we have to take
an account the cost of our cover crop
seed and what it cost the seed but I'm
looking at it that will offset those
expenses with reductions in applied in
organic fertilizer that's my goal for
the farm is to bring our level of
applied in organic fertilizer reduce it
by forty to fifty percent that would be
a good goal it's an ambitious goal but I
think it's very attainable
[Music]