[Music]
we explain why the Blue Planet lacks
water water is fun water is a necessity
for all life on Earth some even predict
it to be the new oil but why isn't there
enough for
everyone even though our Blue Planet
consists of 70% water we can only use an
extremely small part of it as drinking
water 97% of all water is salty and 2%
is Frozen the the remaining 1% could
still be sufficient for everyone but
unfortunately its distribution is pretty
unfair today more than 700 million
people have no access to clean water
like Aza who has to walk for miles to
collect it and carry it home while Tim
in another part of the world simply
turns on the tap he uses more than 100 L
per day what's behind this
Injustice in agriculture groundwater and
water from marshlands is used to
irrigate the fields in countries with a
dry and hot climate this is especially
problematic once pumped out of the
ground the water doesn't come
back on top climate change and pollution
make matters worse the local population
must live on dried out
land and as the world's population grows
the demand for water is growing too the
UN estimates that in
2025 demand will be up to 40% higher
than it is today this Bears the
potential for conflicts about the use of
water
resources governments and societies need
to change their attitudes towards water
water systems infrastructure and
Technology must be upgraded and new
Frameworks for intelligent Water
Resource Management and conservation
have to be forged because there is no
life without water