so there's gonna be five simple steps to
raising mealworms
[Music]
hello and welcome to wholesome roots
today i'm gonna talk to you about
mealworms 101
mealworms are an easy to grow
high-protein treat for many different
types of animals we raise them for our
chicken quail and other poultry some
people use them for their lizard or
other reptiles so first off you need to
know the life cycle
of the meal worm so the egg will hatch
out into a teeny tiny little worm or
otherwise known as larva that worm will
grow and shed its skin
and grow some more and shed its skin
multiple times in this portion of its
leg then when it reaches a full size it
will turn into a pupa in this stage
a lot of transformation takes place it's
kind of like the chrysalis of a
butterfly once the transformation is
complete inside of the pupa and that
larva has turned into a beetle
internally it will shed its exoskeleton
again one more time and turn into a
beetle this beetle will then
continue the life cycle by breeding and
laying more eggs
lots of different people who raise
mealworms keep them in separate
containers they'll keep the larva in one
the pupa in another and the beetle in
the other the reason why they do this is
because
some people find it easier that way
because it's easier to harvest the worms
when they're at full size and some
people are concerned that the beetles
will eat some of the larva but i have
found that it's a much simpler way to
keep all three stages of the life cycle
together as long as it's managed well
and you harvest your worms and don't
allow the beetles to become too high in
numbers you'll be fine and the nice
thing is is my chickens actually will
eat the beetles too so when my beetle
numbers become too high i will harvest
some of them and feed them to the
chickens as well so there's going to be
five simple steps to raising mealworms
one you want a container
we use this old fish tank just because
it's what we have we like to use things
around the homestead that are things
that we already have
it also can just be a rubbermaid tote
this i like because i can see through it
easily and check on the colony without
removing any lids or anything
so i do keep a screen lid on top once i
have the colonies established in
the tank i do want to protect it from
anything getting in
so make sure that your container is
clean and sanitized we sanitize with
vinegar wipe it clean make sure it's
super dry before you add any of the
bedding or the mealworm then you're
going to want to add a food source
we have this food source right here it's
bedding and food and it's just
wheat bran so something i like to think
about as a analogy for the mealworm
feeding and bedding is soil layers so i
do this as my foundation
layer it's at the bottom and i pour it
in
and then i add my mulch
i put oatmeal over the top then
i add slices of potatoes
[Music]
so the food
brand cereal
is fine oatmeal is fine
i've even had to feed them layer pellets
or quail food when i was in a pinch and
it worked great we add slices of carrots
potatoes apples but you have to make
sure that you keep an eye on these
slices that they don't get moldy
or you will have to definitely remove
them another thing to keep in mind that
it's extremely important with your feed
that you give
the
mealworm colony is that if you get wheat
bran or oatmeal from anywhere no matter
what the source you will want to put it
into your freezer for 48 hours before
you feed it to them to kill any
active
mites or moths mites and moths are quite
commonly found in these food products
that are sold in the store for people so
it is a good idea to make sure that you
freeze off any of those pests that might
be already in
these containers
so other pests that you want to look out
for is going to be any kind of crawling
critters that might get in here i've had
spiders take over and sometimes that's
good
because it keeps anything else out but i
have found beetles in the spider
webs in the past so i try to keep those
pests out of my tank
now a lid with a wire top is not going
to completely keep them out so you will
have to keep an eye out for it and you
will want to provide a top for your
colony because you don't want any other
critters
or rodents getting in there and trying
to eat your colony getting a great
healthy colony is our third step of
success and
making sure that you start out with some
really nice mealworms now some people
will
sell you
the all three stages but that is not
necessary and if you have a friend who
lives nearby that is raising mealworms
they are very likely to provide you with
all three stages no problem if you just
have when you purchase a container of
mealworms online they are going to
arrive in the mail here's ours
oh yeah
they definitely arrived alive
give you a little snack
fresh out of the mailbox i want to make
sure that they're
i have enough hydration give them a
little slice of potato
i'll leave a link down below to the
amazon purchase that this was made from
so if you just have the larva stage they
are going to continue on their journey
and pupate those pupa will turn into
beetles and the life cycle will be
re-made for you
so it's been a couple of weeks since we
received our order and we already have
all three stages when they arrived they
came in this small container with holes
on top i poured them into this container
so that i could give them more food and
room to begin their process of growing
as you can see
we already have plenty of pupa
and the beetles
are in here too
i have a couple of them
that have pupated out into beetles so
don't feel like you have to spend the
extra money on all three stages when you
can just get the larva and have great
success as well when handling your
mealworm and their colony once they're
getting established there's going to be
a lot of feces in this material and it's
going to be very dusty so you will want
to use gloves
and a mask if you're sensitive
so step number four is monitor your
colony you're going to want to
constantly check those potatoes and
apples for any silent mold and remove it
right away along with any bedding that
becomes moldy from touching it you're
going to want to watch and see if your
ratio of beetles becomes too high and
they do start to consume larvae that is
something that you will have to address
you can remove the beetles and feed
those to chickens if you have chickens
that will eat the beetles that works out
really well for me
or you can freeze them in your freezer
for a humane way of disposing of them
you'll also want to be watching out for
any signs of pests the most common pests
with these guys is going to be grain
mites which are itty bitty tiny
creatures that you can hardly see but
you'll know when they're there because
they will start crawling up the side of
the container
trust me
i know from experience and then the next
biggest pest that you're going to see in
there is going to be pantry moths
and that is something that you don't
want getting in your
pantry stores so you definitely want to
keep on top of it you'll see little
moths flying so then it comes to our
fifth and final step and that is
harvesting your mealworms
one of my favorite methods is to feed
them so
they love the potatoes apples and
carrots even though their primary food
is their cereal or oatmeal at the bottom
they do really love their potatoes
carrots and apples
and will probably be located right
underneath that potato when you go to
pick it up so what i'll do is i'll
remove all the potato and apple slices
out of the container for a day or two
and then i will add them in on the day
that i'm planning on harvesting some
mealworm
and i'll put them in in the morning and
that afternoon when i pick up the potato
i find a whole colony of crawling little
wormies ready for harvest so i just
knock those into a separate container
and voila i can feed them to the
chickens the quail and any of our other
poultry
this is a
low-cost high-protein way to supplement
your animal's feed we love watching them
grow and transform and my kids have made
this one of their favorite projects they
love to feed them the apple slices they
love to harvest them they love to feed
them to the chickens so it's a great
project for a homesteading family to
get this colony started and start having
a more affordable supplement for your
chicken treats thank you for watching
we'll see you next time on wholesome
roots