it was a cloudy and overcast morning at
UK's research and education center which
made for comfortable temperatures not
usually the case for July in Western
Kentucky
but welcomed by the crop scouting teams
the eight high school teams consisting
of four to six members rotated through
ten stations in the competition ranging
from soil properties weeds corn
agronomics and more in a very hands-on
event so insects disease we're teaching
them how to scout fields work with some
of our soil issues and also some basic
corn soybean agronomics as well because
there is a younger grouse stage do you
think that Kirsten why said the
competition is very similar to what a
professional crop scout or consultant
would do in their job and gives UK a
chance to showcase its facilities we
think this is a great opportunity for
the University of Kentucky to interact
with high school students particularly
students that are interested in
agriculture of course I did some
scouting when I was back in high school
in college
Bobby Schmitt was taught agriculture at
Livingston County for 25 years was
excited about the opportunity to bring
his students to the competition and be
so close to home I've been over here
several times for field days and stuff
and if nobody's ever been here it's
really a neat place because you see so
much on relatively a small acreage I
think it's a good good representation of
West Kentucky are the soils that we have
and a lot of growing conditions you
mentioned some of the insects Schmidt
liked the fact that contest involved UK
specialists guiding the students through
the stations UK faculty graduate
students and interns all were involved
in the competition and the students in
the contest said they learned a lot
going in like
staging corn and like which sage it
comes in and like I learned the same
with like soybeans I got to learn like
where you look at the plant like which
node you need to look at and different
stuff like that so that was pretty cool
I believe it will give me foresight for
the future to kind of see what I'd be
getting into like taking that college
courses saying well hey you know this is
kind of what this is about you know give
me just a little bit of information
before you dive deep into that big
terminology officials at UK's research
and education center hope to make the
competition an annual event from the
University of Kentucky College of
Agriculture Food and environmental
reporting
[Music]