about 3 years ago I bought the paperpot
transplanter system to use in my no till
deep compost mulch Market Garden the
first time I used a paper pot
transplanter it was for beets and I
threw the tray in the trees back there I
was pissed I couldn't believe I spent
$3,000 on this thing and the first time
I used it wasn't burying them the the
plants were getting twisted around each
other basically it was Beats so like as
the Paper Pot transplanter unraveled
they were a little bit leggy and it just
tore the plants apart it was a complete
disaster but my friend Paul from
Mountain Roots Farm has been a good
Mentor to me over the years called him
talked to him about it I was like man
this thing sucks like what the heck and
he's like ah yeah man you just got to
keep practicing right like it's a tool
and it takes system there has to be some
sort of soil work to get the tool to
work properly I I suppose everybody's
going to have different soil conditions
but in this video I'm going to show you
the exact system that I use to use the
Paper Pot transplanter in a no till deep
compost mulch system so in my last video
I showed you guys how I start seedlings
in my basement under grow lights using
the quick click drop seeder into the
paper pot transplanter system so these
are the same seedlings it's a couple
weeks later now and today we're going to
transplant these into my noil garden and
I'm just going to show you the whole
process and how it works in my system
they've been sitting out here for about
2 weeks now leaving them sit out here
for a couple of weeks before I actually
plant them into the garden helps them to
harden off so that
they'll survive when I plant them it has
to be soaking wet or else when you like
start to use the transplanter and pull
it these paper chains are just going to
rip so you want to saturate the whole
tray in water before you plant it and
that's something that like nobody ever
told me before I used it the first time
I used the Paper Pot transplanter I just
took my tray and then I tried to
transplant it and they just kept ripping
the whole way down and I couldn't find
any good resources to tell me why but I
learned that that's why you have to
saturate the whole TR
in water and the way that I do that this
is like a 18x 26 in uh commercial cookie
sheet basically but it just happens to
fit these Paper Pot trays perfectly so I
just sit the trays in that and then I
fill it up with water and then I just
let them bottom water and soak all that
water up and it doesn't take long these
things soak the water up super fast and
so I'll just let that sit there and soak
up the water while I get everything set
up with the transplanter to plant and
then we'll come back and grab that in a
minute so then the typical bed flip
method that I'm using is we clean out
the previous crop I String up the beds
to keep the beds straight and looking
nice we broad for the beds so we put
about three wheelbarrows of compost on
every bed flip that we're going to use
the pap poot transplanter next on and
then I used the never syn icono class
tilter to smooth out that top layer of
compost so it's never actually like
tilling the soil at all it just like
gets all the chunks out of the compost
sometimes it's chunky and those chunks
will get like jammed up in the furrow
the Paper Pot transplant so you need to
make sure that your compost is nice
broken down and fine or it's going to
cause you problems you can't have rocks
in there and then after we tilt it then
we come through with just a regular like
garden rake that you would use to rake
your garden with leaves and we make it
nice and smooth so we make kind of a
raised nice smooth planting bed at a
compost while never actually tilling the
soil and we use a broad Fork to just
make sure that the soil is not compacted
I find that the broad Fork uh just kind
of helps the furrow get through the
compost and be able to just kind of
barely dig into the actual native soil
so that the roots are getting into the
soil but then the actual plants are just
like kind of planted through the compost
and then it grows down through the
compost into the native soil and the
compost basically just a mulch on top of
the soil and then generally after we'll
Harvest a bed like that like these were
Paper Pot transplanted right right and
then we've got two rows of Salen NOA
lettuce on the sides of tomatoes once
these beds are terminated we'll just uh
not broad fork or anything and just
plant arugula probably we'll just direct
seed arugula and then so that's kind of
like the bed prep system we broad fork
and apply new compost whenever we're
going to be using the paper pot
transplanter and then those beds are are
good because the next crops we're not
going to be planting salanova lettuce
over and over in the same beds we're
going to be doing like a rugula or
spinach or tomatoes or whatever the next
crop is it doesn't require the Paper Pot
transplanter so we're really only broad
forking if we're using the paperpot
transplanter just kind of make sure that
we're breaking up the compaction because
I just find if I don't then I regret it
you just need to do the proper bed prep
basically but then you have to have your
plants or your seedlings like exactly
the right size there's a perfect size so
for me I start my trays of salanova
lettuce and that's basically the only
crop I'm using a paper pot transplanter
for I don't really find it to be
profitable for a lot of other things cuz
there's a huge cost you don't want to
use a Pap poot transplanter if they're
too small wheels like bury the furrow it
like will bury the plant but then if
they're too big the bottom sides of the
tray The Roots will get tangled with
each other so when you drag it the roots
are not letting it unravel correctly so
while it does transplant well like that
because the furrow can close the
overgrown seedling in a little bit it
won't unravel well so it pops up out so
all I do is just kind of you have to
like them apart and like kind of stage
them and then I can pull it and then
it's not really a big deal and it goes
pretty fast like that but it's like it
took me some time to learn that and
that's something that nobody really
talks about on YouTube videos I just was
left to kind of learn these things by
myself and observation and there's
adjustments on the tool to adjust it up
and down you can adjust the the wheels
you have to fool with the adjustments on
like the depth of how deep you're
planting it how it berries the seedlings
after they're transplanted into the
furrow and that's going to be different
for everybody's soil conditions I have
mine set up so I just leave it the same
I don't fool with it but it took a lot
of fooling with to get it just right I
had a bed of cilantro which had been
Paper Pot transplanted so I just went
and like cleaned out the whole bed of
cilantro I left like the roots and
everything right in the ground so I just
like cut the bottoms off cleared out the
bed I didn't put any additional compost
or anything and I just tried to drag the
paperpot transplanter through but it
didn't work very good because it get
caught on the roof RO system of the
cilantro to use the paper pot
transplanter after a crop like cilantro
didn't work very good for me cilantro
just has like a really big root system
but for me to like use the paper pot
transplanter after I harvest the bed of
carrots like that's ideal right