what are your thoughts on sustainability
and this kind of sustainability movement
in agriculture how would you kind of
frame that up well that's a great
question because I'm also uh on the
Texas peanut producers board and I'm on
a couple of committees that do
sustainability now so it's so creative
where A's been you know we used to do
all chemical fertilizers and even on my
operation now we do a lot of manure or
compost my son actually does a lot of
compost where we don't do any kind of
natural fertilizer so we've spread 3 to
four tons on our peanuts which that's a
sustainability issue is chemical
fertilizers you know and we use them on
our Organics down here also you know our
compost