in this video we're going to cover
trenching laying pipe for your sprinkler
system back filling and installing
sprinkler heads let's get started
[Music]
the installation we're recording today
is happening in Texas
here we use schedule 40 PVC pipe for the
main lines in class 200 after the valves
your area may require different
materials so check with your local
authorities to make sure you're using
the recommended materials for your area
the Pikes you see here mark the location
for sprinkler heads and valves use
marking spray to lay out where you want
your inches here you can see our
installer marking the location of a
valve box use the different color than
the ones marking your utilities to avoid
confusion
speaking of which remember to call 8 1 1
before you do they'll send someone out
to mark the property with flags or paint
to indicate where utility lines are
buried this is always your first step in
a turning project you're going to need a
variety of tools for this project
including shovels trowels rakes and PVC
pipe cutters you might want to check out
our video titled necessary sprinkler
installation tools for this installation
we're digging trenches 6 to 8 inches
deep the area where we are installing
this system is not prone to hard freezes
areas that are prone to hard freezes may
need deeper trenches to protect piping
you should contact your local authority
for recommendations notice how clean
this crew member is taking out sections
of side this team always puts the sod on
one side of the trench and the Philbert
on the opposite side this will pay off
big one backfilling notice how flat and
even the bottom of these trenches are
that's ideal strive to get your trenches
flat like this
one of the crew is pre assembling the
swing joints to the tease and sprinkler
heads this is so much easier and quicker
than trying to assemble this in the
trench while on your knees hunched over
it saves both time and your back routes
can be a serious challenge if you're
lucky you can tunnel under some of them
however you may need to put some muscle
into it swinging an axe will pull off
the heavy artillery and go at it with a
chainsaw
please take safety precautions when
using an axe or chainsaw
[Music]
when digging in a flowerbed the trick is
to do this little disruption to
establish plants and shrubs as possible
trenches should be planned in such a way
as to minimize the amount of digging
necessary right here's where our 12 inch
pop-up will go this crewman is using a
sharpshooter to dig down about a foot to
accommodate the height of the head the
top of the head should be level with the
ground our technician is cutting links
of pipe that will be heading out to the
valves and sprinkler heads it's optimal
to have several pipes utilizing the same
trench and it's perfectly fine to have
pipes laying on top of each other he's
using extra bits of PVC to keep the pipe
out of the dirt while he applies primer
and cement quickly push the fittings on
to the pipe after applying the cement
hold in place a few seconds wipe away
the excess remember cement as a solvent
wiping away excess prevents it from
continuing to weaken the exposed
portions of the pipe PVC pipe often
comes with flared ends this allows you
to connect pipe without having to add a
coupler you could use cut off nipple
risers to save some money but you'd
still want to use swing joints near the
driveway and street so that if a vehicle
drives over the sprinkler head you don't
end up with a brake
additionally swing joints make it much
easier to place a sprinkler exactly
where you want it and it makes it simple
to adjust the height of the head should
the soil eventually cover the head
carefully fill soil in around the
sprinkler head remember to pack some
soil underneath the head to prevent it
from sinking down do remember that
you'll need to run wiring before
covering up any trenches that go from
your valves back to your controller
wires should be tucked into the piping
to provide protection for lawn equipment
and animals
[Music]
be careful when backfilling not to hit
your pipe with the edge of a shovel or
you'll likely be repairing leaks
and now we're replacing those sections
of side care taken while digging the
trenches and backfilling allows your
yard to recover and look great quickly
the tamper helps get the soil back to
level
[Music]
Fila flushing the system strength ler
heads
often arrive with a flush cap in place
it allows the dirt and debris to wash
out of the system while also quickly
testing your new system our team is
installing nozzles for this installation
we're using Rain Bird our bands and H
evens the H II bands are high efficiency
spray nozzles their patterns can be
adjusted from 0 to 360 degrees they also
emit large droplets making them about 40
percent more efficient than standard
sprays our bands are rotary heads that
shoot out fingers of water rotary
nozzles like this are incredibly
efficient
they met large water droplets which
prevents Wynn from carrying the weight
of water this means about 30 percent
more water reaches the plant roots
compared to normal rotors the our vans
are numbered 14 18 and 24 that number is
the maximum throw distance and feet to
install a nozzle pull up the head by the
flush cap while holding the riser in the
up position unscrew the flush cap put in
the filter and screw on the nozzle then
adjust the direction of the spray head
by turning the pop-up riser that
ratcheting sound is not hurting the
pop-up head they're meant to be turned
like this here you'll see two sprinkler
heads installed close together that
wasn't a mistake
one of these heads is for the flowerbeds
only and the other is for the lawn this
allows separate watering schedules for
the beds and for the lawn the 12-inch
pop-up allows the spray to shoot over
the plantings in the bed while the lawns
typically only need a 4-inch papa now
our team is adjusting each of the
nozzles for distance and pattern for
distance you want head-to-head coverage
that means throw the sprinkler should
reach the next sprinkler head this
creates even coverage remember sprinkler
Warehouse has everything for your
irrigation needs so your trees lawn
flowerbeds and gardens are lush and
beautiful and if you have any questions
about our products chat with one of our
amazing customer service agent
on sprinkler warehouse.com they really
know their stuff and they will get you
squared away subscribe to our YouTube
channel for helpful tips tutorials and
general sprinkler instruction I'm Duane
Smith for sprinkler warehouse
professional quality rock bottom prices
[Music]