hi everyone this is a read it told
myself arm this video is about rainwater
collection so this is a Quonset hut
building that is 40 feet wide by 80 feet
long and it's right beside our seedling
production greenhouse and we have very
saline well water so we're catching
rainwater off of one half of the Quonset
hut with this gutter just simply
anchored into the side of the Quonset
with concrete anchors I think we
initially did it with lead slugs and
ultimately had to replace them with the
expansion bolt type of concrete anchors
but now it it holds pretty well and
whenever it rains the Quonset structure
drips into the trough and then the first
step here at the outlet it goes down and
there's a T facing downwards in the ABS
I think it's four inch EVs looks like
three or four three apparently and that
T goes into a dead-end shunt pipe which
runs down and down and down in this
little trench always graded and then
here's the outlet of that little shunt
and you probably can't see but
down here is a tiny hole drilled in it
and that allows this what's called a
roof washer or a first flush diverter it
fills up with the first dirty pollen and
dust filled first flush of water that
lands on roof comes down down the trough
through the tea flows down into the
shunt pipe fills the first flush
diverter and then thereafter the water
can continue on into the sump for
transfer but that first dirty flow of
water goes into the first flush diverter
and then in between rainfall events it
trickles out through the tiny hole in it
so once the diverter is full water flows
over here into a sump a nylon stocking
as a basic filter for particulate and
then ordinary cheap sump pump there's
also a stock water here in their stock
tank water heater that we use in the
early spring to thaw out the block of
ice that forms in here in the winter so
that we can start running the rainwater
collection system earlier rather than
having to wait until the ice thaws
naturally so then the sump pump runs up
through the blue pipe and blue pipes
attached to the filler with a cam
coupler this one here is overflow should
we ever get more than 2,100 gallons so
this is a 9,000 litre opaque reservoir
which is about 3000 gallons and for
every rainfall event here based on the
roof surface area if we get a millimeter
of rain we get a hundred liters of water
for 10 millimeters of rain we get a
thousand litres of water so 10
millimeters of rain is like half an inch
not quite probably three quarters of an
inch of rain is to just know it's like
7/16 of an inch of rain so you have to
do 2.5 millimeters of water would be an
inch for an inch of rain we get 2500
liters of water which is about I don't
know 20 500 litres is I can't figure
what that is in gallon but you can see
care of this morning's condensation that
there's currently between is about 500
gallon of water sitting in the rainwater
tank and the ball valve really outlet
open and this hose runs over here
and into the green house in the green
house comes in through the wall and it's
one of the two possible sources for this
jet pump which is our booster pump to
provide pressure here in the greenhouse
or watering all of our greenhouse stuff
so inside the greenhouse installation
looks like this there is a an indoor
reservoir here a thousand litre cube and
then there's that this connection
between the cube and the inbound
rainwater and the jet pump so that you
can choose which one you're using in the
really early spring we start by filling
the cube and using that until the
weather is warm enough to let us open
the valve and use the rainwater system
so that's all of our greenhouse water
supply for our seedling greenhouse and
it makes a huge difference to the
quality and health of our seedlings to
be able to use rainwater rather than our
saline well water which certain things
like tomatoes or even more particularly
peppers these are happy looking peppers
because we've had lots of rain and
rainwater this spring but peppers are
super sensitive to the salinity needed
the disaster when we don't have rain
water for them so this is a April stage
April 27th this is what our seedling
greenhouse looks like in late April
I'll do another video about this
overhead washing thing which we call
this flying sis tune do that in a
separate video
voila