This video focuses on general safety
practices for operating farm loaders and
skid steer loaders. Tractor rollovers
are the primary cause of farm accidental
deaths and many of the rollovers occur
when operating tractors with loader
attachments. Rollovers can occur when
the bucket strikes an obstruction such
as a truck box or embankment. Operating
loaders with the bucket up also
increases the risk of
rollovers. The most important way to
prevent serious accidents with loaders
and skid steer loaders is to equip them
with rollover protection devices or ROS
and make sure you don't exceed the
maximum load limits as described in
operator's manuals. Be sure the tire
spacing and rear ballast is correct
before using a loader. Always wear a
seat belt when operating a tractor and
loader or skid steer
loader. Loaders overturn easier if the
bucket is raised too high when loaded,
especially when turning or on uneven
surfaces. Understand that the center of
gravity with the load changes with the
load in different positions. The center
of gravity of a load lifted high
increases the likelihood of a rollover.
A topheavy condition can lead to a
backward or side overturn. The
likelihood of rollovers or tipping
increases if you raise and lower loads
too fast and or change the lifting rate.
Always stop loaders gradually when
raising or lowering
loads. Be particularly careful when
lifting loads around people. Loads
falling on people are common causes of
accidents with loaders. If you must move
loads around people, be sure to fasten
the loads with ropes, chains, or cables.
Turning uphill on a slope increases the
risk of overturns because the center of
gravity moves to the rear of the
implement. Turning too fast on a
downward slope may also cause an
overturn because the center of gravity
is transferred forward. While driving a
tractor and loader on public roads,
carry the loads close to the ground to
aid visibility and to keep the center of
gravity closer to the
ground. Allow for the additional
equipment length while
turning. Be careful to balance load so
the weight is evenly distributed and the
load is stable. Avoid carrying loads
wider than the tractor.
Use flashing warning lights and
slowmoving vehicle emblems on loader
tractors whenever operating on public
roads. And never operate a tractor with
a loader on public roads after dark. Do
not handle large round bales unless the
loader is equipped with an approved bail
handling
attachment. Using a regular front-end
loader to move bales poses a problem
because the bail can roll out of the
bucket and down the loader arms onto the
operator. Do not lift round bales with
the standard loader unless you have
proper bail restraining
devices. Tractor rollover protective
structures are not intended to protect
against falling bales. Remember to keep
the bail as low as possible while
moving. Always engage the parking brake
or place the transmission in park. Lower
the loader to the ground. Shut off the
engine and remove the ignition key
before servicing loaders. Know and avoid
the pinch points and rotating parts
before doing maintenance on loaders. Do
not walk or perform any service under a
raised loader, bucket, or attachment
unless it is securely blocked or held in
position. Escaping hydraulic fluid can
penetrate skin causing serious injury.
Avoid the hazard of high-pressure fluids
by relieving pressure before
disconnecting hydraulic lines.
Tighten all connections before applying
pressure. Search for leaks with a piece
of
cardboard. Following safety precautions
does take a little more time, but being
safe is your number one commodity.