[Music]
the irrigation of the imbo nord
a project under the institutional and
operational support program for the
agricultural sector payoza
implemented by annabelle for the
burundian population
with funding from the kingdom of belgium
and with technical support
from cher situated in the heart of
central africa
the natural region of the imbo nord is
located in northwestern burundi
along the border with the democratic
republic of congo
south of rwanda and north of lake
tanganyika
this region doesn't have any large town
and the vast majority of the population
is rural and lives on agriculture
and animal husbandry the imbe plain
benefits from abundant water resources
and fertile soils
enhanced by the construction of
irrigation networks
several decades ago
how does the irrigation network work
[Music]
a run of the river diversion intake
feeds a primary canal by gravity
which serves several irrigation blocks
in which water is distributed from
so-called secondary
tertiary and finally portonary canals
in order to cover as widely as possible
the entire area to irrigate
finally any excess water is collected
via a drain in order to be discharged
into the rivers downstream
the imbo-nord irrigation project
[Music]
the topography and hydrography of the
imbo have guided the organization of the
area into small holder farms since the
1950s
with the aim of promoting food and
industrial crops
but it was only in the 1970s that
irrigation networks were built to
intensify
development of the smallholder farms
this potential was however strongly
threatened in the late 2000s
due to poor maintenance and management
of the networks
resulting from the political instability
of the region during the 1990s
after its rehabilitation in 2015
the inbo nord irrigation project
benefits approximately 33 000 people
out of the 200 000 identified in the
project's beneficiary districts
it covers 2745 hectares
through more than 150 kilometers of
canal networks
fed by the niyama ghana and the near
kagunda rivers
two tributaries of the rosisi which
connects kivu to tanganyika
in addition to the irrigation and
drainage infrastructure
this project also enabled the
rehabilitation of nearly 30 kilometers
of feeder roads
as well as the post-harvest and storage
infrastructure of local development
cooperatives
for a total amount of approximately 10
million euros worth of works
works on the irrigation schemes ended in
may 2020
providing the population with a
functional irrigation system on the
whole project area
[Music]
the impact of the project on the
increase in agricultural productivity is
undeniable the areas under rice
cultivation have increased from
37 to 53 in the rainy season
and preliminary analysis indicate that
gross production per hectare
estimated at 4 000 euros before the
project
increased by more than 50 percent
[Music]
you