[Music]
in this country
in the last 70 years many achievements
are there
we have built businesses we have built
industry our scientists
are going to mars but of all these
things
the most significant achievement for us
is that our poor farmer
without any infrastructure hardly any
technology
just with traditional knowledge he's
been feeding
over a billion people this is not a
small thing
but we are taking that away from him
[Music]
today go out and ask anybody any farmer
how many of them want their children to
go into farming
it is less than 15 percent in another 20
years 25 years you will see
you will not know how to grow food in
this country
[Music]
in the last 12 years three lakh farmers
have committed suicide
even in a war that many people don't die
this is happening essentially because of
the investment
that goes into irrigation projects and
inability to access market i was just
talking to a tamilnadu farmer
who is 27 years of age he says he has
sunk nine
borewells in three and a half acres
he's never going to make it he has to
either sell the land
or run away from the village or hang
from a tree
it's very important that farming is made
into an attractive process
economically very attractive process so
that youth will get engaged
with farming this will only happen if
the irrigation and the marketing large
companies take it up
these two things can never be addressed
unless
there is scale one reason
why rural population can never scale up
is because the land holdings are so
small
with that level of land there is no way
to invest
or to organize or to you know be able to
leverage the market
there is no possibility so one solution
that we are asking for
is to form large-scale farmers producers
organizations
see if let us say ten thousand farmers
came together
as a farmer's producers organization if
ten thousand farmers came together
let's say on an average three four acres
if they own also it's 30 40 000 acres
this does not mean integration of land
just aggregation of irrigation
and aggregation of marketing forces and
aggregation
of value addition aspects of the
agricultural produce
if land is properly demarcated and
irrigated and
irrigation is managed by a company
nearly 500 million people
they will be available for ancillary
alternate
and value addition activity if you
provide the necessary skills and
opportunities
and bank loans and stuff you will spawn
a whole
revolution in the rural india
and if marketing is also taken over by
companies which are capable of doing
this far more focuses on just producing
food
it is very easy within three years time
that you can multiply agricultural
income
in terms of economic value at least by
300 percent
and we've been appealing to the
government because in this country
individual agricultural income is not
taxed
but if you organize yourself as a
farmer's producers organization you get
tax fortunately in this budget they
responded
that the tax on the fpo has been taken
away
we have a farmer's producer organization
here coimbatore i gave
three young people three smartphones
they just renegotiate the produce
every day with this the farmer's income
has doubled
[Music]
foreign
there are many things to be done on the
ground but if we handle this one thing
india's economy the agricultural economy
can go up 200 to 300
in a matter of three to four years time
an enhancement of rural economy means
enhancement of economic possibilities
for 65 percent of india's population
for this farmers produces organizations
to be successful
the corporates in the country the social
organizations
and above all the financial institutions
have to pitch in
and this will be lucrative for the
corporates this will be
very fulfilling for the social
organizations and
very safe and secure for the banking
sector
because this organization will benefit
all and above all
it will raise the level of life in rural
india
this can be a game changer if we do it
right
we are at a threshold where we can move
an entire massive population
which is nearly 700 million people from
one level of living to another
if we just do a few things right in the
coming five years
i request the leaders in every sector
that we mentioned to be a part of this
and see how we can make this happen in
this country you