[Music]
foreign
Revolution
human Enterprise technology and
innovation has shaped man's interaction
with land
with each successive phase the newer
less labor intensive and precise
methodologies have come to the fall
casting Point Conservation agriculture
conservation agriculture has three
principles
one talk of a minimum soil disturbance
second principle maximum soil cover
and then the third principle crop
rotation whereas the conventional
agriculture you just use the normal ways
of large tillage conservation
agriculture we advocate for it so that
we can minimize the costs of production
improve water retention and also you
have better yields the k-step crawl is
an expansion to the Arid and semi-arid
glands of the Kenya serial enhancement
program which became effective in 2014
through a partnership between the
government of Kenya the European Union
an international fund for agricultural
development
program follows a value chain approach
to support small holder Farmers
transitioning to commercial or
enterprise-based agriculture
case of cruel interventions have
provided a much needed boost in raising
Farmers yields
the concept of individuals offering
conservation agriculture Services known
as conservation agriculture service
providers has been the main vehicle in
rolling out this intervention
[Music]
by a conservation agriculture
uh
benefits
[Music]
five acres one day
ten thousand
whatever
it is yeah
2021 Johnny majority 354.
[Music]
99 600.
this farming technique is
revolutionizing small holder farming
with Farmers trained storage provided
and yields Bountiful the future looks
all conservation agriculture
foreign
[Music]