chinampas often referred to as floating
gardens were an ingenious agricultural
system developed by the Aztecs this
method involved creating small
rectangular plots of fertile land on
Shallow Lake beds Farmers constructed
these Gardens by piling mud and decaying
vegetation which resulted in highly
productive soil The chinampas increased
crop yield significantly allowing the
Aztecs to support a large population
crops like maze beans and squash thrived
in this environment benefiting from the
nutrient-rich sediment and water this
sustainable practice not only maximized
space but also showcase the Aztec's
Advanced understanding of irrigation and
ecosystem management laying the
groundwork for modern agriculture
techniques