[Music]
welcome to spotlight
i'm liz waid
and i'm bruce gulland
spotlight uses a special english method
of broadcasting
it is easier for people to understand
no matter where in the world they live
[Music]
imagine you are in a meeting at an
office building
your boss is speaking about next week's
project
then everyone takes a break for lunch
but you do not go to a restaurant or
store
instead
you exit the room
inside the walls of the building are
thousands of plants
some produce fruit
some produce salad greens
you grab a small plate
go to the wall
and pick the ingredients for your lunch
then you sit down under a tree and begin
to eat
you are 30 stories above the ground
this may seem like a fantasy
but this describes plans for a real
building called the jammu tower
it will be built in shenzhen
a city in southern china
and it may represent the future of
cities
today's spotlight is on the xianmu tower
and the future of cities
[Music]
the jianmu tower is a kind of vertical
farm
it is not the first vertical farm
vertical farming is already happening in
some countries
the country with the most vertical farms
is the united states
but there are vertical farms in many
countries
including japan
thailand
germany
the netherlands
and the uae
many of them grow
leafy green vegetables like lettuce and
kale
economic experts consider vertical
farming a growing market
but the jianmu
is one of the biggest planned projects
the jammu tower will be a tall glass
skyscraper
it will be 51 stories tall
it was designed to have offices and
apartments
but it is also designed to grow plants
each window will be filled with them
and the building will produce 270
000 kilograms of food every year
carlo roti is an italian architect
he designed the john moo tower
he named it after a tree from old
chinese myth
in the story
this tree connected heaven and earth
rati designed the tower for the chinese
grocery business
womart the tower will be wumar's new
headquarters
but
people can also rent rooms there
each person living in the jianmu tower
will have their own garden
but these are not just any gardens
they are vertical gardens
and the whole tower is one big vertical
farm
vertical farms are different than
traditional farms
traditional farms need soil to help
plants grow
but vertical farms use methods like
hydroponics
these methods give water and nutrients
to the plants directly
they do not need soil
vertical farming also lets farmers put
plants anywhere
in a vertical farm
farmers hang plants above and beside
each other on a wall
sometimes they use special lights to
help the plants grow
others like the john moo tower
hang plants by windows
the tower is so high
the plants get plenty of sun
doing this also has another benefit
when plants take in sunlight
they also take in heat
this helps control the climate in the
tower
so the tower will use less energy
vertical farms can be very efficient
traditional farms can only grow food at
some times of the year
but vertical farms can grow plants all
year
some vertical farms trap rain water
they can recycle the water they use
so droughts or reduced rain
do not affect the farms
the jiam mu tower will even get moisture
from the air
but vertical farms are a very good use
of space
they use far less land than a
traditional farm
brian mouladi is the manager of a
vertical farm
he told spectrum news
with the area of growing
you usually expand out
but with this
you are expanding up
you use less water and land
and you create less waste
it is a more sustainable way to farm
today
environmental experts encourage people
to use land efficiently
they want people to use natural
resources in the best way possible with
the least amount of waste
land efficiency will be especially
important as the world's population
grows dixon de palmier is a former
professor at columbia university
he invented the modern idea of vertical
farming
he talked to the website big think
we expect the human population to
increase
so over the next 40 years
you might have three billion more people
to feed
and you look around for the land
where that food will come from
and you do not find it
it is not there
so the biggest problem facing the global
population
is
where will the food for the next three
billion people come from
so it could come from some place other
than a traditional farm
the question is
could vertical farms
solve that problem
efficient use of space is important for
another reason
it helps fight climate change
according to the world health
organization
over 50 percent of the world lives in
cities
but most of our food does not come from
it comes from the country
this means that people living in cities
must ship food into the city
the food must come from even farther if
it is not in season
some fruits like avocados can travel for
thousands of miles before people buy
them
this uses a lot of fuel
food producers must also use
preservatives to keep the food fresh
this damages the environment
it also adds to climate change
vertical farming might help reduce these
problems
a traditional farm cannot fit in a city
but a vertical farm can
the john mu tower shows that even if you
live in the city
there can be a farm in your home
much of the food people eat in the tower
will come from the tower itself
they will not have to go anywhere to get
it
they will not have to ship as much food
in
and the food will be grown without
pesticides or preservatives
it will be better for the people
and the environment
vertical farming can even help in places
where people cannot grow food
fukushima is a city in japan
[Music]
it once had several nuclear power plants
in 2011 there was a big earthquake
the earthquake caused a tsunami
this huge wave hit japan and caused
terrible damage
the power plants in fukushima melted
down
this contaminated the area with
radiation
people could not go there without
getting very sick
people in japan were very scared of the
radiation
[Music]
they did not want to eat food grown
anywhere near fukushima
so the government funded vertical
farming
these new farms were safer than
traditional ones
they allowed people to have fresh food
without fear of radiation
vertical farming is not a perfect
solution to these problems
a vertical farm can cost a lot of money
to build and run
some vertical farms use lights to grow
plants
they also keep their plants in
controlled climates
this uses a lot of energy
it can even lead to more pollution
making climate change
worse but many people believe that they
can overcome these problems
they believe buildings like jammu tower
will help
carlo rati even believes that buildings
like this are the future of cities
he writes
this approach will be a big part of the
design of future
cities it is an answer to one of today's
most difficult building design
challenges
that is
how do we bring the natural world into
building design
would you live in a place like the john
mu tower
would you like to work in one
you can email us at contact
spotlightenglish.com
you can also find us on youtube facebook
instagram and twitter
the writer of this program was dan
chrisman
the producer was michio ozaki
the voices you heard were from the
united states and the united kingdom
all quotes were adapted for this
programme and voiced by spotlight
this program is called
vertical farming and the future of
cities
visit our website at
www.spotlightenglish.com
to download our free official app for
android and apple
devices we hope you can join us again
for the next spotlight program
goodbye
[Music]
you