hello my name is hans kandel i'm an
extension agronomist at ndsu
today's talk is about early planting of
soybeans
when we have a
nice season
when the temperatures are good and the
forecast is decent we can't try to start
planting soybeans in the early part of
may
in a large study that we have done with
investigating what farmers actually are
doing we found that about a third of a
bushel can be gained if you plant one
day earlier within that planting window
and the planting window is somewhere the
first week of may till the end of may
so in the experiment that i'm discussing
today we planted as soon as we could get
get into the field which was the first
week
of may and then we came in two weeks
later
so the objective of this study is to see
what is the difference when you plant
early versus planting late
one of the dangers that we can have when
you plant a little early is that there
can be a frost at the end of the
the beginning of the season like in may
this year we had a frost on the 28th of
may and that caused some of the plants
to be somewhat injured but in most of
the years if we plant in the second half
of may like starting what the 15th of
may the plants will take about a week
before they germinate and once they come
out of the ground the chance for frost
is limited so there's also a danger if
we plant too late
that we might have a frost
at the beginning of the september month
like we had last year in 2020 where
there was a frost at eight of ninth of
september
versus what is traditionally the frost
date around the 21st
so we can have the frost early in the
season
and late in the season but what we want
to do is maximize
the amount of sunlight during the time
that we plant till we harvest so in the
trials that we have done we have found
over about 18 different environments
that planting early gives about a seven
percent yield increase
however under certain conditions for
instance if you have tile and you can
get in about a week earlier than on the
non-tile there we saw between early
planting and late planting even at 28
difference in yield
now the benefit of early planting is
that we also have the opportunity to
select a variety that matures a little
bit later so we can capture the sunlight
from the beginning of the season all the
way to the end so we have maturity
groups the zero group if we just go one
or ten
one or two tenths of a point more
then we can capture more of the sunlight
at the end of the season
we found that when we look at three
tenths of a difference
difference in maturity that we can pick
up maybe six
percent in yield
so in the trial that we are looking at
we can see here behind me is the late
planted where there is still leaves
green and yellow leaves whereas if we
step a little bit to my right where we
planted a little bit earlier all the
leaves are already gone
so the difference between the plots that
we are looking at
is we have here uh
early maturing
variety
and we have a late maturing variety that
was planted a little bit
earlier
so the benefit here is looking at the
combination of early planting
and maturity
and if we combine those two
we know that if you have the opportunity
to plant early with that later maturing
we pick up some yield
so the other factor that is important of
maximizing yield is looking at the
interception of sunlight so we need to
have the right amount of plants within
the fields
our recommendation at ndsu is to have
about 150 000 established plants per
acre
the second factor that is important is
the row spacing
if we have white rows
we are losing some of the yield
potential because the sunlight is
penetrating into the canopy and reaches
the soil surface instead of leaves to
maximize yield
so in the combination of looking at
planting date
maturity and seeding rate
our trial shows that the highest yield
is obtained in the combination early
planting and late maturing
those plants will have the most
capacity to maximize yield however as i
mentioned
we need to get the crop mature before
the fall frost so selecting a maturity
still need to be within what is normally
for your region
maybe go one tenth or two tenths of a
maturity later but don't go too late
because then in the end we run into the
frost
here we see the 08 maturing where we
still see yellow and
green leaves on the plant laid planted
the same 08 maturity
if it was planted in that first week of
may we can see that the plant already
has dropped most of the leaves and will
be ready for harvest pretty soon
here is an example of a o5 maturity bean
that was planted about two weeks later
than the earliest we could get in this
one was planted roughly in the third
week of may in 2021
i'm comparing this one with a late
maturing variety
this is an 08 maturing variety that was
planted early
and as you can see the o8 has already
dropped its leave
and based on our previous research
we are anticipating that the early
planting
and the late maturing the 08
maturing variety will actually outfield
some of the early maturing material but
key is early planting to maximize the
sunlight that we
are receiving during the season