[Music]
jumbo kaributana to this organic
strawberry farm this is your farm in
geroge and i hope you're learning
something and welcome to our strawberry
farm we are located along waiaku a place
called odero corporation in this episode
i'm going to teach you how to manage
your pests and diseases organically
machacha let's do this
[Music]
the first pest and disease is what we
call
leaf spots
now this spot is caused by three ways
number one
through overhead irrigation
because when water gets in contact with
your leaves you're definitely going to
get leaf spots it can also be caused
because of rainfall
i can also because at extreme scenarios
because it's caused because of
red spider mites but you'll find red
spider mites for farmers who are growing
strawberries inside a greenhouse
this armed in an open field system is
because of the rain
so
how do we prevent and manage this thing
so if you're doing irrigation using
overhead irrigation i'll tell you this
stop doing overhead irrigation and
either adapt either to drip irrigation
or do it manually
in case you have this because because of
the rain all you have to do is just
prune off the leaves and throw them away
in case you're in a greenhouse and
you've actually been faced because of
red spider mites and of course the leaf
spots you need to use a biological
control
now remember this there's organic
they're synthetic and it's biological
let me just explain briefly what
biological is biological is using one
pest feeding on another pest or one
animal feed or another animal
think about the ladybird a ladybird will
feed on aphids that is biological so
there's a biological control from cooper
kenya that is called spidex
so the spidex is what you're going to
come and apply on your leaves and it's
actually live organisms that's actually
going to feed on your red spider mites
we have tested this
in different forms
of one farm is in cabarack another farm
is in
nanuki and the results we have actually
seen after two weeks
all your spider mites are actually dead
because the spy decks actually works and
see the good thing about it you could
hear what you're saying you can also
link you up with these farmers we'll
talk to them hear it from the horse's
mouth itself but with the spiders and
the leaf spots that is a done deal
the second pest and disease is actually
going to affect your throats there's
what you call anthrax and botritis so
your fruit will look like this honey
you're probably wondering ew looks very
bad yes it looks very bad it's a good
fruit the fruit started off very well
but because of anthracnose this actually
happens
so
for you to avoid anthracnose now
remember anthracnose is more like a
fungal disease
so and because once once the food gets
in touch with water
you're actually going to get such kind
of a challenge so you're probably
wondering somebody who's inside a
greenhouse they'll be smiling all the
way to the bank yes they will bother
about the outside farmer it's still okay
what i'd encourage you to do
get your greenhouse paper you see what
i've done the low tunneling system i'm
going to come and take my greenhouse
paper and cover on top of my beds
this way if it's raining my fruits are
not going to get in touch with water so
antarctica's end botrytis is avoided
okay
and it's something i'd encourage you and
every other farmer
please
in case that happens to you do not be
alarmed
okay
because it actually works the third pest
and disease is from slugs
yes the difference between slugs and
snails
i know you probably thought it's one of
the same thing but it's not so for slugs
what they do they actually come and end
up eating the entire fruit or eating a
portion of the fruit
that becomes a waste
so what you are doing so far we're doing
our research with the secret to actually
try to understand what really causes the
slug to come and eat the strawberry
fruit what really attracts the
strawberry also attacks the slug to this
strawberry fruit
it is something that really puzzles
quite a number of farmers but yes we
have tried our own concoctions that
well it works
but you want to get definitive results
and that you're going to get from your
cpa so again we'll definitely keep you
updated on that and even if you follow
us on facebook or facebook page but also
in the description and even the comments
will definitely ensure to tell you the
results that we found from isupe slugs
is one thing that you actually want to
avoid in your strawberry plantation open
field farmer i know you're probably
wondering what about the birds yes birds
are a blessing
but
they're going to be a blessing to you so
much once they start eating your fruit
so how do you get rid of birds now the
first thing do not kill birds again i
repeat do not kill the bugs
so what you need to do you need to
prevent them from
eating your strawberries so how we do it
we're going to use netting
so you can use one
a button it
you can use a sheet net if you're going
to use a shade net ensure your shade net
is 35 percent
go to the shop and tell them i want
cheddar that is 35 percent
third one you can also use a fishing net
fishnet also you can also use the
fishing net but
also you have to look at it in terms of
the cost also okay
if not you can also decide to use
galvanized chicken mesh
okay it'll actually work and remember
the key word is galvanized chicken mesh
why i say is because let's say trains
and elements you do not want that rust
to actually fall on your beds or even on
your plants or even on your fruits okay
but once you've covered
the strawberry plants with a different
kind of netting you've actually
prevented birds from coming to eat your
fruits buds are notorious but remember
they're also hungry at the same time so
for you you need to be very careful and
be careful in terms of don't let those
birds just come and eat the hard
labor that you've done okay prevent them
by using the netting system remember you
can either do it overhead or you can try
to use it the low tunneling system the
choice is yours but personally for us
the strawberry farm will always choose
to do the low tunnel system because of
cash money wise it saves us a lot of
money
in our next topic
we are going to learn about costing
you're probably wondering so how much
does this cost how much will it entail
for me to actually set up my own
strawberry farm how much am i going to
get
the mathematics
is in our next episode before that make
sure you like share and hit that
subscribe button because trust you me
i hope you're learning something new
see you in our next episode
you