thank you everyone for attending today
speakers presenters and sponsors this
event is put together by the South
Dakota no-till association's SDSU
Extension and some help from the NRCS
crop consultants you can receive your
CCA credits for each session each
speaker has a separate sheet if you want
to receive credits you have to sign-in
and sign-out before and after the
speakers the sheets are in the back of
the room over by Ruth Beck
the first speaker today is Michael
Thompson he's a farmer and rancher from
Almina
Kansas might go along with his family
and brothers operated Thompson ranch and
farm and ranch LLC the farming operation
grows wheat corn oats barley and a
diverse cover crop mixes the ranch
consists of a cow-calf operation that
grazes on native range and cover crops
on farm grant farmland acres in 2009
Michael began a soil health regimen
program which has boosted yields lowered
costs and improved profits he has also
built a network of no-till producers he
has brainstormed with over the years
today he's going to share his knowledge
and successful strategies for a
profitable no-till farm and ranching
operation everybody hear me all right
yeah I am from Almeida Kansas I live in
Kansas bye-bye where my house is but
everything that I farm is actually in
Nebraska and I'm kind of an oddity and
not a President of Colorado no-till
associations so before we go too far I'd
like to invite you all since I am
president of the Colorado conservation
tillage Association this was 32 years
ago they named it it actually is now the
high plains no-tell conference February
4th and 5th we'd love to have you there
if any of these things that we're
talking about today with grazing with
cattle on cropland interest view we have
a lot of speakers that are doing this
and western Kansas eastern Colorado and
some dry land climates about like here
so our farm is basically myself my
brother Brian and my father Richard
basically my father Richard was the only
full-time person up until three years
ago
I quit my elementary teaching job as a
kindergarten teacher and came home to
farm and helped him out my brother is a
full-time accountant and he helps out
all the time when he can so basically
we're in a 18 to 22 inch rainfall zone
depending on what you look look at
whether it's fifty or a hundred years
but we're in a pretty similar climate as
you we're just a little further south so
we do have rolling topography our
flattest field is one percent slope but
most of its 12 to 20 percent slope so we
have a lot of rowing rolling topography
I guess I want to start off by saying
kind of I'm not here to step on
anybody's toes I think that's how we
grow is maybe hearing some new ideas so
I'm not trying to insult you if you're
still doing some of the practices I'm
talking about that I think that that's
how we grow if we hear how other people
have got away from maybe like summer
fallow or going going away from you know
going to different processes so please
keep that in mind today with that in
mind I think that we've done a really
good job as farmers of being very
proficient in chemical farming of
treating the soil like a chemistry set
you know knowing how much nitrogen to
put on how much phosphorus put on how
much potassium how many micronutrients
the soil needs to grow a crop but in
doing so we've kind of discounted soil
biology and the but and the benefits
that soil biology can give to us so I'm
going to talk a little bit more about
the ecological functions and about what
we're doing on the cropland to actually
stimulate the cropland to kind of do a
little bit more with a little bit less
of the fertility and the inputs so first
off we kind of become ecologically blind
like I said we've really got good at
treating it like a chemistry set but
they always call this country next your
country you know if we don't hit it this
year there's always next year you know
maybe it'll rain next year or maybe
we'll get an extra snow or something to
get a little bit better crop but a lot
of times we discount what we do in this
year makes or breaks us in the next year
so I'm not cool it up there you know
about it's not next year country but
last year's country you know how we
treat the ground this last year is going
to determine how our successes in the
next year you know in 2020 so you know a
lot of times I think also we've always
got the mindset to get just a little bit
more maybe
little more profit or get that extra
grazing or get that extra hang out there
and sometimes we've got to defer that
and leave it for the next year to feed
that soil life so that we can have a
better soil so I believe in this quote
that by Gandia says that there's enough
for every man's need but not every man's
agreed you know going back to when we
first started farming we were
conventional till we did wheat fallow on
a lot of our acres and I can remember it
would set up like a brick and even when
we switched over to no-till when we're
Kim Fallot it's set up like a brick we
didn't have pore space our water would
run off you know on we need to farm more
like that sponge you know we need to
keep a living root in the soil we need
to have that pore space so that water
and air and biological life can live you
know I'm not here to criticize anybody
this is in our area so I know that
there's people that are still doing to
this today you know how close are we to
actual soil are we close to dirt on our
farms you know I want you to think about
introspectively on your own farm are
there places on side hills where you
still got ditches are there places you
know where you know you could do better
and so that's kind of how we got started
into this but you can see that you know
water erosion still a huge problem in
our area wind erosion is a problem this
is actually a soybean field that was no
tilled and it still blows so if you
don't have that cover the wind can be a
pretty big problem this has been a huge
problem since grain prices were high in
the about 2008-2009 on a lot of our
rangeland is getting converted into
cropland this is about six years in so
what have we done to our rangeland we've
taken productive rangeland and turned
into really poor cropland you can see
that there's a lot of places on there
that you know our water cycle isn't
functioning our water cycle is causing a
lot of erosion and we're losing a lot of
topsoil there so I'm taking some
productive ground and turning it into
unproductive farm ground you know it's
great to be ecologically aware but that
doesn't pay our bills does it we also
have to see where the profit is so
protecting that soil resource I can tell
you there are some profits and some
helpful things you know that that are a
profit profit wise that will help you
and first off it's it's estimated that
about half of the fertilizer we
currently apply to farmland is actually
applied just to make up for all of what
we lose
erosion whether it be wind or water
erosion you know so that's a pretty huge
amount and we really don't think about
how much erosion actually happens when
we see ditching across a field but if
you think your thickness of a dime
that's five tons of soil top top soil
lost so you know it doesn't take much to
blow or much to wash away before you
have quite a bit of nutrients and quite
a bit of topsoil leaving your field you
know as we go through this talk and as
we go through when you go home I hope
you think about it are you a banker are
you a miner of soil carbon soil carbon
basically most of our farmland and even
most of our rangeland has probably been
mined since we first came out here and
converted it to either grazing or or
farmland we took a really carbon rich
soil and you know we took grains off it
we took a hay off it we took many pounds
of beef off it we over grazed it person
that's more like the banker would
probably be somebody that's returning
their manure to their soil trying to use
some cover crops keep something growing
as much the year as possible they're
probably also trying to try to plant
some diversity in their rotation somehow
to get that Criswell carbon you never
really think how much soil is capable of
because what we currently call soil is
much more like dirt than it is soil and
I never even knew this I'm kind of a
soil I guess you'd call junkie or
obsessed with understanding how soil
works so actually I was watching a it
was a documentary on the 1930s what led
up to the Dust Bowl and how we got there
you might think that this is basically
Ohio Indiana Illinois somewhere that had
really rich topsoil this is actually
Springfield Colorado which is down by
liberal Kansas and in Southeast Colorado
where if you go through today it's full
of yucca and basically looks like a
desert but when they first wrote that
look at how much carbon they didn't use
fertilizers in 1900 this was just
freshly broke ground and that carbon
grew that crop you know even mrs. guys
short those oats that the heads are over
a foot tall so you know that there was
an abundance and they talked about the
abundance that they first had when they
came west and you know as they tilled
they burned a lot of that soil carbon
out so you know growing up I was no
different than maybe a lot of you I'd
like to say I come from 40 or 50 year
no-till operation which is not so
basically we're riding at
years when I came back to farm with my
dad
we basically converted from conventional
till my early recollections were on a
forty three eighty six international
tractor and my job was to follow the
combine and disc as fast as I possibly
could because our ground set up like a
brick the other thing I remember is when
I was doing fallow there were ditches
all over on our side Hills and my job
was to go out and work the ditches in so
then I could work across it so that we
could go ahead and plant that ground
without the ditches we never thought
about why the ground was hard or why
there were ditches there is just the
things that we did you know we just
didn't think about soil that way same
way on a grazing operation we'd feed all
winter long in a dry lot setting we
kicked the cows out probably at the
first of April and we'd leave them till
probably end of October 1st November and
bring them back to the dry lot of our
pastures were always out of grass by
about August first they'd be tearing
down fences getting into crops and I
absolutely detested cattle so if you
think that I loved cattle and I got into
cattle you're wrong because I remember
about 16 17 years of age I was like when
I become a farmer I'm gonna get ever rid
of every last cow in the place and we're
gonna farm everything luckily through
some college roommates and through my
dad talking me out of it you know we
still have cattle on the place today and
I have found that they've been very
beneficial which we'll talk about in a
minute the thing that killed me though
was by age of 18 I was set down from my
mom and dad well technically my mom
because my dad didn't really want to
tell me this but break the news to me
but they said dad's gonna be the last
farmer in our you know family that the
barns not big enough it's not making it
financially you know go go to town get a
good job you know with benefits and stay
away from the farm so I was pretty
hard-headed though so I went and got my
elementary education degree and I
returned home I started teaching
kindergarten and you know farming nights
weekends and I was able to rent and buy
some ground that way so I I didn't give
up on it but I knew that that
conventional tillage way was not going
to be the way so basically I started
looking in how was the soil formed our
Prairie soils were formed under you know
animals livestock out on them they had a
living cover or a cover on him
year-round and they had a living Roode
as much the year as possible you know so
we needed to have more of that on our
cropland to start restoring those water
cycles and the nutrient cycling some
might think that I'm open to change
because I'm young actually it was the
other way around I kind of liked that if
it isn't broke don't fix it you know but
I knew that that wasn't going to work
for me because I had to fix our soils if
I was to have a chance you know not
farming so back when we were under
conventional till we never thought as
well as anything more than just
something we'd planned it into you know
it was either dry or it was wet or you
know it was eroded whatever we didn't
think about it we just put the
fertilizer down the plant grew well now
we look at soil as being the priority
and the most important thing on our farm
because whether it's on the range land
side of things or whether it's on the
crop land side of things that's where
all your profit is derive from you know
there's no tract or no plan or no
combine that are gonna that's going to
make your soil better you know you're
gonna have to put the investment into it
and and see how you can make that soil
better I like to view the soil like I
view my son or my children I wouldn't
leave them out in the Sun you know on a
hot day because they get a sunburn right
well think about if you go out and you
hay or you go out and your work your
ground and leave it bare to the Sun it's
gonna you know get a sunburn it's gonna
hurt that soil life same thing you know
with the tillage you wouldn't stick a
sharp implement in your kid they'd
probably bleed to death right well the
soil doesn't like all that tillage in
that disruption either so you know some
of those things are things to think
about here's been the hardest thing for
me personally to shake I think most of
us in this room have always grown up we
only get so much rainfall so much
snowfall there's only so much moisture
right so we come from that let's banking
you know that's that whole back back
mindset with summer fallow we've got to
Bank that soil moisture and I'm not
gonna say it doesn't take moisture to
grow covers and also grow crops but
without that good cover over the soil
you can't really regulate your you can't
regulate any of your you can't regulate
your moisture at all you know there's a
lot more days with our winds and our
sunny days to lose moisture than there
is to gain moisture you know we have a
lot more windy sunny days than we do
rainy days also we when the first time
when it gets dry what happens to our
soils that don't have resiliency they
start in the crops
hurting and they look like they're
starting to burn up so we pray for
moisture right well if we pray for
moisture and we only hold a third of
that moisture have we really done us any
service no not really we have to have a
place for that moisture to be held down
in the profile not just on the top of
the soil you know if I can say one thing
that changed my mind about moisture the
most there's a PDF down here at the
bottom called the new water paradigm
water and recovery for a climate that is
an absolutely free pdf you can get off
the internet and it talks a lot about
the water cycle and recovering that
water cycle so if you're interested in
that it's about 75 80 pages worth but it
really goes into depth about how the
water cycle works so i really suggest
looking that up you know as a PDF it's
really good you might have to read
through it a couple of times but it's
not really like a scientific paper it
reads pretty easy so something really to
look into you know in our area we're
always told cover crops use too much
moisture right well this was kind of the
side-by-side comparison this was really
apples to apples because the planters
rolled on the same day the only
difference was is my neighbor stopped me
or my neighbor's hired me and stopped me
and he's like what are you doing four
down pressure on your planter you know
we can't get it in the ground up here at
the top of the hill and we're getting
stuck down at the bottom of the hill and
I was like we just a backed her down
pressure off the cell it swells mellow
and so that's the difference with the
cover crops basically on their side that
was just wheat stubble you can see how
it's browning up and burning up on the
other side where we took wheat stubble
when we planted some millet some daikon
radish some rapeseed things to help with
the infiltration we did use moisture to
grow that crop but then when the rains
came we're able to keep the rain further
on the side hill and not all down at the
bottom so here's the After Effects you
can tell pretty much probably which side
had to cover if you look between those
those rows it's not too hard to see that
there's still some cover on the cover
crop side and on the side that was just
wheat stubble there's basically nothing
left a lot of that that's that heat
heeded the plan up and it burned it up
basically it couldn't pull enough
moisture out of the soil fast enough and
over here so is about the difference
between
and ten bushel corn and the neighbor had
an insurance check so you know what
excites me about the whole thing about
covers and about soil improvement we
don't have to spend a lot of money on
them yes you have to plant you have to
spend money on the seeding and the seed
but we can use a lot of the free
elements number one the Sun we're using
capturing all of the rain and snowfall
that we possibly can
we're also using the carbon we're
capturing carbon from the air which is
totally free and I think that in the
next few years you they talked about it
for twenty thirty years now but I think
that we're really close to getting paid
for carbon credits that you will see
that as a big thing for your car if
you're starting to sequester carbon in
your soils we will start seeing a push
for that we're also increasing organic
matter by having that living root in the
soil we are stimulating soil biology the
earthworms the fungi the the bacteria
they're all making nutrients that are
plan available a lot of things that we
put on as fertilizers have to be
converted with it's biology and if you
have the biology working for you there's
a lot of amino acids and a lot of
peptides and other things that feed the
plant and you don't have to put it on
it all starts through the Sun most of us
don't think anything about the Sun at
all you know the Sun has a huge amount
of horsepower 500 horsepower tractors
pretty big right well that's five with I
think 24 25 zeros behind it four
horsepower to put it in another way if
there was a nice bridge that was two
miles wide and one mile thick from the
earth to the Sun it could be melted in
less than a second the sunlight that
falls on a square meter could power the
desktop computer for over a day so
there's a lot of energy and if that
energy doesn't have a green growing
plant it's basically like an oil spill
it's a it's a wasted opportunity we're
wasting that sunlight so we need that
green growing plant to have
photosynthesis and to pump sugars or
exudates into our soil those sugars feed
the soil life and then the soil life
feeds our crops so if we don't have that
like this field if we have bare soil
like this you know even though it's
planted to a wheat crop there's nothing
up there it's basically the sun's
working against us it's drying the soil
out it's killing off our microbial life
it's doing a lot of things that are
that are working against us so I'd
rather work with the Sun than against it
you know how effective is your rainfall
this is pretty common in our area on
people that are still following you see
that it seals off and it goes down and
it sits in the terrorist channel well
that terrorist channel you might grow a
little bit of crop in the terrorist
channel but that water should be across
the whole you know across the whole
field and stored down in the subsoil so
that your moisture so that your moisture
is there when you need it later in the
summer
you know how effective your snowfall we
do rotationally graze my dad still likes
to put up some hay so he does you know a
few lands around the outside of the
field and then maybe puts a few swaths
through you know for our for our wire to
go so you can see where he actually hate
over here there's about an inch and a
half to two inches of snowfall and that
actually had about 8 to 12 inches of
residual to hold the snow but it just
didn't hold the snow where we had the
stockpile basically there was almost the
foot about 11 to 12 inches of snow out
there you know so that's making the
snowfall more effective because that's
creating a little microclimate it's
still staying warm under there when that
snow still melts it can still do some
infiltration so you're actually making
more effective you're using water to
improve the soil dad thought that I was
crazy I went and got some of these
moisture probes basically they're an
irrigation probe and we're a hundred
percent dry land so he laughed at me he
said we can't turn the water on Sun so
what are you gonna do with this I said
well I just want to know that I'm doing
right with these cover crops that
they're actually doing what I think
they're doing so the black line up here
is basically the moisture level in the
soil this green band is the optimum
optimum growing conditions for your crop
and anyway so this this black line as
you can see we put them in it was in mud
it was over a hundred and ten percent
almost 120 percent of slow water holding
capacity it was wet when we plan it when
we put these soil probes in well we put
our cover crop in and as everybody knows
cover crop season oyster so we started
using moisture and moisture and down
here at the bottom of that green band is
when it started turning brown and it
started getting a little sickly so we
decided we'd start grazing it and dad
was pretty much laughing at me saying I
wasted my money on these because he
could
what was happening you know I was using
up all my moisture well I was feeling
pretty low by the time this band got
clear down there it was pretty much
getting to be pretty Brown I mean it the
top for that blue-white stage is burning
up so one night in the evening we got
two inches of moisture in 45 minutes so
it was a horrible rain it just rained
buckets and I was sick to death because
the cows were out there I thought oh
they tracked my field up probably the
tears channels are completely full maybe
even washed and terraces out as fast as
it came but as you can see when I got to
the field
it really wasn't tracked up that much
there was a few spots and the channels
that had some water but they weren't
full and we didn't have any terraces
washed out I couldn't understand why
well we'd use that moisture up up here
but then when we got that rain look we
recharged everything so it helped the
infiltration enough that we did use
moisture but then we regained that
moisture because it had a place to go if
we would have followed that in that same
time period it probably would have had
90 to 80 to 90% moisture in that subsoil
and then when we got that rain we would
have had like a hundred and sixty or a
hundred and eighty percent I guarantee
it we would have had lots of ditching we
would have terraces washed out so we are
using moisture but we're creating an
environment where we're increasing the
infiltration and getting more water into
our soils we do this by retaining
residue I know this looks crazy too a
lot of people probably because you're
like oh my gosh grazing days you know
most guys want to take it down to where
they see some bare dirt that's not me I
need that residue on top because that's
what's gonna keep my evaporation at bay
so I am giving up grazing days up front
but it comes back to me the next year in
little to no chemical use and then I
also have a lot better crops that make
it through the dry times because it's
got that it's got that covering between
the between the rows
what does grazing look like this is 12
hours of grazing when they go out on the
sorghum Sudan there's a hundred and
twenty pear out there you can't hardly
see them that's about two and a half
acres and by the time they come back you
can see them and for me that's time to
move most people would have probably
gone another day out there till they
take it down even more but for me I want
that standing I want some standing
residue left they stripped all the
leaves and all the good stuff off and
it's time for them to move
so that's what twelve hours are grazing
looks like why is that residue key
because that residue regulates your soil
temperature you can't make it rain more
but you can keep that evaporation at bay
so 130 degrees that's basically like a
lot of bare fallow work ground or Kym
fallow they could get up to 130 degrees
in the summer maybe not quite that much
up here but it could in our area if you
can keep it covered you can keep it down
towards that 70 degrees and that 70
degrees a hundred percent of that
moisture is used for plant growth so the
cooler you can keep that soil you can't
make it rain more but your your water
can go further we are limiting
evaporation this is the same soil probe
that we had it also has temperature
sensors every four inches this pink line
up here at the top is the top four
inches which is going to fluctuate most
with the soil temperature because it's
going to be closest to the top of the
soil and on some of our hottest days
when we're over a hundred degrees it got
up to 87 degrees there so we're keeping
it more than twenty degrees cooler we're
keeping our swell microbiology happy in
that soil and we're also keeping it from
evaporating that way
I will harp a lot on soil cover and
carbon because that's what we're
deficient in we're gonna have to give a
little bit to get the system started so
why is it important because all life
we're all life forms we're all
carbon-based life forms on this planet
so you know it's pretty important this
is what I want you to take if you don't
take anything else from my talk please
take this home and think about this
carbon holds seven times its own weight
in water so basically every little bit
of carbon you're putting in your drought
proofing your soil it will hold the
water like nothing else will you know
there's no tillage equipment or anything
else that will do as good as carbon well
and that's why I'm gonna harp a lot on
soil covering carbon carbon is essential
in the healthy soil because it's the
food for the microbiology I think we've
all found that out if you're no tilling
for a long time and you have those
fallow periods your organic matter
doesn't grow does it it's because the
microbiology starts eating it they don't
like to eat on that organic matter
because it's like eating cardboard to
them they'd much rather eat exudates
wheat those sugars coming from the root
living roots but they will feed on that
organic matter and that's why we don't
see the organic matter
if you're not growing plants to increase
soil carbon basically they're just going
to tear the house down well this is the
difference that soil carbon makes looks
like a totally different soil this is a
Holdrege silt loam that's 2.1 percent
organic matter that's a point seven
percent organic matter this isn't
perfect by any means but there is a lot
more pore space down here this is a
yulie clay that's like our side hills
and you can see that's a lot darker got
more water holding capacity a lot more
carbon in there than the no-till
neighbor so the difference that carbon
does make we can change our soils and I
would have never known this how do I not
have a field day on my farm they wanted
a slope at night never dug it so up and
I suggest everybody go out and dig a pit
and see what you're doing in your soils
on the stuff that my dad had it was
pretty good soil really raised good
crops you know good corn good wheat
crops so he really didn't push the
covers when we first started out I got a
lot of side hills and stuff next to the
pasture that was pretty much you know
not functioning like it should it was
poorer ground so where we had the poorer
ground where we did the cover cropping
and we did like scat cover crops we did
like a cool season spring one grazed it
out followed by a warm season one grazed
it out and then planted it back to wheat
that's a pretty tight rotation we didn't
have a lot of wheat but then after the
wheat came off we put a warm season
cover back on and grazed it you can see
the carbon that we put in there that
those exudates that's 36 inches of
carbon this is about 11 to 18 inches of
carbon there where the no-till so we're
actually putting more carbon and that's
holding more water so we can we can up
our rotations more again this isn't as
far into the system this is about this
is on our fifth year in no-till this is
only the second cover crop because we
worked this was a on a crop share and
our landlord didn't think that covers
worked until she started seeing our
other ground progressed more than hers
so we started doing this on on her
ground
you'd see there's still a lot of
problems but what are we doing we're
starting to get those we're starting to
get that carbon put down into the soil
microbiology is money in the bank and
that's why it's important to take care
of it
you know a soil that's rich in carbon is
also rich in fungi and microbes
and all these things are cycling
nutrients and making plan available for
free we don't have to go and we don't
have to pay for it and they also when we
do put fertilizer on they stretch that
fertilizer dollar even further I'm not
advocating that you severely cut your
fertilizer especially right off the bat
because that would be a train wreck but
I am saying that you will if you follow
these programs and you make targeted
applied visions or versions of your your
fertility they will go further soil life
creates basically the enzymes and some
amino acids that are beneficial to
plants that don't have to be converted
by the biology that are planned
available this is fungi in our soil so
the thing about fungi that's important
is that fungi roots can only go so small
and to get into fissures and cracks in
your soil and then they can't go any
further
but the fungi is so much smaller and
more microscopic it can go into small
small cracks that are microscopic and it
can go find moisture and find nutrients
that the the roots can't and then it'll
take it back to the it'll take it back
to the plant because the plant's gonna
feed it sugars to keep the fungi alive
because the fungi feeding the plants so
it does work together so that's
important even in dry times don't be
afraid to put something cheap out there
this is primarily a military op but they
did put some daikon radish and turnip in
there I considered this a failure
because I planted it with intentions we
were gonna get some rain after harvest
at some point it was dry bone-dry when
we planted I didn't think it'd come up
you know two weeks later three weeks
later we had this you could see it
coming up only got about you know ankle
the boot top high you know it didn't get
over a foot two foot tall so I
determined it was a failure because I
wanted it for grazing the cows actually
the deer and knocked down an electric
fence next to this and the cows got out
on it they were just going wild and I
couldn't figure out what were they're
after and never even went back and
looked at it but they they were going
after these turnips and this this radish
they're recycling those nutrients that
were left over after that wheat crop so
we can recover some of those nutrients
this is what a cover crop looks like you
don't see much bare soil you see a green
growing plant you know this is millets
this is forage sorghum sorghum Sedan
some rapeseed sunflower so I've got a
diversity of broadly sand grasses and
this is kind of what it looks like and
this was a wheat stubble this was
probably planted or this was probably
filmed what about the end of September
so if you rain you can do some pretty
great things you know grazing I'll say
grazing so easy even a baby can do it
you know most people don't want to hear
that um you know grazing can be a lot of
work is what most people think but it
doesn't have to be work I highly suggest
if you have never been around poly wire
or a braided braided wire like poly wire
that you experience that because it's
really easy to subdivide and to get
better use of your cropland
you know these this poly wire I like
this I like the step in post with a very
smallest
spike that you can find because when you
get into frozen ground or dry ground it
goes in the ground if you get too big a
spike like you go to some of these
places that are like the local tractor
supply they have cheaper post if they
have a really big spike on the end and
they won't go into frozen or dry ground
so try to find a one of those portable
posts that's got a small spike on it
basically that's that's all you need
really really I suggest if you do this
spend the money on a fence charger I
mean 500 to 800 dollars on a fence
charger which sounds like a lot but
it'll have enough joules that'll keep
the keep the cattle back you know
they'll respect it whereas if you go get
a cheap fence or they'll be out all the
time and it doesn't take much crop
damage to have a lot of problems with
the neighbor so I'm not so I'm not a I'm
totally into electric fence as being a
good thing but you have to have a good
fencer integration of livestock on the
farm like we talked about
they're basically incorporating the
residue down to the ground where that
microbe the microbes can start breaking
it down their trampling it basically
something that most people don't talk
about is the benefit but they're
stressing the plant they go out when
they wrap their tongue around there and
pull it off you know they're pulling on
that root and that roots getting a
little stressed so with putting more
sugars into the ground they're also
putting some saliva and some bacteria on
there their act and the room and a lot
of the things that are in the room and
coming out of the back end of the cow
start to stimulate a lot of these you
know the soil biology I will show you in
a little bit
what that looks like on our farm why hot
high stock density I like running a
decently high stock density so I get the
trampling so I get the ground cover I
get even residue distribution instead of
bare spots you know I think that it's
important that you have what you can
manage you know if it doesn't have to be
daily moved as if every second or third
day that's fine too but I think that you
need to have them moving across your
cropland because if you just leave them
out on one piece of ground like a
quarter for you know 30 days you're
gonna have some serious some pretty
serious compaction in places you know
who wants to move fence it sounds like a
daunting tax doesn't it to go out and
move this fence you know and change the
fence around well for me on foot I timed
it one day and to cross fence a quarter
it took what about 35 minutes for me on
foot holding the posts and stringing the
wire out if you have a four-wheeler or
you know a side-by-side or something
it's way faster than that but um you
know it doesn't have to take a lot of
time couple that versus the way we used
to look at cows and we used to subdivide
them into groups and put them all over
the country or take us four and a half
hours just to check cows and a lot of
times it's a whole day endeavor if they
tore the fence down and they're in our
crops or the neighbor's crops so you
know it's actually a lot less time it's
a little bit more time to get your idea
of where your watering points and stuff
we're going to be but it's a lot less
time than the way we used to run cattle
and most of all why I like being out
there every few days with my cattle
cattle are tame and they're easy to work
with these are my two year old twins
that just they just turn 2 in December
and they can come out with me and be
around these cattle they don't act like
cattle they act like oversized puppy
dogs it'll kind of freak you out a
little bit because they'll follow you
around you know looking to move Vince
and I'm gonna show you real quick what a
fencing what a move looks like on our
farm you know people think moving cattle
you have to get behind him and hoop and
holler and everything else all you have
to do is drop the wire once they see the
first couple go by they're smart they
know they're gonna get there next
rotation and you know big herds are not
hard to move it one person can do this
this happens to be where we had all
three of us there one morning and we
just moved him in but you could see how
fast they are the cattle are in really
good shape they've they might be a
little bit bigger than you
we're trying to shrink our cattle down
but they are really full they're got a
good-good code on them that's something
that you can't you know I was talking
with some other people you know the sale
barn when they go through the sale barn
they've got a lot better coat there a
lot fuller and that's something that you
you know you can revenue add revenue to
if you're doing this watch forage levels
if anything moved with forage on top
don't be like when we first started this
dad and I decided that we'd leave him
one more day I thought we should move
him dad thought we shouldn't so we did
it dad's way on this first piece the
rest of it we left more forage and the
difference on that following was about
there almost 30 bushels of wheat the top
only yielded about 22 bushel of wheat
because it was so dry and we had
compaction and everything else so why
leave residue residue holds it up it
works kind of like a snowshoe does you
know you don't break through the snow
when you got residue cover over the top
those cattle don't really break through
down into the soil and pug it up very
much they just kind of lightly
incorporate that on the top something
else to think about is this isn't wasted
forage this forage feeds the soil so
your soil can feed your livestock in the
future so it's an investment your future
you know what about compaction this is
on my own farm compaction is not a
problem if you keep them moving
basically this is soil bulk density this
is done in a joint Colorado State and
Kansas State study on cover crops in the
western region and you can see it's
statistically insignificant the
differences between fallow grazed and
ungrazed so basically that's the same
you know long as you keep them moving
this is a penetrometer this shows this
was grazed right before we planted corn
so we'll see how much compaction we
actually put in the ground if it stays
in that Green Zone basically you know
you're able to have your roots move
through so I can do it with one hand so
I'd really didn't have a lot of
resistance so that's working pretty good
so anyway so that's something to think
about
I prefer strip grazing everybody has a
different way to set up fence the longer
or narrower the paddocks you're going to
get a lot more of that back and forth
movement which you thought I think would
be compaction but it does a lot more
with laying that mat down if you do more
in a square pattern you're more likely
to probably have better you forage
utilization but you're probably
not gonna have that good residue Matt
lay down so we'd like to strip graze and
that works good for me because I could
put my tank next to a road or I can put
my net tank at the end of the field
where I've got a well across the road
and just run a hose across the road so
it helps me with water on some of these
things this is the nutrient spread with
strip grazing we'll talk about cycling
nutrients the free fertility that we're
getting if you put one fence around your
corn stock say it's a corn stock field
you put one fence around there and you
leave them continuous out there it would
take you 27 years to get one cowpie per
square yard
I think yep per square yard if you
subdivide and you move them say every 14
days it takes you eight years to get one
manure pack per square yard if you move
them 24 different times you don't have
to have 24 fences set up you just have
to have it divided up so you can move
them 24 times it would take you 2 years
and you can tell down here where we did
it daily you can see the manure paths
that are gonna feed that grass so it
does cycle nutrients it's your free
fertility you know remember to leave
that soil Armour so many times guys are
probably thinking that they can probably
get it you know the extra 10 or 15 head
on that ground you know and take it a
little bit further down but you really
need to leave that soil Armour so that
you've let those earthworms have a good
environment lift up biology eat the best
leave the rest don't be afraid to stop
the bottom of the stalk you can see that
there is a pretty significant amount you
know that we did waste on this but the
next year you know you can raise some
really good crops when you put them into
this so you know you're just using the
that you're capturing some value with
the cattle out there but you're also
capturing the value of the next year
with that and increased soil function
again I tell you know I've told you
several times but remember to leave
cover you know you that cover is
essential to make the whole thing work
why I like grazing a lot of people say
oh I've got a cover crop I'm gonna hay
it well just know if you hate it you're
gonna take off a lot of the good that
you did with that cover crop so so let's
say you run 500 pounds of beef per acre
that's 18 pounds of nitrogen 9 pounds of
phosphorous and 1.0 pounds of potassium
removing so four tons per acre I figure
is probably a dryland yield might be a
little bit low but 200 pounds of in 40
pounds of potassium potassium you take
that to an irrigated yield that's over
400 pounds in so you're losing a lot of
nutrients when you hay that so you're
gonna have to make it up with a lot of
added nutrients so something else that
we get on our farm is we get a really
nice regrowth on our pasture when
they're out on cover crops so that helps
hurt let's grow more range this is in
August the neighbor has buffalo grass
and weeds and basically bare soil this
out here you can see some clovers and
some grass so you know we know that
we're making a difference on our on our
ground I'd be a miss to tell you that
this all happens in one year you know
also many people I get frustrated when I
first started this because you'd hear
these guys talking and made out these
beautiful wonderful looking crops well I
think 2012 might have been a little
drier up here for you guys for you us 13
was the year that really dry in our area
so we did everything right with this
corn crop we had really good soil cover
we planted the corn crop in there is so
dry the corn didn't really even come up
we didn't get hardly a stand so we did
strip graze the corn off but we did
everything right this is the same
fertility package as here and look at
the difference we've got this is last
year's corn we even have the ground
starting to cycle nutrients you see some
bare soil there you know as soon as the
corn comes off it needs that residue to
keep it going but you can just see a
lusher and a stronger plant and that's
the soil biology that's making that you
know and I like to have fun I planned it
a little bit of open pollinated corn it
was a Jimmy red corn so just for fun you
know just to see what it do remember to
leave that soil cover and this is what
it looks like where we have cover crop
between the rows and this was a
harvested this was this Paul's harvested
so you need to have that soil cover
leave that soil cover even if you're
grazing and this is the different soil
cover makes you see the cover crop on
one side this guy hate all of his corn
stalks off so you've got no residue and
look what's happening to his soil so it
makes a big difference we chose the way
you know to change the way we farmed the
way we viewed soil you know we disc we
ploughed we ripped we did
you know so you know I think that it's
important that we think about the soil
and put a priority on soil this is the
difference that the high input no-till
this is guy that uses a lot of chemical
and fertilizer in there basically you
know it is gonna work so all these
little dots that's bacteria you see a
lot of other life and there it's pretty
much all bacteria right soil bacteria is
what's pretty prevalent in a lot of
soils so I'm going to show you on our
side this was the grazing the little
worm-like things a nematode that little
fast things of protozoa there's bacteria
you've got a lot more cycling of
nutrients when you've got all those
little guys working for you they're
they're dying they're they're killing
each other they're giving off nutrients
and this all plan available so that's
the difference we're getting and for me
this is what's important I'm leaving a
legacy of good soil management I hope to
heck but I don't have to tell my three
kids someday that you know you can't
come back to the farm I'd like to think
that we'd find a revenue stream or a way
to bring them back you know and that our
soils will be in a good enough shape you
know that that we can do that so like I
said I taught kindergarten in the spring
when the kids would get restless and
antsy we'd go out and we'd have a soils
unit and as part of our soils unit and
conservation theme we'd read the Lorax
and in in the Lorax it says unless
someone like you cares a whole awful lot
nothing is going to get better it's not
it starts with you know you your
neighbors you know just just trying
something and making it work you know
being committed to it if you are into
this I'd suggest reading there's a lot
of good books out there then that's how
I got my start I didn't have the
neighbors that were good at doing this I
just had to read and figure this out the
hard way but grass fed cattle it's not
really about grass feeding as much as it
is it talks a lot about mobile
structures like watering fencing that
kind of stuff it actually gave me my my
start in to this whole grazing thing
holistic management kind of tells you
some of the things about you know range
and stuff nature and properties of soils
that's my Bible that tells you so much
about soils it is a college textbook but
it doesn't really read like a textbook a
lot of good info about water cycling
nutrient cycling things like that
stumble over soil that's about a South
American farmer who took some really
poor and poorly degraded ground and bro
high productivity good no tell book cal
save the planet water in plain sight
those are both books that kind of talk
about the water cycle and how the how
cattle can actually help restore our
soils building soils we're better crops
that's a free PDF file that you can get
from sare teeming with microbes teeming
with fungi and teeming with excuse me
teeming with nutrients by Jeff blow in
Fell's those are really good books that
talk about a lot of the biology
happening in our soils you know and how
the nutrients get into our plants so if
you're interested in that and I think
the most important thing for me that
helped me grow as a person with farming
the Dust Bowl that book is a first-hand
account from a Southwest farmer that he
was doing everything right for his day
conservation wise trying to grow crops
but he kept having crop failure after
crop failure so it kind of tells you the
what if we don't take care of our soil I
know that what I said might be a lot to
you know chew you know or write a lot to
think about
but I heard the same thing you know
years ago from other speakers and I
thought what do I have to lose you know
and it's really been kind to me and so
that's why I'm here today to to kind of
pay it forward and help other people
hopefully you have success on your own
farms and ranches like I have but a lot
of its mindset whether you think you can
or think that you can't you're right and
Henry Ford said that and 90% of its
mindset if you want to make it work
you're gonna find a way to make it work
so if I can help interview in any way
here's my contact information if you're
on facebook kansas-nebraska soil
stewardship group was me and a few
neighbors that did it cuz we're in
Kansas in Nebraska and it's all across
the region now so if you'd like to be on
that or on Twitter there's a lot of good
people doing stuff on there so please
reach out and if I can answer any
questions great I thank you for your
time thank you
you
[Applause]