good agricultural practice gap our
specific methods which when applied to
agriculture create food for consumers or
further processing that is safe and
wholesome while there are numerous
competing definitions of what methods
constitute good agricultural practice
there are several broadly accepted
schemes that producers can adhere to
topic food and agricultural organization
of the United Nations gap
the Food and Agricultural organization
of the United Nations FAO uses good
agricultural practice as a collection of
principles to apply for unfarmed
production and post-production processes
resulting in safe and healthy food and
non-food agricultural products while
taking into account economical social
and environmental sustainability gaps
may be applied to a wide range of
farming systems and at different scales
they are applied through sustainable
agricultural methods economically and
efficiently produced sufficient food
security safe food safety and nutritious
food food quality gaps require
maintaining a common database on
integrated production techniques for
each of the major agro ecological area C
eco region thus to collect analyze and
disseminate information of good
practices in relevant geographical
contexts
topic United States Department of
Agriculture gap GHP program the United
States Department of Agriculture
agricultural marketing service currently
operates an audit certification program
to verify that farms use good
agricultural practice and/or good
handling practice this is a voluntary
program typically utilized by growers
and Packers to satisfy contractual
requirements with retail and food
service buyers the program was
implemented in 2002 after the New Jersey
Department of Agriculture petitioned
USDA amps to implement an audit based
program to verify conformance to the
1998 Food and Drug Administration
publication entitled guide to minimize
microbial food safety hazards for fresh
fruits and vegetables the program has
been updated several times since 2002
and includes additional certification
programs such as commodity specific
audit programs for mushrooms tomatoes
leafy greens and cantaloupes in 2009
usda amps participated in the gapps
harmonization initiative which
harmonized 14 of the major North
American GAAP audit standards which in
2011 resulted in the release and
implementation of the produce gaps
harmonized food safety standard
topic smallholder productivity
demand for agricultural crops is
expected to double as the world's
population reaches 9.1 billion by 2050
increasing the quantity and quality of
food in response to growing demand will
require increased agricultural good
agricultural practices often in
combination with effective input use are
one of the best ways to increase
smallholder productivity many
agribusinesses are building sustainable
supply chains to increase production and
improve quality
topic soil
reducing erosion by wind and water
through hedging and ditching application
of fertilizers at appropriate moments
and in adequate doses ie when the plant
needs the fertilizer to avoid runoff see
nitrogen balance method maintaining or
restoring soil organic content by manure
application use of grazing crop rotation
reduce soil compaction issues by
avoiding using heavy mechanical devices
maintain soil structure by limiting
heavy tillage practices in situ Greenman
uring by growing pulse crops like cow
pee horse gram Sun hemp etc
topic water
practice scheduled irrigation with
monitoring of plant needs and soil water
reserve status to avoid water loss by
drainage prevent soil salinization by
limiting water input to needs and
recycling water whenever possible avoid
crops with high water requirements in a
low availability region avoid drainage
and fertilizer runoff maintain permanent
soil covering in particular in winter to
avoid nitrogen runoff manage carefully
water table by limiting heavy output of
water restore or maintain wetlands sea
marshlands provide good water points for
livestock harvest water in situ by
digging catch pits crescent buns across
slope
topic animal production health and
welfare
you
respective animal well-being freedom
from hunger and thirst freedom from
discomfort freedom from pain injury or
disease freedom to express normal
behavior and freedom from fear and
distress avoid none therapeutic
mutilations surgical or invasive
procedures such as tail docking and
debeaking avoid negative impacts on
landscape environment and life
contamination of land for grazing food
water and air check stocks and flows
maintain structure of systems prevent
chemical and medical residues from
entering the food chain minimize non
therapeutic use of antibiotics or
hormones avoid feeding animals with
animal wastes or animal matter reducing
the risk of alien viral or transgenic
jeans or prions such as mad cow disease
minimize transport of live animals by
foot rail or road reducing the risk of
epidemics EEG foot and mouth disease
prevent waste runoff eg nitrate
contamination of water tables from pigs
nutrient loss and greenhouse gas
emissions methane from cows prefer
safety measures standards in
manipulation of equipment apply
traceability processes on the whole
production chain breeding feed medical
treatment for consumer security and
feedback possibility in case of a food
crisis EEG dioxin
topic healthcare and public health
quality assurance of the horticultural
or agricultural production of medicinal
plant equals equals see also