all right I just wanted to bring you in
here real quick so I can do a comparison
of the uh plants that I transplanted the
other
day if looking sorry about my my dirty
hands just got finished planting carrots
but that one's really up next to the
third digit right there as you can see
it's not really grown out very much um
look at those still down at the first
digit maybe I I give that the second
digit right there let's go outside and
check out the transplant and if you look
at that one I mean it's grown out
[Music]
significantly another one right there
has grown look at that up to the third
digit easily um it has grown out to Li
gney as well and then this one didn't
grow up very much but it definitely grew
out you can see the new growth in the
middle in there and this is definitely
the the part of gardening that I love
the most