[Music]
hello again and welcome back to horse
life
directly from the horse headquarters in
germany visits nov
for those of you who haven't joined us
earlier today i'm johannes and i will i
will be your host for the english
language sessions today
well a quick reminder on what is horse
life obviously we would have loved to
have you here in person
but because of covet 19 this apparently
isn't possible unfortunately so
we thought about a creative solution to
interact with you anyways
and this is harsh life
fortunately this new format actually
gives us a chance
to present you an even larger and more
international
seminar than ever before
so a special welcome to the
international audience
and thank you very much for joining we
hope you enjoy enjoy the next session
before introducing our next topic and
our next guest
a quick uh remem remembering very
quickly on what this is about
this is horse life and so we hope not
only you will hear from us
but that we will hear from you as well
so please
ask all your questions via the chat
function of your channels
and we'll try to answer as many of them
either
after the sessions from the presenter or
via
the chat function directly to our next
speaker
actually the two upcoming presentations
will cover a topic that horse has been
dealing
intensively with for about two years now
and that's called
biocontrol or biological plant
protection
what is it about is actually the
biological control of pests and diseases
through the targeted application of an
active biological agent
something that here in the eu is somehow
still a niche sector but in other parts
of the world like brazil
this is already widely accepted and
commonly used
our next two guests will share insights
on this innovative and
interesting technology with us from two
different perspectives
the user's perspective as well as the
producers
gregory sanders will make a start and
talk to us about the practical use of
biological agents
in large-scale farming operations
gregory is director of operations of
grupo progreso
a family structured group of
agricultural companies
that will harvest close to 100 000
hectares in two harvests in 2021
their operation is focused on the
production of soy corn
and cotton gregory will talk to us
about using biological control as an
element of their integrated
plant production protection system and
will share information
about related opportunities challenges
cost effects and benefits to
biological management as well as
intended future steps
welcome gregory
sanders i'm an agronomist and operation
director
of progreso group progreso group
is a group of companies familiar
companies
and individual growers that are
established
since 2001 in the state of minas gerais
in the southeast region of brazil and
also in poe
the northeast region of brazil we
grow cotton corn and soybean
and we have also a business of soybean
seeds
and i would like to thank you a lot
harsh
to give me this opportunity to
participate to this life
inviting me and my company to talk about
what we are doing in this presentation
that we are bored biologic control
in our company here in the poe some of
the main characteristics of
progreso group is we are pioneer in
cotton planning with high technology in
poe state we
started planting cotton here in the year
we built our own gene on the year 2006
and since that we become a reference in
cotton
here in the region of cerrado's in pov
state
we are one of the reference in quality
of soybean seeds in brazil
this we get recently we've
invest a lot in our unit here
mainly in poe and
use of new technologies to make possible
to produce
soya bean seeds here in poe in a place
there is a very hot and offer a big
challenge
to get a good quality in soybean seeds
we are known by being innovative in our
production process we
always to be pioneered in
the region we are operating we have
some discovery about ourselves
the way adjusting our process
by our own to make possible to
to explore the crops we are in this
region
we have a characteristic of
share a lot of their knowledge we we
learn
everything we learn here in the region
we used to share with other growers
and we for us is a way
to to make this
these mistakes we we made another people
want to do this and we can
at the same time when we share learn a
lot
things that we it would cost a lot in
our mistakes so this is a characters we
have
is to share everything
that we learned along all over the years
operating here in the region and we are
avid
to new technologies i must say
we are the second harsh customer here in
brazil
and we are very proud of this talking
about our
farms we have a aurobranco farm
located in paracatu miniaturized state
is the only farm we have in the
miniaturized state is the first one the
group
established in the year to 1997
before becoming really a group these
farms nowadays two thousand and six
two thousand six hundred hectares
normally we
have all the area planted with soybean
in the first harvest
and almost 70 percent of the area
planted with corn in the second harvest
we have another farm the peninsula
is the little one we have located in
guadalupe poe
with 682 hectares
irrigated area is very strategic for us
to
soybean multiply and
give a speed in new
varieties of soybean that is is being
developed we have an imperial farm
located in sebastian leo the area tutor
is
10 780 hectares planted area
normally this farm we make
one harvest and they are the the
the second harvest only crops to cover
the soil and make
uh straw in the area we have a hyena de
seja
a farm located in euro suite yoe with a
14 thousand and 300 hectares planted
area
normally this area we can
plant total air in the first harvest
with soybean
and something like 10
and 20 percent of this area along the
years
we can cover if a second harvest of
corn and the rest of the area the same
of imperial covering with uh crop to
make
straw that is very very important in our
region
we have the youngest one a tropical farm
located at bacia grande dohibero
nowadays 17
400 hectares planted area
we can make our something like 15
percent
of second harvest with corn and this
area is
is to be consolidated uh this next
season
it will reach the mark of 20 21
four hundred hectares and we have the
progreso farm that
first farm here in poe state the most
important area
the biggest planted area we have in one
farm
and it's 36 000 hectares is where we
concentrate
our industrial uh
structures we have a cotton gin
we have the our
unit of seeds located in poe
installed in this farm main activities
of the group
as i said soybean corn cotton grow
and soybeans the
the last season 2020 2001 the current
season
we will have in our farms in poe and
minas gerais state
a total of 68 300 hectares soybean
thousand of corn first harvest and three
thousand
nine hundred of cotton and as a second
harvest we will have
sixteen thousand four hundred hectares
of corn
a thousand and one hundred hectares of
serbian
and this soybean irrigated eighty
hundred and fifty hectares will be at
peninsula
in the central pivots
to multiply new varieties that are
in the pipeline to be registered and
for the next harvest the soybean seed
business
we have a unit in orobrenko farm with a
structure
to 120 000 sacks of
2 100 200 and
200 000 seeds like
one sec like this normally
for you to have an idea you can plant
one hectare of soybean with this
number of seeds in one sac so this
structure
can cover 120
000 hectares of soybean
uh all with all this capacity
in in a structure and where we can
keep all the seed storage
in a cold chamber and our main
unit is located at progreso farm and a
structure
to 1.2 million sacks of seeds
really impressive we have
concept this structure since 2004
and nowadays we are
unpleating this structure building a new
big chamber cold chamber to store
ready seeds to to go to the our
customers
i would like to talk about a little bit
about the history of biologic control
in big crops in brazil in the years
80 we had introduction of use
of baccalaureates to control soybean
caterpillar
the anti-carcinogen metals and that time
the growers used to pick up the the
anti-carcinogen metals that seems to be
affected by
baccolo virus and
freeze all these caterpillars and then
in a certain moment put all in a mixer
and then put this solution of
of caterpillar mix it in a big mixer
inside a plane or
a terrain spray or a plane
and spray all this solution in the
in the soybean crop and this time
it used to have a very
it was very heavy the work
to pick up this and
to make all this process and we have
suffered a lot with the effects of
whether the the response of this kind of
treatment by using baccalaureates should
be
very preventive not so you couldn't
use this as in the point where the
caterpillars was giving you uh
damage to your to your soybean
where you would lose money it takes a
long time to control the
the caterpillar so this
failed along the years and the growers
stopped using this kind of technology
then in the years 19 for
big crops we know it's a very popular
and deep basilis du regensis and a
commercial solution
ready for use but it was
efficient not so much
if compared with the chemical control
but it was a way to reduce the impact
to the interesting
bugs present in the crop
but the cost of using the pill
was so close to the
the chemical control that doesn't make
sense at that moment
if you compare the efficiency and you
compare the q
the cost it represented that time
and it didn't didn't work the there was
no not so many growers using this
technology
at that time then you in the year to the
years 2000
the beans soy beans and cotton growers
in some regions some
more cold weather
regions where we have a high altitudes
when you have a
temperature below 15 degrees at night
this this main tree crops start
suffering a lot of if
sclerotine escalo chiaro
this disease caused by this fungus
had a have a very difficult
and very expensive cause to control
by managing fungicides and that's
that was an opportunity for
the biologic control with by using
trichoderma
asean to get succeed
and since that year that year until now
we have a lot of growers in
these main tree crops using constantly
year by year this kind of fungus
or making buying this from
companies specialized companies to
produce or
some producing these by their own in
their own farms
and we had a a big change
in the biologic control in brazil
by the year 2012 when we had the
introduction of
elite corvair parmigia in brazil at that
time
nobody was ready to deal with this new
[Music]
caterpillar very resident for the normal
insecticides we were being using and
to control this this new
caterpillar we should use some
insecticides that was very expensive at
that time
and the helicopter after its
introduction in brazil
live as a legacy many growers
after that started using biological
control
as a way to control the caterpillars and
even
other uses other purpose
and this created a constant demand for
all the biological and this environment
this new environment created after this
event
was a perfect for established companies
that work at this
segment of of business and even for new
startups
to have an opportunity to grow and the
recent most recent uh
changing in this segment of business
was some companies developed some
solutions for the growers to produce
their bio control agents inside the farm
on farm
in the year 2019 progress made a
contract
with agrobiological
companies situated at lemmy some
polystate
southeast region of brazil that is
specialized in producing solutions for
production of biological control in
on farm this contract
we made an agreement to
buy only their kit they have a
feed kit for bacteria multiplication
called multibacter and
they've accommodated us
20 bioreactors capable of 2 000 liters
each so we have a capacity
to produce at the same time 40 000
liters of bio agents at same time
and this contract this agreement
leave us free to buy any source of any
bacteria to
any other company to be multiplied
inside
the b reactors that are accommodated
with them
the year 2019 we use by using an
existing building we installed the 20b
reactors of 2000 liters
at fazenda progreso centred
between other tree farms to produce
and deliver all the bio agents
to other farms and then november 2019 we
started
up this structure very simple use
by mixing the multibacker kit
and the desired bacteria you need
we could produce at each reactor 2000
liters
of the desired bioagent after
producing we put all the this solution
in of each bioreactor into
ibc's of 1000 liters and
after that analyze storage in a
cold chamber or direct use
by spraying with our planes the main use
of each produce are for
caterpillar controls nematodes
and live disease
and we've felt a lot the
effects of reducing the impact so this
structure is very simple and we are
using this spraying that our planes
as the same as other chemical
insect size and fungicides to control
the main
bugs and diseases we
we have in the our crops with less
impact
environment we are controlling now
white flies the complex of caterpillars
stink bugs spider mites and
diseases by using these biological
products at the same way of
chemical we use to do
before the multibacter technology
create a very simple table for
any agent you want to
multiply in the columns
you have all the agent a commercial
prude
product that you you can buy to use as a
source of
of this bacteria the time of
multiplication
the amount of commercial product to per
each 2000 liters
of the desired product you
you may multiply and also you have the
shelf life of the
product at the ambient temperature
the shelf life extended that's
more or less 50 percent when
cap when you storage this this product
at 12 degrees celsius and you have the
target
for each agent you have a target a
specific target
on the crops and also the dosage
of each each product to to control the
target
for instance this table help you
to plan everything you need to produce
how long will it take and how long will
it be
have available for you to use like the
first
column basilist origins uh variety as a
why
the commercial centauri it takes
48 hours to to be ready
the most you will use is 4 kilograms of
commercial product to
produce 2 000 liters of the
the product and if you keep this at
ambient temperature
eight days duration if you put in the
cold chamber 12 days of duration
and the purpose of this product is for
spodoptera species and pseudo pluses
pieces
and you take between three or four
liters per hectare spraying
to control these caterpillars
in any crop it could be soybean beans
cotton and here we have the nine
main agents we work with
in the last season 2019 2020
with any purpose you have
here in in this table to have an idea
what we did
last season 2019 2020
here you are some volume of each
agent we multiply it the total
amount of bu agent we produce it
on our b reactors was a total of one
million two hundred and ten thousand
liters
of bu agents most of them with a purpose
to control the caterpillars
talking about advantages so many
you can save interests bug
that help you in the
pests control and biological you feel
this a lot
we can feel the the increase of spiders
in the in our crops even then so i've
been
even in cotton by using this kind of
products and reducing the chemical
control
and talking about money saving
with i find a very simple way to compare
what what's being saved in about in
terms of
money not to mention and other
advantages and other benefits
of the use of the biological control
that are
difficult to measure we didn't measure
that
but talking about money like soya bean
last year
we sprayed a biological
it was an average in soybeans of 2.5
springs only using the biological
control
with with no chemical there so 2.5
sprains are i changed the chemical by
biological
with the same result of the chemical but
with economy of 4.1
dollar per hectare if you multiply
by 2.5 and the area a total economy
of 488 thousand
dollars almost 489 thousand dollars in
soybean only considering
the caterpillar control with biological
in cotton we had a little bit more
sprayers
we used the four sprays removing
the chemical control only biological
control
so the the chemicals in this kind of of
purples are a little bit more expensive
so the reduction was eight five point
eighty five dollars
per spray multiplying that by four
sprays
and the area four thousand five hundred
hectares
we have an economy of 105 000
so the total considering just this crop
these two crops
and this control of caterpillars we have
something
like 594 thousand dollars
the pandemic of coronavirus uh we suffer
with that because
we couldn't get any more sources to
multiply we had the
multibacter kit but we didn't we
couldn't buy
the source of bacteria mainly the
bacillus turijins and
saccharopolis prospinosa for use
in the coverage crops that we plant in
the areas that
we don't make this second harvest we
plant
millet we plant bracciaria and
we we could have a
higher economy a higher saving of money
if we could use that that point that we
main
we intend to use in this next harvest so
we are in the
rain season 2020 2021 as
we are about in the middle of this rain
season
so we are estimating um economy
much higher than the last year so in
soybean this year we have a little we
felt
a little a little lower pressure of
caterpillars in soybean and also cotton
i don't know but
i i estimate to be the same so talking
about soybean
we believe we will use 1.5
spraying in the total area removing the
chemical control and using the
biological control
so the economy of a little bit higher
this year because the dollar
is increased its value
against the real and the cost of all the
biological was
in real so this year the economy is a
little bit
higher than last year in terms of prices
of product
so multiplying 5.0 to 1.1
1.5 spraying to in the total area of
49 and 900 hectares of soybean
treated with biological we will have a
economy of
uh 375 000
this year we remove it the first
chemical fungicide spraying we changed
this by
using the bacillus soup chilis so we
removed one chemical
spraying in the first in the vegetative
phase of the soybean
and introduced only the basil subtil so
considerable reduction of costs
6.4 44 will reduce the cost
in this spraying one one spray in total
area we have
a savings of 321 000
about cotton this year the area is 3900
hectares
four springs because uh the difference
of course become higher 7.04 dollars per
per sprain by changing chemical to
biological
so if you multiply these four by four
and by the area we had
109 000 of
economy in this year different
uh to the year 2019 and 2020
we have we will do the the control of
caterpillars in other crops like sorghum
millet and brachiari
the total will be 50
400 hectares we estimate
at least two sprains for economy because
the
products the chemical inset size we use
in this in these situations are
a little bit cheaper than the other than
the cotton and the soybean
will be a reduction of cost of 2.06
dollars per sprain multiply it by two
and multiply it by the area will will
expect
uh 207 000 dollars of
economy so estimating
all the all the use only based on
what i changed by chemical to the
biological
this year we expect saving 1 million
14 000 dollars
of savings by change the chemical to
biological with
with no with no uh
loss of of performance
we had some chance comparing the season
2019 to 2020
to the season 2200 2020 in 2021 that is
in course
we removed the chrome bacterium subsur
guy
to our from our program because
the efficiency of this kind of agent
you should at least spray this weekly
and this is this impacting in our
operation
mainly in the planes areas to be sprayed
is very very high and doesn't make sense
to us to continuous with this agent
that requests so many so many sprains
because
normally the use of biologicals goes
with
other products goes with fertilizer and
there is no significant change in our
in our process of of production
the first as i said the first chemical
fungicide
sprayed in soybean which was changed by
chemical
to the biological in most of the
varieties of soybean
so this gave us a significant
reduction of costs but we didn't see any
change in the
performance of the control of the fungus
disease leave diseases in soybean and we
are
concluding our microbiology
laboratory to have a sample of of
each production bioreactor and
analyze this sample to ensure we are
having a good quality product to be
sprayed in the hour
in our areas we plan some chains for the
next season 2021 2022
agro-biological company that we make
that agreement
we have a contract is developing a
feeding kit to produce fungi
agents in the same bu reactor at the
same system
we are multiplying the bacterias so
by these we will have some new agents
that are very important in our
production like we
will be able with this work we will be
able to
produce balvari basiana to control
whitefly
on soybean and cotton we will be able to
produce izaria from formosa rosia
to control daobulus mites that's a very
important bug nowadays in the corn
that request a lot of sprains to control
this pest
and you have to take too much care of
the corn you have to protect against
this bug because is it transmits some
virus that can make a disaster in your
corn
so we expect a very
significant reduce of course in the
control of this
main main two pests the whitefly
and bulus might said corn though blues
minds that corn and white fly and
soybean and cotton
and uh we plan to start producing
trichoderma
arzianum and the purpose of this is to
use
in the full in the planning forum during
soybean planning operation
to reduce the nematodes to reduce
the soil disease that attack the roofs
of
all the crops here in our explored crops
so this uh these changes for
the next season will increase a lot this
money savings
we are expecting a lot of money savings
by this main two
new agents these fungi new agents that
we will
be able to introduce in our control
system
and that's it well i would like to thank
you all
for the attention i hope you enjoyed my
presentation
and this can contribute to your business
and i can you can contact me
via email that i show in the beginning
of presentation
gregory at fazendaprogresso.com.bro
even accessing our social media
live with us from brazil gregory welcome
and thank you very much for this very
insightful and interesting
presentation and that you shared with us
um how's it going in brazil
we are starting to harvest
very good that sounds good so already
good luck for that
gregory thanks for being available for
answering some questions and the first
question
isn't directly related to the topic
you were talking about it's rather with
regard to the
opportunity to do two harvests in one
rain season
one of our viewers noticed that in the
first half for the first harvest you
plant
around 81 000 hectares while for the
second harvest it's
only and that's still an impressive
number but roughly 20 000
hectares so what's going on with the
rest
with the rest of the 60 000 hectares
what what's being done with them
at the time of the second harvest we
used to plant some crops to cover the
soil we need a lot of straw
to to protect from losing the moisture
here in brazil is very important to to
keep this
and we don't have a window a correct
window to produce corn for in the whole
area that
was the best the best world for us
and we use in other crops that request a
little bit
less water to to produce a a month
a considerable amount of uh straw okay
that's
very important for us okay well thanks
on that
coming uh to your presentation and
to questions on that so you made it
certainly clear that you're using an
integrated system for plant protection
so you're not replacing 100 of chemicals
with
biological control so question on that
is
what's the ratio of biological control
and chemical control
and what efficiency level do you see on
biological control compared to
chemical control okay the
the situations we remove it uh as i was
talking about in my presentation for
caterpillars in soybean
we removed all the chemical control
but you have a stink bugs white fly
and other kind of pests you can't
control that
efficiently in the system we have
by using biological but caterpillars
that is the
the we what the tasks we most
spend money in the control the
biological
biological substitute changed every
chemical to biological okay and
that other pests we continue to use the
chemical but the fungicides control
we remove it we change it 25
between 25 and 30 in 30 percent
by using substituting the bio the
chemical to biological
so specific targets
talking about pests we are we changed it
25 percent and the of course to
biological and the
fungicides control 25 to 30 percent
do you do you see an increase in that
possibly in the future or
um will that stay at the same level
for the time being so we force
these specific targets like stink bugs
and white flies
we have we expect a better control if
you by using
fungus where the bacterias that the main
bacteria that we are producing on farm
are not
efficiency in the system we have but
with fungus
that we expect the next season be
producing on farm we expect
to control these other uh these other
bugs
by by using this this new
kind of engine agents
um on one of your last slides you uh
mentioned that one of the agents you
used in the first season in 2019 2020
you
removed that um can you tell us a little
bit more about the reasons for removing
that what was
um what what made you take that decision
was it
efficiency that made you decide to
switch over again to chemical
that specific agent chromobacterium
sugar
was being used to control
the stink bugs and white fly
but to be efficient we should spray at
least
weekly so at each seven days we would
have to spray again the chrome bacteria
subsur guy to have
efficient control and our
operational capacity of spraying with
planes and
other sprayers we we are not uh we don't
have this capacity to do
weekly spraying all over our areas
so there that doesn't make sense to
continue with that agent
that's why we stop it using and
um so do i understand right that there
is an effect on workload
for biological control of biological
agents so that you
in general would say there is a higher
workload when applying
biological agents because you need to
spray more
possibly as well as more often
in this case as i said before i
remove it because it it would increase
the number of spraying
but the system we are now the changes we
made from the last season to this actual
season
we are not spraying more we substitute
the chemical by biological in the same
spray okay
and the the main the main point is
when you use a chemical you have a need
to spray
you go to your storage you got a product
and you spray and with bio-biological
produced on farm
is very different you have to to see
the need you have to produce the
biological agent you need
and you have to spray that and you have
a very
lower shelf life of each product you
produce
if compared with to chemical so
everything
must be very synchronized to be
successful in this kind of control
did you change anything within your farm
system to be able to do so
to anticipate when a biological agent is
needed
did you i don't know hire weather
specialists
or run your own weather forecast system
or things like that to
to be able to to adopt to that
yes we have to like
to like how do we say in portuguese
to have all the area in your hands
to see to know everything is happening
to control in this in the right point
you can't lose the control you have to
get the control in your hands
of the whole area that's the main
difference
and you have to synchronize how long you
take to produce the product
and you have the capacity of planes and
so
everything must be you have to to be
at least two steps ahead if compared to
other system
by using only chemicals a question
in this context is do you spray the
whole farm at once or do you check
within the fields which area has
caterpillars and really needs to be
sprayed
yes that's real what we do
we we spray when needed normally when
needed
the first the first spray between the
first 40 days of this
mainly soy bean you
as on demand but we have to enter
spraying for the fungicides mainly to
protect from
ferrous in asia i don't know how to say
that in
english it's a very important
disease we have in soybean and
yeah do you they have so i've been roast
like let's say like that i don't know in
the
in the united states they they don't
have this
we have uh this roast and we have to
protect from that
and at least 14 days each 14 days you
are spraying
and if you need to put something to
control caterpillars you put if not you
don't do it
okay that's that's the main point as
needed okay
all right thank you for that um
coming back to your integrated system
since when
exactly so you you mentioned in your
presentation that you started to produce
your own biological agents
um in 2019 for the first time
um and was 2019 actually
also the first time that you actually
used biological agents or did you start
the usage
already before some agents
we were using before basil study genesis
we use it
a long time ago some some situations
but it was our our only usage
so we buy like a d-pal i
mentioned that my presentation i for a
long time used
the d-pal but the cost of the pail and
the efficiency
if compared to the the other
doesn't make sense at that time and then
we we were present to agro-biologica
the company that gave us
all the support to to produce on farm
and we start from
zero producing to using a whole area
at the same year so we start because the
cost
allows us to do this
okay um
coming back just quickly once again to
the um
question of of the actual application um
um one of the audience asks how many
liters of water per hectare do you spray
with the three to four liters of
bacteria so
in in your in your table that you showed
in your presentation there was i think
like
you need three to four liters of product
with how many liters of water would that
be sprayed per hectare
normally we we
well yeah oh here you are again well we
lost you for a second but you're back
again
thinking perfect okay normally each
agent
between three or four liters per hectare
like if i you will use three agents
normally between nine and twelve liters
but they spray
now we we can hear you we can hear you
uh gregory you
can continue talking we hear you so yeah
by
by the biological we use only by planes
depending on the the amount of chemical
and biological we are going to spray
normally it goes from nine to fif
to 18 liters of total
of total uh
total leaders per hectare total amounts
yeah okay
great so i think it's time for um one
last question
um that would be regarding um the
economic effects
so thank you very much first of all for
sharing this profound insights on
numbers
with us and with the audience
i mean when one looks at those savings
that you mentioned
one has to ask oneself why is not
everybody doing it
this way because the savings that you
that you mentioned that you show are so
obvious that that normally everybody
would have to
do it immediately the same way um so the
question is
is there any any negative effect that
that comes along without saving so
do you have a less turnover less revenue
that you have to compare those savings
with um
or is it actually the true savings and
and and it's it's just
a positive effect very generally
yes that is the only the savings i can
measure by changing the chemical
by changing the chemical by biological
and the cost of this change because the
rest is the equal and the efficiency
we are having in the in the products we
kept
use are the same we are not
there are a lot of effects of
not don't when you use this you don't
kill
benefit uh benefit bugs you have in the
crop
and there are a lot of things i i the
nematodes
control that we are we are not
mentioning this
and so the difficult to to
is not really the efficiency the
efficiency when you have a
synchronized production system
are the same of chemical by with a lot
of savings of money
but the difficulties people to manage to
have the
the the control to produce the the
agents on farm
to build this so it's a it's it increase
you
uh the difficult to to
to deal with the problems you have to
and
another another another thing that is a
manufacturer to do the biological
products on farm
it's an another activity another
activity you have to
to keep in your farm gregory thank you
very much
um i think that was very very impressive
to learn
and get these insights from you um for
me personally i learned that that that i
think there's not that much
um against um integrating biological
control in your system and i think it's
definitely worth looking closer to it
here in the european union as well
looks very promising to me what you've
already discovered in brazil
so yeah once again thank you very much
for joining us
for giving us these insights and all the
best for your harvest
and hopefully talk to you soon
thank you very much johannes
thank you so dear viewers um
that was gregory sanders from brazil
with uh yeah very impressive insights on
biological control from the user's
perspective
horse life will continue in about well
already ten minutes at six o'clock
central european time
with our next guest on the same topic
but from a different perspective
so i hope you will join us again soon
and see you in a bit