although for most of human history
people have been connected with the land
that fed them today this connection has
been broken for most of us the majority
of people do not know where and when
their food is grown they cannot touch
the soil or talk to the farmer who tends
it food comes from stores and
restaurants and vending machines it has
been washed processed packaged maybe
even irradiated and transported long
distances but this isn't the only way
Community Supported Agriculture CSA
along with other initiatives seeks to
shorten food supply chains and restore
the connection between farmers and
consumers in a way that we socializes
food and enables products to reach
consumers embedded with valuable
information Community Supported
Agriculture is a connection between a
nearby farmer and the people who eat the
food that he or she produces the essence
of this relationship is mutual
commitment the farm feeds the people and
the people support the farm and share
the inherent risks and rewards indeed
CSA is an innovative model of food
production and distribution it consists
in a partnership between a group of
consumers and the local proximity farmer
where consumers pay for the costs of the
production usually for a seasons term
CSA farmers are open for partnership
cooperation and communication with
consumers together with consumers by
mutual agreement farmers calculate the
cost of production and of the weekly
basket plan the crop rotation and
provide regular information about
farming and harvest consumers are not
just passive recipients of safe food
they actively participate in the
collective management of the partnership
their participation ensures transparency
equality mutual assistance and
democratic management of CSA consumers
are not only citizens willing to cook
and eat at
a variety of local food but they are
also partners sharing the benefits and
risks usually food distributions take
place at a common point with the
voluntary assistance from one or more
consumers the CSA movement has developed
in the second part of the 20th century
in different parts of the world starting
with Japan in the 70s all are different
but various initiatives share four
essential traits one partnership CSA is
based on a partnership
usually formalized through an individual
contract between each consumer and the
food producer and characterized by
mutual commitment to local dimension CSA
movement is oriented towards making the
food production local again three
solidarity CSAs are based on solidarity
between producers and support groups and
involves sharing both the risks and
benefits of an extensive small-scale
production adapted to the natural rhythm
of the seasons a production respectful
of the environment and of the natural
and cultural heritage a fair income for
the farmer to guarantee a dignified life
for the producer consumer tandem is
another key feature of CSA meaning that
the partnerships are based on direct
person-to-person contact and Trust with
no intermediary and hierarchy in Europe
today more
half a million people participate in CSA
partnerships and their number is
continuously growing why participants in
CSA is benefit from receiving fresh food
from a known source produced in a
responsible manner of sustainable
agriculture the environmental benefits
of fewer food miles less packaging and
ecologically sensitive farming with
improved animal welfare a local economy
enhances higher employment more local
processing and local consumption CSAs
have a direct contribution to the
support of sustainable farming and
biodiversity conservation what's in it
for small-scale farmers a more secure
income more time for planning and
farming as they don't have to spend time
to sell their produce is on markets a
higher and fairer return for their
products increase participation in local
community opportunities to respond
directly to consumers needs support from
partners help with labor and planning
initiatives for the future trust and
care we hunger for a true connection to
what's on our plates we want to know who
grows our food and where how it's grown
and why we want to participate in a food
system that is ecological just
nourishing and connected to community
the CSA movement offers all this and
more get more information on CSA in
Europe accessing wwr Jensi net or click
the logos for instant access on
different national networks
you