today we're gonna do our own solar
system we know you want your own solar
system you want that free power baby
we're gonna play with some 240 volt
wires and try not to shock ourselves
get some free power out of it let's go
so in front of us we have all of our
components
the big boy the 295 watt solar system
295 watt solar panel the star of the
show
you thought that was it this is it the
micro inverter this allows you to string
them all together and get the most power
out of each one of them hell yeah
here's your performance meter in meters
performance
ac disconnect
big turn off
turn on
this is for uh mounting the actual racks
and panels to the roof this is the wire
to connect all the micro inverters
together
run it to your system and finally
combiner this is where you combine your
strings
nice so here we are on the roof we're
getting 24 panels at 295 watts each that
works out to about 7 000 watts
getting 12 panels on this south facing
exposure
and 12 more panels
on this west facing explosion so right
now we're going to do some layout for
those rails
rails on those exposures that i
mentioned we need three feet from the
top of the ridges to the top of our
solar panels so we're going to lay that
out take our measurements get to work
so
so it's a little hard to tell but we
laid out our grid by doing a perimeter
measured everything out put in the holes
around the perimeter
and then we just ran our string line
between each point to make a little grid
and we just drill where the string lines
meet
and put our pieces down after that comes
the rails
[Applause]
yeah they only go on one way okay they
idiot roofed up man
on the dc right
so here's the actual micro inverter
you use one fastener in the center and
that slot
slides into the top slot of this rail
and doesn't even need to slide in and
actually drops in
easy
do you want me to hold it
so the full run of railing spans 20 feet
uh but the railing sections that we have
are 14 feet each
so we have these couplings and go
between them and we'll stitch on an
extra piece to the end
[Applause]
okay here's our first string runs from
the bottom set
up to the end of the top set
there's the end of it which will go to a
j box
and get ran off the roof to that
combiner box drinking game every time i
say daisy chain take a shot so a quick
difference between a traditional setup
and the micro inverter setup normally
you would just daisy chain each solar
panel to
every other one in the chain and then
you would run that
dc wire to an inverter with the micro
inverter setup
you run
a micro inverter for every single panel
so the dc solar panel wire then goes to
the micro inverter and each one of those
is daisy chained together uh and at that
point it's ac that's what the inverter
does
so
right now we have all of our micro
inverters laid out before we get panels
on the roof
we're going to daisy chain each micro
inverter in its respective string
together and run it to the end i'm
watching it
here's the start of the second string
this one's only half a string the other
half of the string
is on the other roof
so we'll run it down here
jbox at the end of this guy
then we're going to run this through
some conduit to match up with the other
half that's going up in a little bit
another look at these micro inverters
here they are this is your dc connection
for your solar panel
and this wire right here is the daisy
chain ac wire
solar panel here
ac there
to your jbox
to your combiner so just a quick
overview of the difference between your
central inverter versus your micro
inverter
benefits and downsides with that central
inverter you have to run low voltage to
each panel and then all the way down to
your inverter so there's some voltage
loss but the bigger disadvantage is that
it's kind of the idea that your chain is
only as strong as your weakest link with
your central inverter set up the string
will only do as well as the lowest panel
in that string so if you have one panel
that's in the shade that whole entire
string is going to suffer because of it
with the micro inverter setup each panel
has its own micro inverter and the
output just gets added up between them
if you have a roof like this one where
we have panels in different elevations
where the amount of sun that each panel
is getting varies quite a bit from panel
to panel within the same string
you definitely want micro inverters the
biggest downside of a micro inverter
setup is that it's more expensive you
have to have a micro inverter for every
single panel we have 24 panels on this
roof which means 24 micro inverters and
the cost certainly adds up but
especially for this roof the benefits
far outweigh the cost
and i wouldn't want to do a traditional
central inverter setup for this guy
we have our first six panels on the roof
we're gonna get those connected
and mounted and go from there
for fasteners
they just use these little
bolts with uh caps on the end of them
that basically just pinched down on the
panels
and a couple spacers for the end pieces
and while we got the dream team
doing panels
we got my dad doing layout
here are the end spacers and back to the
fasteners
just clip these on
and this is used at the start and end of
a run so we have our six panels on the
bottom
[Music]
that gives us some support on the end
just like that panels are on
okay here's our second
set second elevation
you see all the micro inverters are ran
and strung
important step so these are the ac wires
the daisy chain the micro inverters
together
before we hook the panels on it's
important to note you do want to cap off
this daisy chain wire because as soon as
the panels get some sun they're working
as soon as you connect those panels
they're sending electricity through here
so yeah i kept these off because they
will be live when they're hooked up to
panels
and just like that
we have two elevations of solar panels
we got 12 panels here
12 panels there
24 panel system 7000 watts next up we
need to run our wires some junction
boxes and some conduit and then run it
down to the disconnect and the combiner
and all that stuff down there so that we
can actually get some power out of this
so we're back from the future we did
these panels a little bit wrong
in the sense that when you wire them you
cannot have the wires actually sitting
on the roof
so this time we're going to use these
clips
to hold the wires
in place off of the roof
we're going to put the panels back down
and then we'll be good to go
easy as that
and here's what the roof looks like with
the j boxes and with the conduit
installed an important note is that this
kit actually called for three quarter
inch conduit but we used one inch
conduit this made it so much easier to
run the wires through and when you're
pulling this many wires through
three-quarters conduit it's just not fun
go with one inch it'll save you some
time and struggle
and here you have the combiner box you
can see the three strings
are the top two breakers
as well as the one on the bottom left
the red black and white
this middle breaker is the power that
goes out which then goes to the ac
disconnect this allows you to quickly
turn your system on and off
the power coming from your panels then
going out here's the performance meter
without it installed obviously that's
for the power company to do
and here is where it goes back into the
panel
you can see our breakers clearly labeled
up there for the solar system
here's the conduit running down from the
roof to bring those into the combiner
box
lastly we have the system all buttoned
up here's our panel that we shot
here's the performance meter again the
city needs to install the actual meter
here's the ac disconnect closed as well
as the combiner box closed
and sitting on the wall it looks pretty
neat and organized almost professional
almost and we're back to show exactly
how much this thing is made
so right now it's a little bit overcast
the sun's poking through just barely and
the system's making 3.6 kilowatts right
now
so throughout the span of a day
it'll vary depending on where the sun's
at a little less in the morning and
evening but uh you can expect with this
right now to get about 30 kilowatt hours
a day
and we've had it running now for about
six weeks
and it'll cycle through and tell us
that it's made 1375 kilowatt hours which
you know you do the math that's roughly
about 30 a day so we're tracking right
there that adds up a lot especially
with power costs increasing depending on
where you're at this could be a
significant reduction to your bill and
you saw how easy that whole thing was
highly recommend the micro inverter set
up to get your maximum output on your
entire roof and as you see it will
directly save on your power bill please
like comment and subscribe if you enjoy
this video and feel free to comment with
any questions you have if you're doing
your own home system or you're just more
curious about how this works thanks guys
we'll see you next time