[Music]
oh
all right welcome back
richie aldo are you there
yes how are you i'm doing well how are
you
all right looking good in summary
there he is with his chickens
all right well um for those who've been
attending
thus far you don't need any introduction
um
we have you know laid out a
series of presentations where you're
going to start with the
the deeper framing of you know
colonization and indigenousness
and work us through our own process and
then
towards cultural um engagement more
deeply with those insights
so um i think it's the stage is yours
so we'll let you uh take it away
welcome everyone we're gonna go through
a high level continuation of the
previous
conversation on decolonization
of science process methodology and
management within the context of
regenerative agriculture
thinking and to
be clear there is a lot in the previous
two presentations
that uh is is um
critical in order to understand the
the points that we're going to go
through today
now the there will be a lot of questions
i am assuming because of when when we
address these kinds of large-scale
issues and conceptual
uh frameworks there is a lot of
detail that needs to be worked out so a
lot of that detail has been also
um addressed in previous presentations
not all of it this you know business of
systems change is quite extensive and
complex
uh so today we're going to focus on
just thinking through the mindsets
the processes that we use to
in the methodology that defines how we
manage
our our presence as as organisms of the
earth
within the ecosystems that we inhabit
and so on
and so you will find that we will be
addressing
yeah you know specific issues as to
property plant and equipment management
when do we bring equipment um to what
end
uh when does nature needs us to do those
things and how are we approaching this
from a conquering colonizing extraction
perspective or are we seeing it from a
you know perspective where we are part
of the system that we are working with
instead so to that end there are certain
key outcomes that we need to be familiar
with
and in this case when we look at you
know
um regenerative agriculture there are
some some things that we assume
uh to be regenerative when they are not
they are neces they are not necessarily
part of a regenerative framework they
are just simply part of our colonized
uh ways of being which is it comes
natural
in to us and it's also more of the
mmo that we all are accustomed to and
trained into and domesticated into
so in this case when we look at
the acceptances perpetration of
extractive and exploitative practices
i mean think of organic farming for
example is
not conventional completely but it's
still conventional
it's still about row crops about
confining animals
and so on it's still about extracting
volume and exploiting
uh the space and all of that i'm not
saying it's good or bad
simply i'm saying those are facts those
are indicators
that we are still using a colonizing uh
process in when we design and engineer
agronomical
processes and economics and management
and so on
community social and economic
independence is compromised
when we operate as individual farms our
whole community and social
infrastructure and our interdependence
with other species and also with other
farms
is compromised and there is a tremendous
challenge in trying to work with farmers
within collective systems most farmers
are
are really radically individualistic
and so that is a colonized way of
thinking as well is the result of a
colonizing culture that we act that way
the legitimization and legalization of
violence against
anything that is counted to the system
so when we talk about ancestral
traditions and knowledge and culture and
food sovereignty and it's it's most of
the time
relegated to those who are suffering
minorities
and so on and so forth because they are
the ones who are in trouble the rest
is somehow okay well no it isn't
we are not okay as a society uh so
this legitimization of violence uh also
somehow we use it to legitimize our
attitudes
when it comes down to talking about uh
food sovereignty justice injustice and
um
and diversity and so on the legalization
of abuse of government sponsored
corporate takeovers and market
manipulation
this is this is like day-to-day stuff
we're looking at government sponsoring
corporations to take over whole
countries
food systems uh or whole regions or
or industry sectors and then those
corporations you know manipulate their
way into
into creating artificial markets but
then make it infinitely impossible for
real farmers to succeed
so really important because that is at
this
core of colonizing structures that we
have been building for a long time
that also results in the concentration
of ownership and control of
whole systems i mean we are no longer
looking at farms we're looking at the
whole
system from who owns the brands all the
way through who owns the capital
who owns the infrastructure that
produces that capital
and also the concentration of ownership
and control
on those elements of the system that
make
money versus the the
offloading of all of the risky aspects
of the system to
unsuspecting farmers workers and so on
that's a really important indicator
of a colonized culture that is actually
getting us to this brink of um
you know global collapse the
systematization of vibration of
indigenous knowledge and science i mean
we tend to always want to
um verify so is it scientifically proven
right
so say we are doing poultry with
with the foundational indigenous
knowledge that we inherited and
we're putting poultry back into their
natural environment where they evolved
over
millions of years and yeah that's
indigenous knowledge
and that's in digital science and it is
proven and tested to be more effective
and to be superbly effective and
efficient
yet it has to be somehow
tested and verified by the conventional
community of science scientist community
in order for
for it to be real yet it's more real
than the
recent inventions of of colonizing
science
and management uh so we don't
we don't require that say
monsanto monsanto scientifically
you know or bayer in this case
scientifically demonstrates that
their chemicals will not harm and
instead
enhance the ecosystems if used yet
we demand and we don't accept indigenous
knowledge which is proven and
tested for hundreds of thousands of
years to enhance the environment and to
feed people so
very important uh you know uh systems of
repression that we have
built into our narrative and then our
management systems
now at the end what this results in the
uprooting of
spiritually grounding traditions
individually
raising to the bottom consumerism
climate disruption ecological collapse
war conflict disease and social
breakdown
i mean if you are not seeing those
indicators
scream at us from everywhere in every
corner of the earth right now
um then we are in the wrong room
now there are some also some key outcome
indicators of a decolonized regenerative
bipolar system
and we'll look into a few things that
uh hopefully shifts your paradigm in a
second here
but one of them is that natural
resources are managed in perpetuity not
expected
for short-term gains and it also happens
that managing ecosystems in perpetuity
is at the end more conducive to regular
to generating
wealth than the extraction short-term uh
gains that we can achieve
through exploited colonizing systems now
the difference is
that when natural resources are managing
probability a corporation can't just
come
and extract all the value from an
ecosystem walk away and
leave their locals to to pay
in the communities at large to pay for
the consequences
of the extraction of that value now they
may only be extracting
five percent of what we could extract in
perpetuity
but they do it right away and they are
very efficient at it
and that somehow is validated more
above the more wealth creation and the
more well-being that we can generate if
we manage resources
in perpetuity under a decolonized
process of management
the social and economic independence is
supported as a foundation of success
if that is the truth then you know you
are not in a completely colonized
uh setting ancestral traditions
knowledge wisdom are validated to ensure
collective mental physical and spiritual
well-being
this is central to indigenous ways of
farming
and living community building governance
ownership control
governance organizing and production
infrastructure reflect community needs a
priority for collective wealth creation
distribution
it is not about someone making a profit
it's about everyone being collectively
wealthier
and that at the end of the day generates
a much better quality of life
when resources are distributed on the
basis of how they
their governance infrastructure is built
then the management
of all of that wealth is also done
differently and because of that
more people benefit and there is more
um you know less conflict less war less
of volca these kinds of things that we
have seen under
the colonizing systems we did today now
all supply chains
from land to fork are collectively
controlled in government
you don't have a single company owning
the whole supply chain
and dumping all of the high risk assets
onto farmers such as the
uh as a land and property plant and
equipment in this case
um defending protecting enhancing
collective interest is structured within
the system level governance structures
at all levels at this point we're
talking about indigenous governance
systems that
have survived in the case of guatemala
over
500 years of colonization and are still
defending in protecting
and enhancing the interests of the
communities
that are within those territories so
that is because though we still have
some of those
incredibly structurally sound
and also resilient uh governing
structures from ancestral traditions uh
the current
governing systems have have paired up
completely with the extractive system
that is destroying the very foundation
of what they are governing so
when you focus on this um kind of
outcomes you will recognize
a regenerative system when you see it
the verifiers are simple
spiritual introductions are uplifted um
i'm sorry that i i
got this whole thing in a in the wrong
order so
just stick with me ownership control and
governance are called a collective
affair
okay you don't have a board of directors
of a nonprofit
or a corporation that is actually
or even a country's government that is
actually in control
of the whole system it is a collective
affair
if if you see that then the system is
regenerative
if not it isn't meeting basic food needs
of communities and regions
is the priority not the production of
cocoa for export or coffee for export or
corn and soybeans or
it's not about the practices on the land
i mean that
is part of it of course but it's
regenerative outcomes
can be verified are verified from a
whole different angle when you look at
it
from a decolonized perspective the
environment is protected locally and
globally
but why because if you pollute the
mississippi river
out up all the way up north in the at
thai scale
itasca park for example that pollution
is going to go down the mississippi all
the way to new orleans all the way to
the gulf of mexico
and then from there spread across the
globe so
the whole issue of environmental
management ecological management
it isn't it it's a global priority
it's a global management plan and then
verified yes
locally resilience non-profits
and extraction is a central system level
goal but why
why not profit because we don't really
need to make profits to hit the world
they the communities have fed themselves
for
centuries thousands of years by
exchanging the value of the different
things that
they they generate and yes exchanging
value is the term so but not
profits necessarily a profit is a term
that is is completely connected to
extracting something
out of something else owned by someone
else
normally that's the case so social rule
central and accountability
interdependent and interdependency
well this is where the accountability
then
moves it moves us into the um
the um the objectives of the
of the system so governance for example
is the result of accountability who owns
and controls that's a result of
accountability
and and and so on you know health
focuses on well-being
rather than the management of disease
now think about
the the whole thing we have right now
with uh
diet related diseases in the united
states and
i can remember we're like 10 years that
i heard that it was over 400 billion
dollars um cost to the
society now why why would you really
manage a disease that shouldn't exist in
the first place
right and again the the
health of a community is not it's not
measured by the absence of disease
but but the ability of the organisms in
that community to resist
and bound back from disease that is
called well-being
and that is a foundational principle of
health management
not managing diseases which is where we
focus the colonial
the colonizing processes no wealth is
built and shared
not extracted delivering nutrition is
not simply
food or fill it's the top system
priority so delivering nutrition is the
top system priority
notice it's not about food it's about
nutrition
this system simply is
or isn't regenerative certifications or
outside control schemes are
unnecessary and they are also irrelevant
for a system to be regenerative
if it is then it's regenerating if it
isn't
it isn't regenerating it doesn't matter
if anybody has certified it
labeled it uh built a brand around it
put all these
claims on it that doesn't matter it's
either we tell the court is not
simple as that the focus is also on the
system level indicators outcomes
as products form a farm
or fund practices are simply not
regenerative on their own because only
systems can regenerate that is a
fundamental mistake we're making today
on how we are approaching
this aspect of regenerative thinking
because we are still using
colonizing practices management
science and methodology to
enter this space and instead of
enhancing the ability and preparing
ourselves
in our own approaches to optimize
the incredible magnificent uh
benefits of regenerative ways we are
instead
colonizing this space appropriating it
labeling it
naming it and then building
infrastructure to
protect whatever it is that we think it
is rather than just
allowing it to be the generator
so understanding decolonization
you know this is really critical because
i just what i just said results out of a
mental process that we are
indoctrinated into and domesticated into
so the first step here is the
discovery you know you heard this before
right it's a new land there's new people
there's a new concept there's a new
story
this new discovery then is named then
after his name
is legally appropriated and expropriated
from those who
have preserved it in this case the whole
idea
of how we regenerate ecosystems uh
held together for all you know despite
the incredible forces of colonization
and depression
killed by native communities who are
still practicing indigenous ways
across the world uh according to the u.n
over
80 percent of the biodiversity on the
planet
is held under indigenous communities of
native communities
why because they have always
operated on on mostly decolonized
processes
and so this legal exploitation is
happening to that concept of
regenerative
thinking right now as well um the
standardization and
scale depression ownership and control
systems think about
what we are doing by what we did to
organic by bringing it
under a government institution now
corporations can decide what
organization is and then to a great
extent
and because of that we have still
animals in confinement
and and we still got corn and soybeans
and
row crops and tilling and you know you
know release of
co2 into the air and an organic matter
into the water systems and excess
fertilizers and inputs uh organic or not
they they still destroy the balance of
life
on the ecosystem so this is important to
understand as we think about
what the difference is between you know
conventional regenerative
and organic and all this other uh
terminology that is thrown around all
over the place
now build systems the the the process of
pronunciation
you know optimizes that the last piece
which is the
what i call the colonization of the mind
where with the systems to repress
indigenous thinking and attempts and
indigenizing ways of living and
intellect
are actually consolidated with the
purpose of invalidating
you know in fact scientifically
invalidating or co-opting indigenous
knowledge
the subsidization the subsidizing of
pseudo solutions
such as you know genetically engineered
crops and things like that
are the cost of real and permanent
well-being and progress
so to understand decolonization then you
got to
revert that process in your head you
know we need to go back and rediscover
aboriginal systems and and so on ideas
concepts stories
names of places in in start reversing
that in
in our heads but also in the day-to-day
practices
we need to rename these things we
reclaim and we insecure
so if we're going to name something
a way of uh doing things uh such as
legendary
let's not define it but rather let's
just
rename it it's indigenous agriculture
actually
indigenous not from the perspective of
people who are native to minnesota
or or to my my native country in
guatemala but rather
are indigenous to the earth right this
is a way of farming of thinking of
managing
our relationship as beings of the earth
in you know
as as beings of the earth that depend
on all life on earth and so as we become
more indigenous with our own nature then
we can i absorb this concept and we can
start
you know uh either even naming it we may
name it
a hundred or a thousand different ways
as long as the concept the idea the
story the length
all of those things the rituals and
traditions are actually
uh representative of a way of thinking
that grounds us back
with the original geo evolutionary
processes of the earth
and the magnificent design that we were
delivered for the transformation of
energy
from non-edible into edible forms
through biophysical and chemical
processes
that have existed forever and that are
more than tested to deliver
sufficient food for all of us
so rebuild community governance and
protection systems we're going to
address this
and the last uh of this series uh
indigenizing governance we
we have been you know bringing this back
as a process of
of um of um systematizing decolonization
processes
where governance and the
re-indigenization of it
the holistic governing systems and so on
are
our central standardizing processes to
reclaim and return
aboriginal systems to their original
purpose the purpose of a system and food
from an indigenous perspective is really
to support the holistic thinking
appreciation and enjoyment of life
design and engineering to ensure the
full expression of all living organisms
is materialized now it just happens that
all of that is already going
on we don't have to be engineering a lot
of the
stuff that we are engineering all we
need to is understand how it was already
engineered
and by nature itself and ensure that
every organism
you know expresses itself in the fullest
potential that he was giving
through the geo evolutionary processes
and what it means is simply
you know accepting that a
corn plant may not produce 400 bushels
of
corn per acre if uh managed
in a more holistic way and that is not
a measure of inefficiency or it's not an
indicator
of inefficiency for efficiency
in agriculture in the in in under a
decolonized process
is measured not on the output
of product and pounds and stuff but
rather the throughput
and the transformation ranges of energy
within a system
and so this is um this is an area where
we're going to have to expand
a lot more in the you know and if we
expand it a little bit more on the
previous presentation
and watch that that part of energy
management and
stewardship as a foundation of our
relationship to food
rather than producing things so
expand and organize new systems so we
need to scale up
organizing across communities locally
regionally and nationally
we need to build aggregation of
representation from local
localized governing councils all the way
across the board until we reach
the national levels of building you know
a rejected
congress agriculture congress or
something like that that is actually
growing up from the the communities that
are
embracing degenerative ways so
basically regenerative thinking is a
radical um
is a it's a radical perspective it's a
nature-based foundation
it is subversive uh it's it's it
happens when we become intellectually
insurgent
so what we need is an intellectual
insurgency so that we can
flip the paradigms on which we operate
and build the systems with the integrity
and commitment
when you think as an insurgent then that
integrity and that commitment
becomes the thing that drives you
forward we need that level of passion
but an insurgent is characterized by in
order to actually achieve this
decolonization goal
the beauty of it is that this the
regenerative is an evolutionary process
because
it ignites engagement at scale there is
no better time in the history of human
beings
where we need disengagement at scale
under
structures and organizational processes
that allows us permanence
i'm not talking about a scale as in
protesting
and then going home but rather scale as
in
as in liberating the the consumer from
conventional products
the land from conventional practices
asked from
bank debt of the farm and on and on
adults
um evolutionary we can
adapt we are agile we are resilient when
you
when you operate under a regenerative
framework
this characteristics are the uh
part of the um what defines
what you do this is how we arrive at
this uncompromising destination
called together so no longer think of
regenerative agriculture as
no-till or soil health or or
rotational crops or those are practices
that they are important they are
critical in transitioning
towards regenerative they are i mean
they are all good
they are not the destination though a
regenerative destination
is way way way beyond that
now here's a quick view for one
one process that we have followed in
terms of
how we approach poultry from this
indigenously colonized
way of seeing and working with these
systems
you know first of all we saw the the
landscape
uh from the perspective of the chicken a
landscape the chicken
wants shade it wants canopy he wants to
be protected from the sun
aerial predators it's
wants to have a sheltered or a protected
area to sleep on
normally they will do it on trees blah
blah blah it's a
long story but that's the way we started
the process of
engineering rather than um thinking of
from homo centric perspective what would
we
how can we grow and produce chickens
rather than thinking it that way we said
what would make the chicken express its
maximum potential as an organism
and that's how we ended up with our
current design and our current design
really goes
back to the foundational currency of
farming which is carbon
the the process of managing that
so that we can achieve efficiency
efficiency
not in necessarily the measured in
productivity
or or pounds of chicken per acre or for
building
but rather transformation of energy and
so when we think of it that way
we also achieve the outcomes we want the
pounds and all that
and exceed the expectations but when we
focus on the pounds as a beginning point
then we go quickly into heat conversion
rates and we get locked into that five
percent
of possibilities for innovation and we
ignore the other 95 percent that could
come
from a decolonized point of view
they're naturally occurring energy
transformation systems is really the
foundational production engineering
management sciences
uh in regional economics uh think about
agronomics
in the political system we are deploying
now uh you won't find
a lot of that traditional you know
linear recipe-like
uh process rather what you have is a lot
of indicators observations
and knowledge and wisdom building
formulas
so that we can actually interpret what's
going on so that we know whether that
chicken is actually uh uh
achieving that optimal state of
performance as an organism
and as a result you know we can have
more margins
lower cost less work and so on
uh and then governance the integration
of local regional national collective
enterprises so that we can move
the management systems into the
structures that allows us to
to govern um collectively but also
achieve
those scale level scale levels that
gives us that competitive advantage
in management and so on at that point we
can use a lot of the colonized sciences
because the science itself is not what's
bad the
the corporate structure is not
necessarily what's bad it's the people
and the objectives and
to what end those systems and tools are
used that's what is wrong today
and fortunately for all of us it's a
very small amount of corporate
executives and folks around the world
that actually dominate the colonizing
system
so to actually change it as long as all
of us get together
and start doing this they really don't
mean very much they get all the money
right now because we give it to them
but it is just just that you as he was
given
can be taken away
here is the process by which we
structure a
a multi-dimensional way of thinking
about the chicken
the three places where energy is
transformed at a mass scale on the earth
is one the photosynthetic processes of
plants
so that more photosynthesis for the
synthetic surfaces in your farm
the more effectively you are you are
achieving that first level
of transformation of free accessible
freely accessible energy in the air and
all around us
four times and so on and then bringing
them into that space that you are now
overseeing from an energy transformation
perspective
the second place of transformation on
mars at a mass scale
is the the intestinal gut and the
chewing mechanisms of
animals so whether it's cows and sheep
and pigs and so on so forth
in this case chickens well they don't
have teeth on their beaks but they do
have
uh gizzards which act as a chewing
mechanism
and so that process breaks down
molecular
structures that are molecularly more
difficult for microbes
and other organisms to break apart into
it into
dissolved into the the original
foundational nutrients
so that process in the intestinal gut
and the animals
chewing mechanism is the next place that
on a global perspective
the next level of energy transformation
happens and so as that happens we get to
harvest certain forms of energy
such as eggs and fruits and nuts and all
the
things that we would take on the farm
but it's not about production it's about
energy expressions
and so the next level of transformation
happens in the soil where
again microorganisms both the at the gut
intestinal
microflora and the organisms of the of
the soil
is the equivalent of the intestinal
microflora in our
in our our guts and so those three
places is where
most of the energy is transformed on
planet earth
in between these processes there is a
magnificent assembly of
millions of micro transformation
processes that are
that resulted from the adaptation of
micro and large-scale ecosystems over
geological time
and governed by the laws of
thermodynamics that define
the biophysical and chemical
processes that go into ensuring that
this energy
is endlessly transformed and endlessly
being put into
embark into feathers into eggs into
vegetables into nuts and fruits and so
on so forth
that system never stops to the extent
that that energy
is freely allowed to flow and or is at
least not interrupted as much as we are
doing today
and as long as each of the organisms in
this whole system including ourselves
are expressing the maximum earth given
genetic potential we don't need much of
the engineering that we have
we have done today to colonize the world
the
engineering we have done is mostly for
the purpose of
profit and extraction of it not for the
purpose of feeding the world that that
if anybody doesn't have that clear yet
um
meditate on that um so anyway
out of these processes we get to harvest
energy in different expressions
some of it is not immediately edible so
it goes back into the process again
and again and it becomes different
expressions of energy
you know like the manure from our
chickens is taken out of the barns and
then put into
different agroforestry systems so we can
generate grains and
vegetables and there is no herbs and
anything in the grocery store
uh pretty much or on your table every
day
some of them energy comes back into the
system and that
is how we see energy transformation
as a foundation of the efficiency in
agriculture
now it just happens that according to
some scientific
scientist partners that i work with that
we estimate that no more than 30 to 40
percent of the
energy that is uh um
processed in this cycle needs to it's
actually harvestable immediately
which means that 60 to 70 percent of the
energy
that is captured in the cycles is put
into the system for the next cycle
which means we start energy rich so
meaning
wealthy if we understand that energy
is the currency of agriculture
basically what i'm saying is we
don't operate on flat or linear
uh equations flat surfaces or linear
equations
we think of the landscape as
three-dimensional
first starting from way down under the
ground where the deepest roots can reach
all the way to the top so that we can
optimize the
the every organism capacity
to be the best it can be and to
process the most energy possible if we
do that right
then we will add and we will
automatically become
connected to the fourth dimension to
this space and organisms
which is the spiritual aspect when we
would connect on the spiritual level
then we can achieve the
three-dimensional view
in the three-dimensional capacity to
transform or
support the process transformation of
energy and as a result of that
achieve what many are calling the triple
bottom line
for for the the the economic
social and ecological outcomes are
not in isolation they happen when we are
able to see this three-dimensionality
and as a result of that connect
spiritually then we can achieve a triple
bottom line
and feed of animals the healthiest
foods you could ever find
so this next aspect
is really about just um taking all of
this from the land from the farms
and building collective uh assemblies
of all of these different expressions of
ice
so whether we are farming chickens or
vegetables we
are part of these affinity groups that
can be layered
or across the landscape to build a
collective impact on the basis that
those affinity groups
have common goals and objectives and
measuring
the wealth creation um on the basis of
indicators of collective well-being
so in southeastern minnesota for example
where we
are working right now with 20 farms of
which 11
are bipod community members we
are measuring our collective wealth at
just around 32
million dollars in property plant
equipment
and probably up to 20 million
in intellectual uh property
and uh brand value and all of that so
we are right now collectively sitting on
around 52 to 60 million dollars worth
of collective uh wealth and what that
means is
that we are achieving a level of
collective well-being for example when
we feel depressed or when we don't
have enough time to do the work on the
farm such as last weekend when i needed
to plant ten thousand nasal nuts
there were over 15 of our partners in
the region that
came out and we were able to plant all
of the 28 21 acres
of hazelnuts in three days that's a
collective well-being
why because i'm not suffering mental
depression or
any of those other problems um
individually
while because i have a collective wealth
that we can tap into from the uh
have a little deficit like that that's a
very different concept and it's very
hard for
traditional linear economists to
understand
what it means to actually operate in a
circular economy
thinking designing for and building at
scale we're not compromising scale in
any way
in fact we can design systems that can
deliver much larger scale than the
current conventional
uh system and we can change the numbers
with you on that too
but we don't compromise the small scale
why because in this case for example
these folks from uh urban community in
our region
came to the farm bought the chickens at
eight dollars uh
and then processed them because we have
equipment that they
can use we took all of the byproducts
put it back into the
layering composting systems that we use
we are
able to utilize 100 of the chicken but
more importantly
these families who have traditionally uh
use
the whole chicken they understand that
the value
of the chicken isn't in the breast it's
actually in the thigh the dark meat and
especially
the medicinal value is in the giblets so
the heart delivered the gizzard
all of those parts that i discarded
that's where most of the value for some
of us
is this way they were able to walk away
with about 30 worth of
value for each chicken they purchased at
eight
and which would have sold you know if
they had buy
that chicken in the market they would
have gotten
not only uh not only would they have had
to pay about 22
22 for that chicken but they would have
gotten
about 30 to 35 percent less volume
in terms of nutritional quality so this
way
we can actually deliver food that is so
inexpensive keep in mind inexpensive
naturally is the most most expensive
food
in terms of nutritional value delivered
at the least expensive
cash value at eight dollars in general
terms this is
cheaper um or less expensive
to a family in the inner city than
taizen chicken that is going to make
them sick
or that or other kinds of chicken that
is actually loaded with
antibiotics in in in pharmaceuticals of
all kinds
and also loaded with exploitation of
people and pollution of the
water systems and so on and so forth so
whichever brand
is coming out of conventional systems
out there
is never going to be able to deliver the
kind of nutrition that we can deliver
this way at the cost that we can deliver
now this
is a whole different aspect of food
access thinking
from a decolonized perspective and yes
people have to do their part
these families came to the farm if
they're not willing to do that
i don't know how an inner city family is
ever going to expect
that high quality nutritious food is
going to be delivered to them
at a um affordable price
uh without having to go back and
recreate systems of
subsidies and all of that and remove the
dignity that comes with regenerative
being
so the next layer beyond the farm is
mobile movements
we have one of these in in pinewood
reservation in partnership with my
coaching agricultural systems
they can process up to two thousand
chickens in a day on one of these units
and the next step again layering the
scalability of things
uh we bought a processing facility in
staceyville iowa
collectively between all of us in the
region last year and now is deployed to
process up to one million chickens and
then the next layer
we partnered with the state of minnesota
and the city of alderley
to deploy a regionally branded
regenerative agricultural development
park where we can do up to 10 million
chickens and at least 500 million eggs
and about 14 other products that
are um generated as part of the poultry
system
we've also built a brand it's called
chilean chicken and now we are deploying
two inch farms
this is a collectively owned and managed
company but this also integrates all
everything from grain production
grain processing grain sprouting poultry
production multi-processing
all the way to the distribution
at the end what you really have is fully
integrated systems
rather than farms or products and it's
at this
level that this system becomes
regenerative
the product that comes out of this of
the system then
can be regenerative but a single product
through a
linear supply chain it simply doesn't
does the knot up from a horizontal
perspective
so as you go think of this fundamental
elements of decolonizing all of these
processes
management science and systems that we
have put together if you're a farmer
farm but be a producer no more be a
steward of energy transformation
engage money if you're in the financial
sector that be an extractor of wealth no
more
be a partner and allied in building
collective wealth
if you work for justice and equality be
a savior no more
be an insurgent in your own colonized
world and change from within
buy food but be a consumer no more be a
steward of your body
your mind and your spirit and we all
be better off because of it
we have gone through 45 minutes and i
don't even know if anybody's listening
so let's check
i've been listening with great attention
i i continue to think you're brilliant
um and
um i i'm i'm i'm hoping people feel
sufficiently
um yeah there's a few comments coming
into the chat yes people are expressing
positive
positive responses i was just trying to
think about how to how to say this
um the bar that you hold
is is so high that um
i think we all can hopefully
see where we can do better um i think a
lot of times when you hear
presentations or or concepts and people
want to feel like they're part of the
in-group
um there's this sort of okay now i'm
good enough i'm one of these people i'm
superior i've i've
i've arrived but it's it's so it's so
um it's so comprehensive and so
and so um revolutionary um
i just i really really appreciate your
the
the place it comes from and the um
yeah the call the call the call to rise
to that to that level
um so yeah um i'm i'm happy to engage
engage questions we i mean 45 minutes of
conversation
um is probably better if people are up
for it so
um i can start with a couple other
things that have been posted here
but um anybody who's
would like to engage with questions
please put them in the q a
um so roger asked uh what are examples
of success
the maori in new zealand that was about
25 minutes ago
i think you certainly expressed
quite profoundly what you're doing with
the you know chickens in the midwest
it's really impressive
um did you say how many pounds that
eight dollar chicken
was if you did no but it was
all of our chickens weighed between 3.75
and 4.25 pounds and
and in this case that specific picture
was taken out of
dress chickens that were four point
closer to 4.5 because they included
giblets and
all of the actual edible parts rather
than just the carcass
so those are four and a half plus pound
packages and they're certified organic
or certifiably organic now we are
certifying because a client is willing
to
pay the premium for certification but we
have always been certifiable all of our
protocols meet
the certification we always make sure of
that and then we certify
when when consumers actually care about
that
but the point i want to make is that you
are able to
economically produce certified organic
chicken at two dollars a pound
i mean for any business for a while
that's ridiculous
not to be called somewhere in there i
mean we're not
we are because we have we internalize
all of the costs we're not
we're not dumping any cost on anyone so
i couldn't give you this specific number
because right now we are
30 percent higher higher grain values
um so the the price just
significantly changed this uh spring but
yeah i mean if you talk about afford
affordably
affordably producing chicken that is
free of confinement
free of antibiotics free of everything
we don't want
and full of everything we want uh we are
probably your most competitive chicken
out anywhere the picture behind you is
i mean exactly what i saw when i went to
your house that's what it looks like
they're not in houses they're not
you know i mean they're not confined
except by a fence that's something
of an acre and a half it's it's really
quite inspiring
um and i i don't know if people have
grocked that but i
i i certainly as someone who's been
raising chickens for
i don't know 35 years or something um
you really i feel like i have yeah and
and think keep in mind that
our our methodology and our management
process
is is is grounded on some very simple
principles like for example when we
design something
we always ask everybody to think about
it
from a perspective of being allergic to
work
yeah so if you have to work
find a way not to that's not the point
we don't want to work
now if we have to work on something then
let's make sure that that work is done
in the more in the easiest most most
pleasant and more enjoyable
possible way and that those are simple
things that
have incredibly transformed the way
we actually operate our farms it's
actually really enjoyable
and it's not a putter because that's all
you're doing because the system's in
place and you're just doing a little bit
here a little bit there and it's not
hard we're not hauling chicken tractors
across for a few chickens
we our flocks are 1 500 broilers per
flock
and those chickens don't even like
people because they have never had to be
close to us
they are as as naturally behaving as
possible they got a canopy of trees that
those hazelnuts produce between three
and four times more hazelnuts over the
chickens than on the
where there is no chickens those basil
nuts are also expressing their full
capacity the ground i mean we had soil
scientists geologists we had all these
people come out and
they're like kids in a candy store when
they come out to
evaluate the soil here so anyway
that is beautiful there is no need for
us to be
stressed out about work or getting up at
5 a.m every day i mean i don't really
like that i was
i was a laborer i grew up in poverty i
had to work
from sun up to sundown every single day
and go home
still hungry and poor i don't like the
idea of work
so if i can avoid it believe me i'll
avoid it and that probably
is our greatest competitive advantage
because it just happens that most of you
capital on the farm
goes in this case for poultry goes into
feed and labor
yeah um so i just going to
go back to this question what are
examples of success and
roger asked about the maori in new
zealand i don't know if in this
presentation
you have you've referred to it um and
because i've talked to you in the past i
i think i know what you're saying but
i mean you in today you also talked
about the the
you know the culture in guatemala where
you grew up
and how that is still operating along
these principles and you
referenced i'm not sure who it was some
international agency that said 80
of biodiversity on the planet is
um on land where the people living there
are still indigenous in their mindset so
i mean there's examples of this globally
but are there things you want to say
specifically about your experience in
guatemala or other things
other models where people can see or
understand
where this sort of ultimate paradigm is
is is dominant yeah i know for example
we have
um era and iota those two
they're not girlfriends they're actually
two hurricanes
that hit guatemala honduras and el
salvador
last uh the end of last year in october
now it happens that some of the
communities we work with
are so remote and there are so many
rivers in between and all the bridges
were taken out
uh so those communities actually
reported
having having just they protected the
chickens
and they fed the chickens because that
was their source
of at least one egg a day for every
person
for a few months while the roads reopen
and all that
and it was something that they they they
could feed them
herbs they could harvest the forest they
could do
so many other things they had so many
more options because of that that's a
success story to us
um we also just launched the regenta
poultry cooperative in southeastern
minnesota
all led by minority mostly
you know as hispanic latino um
african-americans
and asian uh farmers and then you know
fully inclusive of a lot of the white
farmers in our region of course
but you know led by us only because we
seem to be more connected to that
indigenousness and these folks were were
interested in that
so they join and of course we're
welcoming them too but
that is another level of success why
because we have succeeded not
necessarily because we built a co-op and
now we're gonna you know we are raising
one and a million dollars and
more people will have access to land and
we've got more more cash flow
that's not a measure of success the
measure of success for us is the fact
that we are able to liberate about
in this case about 1 million chickens
from confinement about i know calculate
how much pharmaceuticals are no longer
going to be part of that
and we are liberating a very large
network of people who would have been
enslaved and meet packers
in other places while having all this
wealth of knowledge and capacity
those are the success stories for us
that's how we measure
success now if we break even
that's like fourth in the list it's
important
of course but breaking even for us is a
whole different
concept i i can't use a regular bep
formula
because it doesn't have enough lines to
include all of the value we create
and so as we think of success those are
those are the the the indicators that we
are succeeding is when people are
liberated
from from stationary exploitative
inhuman conditions
every person is a success story uh that
comes out of a factory farm or a factory
meat packer every farmer who instead of
you know being limited and discriminated
against now owns and operates a farm
uh that they can market where they can
regret
grow driven chickens uh that's a success
story
every chicken that is now in the market
that is not coming from a conventional
system
that's a success story so we have
so many success stories that uh we will
need a bonfire
in some more time to tell you all of
them but also
we have built a super competitive
uh system level scale solution
that is also a success story but most of
the time people start there
that for us is the total outcome of the
individual
success stories that collectively
aggregated
uh signify a system level success
you brilliant and i i would just say
what is coming to my mind right now
is the comment you made about you know
if you're uh
you know if you're a farmer don't you
know harvest crops anymore be a steward
of energy if you're a
you know you work with money don't be a
um
extractor you know however you frame
that i'm sorry i don't have it
um integrated yet into my subconscious
but i think i mean you made the point
about
um how we the people are
actually giving our power to the
corporate system
you know by purchasing these products
and and you know and we and we can we
can give it and we can take it away i
think
you know from some foundational
perspective the responsibility that each
of us has
in how we choose to engage the supply
chain is
the way the world has changed and you
know it's it's great to have these
philosophical conversations
and sort of hopefully be inspired and
and you know
um you know insights are coming to you
but but but walking the talk
thereafter um you know for all of us
is is uh you know
i think we need to be grounding this so
just to just uh just to make that point
um not sure if you want to say anything
about that before i go to the next
question
oh also how how actually easy it is
now i came to this country in 1993
technically
and immediately after i arrived i made
contact with farmers
i made contacts with grocery stores that
sold organic
products and all of that and i think
since
i lived here from since 1993 forward
i have never given profits
to conventional corporations in the food
sector
beyond basis and if they have a role
maybe emergency basis and you're hungry
for a rental car and i i am not
malnourished i am not unhealthy i
actually
all i am well nourished and healthy and
mentally healthy which
took a long time to get to because of
the consequences of the war and all that
but
yet i totally
totally believe and i have
i am proof that everything i laid out
for you
is not only possible it is better
when you do that because you do achieve
the full expression of yourself
and who on this earth doesn't want to be
the full expression of themselves
yeah beautiful now if you don't want to
that's fine dan
uh don't be but i am trying to
i'm just kidding your your passion and
vitality is is infectious it's it's hard
it's hard
i'm going to proceed forward here with
some questions chris
says reggie i'm completely intrigued by
your discussion of organizational models
for creating collective value
and collective impact at multiple scales
where would you point us to learn more
about the details of designing these
types of organizations
oh boy um there is
actually anybody in the group
is part of the food the farm
forum for the future good form for the
future um
organized by this organization out of
england because
she actually just sent a whole list of
resources
answering that very question because i
actually never cared to look around
very much so i was going to
maybe i should just send it to you um
and then you can
distribute to some of those people if
you can find a link and post it in the
chat then everybody
i always uh it's a whole pile of them
but let me um
let me just um look for it while while
we take all the questions
okay um
somebody already just put it on here shy
originated farm
just put to the panelists looks like
oh okay so see if um if you can see the
last
update that the director out of england
sent out
uh was talking about the um
the this resources uh
on secular economy collective collective
management
and so on and they're not calling it
what i call it but
that doesn't matter the name doesn't
matter it's the outcome
all right um greg asked um well says you
are going forward with tree range
chickens
how can we do the same in our own areas
in this case southern california or can
we join your collective
yes no it's a very very
methodically structured takeover plan
literally so the way we operate
is it's pretty simple you have to go to
go to that link region poultry.com
um get in touch with us what we'll do is
instead of us taking our chicken to you
we will work with you as an operating
partner
and then you build a system like the one
we built in southeastern minnesota
in your own region so those operating
partners
have a high level of business
development and ecosystem management
responsibility
but we will transfer all of that to you
and it will take a little bit
it will be slower at the beginning it's
not like just setting up chicken coops
and
and processors and all of that those are
important but
if you start from there then you just
flip back into that colonizing mentality
yeah so so it's critical that we
that we um we talk about it offline
we have a methodology a process and an
organic way
for building regional systems and then
our goal is to build at least
one regional system per state in the
all of the 48 continental um um
territory of the united states the 48
states so once we do that
the goal is to reach at least five
percent of the total
eggs and burials that are consumed
technically
we consume about 20 chickens and 20
dozen eggs a year in this country
we want us as an ecosystem as a national
ecosystem of free-range farmers
to capture one of the egg a dozen eggs
and one of the chickens
as a pivoting point to tip over and then
from there
actually scaled to more regenerative
levels brilliant um okay
dara asks uh when are prices going down
for families with three four and six
kids dozens of eggs a week at six
dollars per dozen is out of reach
premium pricing is a huge barrier that
scares off support i think we talked
about this with your
pounds dollars per pound on the on the
chicken itself but are you selling your
eggs at six
six dollars a dozen no that's what
retailers
sell them up so basically we also have a
dysfunctional system
that increases the cost of of the goods
unnecessarily in some cases
necessarily in others some farmers are
are
increasing the cost of their eggs and
chickens because
because honestly they are working too
much and yeah i don't want them not to
be paid for their
for the work they're doing but for the
most part we have found that we can
we can raise a flock for example on down
to 80 hours per flock
when you know some of the farmers are
using up to 300
hours to flock and that's not we
shouldn't burden the consumer
with that artificial cost that we are
incurring because we are not being
intelligent about
how we manage our own you know labor so
that's one way
it's a criticism but also an
encouragement to think
deeper second um when
you know we can produce a dozen eggs for
about a dollar ninety
uh organic certified in up to 2025
when it is actually very uh expensive to
raise them
whether it's because it's dry or because
the feed went up
uh or so and or we had an incident we
lost
chickens whatever the case may be so but
at that price
the egg is very affordable still now
i know not everybody can access direct
to from the
from the farmers but because we are
building these farms across the
landscape the idea is that eventually
people will have access directly to the
farms
uh so that this eggs don't have to go
through their supply chain
and become triple their value their
their cost
so that's one way to solve this the
other way is
to really operate collectively at such a
scale
that we can move that product without
artificially increasing
the cost out of inefficiencies in the
supply chain
i mean the conventional system raises
the price because they want more profit
so you know those those organic
confinement eggs
they don't have to sell at four and six
dollars they're just making a killing on
it
now in our ecosystem collectively
governed and managed
you know we can be partners all the way
from consumers to the farmers
and we can all do better and including
consumers paying only half of what they
would normally be paying
and still farmers having a decent living
and not
in an honorable way of retiring and so
on so yes that that's the way to
organize this but
but it will take some significant
intellectual insurgencies and
more regional uh regional capacity like
the one we're building in the
bordering region of minnesota i will end
wisconsin
and to be consumers no more as you said
to not just see yourself as someone who
goes to the store but actually take
responsibility for
reintegrating i mean into the process
and that's that's part of it is
as long as you're colonized in that in
that framework that's probably what's
going to be your experience
so that's i mean i've i got my rant
about occupying the land and not
everybody has to be a farmer i
understand but
you know i think a lot of these
solutions only occur
as we deepen our relationship with the
environment and nature
and community um we can't we shouldn't
expect them
to sort of come sort of magically it
only comes through
engagement uh bill and jay asked
are the hazelnuts for chickens to roost
human food or feed
the chickens don't roost on the
hazelnuts um
we have made sure of that um by
trimming the bottom branches if they
start doing that they destroy the plant
and
the hazelnut is very happy to have the
chickens under but not on top
uh they do better uh the the other thing
is hazelnuts are a precious product so
we
if we don't have to feed it to the
chickens we don't
uh we harvest them out of the trees and
it's a product that needs to be roasted
and processed
so it can be food grade uh even if it's
coming from the chicken paradise
now the um as we scale up
uh hazelnuts yes we are thinking of it
as animal feed
but not for the chickens see the
chickens um technically they don't
truly appreciate this kind of gourmet
food so and we can feed them many other
things on the on instead what we are
doing is
developing another line as we increase
the production of hazelnuts
and we're going to be producing a
hazelnut and acorn finish finished
three-range pork
nice and they also provide shade i think
is one of the key
and protection from airborne predators
right yes now the
the hazelnut has evolved over millions
of years probably
um in its own ecosystem right so they
for example the hazelnut can harvest up
to
300 pounds of nitrogen per acre the root
system sprawl
up to 15 feet in in you know from the
you know was seven and a half feet in in
um
radius from the trunk of the tree uh
harvests about eighty percent of his of
its energy
within the first eight to twelve inches
of soil and so
it literally is an inverted umbrella to
capture
especially baltimore and so it's it's uh
phenotypical characteristics also
evolved to attract birds to their trunks
so that they can attract the manure and
so just similar to aronia attracting the
buffalo
and the deer to the wallows in the in
the great plains so that they could
thrive
same thing the hazelnut did the same
thing and he became extremely smart
at doing this and so the chicken
naturally
recognizes this the hazelnut recognizes
it and then they
come become a community there and they
become you know so they feed on each
other so the hazelnut produces a
very thick canopy no hawk can see
through that
and also it sprawls over you know in an
umbrella like
because that's what the chicken needs in
order to conglomerate in there
and then guess what i'm scared chicken
because a hawk is going on over
is what they do right after they run
over and stop
they poop so this is not coincidental
this is
all magnificently designed and so all we
are doing is
reading it learning from it developing
our our indigenous intellect by using
this innate intelligence we were given
at birth
and as a result of that we see all of
that 95 percent of innovations that we
can bring about
because we are not here to colonize the
space when you colonize
you operate on five percent of your
capacity when you decolonize
you access the other 95 percent not only
of the landscape capacity
but of your own capacity in your brain
capacity
your physical capacity it's just
magnificent
that is the story of the aston martin
and the chicken
wonderful and i just want to bring up i
mean as when i walked around your farm
and saw what was going on it wasn't just
hazelnuts
you had you know comfrey and other
things that were also critical
ingredients in the in the paddock so i
mean i'm not sure if you want to share
any of those
specific details for people but one of
the other things that was also
interesting to me was you said certain
plants
don't like chickens underneath them like
apples and peaches
that was nothing i'd never known before
i
you know growing up we had the chickens
in chicken tractors in the orchard or in
paddocks
in the orchard underneath fruit trees
and you said that's really is
counterproductive
so any any moment of insight on that
topic which
i don't know think of it this way every
organism
has a blueprint that is seeking to
accomplish
so whether it's or a nutritional
blueprint
or in the case of northern climate for
example
deciduous trees drop their leaves that's
a blueprint
they are embedded with and they need
certain conditions in the environment to
achieve those
those steps in their process of living
so apples for example
the the that whole family
or the whole species or what you call
genus
requires an amount of cold hours
the plant has to accumulate a certain
number of cold hours
in the root system especially in order
to set fruit to hold it to develop it
and to
reproduce and so what happens is with
the broilers
the broilers conglomerate under the
trees because that's where the shade is
and that's what they get protection from
the predators right
now the other thing that happens as a
result of that is that
they lay on the ground and because they
don't sweat
uh they the way they cool off is by
sprawling
and releasing the heat to the cool
ground under the shade which is around
72 74 degrees on an oval basis
now if their temperature out there is
say 90 degrees
and the temperature of the um the
chicken body is 98 degrees the
temperature of the soil is 70
or 72 within the next two three days
and then forward from there the ground
level temperature
below the chicken breast when they're
laying there is going to rise upwards of
86 degrees and that's beyond
what the apple in this case needs in
order to
cold on and accumulate it it's called
ours
and so i mean i learned about cold hours
in agriculture
school and so when somebody told me in
guatemala right
when somebody told me here that it was
the chicken minor that was causing the
problem i said
i don't think so because there isn't
enough defecation in there
to actually affect the tree in any case
it would benefit it
oh no because it heats up well i took
the temperature readings and no it was
not heating it up
but it did heat up when the chickens
were laying
under so once we isolated that factor
that's when we learned
yeah certain trees uh certain fruit
trees that we
cut those requirements they will not do
well so
knowing the phenotypical and the
genotypical characteristics
and the environmental requirements of a
species is
central so that you can reconcile the
behavior of animals and this is the
black applicable
not just to the broilers but also to
sheep and cows and
and all kinds of other livestock it's
called indigenous intellect for a reason
and so the next step for us was to test
egg layers because egg layers don't sit
around
and so the apple trees took off again
that is the story of the chicken
the broiler and the apple tree and that
applies to a pear tree and a cherry tree
and
a peach tree possibly i didn't try them
on the pears
but i know that if they require the same
which i think they do
yeah then yes okay yes and even even
wild plums had the same exact response
yeah
i think that's very interesting and it's
not the kind of thing you would think
about but i'm sure it's part of
the the deeper training that you provide
people so
um for whatever it's worth i you know i
was totally
like five times now impressed going to
see your operation
um all right we've got about 15 minutes
left and eight nine
let me see if i can move through a few
of them um have you looked at black
soldier fly
feed to cut some of your grain costs to
recycle some food waste
no but we hope somebody in our ecosystem
does that
um bottom line i don't want to do that
work
um honestly but i understand the value
i basically you know listen to one of
those
innovators at a big forum in san
francisco and i thought
well that would be an amazing
opportunity for for
an entrepreneur to come into one of
these ecosystems and set up a
black soldier fly operation so that we
can do exactly
that but the way we see these solutions
is not
i am it's not on a farm level i don't
want to do that on a farm level
when we implement something it's because
it works for the whole
the whole collective and if something
doesn't benefit the
collective uh then we don't do it so
that's why
grain is the same thing until we knew
that we had enough throughput
we didn't get into that now this year we
incorporated a grain elevator because
now we can incorporate the farmers too
so same thing with these other options
we want an entrepreneur to emerge
that entrepreneur then goes and figures
out how to do this part
and then the ecosystem comes in to
ensure that we embrace that
entrepreneur and then solder flies
become part of our ecosystem
but that is that the colonized
management process right there for you
well i mean i think the the idea is if
there's food waste
and it can be used to produce blood
shoulder fly larvae that would
potentially
be a a food source for the chickens
which could easily be applied across the
ecosystem
um oh yeah from uh from a purely you
know biological
and you know purely scientific
perspective i think it's an
awesome option um we just need to be
able to organize it properly from an
entrepreneurial and management
perspective
cool all right cal asks how do you
operate in the winter
layers or broilers taking a winter break
with rollers we take a winter break um
with um
and that's why we are setting up new uh
regional collectives so we just started
the collective out of omaha
and we hope we can find an operating
partner down in
in oklahoma so we can set the southern
collective
and that way we can produce uh broilers
year round without ever having to
produce
in the north uh because we will have
partners everywhere
the egg layers however is different we
we keep them in the winter so the design
of the coops the processes
everything is it's almost like yeah it
is
completely different animals between egg
layers and broilers
so just to give you an idea the egg
layer has a solarium system the solarium
is
passive solar the passive solar allows
us to we focus on heating the ground
as we heat the ground then we can sprout
grains in the winter
we can then sprout grains in artificial
settings and then
freeze that grain and use that frozen
grain as a way to absorb extra
nutrition from nutraceuticals like
elderberry syrup and
and garlic and onion mixtures with
comfrey
extracts and all kinds of things like
that to germinate them
to germinate so sprout the grain before
we freeze it outside and bring it back
into the solariums but then it defrosts
and as it defrosts then it rehydrates
the whole system of the chicken
and those those agronomics and
managerial practices
allows us to eliminate all of the
artificial manipulation of light
and everything else and keep the
efficiency at about 85
during the winter months and the
chickens happy even though we can't let
them out into the open fields
yeah i hope people understood what you
just said that was
it's very impressive um uh
jarrah asks again or she was we had
talked about the six dollar a dozen eggs
she said
the sustainable farmer that delivers
charges six dollars a dozen for eggs
and 15 a pound for kosher chicken so
that's obviously hopefully they're
making good money there
um it's a pretty high price yeah yeah if
they are not
um they're just giving it away to
someone else that's that's the way i see
it and
i don't think there is necessarily
something wrong about it i mean if they
are paying
an immigrant worker a much higher salary
because of the fact that they are
selling that egg
at a much higher price well then let's
all celebrate that
but if they are wasting it and buying um
you know machines and diesel and
gasoline
and something that extracts the value
from that supply chain
well then this be it's been smarter
about it
the basic point is it doesn't need to be
that much right there's there's ways of
doing it much more economically
but yeah oh yeah direct sells i mean we
can do well
at about 350 to 4 a dozen egg
um you know and that's the wholesale
value we are charging
um for actually for i i take that back
the pound of chicken
um so yeah three
times um well yeah about 15 bucks
16 bucks per chicken yeah
um okay um dear asks again john kemp
mentioned that general mills is
transitioning farmland to sustainable
practices how do you feel about that
corporations changing well if they are
doing that
and it is sustainable let's celebrate
that too
um corporations have an important role
to play in regenerating the planet
um but also remember that
like i said before the most corporations
are ran by people who
don't give much of a value to feeding us
into community well-being and health and
all of that fortunately for us it's a
very small minority
so if general mills is
one that is doesn't want to belong in
that space of
exploitation and extraction and
destruction of the planet
that's one more on our side of the fence
and that is always good
now whether they're actually doing it or
not that's what we got to verify
which now the trust issue is there is a
real issue here
i think i've read something about
another there was a was it 15 000 acres
or 5 000 acres or
something i'm not sure where it was in
um
south dakota that they had taken over
and yeah i think it was
two million acres whatever yeah yeah
yeah i mean you can't you really i
didn't yeah it is laughable because
because that ecology doesn't support
what they are doing there
so by definition just growing
oats directly buying them directly from
farmers that has nothing to do with
sustainability or resiliency or
regeneration that those are just
different management
practices that allows a company to claim
another space and to
you know build up a little bit more of
that karma with consumers so that they
can push more products down the line
i mean that's what i see most of the
time but
hey i don't know the specific story here
somebody can tell it and say
no this got integrity then let's
celebrate that
but no integrity no celebration greg
says do you think the healthiest most
nutrient-dense foods can
should also be the least expensive in
theory and to that point if you're going
to be doing monocultures on 5000 acres
um you know only producing one crop
functionally
increases the the cost of production of
that crop right it's only when you've
got these
multi-factor systems where you're you
know cycling cycling energy
and pulling a little bit out here that
that the
the actual cost of production goes down
um yeah
that is correct that's the secularity of
the of natural economics
and and it is extremely efficient at
producing value
uh value that we can harvest and so
yes now the um the um
uh nutritional density and the cost and
all of that
without any fuss right now
we produce nutrients and we deliver
nutrition to consumers at about half the
price of a conventional product
now here's the qualifier dollars per
nutrient
yeah exactly yeah we are not selling
pounds of food
we are selling pounds of nutrition and
from that perspective
it takes up to seven or eight carrots to
deliver the value of one of our carrots
now the carrot itself one of our carrots
may be
two times more expensive than one of the
carrots from the conventional system
but the nutrition in it is about half
the cost
of the nutrition that of the that you
will need to
spend in buying enough nutrition because
you need about eight of those cheaper
carrots to get the same nutrition
so on the nutritional value we are half
as expensive
yeah brilliant um matt
asks um best guess please how much
energy can be saved when your model of
regen farming is compared to an organic
system
and a conventional system from fork to
plate
we really don't know we haven't done a
complete
footprint with imprint
mostly because the methodology being
used actually
is is not compatible with the systems we
are deploying
so the tools are not there to actually
get a full imprint
um i can't tell you that but what i can
tell you is that
just in general conversations with folks
who do this
day to day like david johnson and folks
like that and even you then
what we have figured out is that we are
not harvesting more than 40
of the total energy that we are
harnessing in that space
and that by definition means we end up
it's like if you earn
a dollar and then you only needed to
spend 30 to 40 cents to actually live a
really comfortable life
and every day you put 70 cents into your
next day's
pool that's exactly what we're doing so
i'm happy with that equation
um i mean yeah it will come the point
when we need to
figure out the tools that would allow us
to completely measure
the all of the verifiers of the system
but
the problem is we don't have those tools
right now uh i think
um bio neutral good association is
working on some of those tools
the instruments are certainly of the you
know the the sort of the colonized
western science you know framework but
some of those values that you talked
about at the beginning are the happiness
of the people
and the security and you know stability
of the culture
which you know i don't know if they can
be monetized or captured
in any of those kinds of ways but yeah
that's a whole different conversation
and that's why i'm saying we don't have
the tools yeah because
we we have never built um i mean the
tools we have capture about the same
amount of
what we use of the of the potential of
the landscape is about five percent
so the tools have been developed to
measure that five percent but
what about the other ninety-five percent
we don't know how to measure that yet
now we know it's there because we can
feel it
and it actually shows and it's real it's
tangible
it's enjoyable and all of those things
and so yeah that's all i need to verify
that this is good
the rest of it yeah leave it to the
scientists that validated the very
system
that is wrecking the planet i don't
think they have the moral authority to
come and validate
the incredible benefits that we are
already generating
there's a yeah there's various paradigms
of engagement
uh just in the last couple of minutes
lenoir asked i'm with you
but given the factors of the way land is
owned by a wealthy few
laws perpetuate degeneration and
colonization and poverty levels
i would like to see a practical
step-by-step insurgency process slash
blueprint of how to transform this local
global entrenched economic and political
system
to a humane regenerative system come to
your next presentation right
yes we we do have not a complete
step-by-step blueprint but believe me we
probably have as close as it gets to
building a global intellectual
insurgency
and to and it goes right down to the
farmer to the consumer
and the steps we need to take to take
back the ownership control and
governance
that is the secret and if we can do that
um here's the thing it is so doable
and it is so easy to do uh once you are
convinced that that's what you want once
you become an insurgent
then it's easy the problem is getting
people from where they are right now
in their position of privilege and
comfort and being willing to be
uncomfortable for a while
and living really in real life so that
they can experience the real solutions
and then become enchanted with the
resolutions to the point that they will
never go back
that's the transition but we're gonna
have the most problems but those folks
like and i hear this person is probably
already
on this other side uh there is enough of
us right now that a global insurgency
now
is totally doable within the food and
agriculture system
and if we can just network ourselves
under the
mycelial structures and methodology of
the earth itself
we will replicate the most powerful
organism on earth which is the mycelia
and that
is our blueprint for the future is
the mycelial blueprint replicated in our
brain
replicated in the order of the universe
replicated in the way we have built and
connected
cities and centers now replicating it to
take over the food system again
we have done it so many times we just
don't know we already done it
yeah beautiful um okay
a couple last little questions uh shire
um
asks uh what are the first three
ingredients ingredients
of your non-live chicken feed
okay so we have um first of all
high protein um non-live
i'm guessing i'm guessing what's meant
is like grains versus
sprouts but i'm not i'm not actually
sure right so
let's put it non-ground okay so
basically
when you grind grain you are killing it
so you have deprived it from its ability
to live
and now it becomes mass biomass and so
literally there is no ability for that
organism anymore to
interact because it's dead so what we do
is
in the non-ground up dead
is where we we focus on high protein
low fiber uh forages and so
within that the king of all of them is
country
26 protein only about 10 to 11
fiber and succulent which means the
chickens can roam forever because they
don't have to go back for water
more than like you know maybe five
twenty five percent of the time than
they
if they were eating dry grain for
example one
two um we look for weeds uh
that are got the same characteristics so
mallow for example lamb quarters
porcelain all of those are actually
succulent but also
high protein low in fiber we avoid
grasses
all together unless it's just sprouted
so we bring grass seeds in the form of
wheat
barley oats and then we sprout them and
we have the chickens roaming in there
within the first two to three up to four
days after this
the grain sprouts but we don't want it
to grow because the second that
that grain starts to grow a stem it
completely flips the equation and it
goes high in fiber
low in protein and at that point it rubs
the chicken
of its nutritional needs instead it will
it works the opposite and when it takes
energy away right
they sprout what you do is you take the
whole grains you broadcast them out
in the paddock you cover them with a
little bit of hay and then if it's
dry out you water them so you're not
sprouting them in trays
inside and bringing them out to the
chickens you're just broadcasting them
out into the paddock is what i
experienced right it's a whole different
way of doing things
oh yeah yeah and part of the part of the
reason we can do this at a scale
is one because you can just put these
grain mixes right into your
tractor spreader and take 600 pounds and
just spread them down the alleys
uh one two it sprays him horizontally
which means it goes under the trees as
you can see in the in the picture
now three th the the the
the cover crops in the ground they shade
from the trees
and the amount of organic matter in that
soil means a high level of
humidity in that soil even during
droughts there is a lot of humidity that
condenses there that means
easy way to sprout and if you're smart
before you get those units
established you can put an irrigation
system which is what i'm doing now in
the new farms not for the purpose of
extracting water out of a system you
could take drain water
put it into a big pool and then pump it
and you only have to do a little tiny
bit
of that because you already have an
environment that will preserve and
conserve the water
anyway and bam you got a massive
sprouting system and
now i know i'll just tell you this
confidently to all of you
uh two years ago we raised a flock of
broilers
and we were able to remove the ground up
feed
100 of it for four weeks
and they still mature just five days
delay than the rest of the chickens that
were on that regular diet
so i'm telling you that they the the
level of innovation
and the ability of us to compete
collectively if we can do this at a
scale
it's so massive uh it's it's a real a
real hack
of a system yeah beautiful well that's
probably a good way to end we're over
time but are there any
final insights or comments you'd like to
share with us before we
say thank you to everyone well it looks
like
greg is fired up and wants to do the
whole thing
so yeah give him my email i don't know
if i have access to his
looks like you gave him you gave me your
website so he can find you but yeah
okay i'm gonna give you my email
directly greg
okay well thank you reggie i really
appreciate
you having gone through now three
sessions with us and looking forward to
the
to the uh the the climax
presentation next time people think this
has been good wait till wait till he
actually lets it all hang out
but yeah thank you very much feed the
chickens
free the people all right
great thank you all
you