[Applause]
[Music]
n
just a few years ago I was right where
you are trying to figure out how to
build an affordable Greenhouse structure
now just a few years later and I've
built four of these green houses that
I'm standing in right now and in this
video I'm going to show you an
affordable DIY Greenhouse so easy anyone
can build it with no experience or prior
knowledge you'll also learn how to build
scissor door end walls install a Wi-Fi
controlled irrigation system with
rainwater catchment and make sure you
watch it till the end cuz I'm going to
show you how I built all this and didn't
pay a single dollar and you might be
able to also hey what's up everybody I'm
Chef Mikey welcome back to Chef's
Harvest Farm I'm a former executive chef
who turned my gardening hobby into a
full-time business when I started
growing food I knew nothing about
gardening I also knew nothing about
building green houses I started with one
little raised bed box garden that filled
with soil that I bought at Home Depot
and I started growing seedlings under
grow lights in my basement my first
Greenhouse was a swing set that I found
in the trees behind my house I'll go
over a few of the options that I
researched before I built this
greenhouse but if you want to fast
forward to the build on this greenhouse
you can fast forward to this time in the
video so I bought some greenhouse
plastic from greenhousemegastore.com
threw it over the top of the swing set
and held it down with bricks and rocks
or whatever I could find at the time and
this Got Me by for a little bit while I
taught myself to grow food but as you
can imagine there were many days when
I'd come home from work and the
greenhouse plastic had blown away so I
started researching how to build a
greenhouse I had very little money to
invest I looked at the cheap Amazon and
Walmart options but I needed something a
little more heavy duty at this point I'd
kind of started selling veggies at work
and I was kind of flirting with the idea
of turning it into a business so I knew
I needed something that would be
Dependable stand up to the elements
strong enough to use the structure for
trellising and possible snow loads so I
started looking at DIY options I saw
some people on YouTube making Hoops out
a PVC pipe and then installing
greenhouse plastic over the PVC pipes
and this seemed like a great option for
me I thought it seemed like something I
might have the skill set to figure out
and it seemed like I could purchase all
the materials rather easily but as I did
more research I learned that when PVC
and greenhouse plastic touch each other
and are exposed to UV light there's a
chemical reaction that will degrade the
greenhouse plastic very
quickly and also PVC is not made to
withstand elements so over time it'll
degrade rather quickly from being
exposed to extreme heat sunlight and
cold and your structure will most likely
not be usable anymore in just a few
short
years so then I saw the cattle panel
Greenhouse and I think this is a really
cool option if you just want something
really small but it would not be a good
option for anything with high ceilings
or that's wider than like 5 or 6 fet so
it's a great option but just not what I
was looking for so if you've used either
of these methods successfully let us
know in the comments so people can read
the comments and then they can get some
feedback from some people who have
actually used these methods because I
just researched them and I never
actually used them next I learned that
many green houses are made made out a
chain link fencing top Rail and that
most of the hardware is also parts from
chain link fencing people use chain link
fencing top Rail and bend the Hoops
using a hoop Bender you can buy a kit
from bootstrap farmer where they'll send
you all of the hardware you need to put
it together and then you have to go to
Home Depot or Lowe's and buy the chain
link fencing top Rail and lumber and
bend the top rail yourself using a hoop
Bender but I wasn't too sure about my
skill set in this at the time this would
be a viable option for me and trips to
Home Depot and Lowe's just didn't sound
attractive it seemed like there was a
lot of room for error plus what are you
going to do walk around Home Depot and
lows with 1,000 lbs of Steel and Lumber
in your cart like nah there's got to be
an easier
way a perfect example of this is that
when I was building the end walls on
this greenhouse I ran out of
self-tapping screws so I ran to loads to
get some more well I got back I tried
the screws and they were not
self-tapping so I had to go back return
them get the right ones and luckily
Lowe's is only 5 minutes from the farm
here so it's not a big deal for me but
you can see how that would get costly if
you had to run back and forth all the
time to Lowe's and it wasn't very close
for
you so then I started Googling
Greenhouse companies and most of the
websites I could find didn't actually
post their prices it's like you have to
send them a request for a quote and then
I got these quotes back and they're like
the $10,000 range and that just wasn't
feasible for me at the
time but then I learned about this
company called farmer friend and they'll
ship you a kit with all the hardware and
chain link fencing top rail already bent
to size in a kit on a pallet and I did
some research and I decided this was
going to be the best option for me no
trips to Home Depot or Lowe's for
supplies no trying to figure anything
out everything you need just comes
together with instructions including the
greenhouse plastic they have two styles
of what they call caterpillar tunnels
they're quanset which is rounded like
this one here or they Gothic which is
what I just built and I have three of
them I like the gothic style better cuz
it allows for more height on the sides
and in the middle and then they come in
2550 or 100t lengths I have four of
these in total right now and they're all
50 ft lengths and 16 ft wide the ones I
have are the pro kits which means they
have a solid piece of chain link fencing
top rail down the center and it also has
12-in lift kits with wind bracing on all
the corners this model currently sells
for about
$2500 then they do sell a more basic kit
which is literally just hoops and the
hardware to attach plastic and rather
than the solid pipe down the middle to
hold it all together it's just held
together with a strap and this model
costs about $2,000 right now so honestly
I just spend and the extra $500 for the
peace of mind that you have a little
extra support in Wind rain and
snow I'm building this greenhouse in an
already established no till Garden so
the day before we built it these beds
had crops in them so the first step for
me was to harvest the crops and get the
entire area cleaned
out then we just ratee the area as
smooth as possible because I've got two
of these tunnels right next to each
other I had to move everything over and
I actually lost a bed to account for the
additional flow of watershed in between
the tunnels so just put some thought
into where all the extra water is going
to go this is going to be different for
everyone but it's something you
definitely need to think about now my
entire Garden is on an 8% slope and I've
built the entire Garden facing down the
slope so that water runs in between the
tunnels and away from the garden so I
don't really experience any wash out
when it rains with this method and I've
also dug a ditch in between clean the
tunnels and line them with wood chips
and this helps with erosion control so
if anything does wash away it's wood
chips and not soil particles I do end up
putting additional wood chips in between
the tunnels a couple of times a year but
this but I do this in all of my Pathways
around the farm so it's just a normal
part of my operational
practices the context in which you're
building your high tunnel could be very
different from mine but it's important
that you deal with any grass and weeds
before you start building your tunnel
one of the great things about this style
of greenhouse is the ground does not
need to be perfectly level like I said
I'm on a 8% slope and I've never tilled
my soil or had it graded I've just red
it and otherwise I'm just working with
what I have but you might need to
prepare your ground
accordingly once we got the area cleaned
out I had one person measure out the
corners and pound in 3ft pieces of rebar
to Mark the corners once we had it
Square I had her pound rebar in every 5
ft which is the hoop spacing we're going
with on these tunnels Meanwhile my
friend Dawn and I were putting the hoops
together every other hoop on this build
gets a piece of wind bracing installed
at the top so we're careful to install
them in the correct order and then lean
them up against my shed in the order in
which they will be installed so when we
install them all we need to do is easily
walk them into place it's just a
headache to install if you don't have
them staged in the correct
order so the next step my friends and I
just walk them into place the entire
process up until this point only took
about 2 hours and the skeleton of the
structure is up next I installed the
center Pearl in down the middle and I
just left it Loose then I go back and
tighten everything ensuring that they're
all exactly 5 ft apart once the center
post is installed I zip tied the
irrigation lines for the sprinkler
system to the pipe it's much easier to
install any additional Hardware like
irrigation or trellising wire before you
put the plastic on I did also install
trellising wire at this point because
I'm planning to grow indeterminant
tomatoes in this tunnel next
season one thing I could never seem to
figure out when researching how to build
a greenhouse is how do they attach the
plastic to the greenhouse Well turns out
there's a piece of Hardware made
specifically for this purpose and it's
called channel lock and wiggle wire and
you can buy this stuff at Amazon or any
greenhouse supply store so I usually
just buy it from Amazon I'll leave a
link for everything in this build below
including a link to the kit and
irrigation
supplies the next big step is getting
the plastic on one thing to always be
careful of when building any type of
greenhouse structure is that you want
the screws bolts in any hardware to be
facing inwards so when you install the
plastic you don't rip it it comes on a
roll and we just rolled it out out to
the length we needed and then we cut it
then the four of us pulled it over the
top pretty easily I used wiggle wire to
hold it in place on the top when making
the final adjustments and then the
Plastics just held down by rope which
zigzags down the tunnel Back in Forth
connecting to the carabiners at the
bottom of each hoop this is what secures
the plastic to the structure so it
doesn't flop around in the wind and then
it also allows you to lift up the sides
for ventilation and then this is it this
is what they say you on the pallet it's
just the bones of the structure and then
the plastic to go over top of it
basically they take the headache out of
trying to build your own from scratch
and then send you all these parts on a
pallet and then the rest is up to you
you can customize the structure to be
whatever you want it to be now you do
need to be able to manage a pallet that
weighs about 1,000 to 3,000 lb I do have
a small tractor with fork lifts but it
only lifts about 700 lb so what I do is
just message Farmers for friend and have
them ship it to a local Freight Hub and
then I go pick it up with my truck and
have them put it in the back of my truck
then I drive my truck to a place it's
easier to unload using my tractor this
way I'm not out in the middle of the
street trying to unload a tractor
trailer with a under sufficient tractor
for the job and I can just take my time
to make sure everything's unloaded
safely and
carefully the next day I had my friend
Max come back and the two of us measured
out beds and walkways and re built them
using my typical no till methods where I
just put compost 3 to 4 in deep in the
beds and wood chips in the walkways then
I did all the finishing touches of
setting up the irrigation and building
the end walls
myself so since we zip tied the
irrigation Mainline to the center
pearlin before we installed the plastic
all that was left for me to do was
install the water filter with pressure
reducer hook into the water line and
flesh out the system before installing
the sprinkler heads the overhead
irrigation system is a kit that you can
buy from Farmer's
friend and all of the drip irrigation I
get from a company called drip depot.com
which is where I typically get all of my
Irrigation Supplies but whatever you do
definitely do not Overlook irrigating
your Greenhouse since it will never rain
in there otherwise you will need to
water everything by hand I have overhead
Sprinklers and RP irrigation installed
in all of my green houses so that I have
maximum control over the moisture in
them and I have it all controlled using
Wi-Fi controlled
timer so I can control every aspect of
my irrigation from my phone wherever I
have an internet connection it's
actually a super simple setup it's just
a beehive timer from orbits that plugs
into a regular hose adapter on my house
and it comes with this little Hub that
plugs into any wall outlet
download the app and you're up and
running the entire Wi-Fi controlled
timer was only about
$150 and it is well worth the investment
I can't tell you how many trips to the
water faucet this inexpensive piece of
infrastructure has saved me and then I
also have all of the drip lines on my
green houses tapped into a line that is
fed from my rainwater catchment tank
hooked up to the gutters on my house but
it only holds 500 gallons of water right
now so it's also hooked into to the
Wi-Fi controlled system to supplement
with City water as needed this system is
a working progress but I'll definitely
be posting a video about the irrigation
system soon now it's around Christmas
and New Year's at the time of installing
all this so it's pretty cold out however
I did manage to have a little bit of a
warm spell with temps in the 50s during
the irrigation setup but it's not
recommended to install Irrigation in the
winter because it's very difficult to
work with with the plastic tubing when
it's cold it will Kink which causes
stress points which will eventually lead
to leaks in your line so generally
speaking you will want to install it on
a warm day with Temps at least in the
70s but since I needed to get this
installed I used a blowtorch to lightly
heat up the tubing so that it's more
pliable then I use it to expand the
connection points for easier
installation these connections can be
very challenging to work with when it's
cold after I got the irrigation all
dialed in now it's time to wrap it all
up with the scissor door end walls now I
did not make this up or anything like
that I got the plans from Johnny's
selected seeds which is where I order
about 90% of all my seeds from I'll
leave a link in the description but they
have pretty detailed instructions on
their website and hopefully with this
video it helps you put it all
together so the first step is to get the
supplies you can order them off the
internet probably but I just went to
Home Depot for these supplies you will
need these clips which Johnny sells for
like $10 each but I just buy the clips
from Amazon and they're like $20 for 10
of them so we're basically building four
separate doors Two on each end and they
will open like a curtain the first step
is to get four pieces of chain link
fencing top Rail and measure the tallest
point of your tunnel and cut them
accordingly I bought 10 1/2t pieces and
I cut them to 9 ft making sure to cut
off the s edged end because then I took
the 18-in piece that I cut off and I
climbed up the ladder and installed it
into the piece of top rail that we used
as the center
pearing I secured it with a self-tapping
screw then I just drilled a hole in the
9t piece of top Rail and inserted what
they call a tension band that I got from
the fencing aisle in Home Depot and held
it all together with a carriage bolt now
my top rail has a loop on it and I can
hang it from the piece that I just
inserted into into the end of the center
pearling which is held on with some more
self-tapping screws so it doesn't slip
off the end of the pipe I took the other
swedged end that we cut off and I pound
that one into the ground right next to
where the doors come together this is
how we will secure the doors closed
using a wire tie then I measured the
plastic and I cut it to sides to fit
each door separately I climbed the
ladder and attach the plastic to the
peak and hold it in place with a few
Wiggles of the wiggle wire then as I
come down down the ladder I attach the
plastic to the inside of the 9- Ft piece
of top rail door using the clips that I
purchased from
Amazon so the door is locked in place by
the wire tie so it doesn't move with the
plastic attached and I can stretch it
over to the side where I can install it
into the channel
lock once I have it attached I can go
and make adjustments as needed now I can
pull it tight and install the wiggle
wire all the way up in the same channel
lock that's holding down the greenhouse
plastic I find I can usually Jam about
three wiggle wires deep in one channel
lock and you want to make sure you start
at one end and finish at the other
pushing out any slack as you go do not
start at both ends and meet in the
middle you'll end up with a crinkled
door that could catch wind or hold water
once I had it installed into the channel
lock then I could go back to the clips
and make any adjustments as necessary
and then I secure each clip with one
self-tapping screw
now to hold it all together I picked up
these heavy duty picture frame hanger
looking
thingies I found them in the aisle with
bungee cords I think they're for
securing bungee cords or something like
that but I attach this with self-tapping
screws on the outside of the tunnel over
the plastic then I just tie it with a
piece of extra rope from the wind
bracing on the inside of the tunnel once
you get the first one done you can go
ahead secure it open so you can work on
the next one and repeat these steps on
all four doors it takes me about 30
minutes per door to install them once I
have everything staged but total time
spent on the end walls was pretty much
most of the day since I had to go to
Home Depot twice I'll also share with
you another type of end wall that I've
built on my Nursery tunnel but I would
not recommend this type of end wall for
several reasons first it's made of wood
so the wood will eventually rot and need
to be replaced it will not stand the
test of time otherwise these structures
will pretty much much last a lifetime
but the main reason I don't like this
style of end wall is because it blocks
the sides of the tunnels on the ends
which makes it difficult to use the
paper pot transplanter and the Jang
Cedar which are my two main planting
tools they also took me twice as long to
build there's far more measuring cutting
screwing and overall work involved and
they do not allow for maximum air flow
through the tunnel when open the scissor
door option is by far the easiest
cheapest and most efficient end wall
option I've come up with but let people
know in the comments if you disagree and
have a better option we should be aware
of now this is the fourth one of these
that I've built and all of the other
three I did completely by myself With a
Little Help From My wife or a friend to
put the plastic on so it's definitely
possible to build this by yourself but I
figure however you look at it it's about
30 to 40 hours worth of Labor total
including installing the end walls and
irrigation which obviously goes a lot
faster with more people but in my
context the ground was already prepared
so depending on your context it could
take a little longer and you may need to
do some ground
workor but the great thing about these
tunnels is that the ground does not need
to be perfectly level or flat and
honestly none of my tunnels are perfect
construction I always find flaws in my
construction something isn't perfectly
straight looks crooked but the truth is
that once I put put the plastic on and
start growing crops I never think about
those imperfections again the plants
don't care and often times good enough
is good enough when it comes to these
types of
structures so as promised let me tell
you how I built this absolutely free in
fact I actually turned a profit from
building this High tunnel there's a
department within the USDA called the
nrcs which stands for the national
resource conservation program the soil
conservation Act was passed April 27th
1935 amid the Dust Bowl leading to the
creation of the soil conservation
service now known as the nrcs and The
nrcs Works within Agriculture and any
type of natural resource conservation
you can think of they offer High tunnel
grants within their equip program to
assist with soil erosion and I heard of
this program before but I just figured
it was for bigger farms and that I was
too small and they wouldn't take me
serious ly but after I paid out of
pocket for the first three I figured
what the heck let me walk in there and
talk to these people so I just walked
into my local County USDA office and
told them I wanted to apply for a high
tunnel Grant they seemed thrilled that I
was there I think it's an underutilized
program and there's a lot that goes into
actually receiving the grant that's
completely out of your control but I
will say this there's some basic rules
and regulations it's the government
you're dealing with here but it can pay
dividends to make these people your
friends I've openly invited them to my
operation which they love coming here I
think my property serves as a model of
what can really be done on a small piece
of land I've also recommended the
program to some of my friends who have
also received the grants and I think
they really appreciate that because if
they don't use the funds allocated by
the government then they lose the funds
for the following year and I've already
applied for another high tunnel Grant
which I've not been approved for yet so
stay tuned for another potential
Greenhouse build in the future but my
point is that a lot of people are stand
office just because they work for the
government but these people are here to
help you be successful once I was
approved they came out do a site
evaluation and the USDA rule states that
they will not put grant funds towards a
high tunnel on land that is more than a
5% grade and my entire Garden is on an
8% slope they came out surveyed it and
told me I would have to have have the
land graded and I explained to them in
detail my noil systems which rely
heavily on wood chip mulch for erosion
control and that having the land graded
is going to be more detrimental to the
soil Health than being on an 8% slope I
mean I spent the last 5 years making the
soil in my backyard like potting soil I
told them that is not worth the money to
have a skid steer back here and they
said okay let me send that to the top
and because of my no tail practice
practices which rely heavily on mulches
they got the head of the nrcs to approve
my high tunnel to be installed on an 8%
slope so I share this with you because
it's not always easy you might hit some
speed bumps the whole process took about
a year it's a lot of work and they're
not just going to hand you money you're
not entitled to anything you need to put
the money up front and then once you
build it they will generously reimburse
you and they pay by the square foot so
for instance one of my friends took his
Grant and built a $116,000 heated
greenhouse and they paid for $8,000 of
it and then he paid the rest out of
pocket and I think that's often how it
works the grant usually pays for a
portion not the whole thing but I
thought the opposite I thought well I
can probably build this for less than
they pay and I did so I actually profit
a $0000 for building this greenhouse and
at the end of the day the nrcs invested
a prettyy large sum of money into my
business through several grants that I
don't need to pay back but one last
thing to understand is that the grants
are for the erodable land upon which it
is built it is not for you personally or
your business so if I sell my house the
greenhouse that was paid for with the
grant money will have to come with the
house but there are time limitations
after like 5 years then I could take it
with me one quick announcement before I
sign off I've leased a new farm for the
2024 season so stay tuned to find out
how I leased a farm for $0 and see how
I'm going to turn this new property into
a no till Oasis all right everyone
thanks so much for watching this video I
hope you got something out of it make
sure to like the video if you like the
video and subscribe if you're not
already and I'll see y'all in the next
one
[Music]