good morning modern standards we've been
getting a lot of questions lately about
our winter piglets I guess they're
really not winter piglets but about our
winter pink so we got to give them some
water
we've got some food scraps for him let's
go have a chat with him like a fireside
chat with piglets they're waiting for us
hello prosciutto and Coppa I'll get some
left over they smell the leftover food I
have some of the first questions have
been your piglets a huge are there
really piglets well that's the debatable
I guess we wanted to get piglets that
were at least 60 pounds so that way we
knew they had enough fat on them to make
it through the winter here being in
northern New Hampshire for just the two
of them being outside once the piglets
get bigger you don't have to worry about
them being outside and if you got like a
thirty pound cake lit and you live in a
northern climate like we do and you only
had two of them they're gonna they're
gonna have trouble staying warm for a
little while so we went to the farm we
picked out our pigs I'll put a video
right here the farm at raised the
piglets out on pasture their whole life
he had six of them in a pen when we got
there there are around sixty pounds or
so when we picked them out these are the
two we wanted so he kept him in the barn
for a week and he fed him grain and they
packed on the pounds if they weren't a
hundred pounds when we got him last week
there are a hundred pounds now they're
huge so we're not gonna have any issues
with these two pigs going through the
winter time which is perfect that's what
we wanted winter pigs are gonna go
through more food because they burn a
lot more calories just to keep warm
their feed to weight conversion
isn't going to be as good as it is
during the spring and summer months now
for us in our area winter piglets are
cheaper
we paid one hundred and twenty five
dollars per piglet in the springtime and
those piglets were around 30 to 40
pounds
our winter piglets we paid $75 a piglet
form and they were between 80 and a
hundred pounds there's a huge difference
right there the biggest reason for that
is supply and demand most people want to
raise their pigs in the springtime and
in the wintertime the average person
doesn't want to be bothered with it the
nice part about that is that's going to
offset the cost we're going to have
invested in the feed and the bedding
only raising them outside hair on
pasture I'll bring you up close to them
the Heritage raised pigs they're not
pink pigs their heritage breeds and look
how hairy they are these pigs are gonna
do amazingly well in the colder weather
we're using hay for bedding they have an
area where they can get in out of the
wind and they can bury themselves and
hay the reason why we're using hay
versus straw straw is like double the
price of hay there's not a lot of
farmers up here who grow wheat so I
think that's the biggest reason they got
a chuck in all the straw pigs do really
well outside of the elements they just
need a place to be in and out of from
the rain and the wind so it doesn't need
to be a fancy barn or heated barn
they just need a place to get in out of
the elements think of wild pigs they do
really well outside constantly when I'm
raising animals I like to think about
that like oh the animals thrive or do in
nature normally how do they do it so I
kind of try to implement those plans in
action when we're raising up here
we're going to be doing the deep bedding
system not just in where they can get in
and out of the weather but the whole
head we're just gonna be layering it
more and more with hay whatever we can
get our hands on throughout the winter
we are gonna be spending money on the
hay and whatever else we can get for our
deep bedding but we need to think about
that as an investment into our food
freedom this right here the deep bedding
system is a big part of our food freedom
we're gonna compost this and this is
gonna grow our beautiful food next year
and then we'll have a huge abundance for
us to give away to friends and family
and feed our animals in return to make
us some peanut better bake it you can't
get any better than that we install the
hot and cold water spigot on our house
okay so we have access to hot water
during our three-day hog harvesting
classes I'll put a link to those videos
right here it's been working on amazing
I even have an access to warm water to
give to the animals the chickens love it
the pigs love it right for shoot oh
you'll love in the warm water the way I
look at that is but no one give them two
Hut cuz we can burn them but on a cold
day like right now it's cold outside I'm
looking forward to going into havin a
hot cup of coffee so I think about I bet
my pigs would like a hot cup of coffee
and I bring out their warm water that's
what I'm thinking I'm bringing them out
their hot cup of coffee for the morning
the afternoon for the night just to
finish the day off not their day off
strong form on the really cold days we
can make a mash out of their food with
warm water thanks I'm glad you like the
sweatshirt we just got our new
sweatshirts and t-shirts in they're
gonna be up on our website at Lemna a
curse.com
we got two different color sweatshirts
two different color men's two t-shirts
two different color fitted women shirts
that Gina picked out in two different
color kids shirts that Olivia picked up
I'll put a link in the description down
below
we just hit 14 thousand subscribers I
wanted to thank all the modern stutters
who's helped us with that when we had
twenty thousand subscribers we're going
to be giving away an automatic chicken
plucker I'm going to put a link to that
video right here and to our blog post in
the description down below
you can go check out either one of those
if I know how you can enter in for your
chance to win one of the other reasons I
love having animals around on the
homestead is when it's cold out and when
do you don't always feel like getting
outside and enjoying it and sometimes
you're not going to enjoy going out and
how to take care of the animals and
that's fine there's nothing wrong with
it but I really enjoy having the winter
animals as it forces me to get out every
day at least twice a day and go feed
them in water and it makes me go outside
and enjoy the beauty yes it might be
called but it's beautiful
right now it's snowing up I wasn't
already taking care of my pigs I'd be
inside so I just love that it it forces
me to get out and it makes me look at
the elements in a different way it makes
me see the beauty around the farm
one thing I love and enjoy doing is
taking photos for Instagram I don't do
it all the time
but I do enjoy taking a nice snapshot of
an area and then I can appreciate it
more when I upload to Instagram like I
wasn't looking at just that one area I
was looking at the bigger picture
sometimes it's just nice to focus in on
a small thing and see what you've done
and what you've accomplished and it
makes you feel a lot better but what's
going on sometimes it's just so much
chaotic stuff going around in our life
in the world on the homestead to just
narrow it on one thing that you've done
or that you're doing that you really
enjoy just makes you feel that much
better and having animals on the
homestead and forcing you to go out
every day to me that helps me do it and
I really enjoy that I hope I answered
everybody's questions if I did it then
even in the comments down below and I'll
either reply to them there or I'll make
another video and answer them we hope
you enjoyed today's video if you did
give it a thumbs up share it it really
helps our channel grow and it helps just
we treat people and we wanted to thank
you all for that
and we'll see you right back here
tomorrow at love the acres guide modern
homesteading self-sufficiency and
freedom I