Health in a lot of ways is about
complexity you need a complex gut biome
you need a complex set of lots of
different types of
micronutrients that's true for people
that's also true for plants right so
plants are sending their Roots out into
the soil and they're asking for a
complex bed of micronutrients they need
like organic Healthy Living soil most of
the time what they get in conventional
farming operations unfortunately is
effectively industrial limitation soil
it's just pumped full of a handful of
nutrients
um and without that fertilizer is
completely incapable of supporting life
that's not soil that that's imitation
soil and when you grow plants in that
kind of soil you get imitation plants
and then you get imitation food and then
you get sort of a host of host problems
associated with that