I'm Tom harlo uh Castro Farm Westminster
Vermont we have 50 acres of vegetables
here and we're doing about 15 to 20
acres of sweet
corn our primary market for the sweet
corn is uh local retail at a roadside
stand that we have as far as crop
rotation goes we usually start with corn
or squash in a field then we move on to
uh greens and then to a root crop in the
third
year being an organic farm we generally
use a lot of compost about 20 yards per
acre on everything except root crops and
then we use winter Ry and vet as a cover
crop on everything every year our
primary cover crop here is rye which we
use at um 100 lb per acre I try to
substitute 10 to 20 pounds of that rye
seed with vetch seed to make a total of
100 PB per acre cover crop seed uh cover
crops are generally tilled in fairly
early for uh some early vegetables but
for corn and squash we like to wait
until miday to let the Rye and the vet
mature as much as possible after using a
mold board plow we uh generally apply
about 20 yards per acre compost and then
we discar two or three times and then
we're ready to plant we do soil tests
here every year on every field and uh we
amend our soils with compost and we use
some Blended fertilizer through the
Planters being an organic farmer we rely
heavily on our cover crops and our
compost to provide us with the nutrients
that we need so that we don't have to
make huge purchases of uh Blended
fertilizers we make our own compost here
on the farm um we have manure here
that's trucked in raw manure trucked in
from the local Dairy Farm best stuff we
get is mixed with a lot of straw dumped
in a wind row we turn it every two or
three weeks with a bucket loader gives
us excellent compost the way it is