There are many useful products you can find
on the shelves of your local garden center,
and a few products that most gardeners in
Wyoming should avoid purchasing.
One in particular is gypsum.
Gypsum is made out of calcium sulphate and
is advertised as a general soil conditioner.
However, gypsum really serves one purpose,
and that is to remediate sodic soils.
And the only way to know that you have a sodic
soil, which is high levels of exchangeable
sodium, is to get a soil test.
But don’t use gypsum as a general soil conditioner.
It has not been shown to adjust soil pH, or
to necessarily lighten clay soils, unless
they are sodic.
Another product that many Wyoming gardeners
should avoid using is lime.
Lime is calcium carbonate.
Most of our soils in Wyoming are already high
in calcium, and quite alkaline, meaning they
have a high pH.
And while many gardeners that move to Wyoming
from other states are used to using lime,
Wyoming soils typically do not benefit from
the addition of lime.
The best thing we can do to improve our soils
in Wyoming is to add organic matter, either
in the form of compost, mulch, or manure.
I recommend that you work with your local
Extension educator to get a soil test to determine
what nutrients your soil is lacking, and to
develop a plan for managing the soil health
in your garden.
For the University of Wyoming Extension, I’m
Caitlin Youngquist, and you’re watching
From the Ground Up.