hello this is Scott Kentucky I'm with
Benson County Extension Service and I'm
in middle walk in North Dakota today and
I just wanted to do a short
demonstration on pruning an apple tree
and at this time it's it's late March
early spring so it's the time that we
want to be pruning before we get a lot
of growth and stuff coming on and that
way we can decrease any disease spread
what you'll need is just a regular
pruners and for some of the bigger
branches if you really want to get after
it we have some a big lopper and then
also a sweet Esau for taking off some
branches and many times you can take the
biggest bigger branches off with the big
lopper and then and then use a sweet
Esau to get up close on that branch
collar but what I'm trying to do is to
open up this this canopy I've been
working on this tree for a couple of
years and just trying to open it up a
little bit so we decrease the amount of
disease and stuff and what I don't like
sometimes and some of our trees get so
awfully tall so I'm trying to train this
one to have lateral branches coming out
a little bit and some of these are you
know they want to grow right up right up
to the heavens and pretty soon you're
gonna need a an apparatus with a basket
on just just to get your apples so I'm
gonna I'm gonna prune out some of these
branches at that goal awfully high up up
into the air and there again if they're
growing into the canopy you want to
remove them because eventually they will
cause rubbing on each other's branches
and you can create a wound and that's
just a perfect spot for disease to take
a foothold in and yeah and get started
we've had a lot of fire blight these
last couple of years especially in some
of the ornamental crabs and one
particular one is estar had quite a bit
in it so by keeping this canopy open we
can certainly keep that disease
potential down and increase the airflow
I just like to give you an example of
God I mean here when I when I make these
cuts I don't want to dig into the branch
itself I just want to be you know right
on that branch collar and then it'll
have a nice cut that it'll help heal and
you won't even know it's there in time
you can see down here there was there
was a cut here a prior year and it
healed up and it's doing just fine they
talked about some of these branches
growing inside here
we kind of want to thin them out a
little bit there again for added
circulation and one thing Tom kelp told
me when I first started to entry's he
said you show that tree who's boss you
you're not gonna kill the tree but one
thing he did caution me on was don't cut
off more than 25% of the branches in one
particular year otherwise it's a bit of
a shock to the tree and it takes a
little more time to recover so if you
just keep up up at it annually you can
you can keep it clean
you