yeah thanks for the introduction and uh
thanks to the organizers for inviting me
it's really pleasure to be speaking here
today
um yeah i'll be talking about the hidden
forces underground soil biodiversity for
agricultural production and
environmental integrity
so i think we all know that there's
organisms living in the soil and
it's actually a huge variety of
creatures living there and they're all
doing things so they are
eating organic matter they're feeding on
plant material they're feeding on each
other and
they
bury through the soil they poop in the
soil they eat each other's poop so
there's this whole complexity of
things happening
and together these actions um result in
certain ecosystem functions
um
and these ecosystem functions can result
in ecosystem services that we as humans
also depend on so um
soil organisms are important for organic
meta decom composition for example
they can improve soil structure and
water infiltration they can store
nutrients release nutrients
improve plant nutrition
provide pest control
and so on
however it's been increasingly
increasingly shown in recent years that
with increasing land use intensification
a lot of these organisms are actually
negatively affected so they get reduced
in their diversity and abundance
and can even go locally extinct in
certain fields
and now the big question is
if we lose these organisms do we also
lose these important functions that we
depend on
or if we phrase it more positively
if we promote organisms and find ways to
promote these organisms in soil can we
actually improve our ecosystem
functioning and get more sustainable
cropping systems
so to put this in a theoretical
framework
when we
look at
a natural ecosystem
we we have usually relatively high plant
diversity we have a rich
and diverse soil life
and we have very efficient internal
resource recycling processes that keep
this system
[Music]
alive over long time spans so it's a
very sustainable system but it's not
very productive in agricultural terms
when we compare this to an intensive
agricultural system
we often have
a
huge amount of external resource inputs
you have crop monocultures
and soil life is not doing so well so we
have less well developed internal
resource recycling processes and we also
have much more
losses of nutrients for example
to the groundwater or as gases emissions
into the atmosphere
so these systems are very productive but
they are not sustainable
so ideally we want to combine aspects of
both to create a sustainable system
where we have
less external inputs required we have an
intermediate
diversity on the field and we have a
rich and abundant soil life so we have
very well developed resource recycling
processes and little losses to the
environment so we have a productive and
sustainable
system
but first of all
we we have to answer the question how
important are the soil organisms
actually for ecosystem functioning
and
to find that out i
performed
an experiment a couple years back in
so-called lysometers so lysometers are
basically big pots um
placed in the outside in free air
and each lysometer can hold the sole
volume of 230 liters
um we filled these lysometers with
sterilized soil and then added two
different soil biological treatments one
we call the enhanced soil life treatment
containing soil organisms smaller four
millimeters
and the other one was the reduced soil
life treatment that only contained
organisms smaller 11 micrometers so
basically
microorganisms but nothing else
these lysometers have a hole in the
bottom where the
water running through the soil profile
can be collected and later analyzed for
nutrients
and we also performed gas measurements
of nitrous oxide and n2 gas
into the air
to look at nutrient losses
so we planted the mace crop in these
lysometers and let them grow to maturity
so they got big mace plants as you would
find it in the field
and when we look at the data so we see
these dark bars the enhanced soil life
treatment and the light gray bars is the
reduced cell life treatment
what we found was that with reduced soil
life crop yields
when we're significantly lower and we
found a similar pattern for nitrogen
uptake and for phosphorus uptake the
effects were
strongest so actually it was more than
half the phosphorus uptake with reduced
soil life
looking at the nutrient losses we found
the opposite pattern so
with reduced soil life
nitrogen leaching losses
went up massively and the same was the
case for nitrous oxide emissions and
important greenhouse gas
and also n2 another
gas being emitted
was massively
increased so this study shows that soil
organisms have a great potential to
enhance the nutrient use efficiency and
support crop growth
in cropping systems
but
it is
a model system
and actually most knowledge we have
about soil biodiversity and how it
affects ecosystem functions is derived
from such model systems that often use
sterilized soil so we have to re-add
organisms
and
yeah we actually do not know how well
these results transfer to
um the real world to an agricultural
field
so i was trying to get um yeah closer to
that and get some some
some answers in real world settings i
did a postdoc in california at uc davis
and
there went to 30 different field sites
differing in management intensity so i
selected 10 grassland sites
and 10 more sustainable tomato rotations
that received cover crops over the
winter and
compost applications and then 10
intensive tomato rotations that only
receive mineral fertilizers and
synthetic pesticides and so on
so i expected
reduced abundance and diversity of soil
organisms with increasing management
intensity
so i went to all these sites and we
sampled and analyzed the soil
communities and we also extracted soil
cores from all these fields
placed them in a greenhouse planted
tomato crops there and
[Music]
yeah measured nutrient leaching losses
and gas emissions and looked at
crop yield also
so when we look at the data for the soil
communities
you always see the grasslands on the
left and the intensive systems on the
right so
we found that with increasing management
intensity indeed most parameters for
solar organisms showed a negative trend
the more intensive the system was the
less diverse and less abundant soil
organisms there
then
we related this data to some ecosystem
functions that we measured so here we
see the relationship on the left
with microbial biomass in the soil and
tomato yield we found a significantly
positive relationship so with more
microbial biomass we had higher tomato
yields
similarly we found for the more
nematodes we had in the soil we also
found higher crop yields looking at
nutrient leaching losses we found some
relationship with the ratio of fungi to
bacteria in the soil so the higher this
ratio was
the lower the nitrogen leaching losses
there which is something that has also
been shown before and hypothesized that
a fungi dominated system has a more
close sustainable nutrient cycling
compared to a bacteria-dominated system
so um yeah taken together this study
could partly confirm what we found in a
model system which was very nice
and then
i performed a different study focusing
on a vascular mycorrhizal fungi or short
amf we heard about mycorrhizal fungi
before savarina was managed
mentioning them and
yeah
these fungi form symbiotic relationships
with the majority of land plants and
including many major crops like may
sweet
potato tomato and so on and they are
mostly known for improving plant growth
and nutrition and there are also other
benefits that have been shown to be
provided by amf so the way this
symbiosis works
you see here microscopy picture of a
plant root
and the blue structures is the amf
structure and actually enter the plant
root even the plant root cells and
develop there then they spread a network
of fungal hyphae
into the soil so here we see the plant
fruit and then we see these fine root
structures spreading out in the soil so
basically they extend the root system
and you see that they are much finer
than the plant roots so they can enter
soil pores that the plant cannot access
and then they take up nutrients from the
soil and
give them to the plant the plant in turn
performs photosynthesis and gives carbon
back to the fungus so both partners
benefit from this association
so i i did a postdoc then
at uc berkeley and there we
looked at this mycorrhizal fungi in
a long-term field trial
the century experiment at russell ranch
in davis where since more than 25 years
different cropping systems are compared
and we were interested in the
communities of microwaval fungi in these
systems and how they affect crop yield
so we selected four management systems
there
and we planted two different
tomato plants in these systems so one is
a normal tomato plant called 76r
that forms regular
associations with mycorrhizal fungi
and then we had this tomato mutant
called rmc
that has a mutation that
prevents it from forming normal amf
association so they only form
yeah very reduced associations with amf
so we planted them there and then we
looked at tomato yields to basically
find out
um
yeah how yield is affected if we remove
the mycorrhizal association
from the crop
and
we see here the data for the biomass on
the left hand side under the crop yield
dark bars are the normal tomato plants
and the light gray bars are the
mutant plants with reduced mycorrhizal
colonization and we see some differences
here depending on the cropping system
but importantly we see that
when we remove mycorrhital associations
from the system we
get up to a 30 percent
decline in yields
and also overall we found a positive
correlation the more mycorrhizae we
found in the plant roots the higher
tomato yields
where
so i think this study also impressively
shows that that soil organisms can
really or really do support agricultural
yields and
matter
so to sum up these
studies we saw that sole organisms
possess
the great potential to increase crop
yields and simultaneously reduce
nutrient pollution to the environment
and we could confirm um
these results in field settings
so
soil life is a crucial factor for
sustainable agriculture and
substantially supports crop yields and
supporting your soil life is good for
the environment good for the plants and
good for you if you're a farmer so you
have more money in your pocket
and need less fertilizer for example
so this is all very nice but
we have to get this information
out to the public
and we don't have much time because
soils are threatened so we lose soils
globally at an alarming rate um and
there's like problems like soil
compaction so salinization
desertification and soil erosion through
wind and
water and also soil sealing through
human activities
that are major problems and also harm
soil life
and
most people or the general public is
maybe not really aware that soils harbor
an entire below ground universe so
actually
one quarter of the global biodiversity
is found in soils and one teaspoon of
soil contains more living organisms than
we are humans on this planet
so there we got this idea we have to do
something to spread
the word about
these facts
and this is where the underpants come
into play
so we trying to make the soil life
visible because it's very hard to see
soil organisms we saw the presentation
before
so you need a microscope and then also
you you yeah it's hard to see them but
we try to make soil life visible by
making
underpants invisible because if you bury
an underpant in the soil it's cotton
it will be decomposed by solar organisms
and over time disappears
so we started um a citizen science
project called bavais gunderhose in
english it's a proof by underpants
where we
wanted to bury underpants together with
the swiss population
with the goal to raise the awareness
about the importance of soils and also
to perform some scientific assessments
of soil biological activity and soil
health across switzerland and also we
want to develop recommendations for best
management practices to support soil
life
and i have to mention that we did not
invent this idea of burying underpants
so this was actually a group of farmers
in canada that started with this in 2015
and
it has already been done in several
parts of the world currently there's
also project in hungary going on in
australia
yeah
um
so
how did we do it we put together a soil
lab kit diy soil lab kit so we provided
standardized underpants to all the
participants
we also included tea bags to look at the
teabag index which is a scientifically
more established method to look at
decomposition processes in soil
and so we
put these things in the package and
shipped it to all participants and then
they got instructions on how to bury the
underpants then they take a soil sample
which they ship back to our labs
and they place the tea bags in the soil
and
each participant received two underpants
so one will be
retrieved after one month the other one
after two months
then we also
together with this partner spotterron
we've developed an app where people can
enter management data and information
about the field where they buried the
underpants
and can also upload pictures
of the underpants
and then they ship after the two months
they ship the soil sample and the
underpants back to us to microscope and
we analyze them
so we um
aimed for 1000 participants and actually
all the available spots filled up before
we officially announced the project so
there was really a huge interest
um
and we aimed for 50 farmers and 50
non-farmers being private gardeners or
just
regular people
um we we told them they can bury the
underpants wherever they want can be in
the forest can be in some reuteral
spaces in the city can be in their
community garden in the rooftop garden
or in agricultural fields
and here you see a map from our webpage
and everyone in each of these dots
actually
represents several
spots where underpants are buried so you
can zoom in and see all the details
and look at pictures and look at site
information on our web page which is
available in three swiss national
languages
yeah then we had the goal to raise the
awareness and we had an event for the
media for the start of the project and
actually it was overwhelming how well
this was picked up so we were
in the media globally with this project
um
in in ghana in india china the u.s
and so on
and um we also had several television
features in swiss and german television
and um
importantly all these media releases
talked about that soils are alive soils
are important and souls are threatened
and we have to take care of them so they
really got our message across which made
us very happy
um we also
put together a picture book about soil
life called the jungle on soil but it's
only available in german and french
if we think about releasing an english
version we'll see how that goes
um yeah it's actually very entertaining
and interesting can learn a lot there
and it's available in bookstores in
switzerland germany austria or you can
also directly order it through us you
can write me an email then you get also
a special prize when you get it through
us
yeah and then there's still the
scientific assessments to be made so the
research questions we're trying to
answer with this project
are um how sole biological activity
distributed across switzerland and is
this biological activity linked to soil
biodiversity
soil quality crop yields and also how
does management affect
the soil biological activity
and um
yeah we also want to assess whether
underpants can really serve as a
meaningful and easy to use indicator for
soil health that everyone can use in
their backyard or wherever they
want because this method has never been
scientifically
assessed so um yeah we really hope to
get answers here how useful the
underpants actually are
so right now we're dealing with the
samples we have almost 900 soil samples
1 600 underpants 10 000 tea bags
we have a subset of soil samples where
we look at soil microbial diversity 800
questionnaires with site information
management data
so we are really busy in the lab right
now so the underpants they are
photographed and then with imaging
software we determine the
amount of degradation of the underpants
the tea bags are weighed
and yeah we hope to be able to make
recommendations for for best management
practices in spring of this year
what we can tell already or what we have
already is data that the citizens
actually entered in the app so they
could
assess how strongly the underpants were
degraded
so we see here the results of the one
month so orange means the underpants are
not very degraded green men means
they're strongly degraded
so what we see so far after one month
months there's less degradation than
after two months
and we see that there are no
large-scale spatial patterns so um
yeah looking at the details will be
interesting hopefully so there's more to
come if you're interested you can
subscribe to our newsletter on our
webpage it's on the landing page you
have to scroll to the bottom
to find it or you follow us on facebook
and instagram
yeah and with this i'm at the end so um
quickly acknowledge acknowledge people
involved in this research plan soil
interactions group at agroscope and my
colleagues the project team of the
underpants project
people at uc davis and berkeley
and i thank you for your attention
i'm happy to take questions
thank you very much
um for your talk and now
we also know what's
how how it was all conducted regarding
the pants and
very um inspiring you want to say yeah
maybe i'm start collecting some pants
now from now on
it's okay um
i will start right away with the
question of felix um he's asking how was
the soil soil uh sterilized and how was
uh ensured that it was sterile
um we sterilize the soil with
x-ray rear irradiation so there are
these companies that provide a service
mostly for medical equipment
and
yeah depending on the dose of the
irradiation you can determine how how
sterile the soil is because there is
always some bacteria that can survive
such
processes
um so we made sure that we did not have
fungi
in the soil anymore no mycorrhizal fungi
and
insects arthropods and so on there might
have been still some bacteria
have been
sorry
alive in the soil but um
yeah but we
um
also saw in our control treatments that
they were mostly free of mycorrhizae for
example we had some contamination
probably through the air because it was
outside
and for the greenhouse we often
sterilize the soil with autoclaving
thank you very much
can you please stop sharing this screen
yeah sure i mean i love the biodiversity
of the of the pants but
thank you
um
okay uh the next question will be by
laying that
um using two domain tomato varieties
introduce more differences than
equals minus amf only so
how do you know the yield differences
are amf based
so these uh
the
this mutant is actually derived from
this 76-hour wild type that we used so
they are
directly related and
it should only be
this one mutation that
that
causes differences in mycorrhizal
colonization and this
pair of wild-type and mutant has been
used in in several studies already
there have also been
tests
planting them in sterile soil to look at
growth differences without mycorrhizae
and they show fairly similar
similar growth
even in sterile soil
thank you
the next question by italia is
how deep have you buried their panties
and
how do you account for the differences
in land use because there is a huge
difference in arable land and a heavily
irrigated home garden
yeah that's
um so
first first part of the question we
buried the underpants vertically in the
soil so that the the seam on the top
looks out of the soil surface
so it was yeah probably from 0 to 15 20
centimeters
they were buried in the soil
um
and yeah of course there's a huge
variation and that's why we also tried
with this app and questionnaires to get
as
detailed information as possible about
what's happening on these field sites is
it irrigated or not how often is it
irrigated which fertilizers do you use
do you apply compost do you apply
pesticides
which crop is growing there and so on
and
with all this information we hope to
really get meaningful answers
thank you
and how did you create the treatments
with reduced and enhanced soil life
and
maybe the first part of the other
question of italia
um yeah so we
we used um sievings basically so we sift
the soil
through four millimeters
and then we had an additional step in
the greenhouse so we put the sift soil
into sterile soil in the greenhouse and
planted some plants in there
and let them grow for three months to
yeah to let the soil organisms propagate
in these pots and
yeah and for the for the reduced soil of
treatment we filtered the soil through
11 micrometer filters and also added
this to steroid soil in the greenhouse
so we had both treatments growing in the
greenhouse in in sterile substrate and
only a small part of
of the two
filtrates was added so we tried to
really
make sure that that
yeah the difference are similar except
for the different organisms
present
okay and another part of the question
was where do you where do the microbes
come from and how much did you apply
um so we went to a agricultural field
like a pasture
[Music]
here close to our research station
from a farmer and
yeah use just native soil organisms we
found in that soil
what was the second part of the
question um this i have to i'm already
um
the second part but one moment
um yeah how much did you apply
uh yeah um yeah
so we we produced this inoculum in the
greenhouse and
then i think we
if i remember correctly it was about
of the soil volume in this lysometers
was um
was the inoculum from the greenhouse
or maybe was five percent or so of the
volume i'm not sure right now i would
have to look it up
thank you uh a little interruption um i
want to remind everybody you don't have
to do it now but all the participants uh
you have to refresh the browser because
otherwise we will drop out
by five i mean maybe
there will be maybe we will be finished
by five but maybe
it take a little bit longer we
just that it's not like a really quick
end so maybe you just refresh the
browser
when you have time within the next uh
five minutes
okay and um
i would continue
with the questions michaela she's asking
is intensive cropping always combined
with bad soil life
or is intensive uh range from overuse
like the degradation soils from us to
special use cropping systems with crop
rotation and cover crops
um
yeah i
probably there's also intensively
managed systems where soil life is doing
well i think there's a lot of factors
that play a role and it's always
difficult to make these generalizations
and we also saw on the data that there's
a huge variability
in the data so some dropping systems are
doing
better than than others
um
and i didn't don't remember the rest of
the question
yeah
yeah is it
um or is it in intensive range from
overuse to special use cropping systems
with crop rotation and cover crops
that's like the second part of the
of the question
yeah uh so i think probably if i
understand correctly if there's like a
gradient of of um
yeah soil
soil health from from more sustainably
to more intensively managed systems um
which i would say yes so you you can't
cannot really put them in categories so
this is good this is bad or the soil
life is going bad good here and bad
there
so it's it's really
a gradient and it really depends on on
lots of details that we also don't
underst understand at this point i guess
okay thank you
uh
she's asking who paid about sending back
soil samples t-bags and pans
participants or your organization
yeah actually the
university of zurich was kind enough to
sponsor the shipment
so we sent the packages already with a
return shipment label they just have to
have to put on the
on the box and they could use the same
box so we try to make it really easy for
the participants to return the shipments
another question by marianne
which results would you think the
license trials had shown if also slurry
had been added
um
yeah
that's a difficult question
i don't
i don't know i think i i would guess
that
in general
they they would have probably gone in a
similar direction
but um
yeah
i can't really say a lot about this
okay and then what's the question about
this
how the soil was sterilized and how was
it ensured that it was sterile
yeah
yeah but i answered this already right
yeah yeah that that's the thing like
because it was not um
showed like that it was answered but it
was already
answered right yeah
so um
[Music]
actually all questions in the chat are
answered now
so
um the final question is
you know it may be already what are the
two uh main take-home messages or the or
one two things you want to share with us
before you or we leave the participants
by five we try
um yeah i think my main message is
make taking care of your soil a priority
it's really the basis of
human existence and then also of the
functioning of planet earth so we really
have to take care of the soil and
get away from only focusing on yields
but really focusing on feeding the soil
and keeping it healthy and alive so that
we
can rely on them also in 100 years from
now
okay
thank you very much wow we are on time
thank you france