this sample query shows how to select
different time windows for different
layers okay so in this specific example
we're going to look at agricultural data
for the Midwestern u.s. specifically
we're going to compare the crop planting
information together with some weather
information okay so let's get started
initially we create a new query we
select from survey right here the 250
meter resolution crop planting map so
this from the US Department of
Agriculture and from the weather
category we select prison historical
data and let's pick the daily maximum
temperature for example okay so now when
it comes to where the prison data is
only available for the continental US
therefore you see here the contiguous US
has been highlighted already for us now
we can zoom in maybe a bit
and select a rectangle somewhere here in
the Midwest like this
to the where we take this option off we
can see now we can allow to choose
different time windows for these layers
okay so for the crop type that simply
pick January 1st 2017 and for the
maximum temperature let's pick something
like June 2017 okay so the idea would be
roughly speaking that from the crop type
one knows what has been planted there
and then one might won't be interested
in the temperature to see you know all
these crops could possibly elope so
let's pick next we don't do any
aggregation for this
give this name and submit it so this is
very straightforward to give an idea
what the result looks like we ran this
query previously so let's click on this
here
see indeed we have the crop layer note
that the crop type is categorically
encoded the codes pretty much correspond
to these numbers you see with this color
scheme they're gonna say no point you
can basically see the value here and
these numerical codes are consistent
with USDA codes okay so similarly we
could of course select our temperature
which we have you know picked here and
again is like now click on a single
point we also get the complete time
series at this point at the same time
you can launch an animation for this and
see how the temperature devolve
de-evolve during the month of June