in this video we'll be talking about the
different ways that you can sample your
soils and some of the techniques that
are best to be used one of the first
things to think of when you're taking a
soil sample is the timing of the sample
so that's important from the point of
view that if you're testing your soil
from a nutrient deficiencies point of
view or wondering what to put on your
soil then taking a sample just before
the plant is at its optimum growth stage
or when you're about to plant the crop
is very important as this helps you to
get the timing just perfect the second
thing to take into account is location
of where you're going to take your soil
samples for example we want to avoid
areas like roads and tracks around
watering points along fence lines and
areas like that that are not
representative of your paddock if you
finding that you've got some bad soil or
you are finding bad germination of
plants it may be important to sample in
that area and also to sample in a good
section of your paddock that's an
important thing to keep in mind if it's
in an area of pasture or a plant of some
description that's growing quite nicely
you might want to sample your soils
where the plants are not growing well
and in an area whether they're growing
quite well and to actually look at the
two differences and it may help you to
identify the soil issues the third thing
to think about is the depth of your soil
samples soil sampling is important and
most of the nutrients are concentrated
in the top 30 centimeters of your soil
so it's important that we sample this
area but that if we feel issues are
affecting us that are further below in
the surface or into the subsoil that we
sample to that depth as well a simple
spade test is done by making a general
hole like this which allows you to
pull up a section of the soil profile
and there we have the surface soil down
into the subsurface which is there easy
for me to test for soil pH maybe Sosa
disa tea and also texture but some
simple infield soil testing