Ral development and Agricultural
Extension Department realizes that
classroom learning or Campus Learning is
not enough for World development
graduates in
Ethiopia the department is putting
further attempts to strengthen the
field-based Practical teaching and
improve professional competence of
graduates the needed professional skills
can be imparted only when students are
exposed to practical teaching and make
them to stay in village for some time
and get exposed to livelihood
surroundings and lifestyles of the rural
life there are no substitute for
learning by being part of the real real
life
situation to improve the productivity of
agricultural sector the country designed
the economic strategy called
Agricultural Development L
industrialization which has been seen as
a long-term strategy to achieve faster
growth and economic
development achieve the desired goals of
the country's agriculture skilled and
competent human resource in the field of
Ro development and Agricultural
Extension is very crucial
to this effect the department of rural
development and Agricultural Extension
is strongly working on to produce
competent and dynamic
[Music]
graduates there is no doubt that all
these efforts contribute towards the
Agricultural Development policy and
forood security strategies of the
country
foree jump high