[Music]
probably one of the oldest methods for
irrigating Fields is surface irrigation
also known as flood or Furrow irrigation
this can be seen beside me this can be
accomplished by digging a ditch at the
top of the field water running down the
ditch eventually hits a canvas Dam built
by a farmer this canvas Dam can be moved
to a desired location in that field once
the canvas dam is built small aluminum
pipes are used to siphon water out of
the ditch to irrigate the crops other
methods in flood irrigation is made
possible through gated aluminum or hard
plastic pipe each morning or evening the
farmer attending to this water opens and
closes the gates to distribute water to
different parts of the field surface
ation is used throughout Wyoming today
especially in the farming areas of the
North Plat Big Horn ly Wind River and
pure River watersheds nationally
approximately 29.4 million Acres of
Farmland are irrigated by flood
irrigation each year as compared to 28.3
million Acres irrigated by spray or
sprinkler irrigation flood irrigation
may not be the most efficient method but
is cheap and low
Tech whether using gated pipes or crude
dirt ditches makes little difference to
the crop needing water all the farmer
needs to know is that he or she is using
a method that's hundreds of years old in
the making from the University of
Wyoming Cooperative Extension Service
I'm Brian SE and this is exploring the
nature of Wyoming