hey all Mike here from allamerican.org
now you may remember a long time ago I
did a video on how to find tools made in
the USA and today we are revisiting that
category but more specifically talking
about gardening tools
[Music]
now you may be wondering Mike why the
heck are we talking about gardening
duels in the dead of winter and that's
really for two reasons one is that you
should always be paying attention to
your garden but second of all it is the
slow season for a lot of these
businesses and what better way to
support grade made in the USA companies
than really supporting them during their
slow period of the year when they're
also likely running some sales so you
may be able to create get a great deal
as well so per usual also written about
this exact same topic so check the
description below for a link to that
article and head over to allamerican.org
for all of our research on shopping
American made first off when it comes to
materials there's a few different things
you need to look out for over here one
is that a lot of gardening tools are
going to be made of some sort of
tempered steel or stainless steel now
there's a lot of great material
suppliers for this raw material in the
US so you should have no problem finding
great gardening tool brands that are
sourcing their steel from U.S suppliers
now you also want to look at the other
materials within the tools as well if
it's a hand tool the handle is likely
going to be made out of something like
rubber or plastic good news is there are
plenty of great suppliers of those raw
materials as well so generally the
gardening tools category is one where
you can find a lot of brands that are
not only doing a lot of their assembly
and Manufacturing here but are also
sourcing a lot of their raw materials
from U.S suppliers as well which is not
always the case for a lot of
subcategories of tools now in order to
find the country of origin you can
always give the brand a call if you're
shopping online if they don't list the
country of origin on their website or
shoot us a mess with your
dollamerican.org and we'll help you find
out out or if you're shopping in store
we have some U.S legislation on our side
that basically dictates that the country
of origin be labeled on the product or
packaging so you should see it clearly
labeled when you're shopping around Home
Depot or Lowe's or any other store that
you're looking at I have a full
explainer video with those tips and more
which I'll make sure to link in the
description below as well as the cards
at the top of the video If you haven't
seen that one yet alright now that we've
covered a couple of tips on material
sourcing let's get into a few of those
great American-made brands that are
making some awesome gardening tools
right here in the USA first up is Rogue
hoe tools now this company also goes by
projo manufacturing they are based out
of London Kansas and make some great
gardening tools more specifically hose
they're a family-owned business that got
started in 1990 and they really began as
just a simple Christmas gift from one
family member to another and that has
evolved today to a product line of over
60 different tools that you can use in
your garden they have a lot of different
varieties to choose from from so if you
need a really durable hoe made from
tempered steel and is super
environmentally friendly definitely
check out roko tools next up is Bully
tools bully tools is based in
Steubenville Ohio and makes a ton of
different styles of tools for your
garden or lawn these guys offer shovels
rakes diggers and pretty much everything
in between so no matter what type of
tool you need for your garden or lawn
these guys will probably have it I find
these guys to be a really good value for
your dollar they have 11 gauge American
Steel in a lot of their heavy duty tools
at a really affordable price next up is
Wilcox All Pro Tools Wilcox makes some
great gardening tools everything from
your travels and diggers to your weeders
and Scoops their diggers in particular
are really reliable they're made from
stainless steel and not just their
diggers but all of their products are
made from 100 US Source materials next
up is Fisher blacksmithing Fisher
blacksmithing is based out of Bozeman
Montana and as the name suggests they
hand craft all of their gardening tools
using traditional blacksmithing
techniques their products are made using
steel heated in a forge and then shaped
over an anvil using a hammer and tongs
they're then set into American Walnut
handles they have a really pretty look
to them and are going to last you a
lifetime and the last few Brands I'll
mention in today's video Cobra head
makes a really popular weeder and
cultivator Garden works also makes a
really reliable travel to give you
another option there and then earth box
if you're looking for some planters
makes some really solid ones out of
their facility as well as far as the big
Brands and the gardening tools industry
and where they're actually made I feel
like I've covered those pretty
extensively in some of my other YouTube
videos particularly the shorter videos
on the channel as well as some of the
full length videos on different tool
categories so make sure to check those
out for popular brands like Cobalt and
DeWalt and others that are also making
hand tools here and check check out a
lot of our written research on
allamerican.org where you'll find a huge
repository of really popular tool brands
in the gardening category and where
they're actually made all right y'all
that's it for this video if you have any
questions make sure to leave a comment
below or shoot me a message on
allamerican.org and I'll hit you back if
you like this video remember to like And
subscribe and as always thanks for
supporting your country and shopping
American made see y'all next time