[Music]
we have been
raised up doing farming though it looked
like
some kind of punishment so it never
in my mind that i could do agriculture
plural to urban migration is very common
especially with the youth
that is because of lack of employment
after moving to the city and setting up
a business
and it collapsed which forced me to
go back home that's when
i can see it was very stressful
i lost all my money and i came back at
zero
that's why my idea for moving to canada
came
i wanted to fly away we have
mighty said that certain countries are
better than ours
and we think that if we go to that
country we can make it big
but right now i've come to learn that
most of the people who goes
abroad they don't really make a lot of
money
because once they come back they still
go back to square one
right now i've come to learn that
agriculture has the potential to create
many jobs because currently in africa we
still have
an opportunity to come up with business
agribusinesses
which can sustain our economy and
improve our life rail
i think the reason why agriculture
is not attracting youth is low adoption
of technology
if technology is brought into
agriculture
it will bring high youth and more income
lane fed agriculture on the other hand
is very
yes disease but due to
thick seasons most of the produce go to
waste
but with the technology like this one
thanks to how they gave me the drip
system
now i can able to produce events in dry
seasons when the prices are good
when i'm working my field it feels good
to see the green crops
growing you are their caretaker it's
very good when you are seeing
crops from driving healthy
it feels good
you