[Music]
the landscape of the Upper Midwest has
has become one of the most productive
agricultural regions of North America
fields of corn and soybeans reach to the
Horizon in every
direction this land though has spawned
another kind of product completely
unintended but no less profound the
runoff from these agricultural
operations compromises the water quality
both locally and farther down the
Mississippi drainage all the way to the
Gulf of Mexico in fact this region is a
major contributor to the zone of hypoxia
in the Gulf where excess pollutants wipe
out marine
life the area of concern is the region
of Northwestern Iowa and Southwestern
Minnesota today the plow dominates a
landscape where once the grass has stood
well over a person's head and Buffalo
roamed freely very few wetlands and
Native prairies remain on the land to
filter the water and slow the pulse of
runoff in addition the mass conversion
of the the Prairie Wetlands ecosystem to
intensive farming has threatened many
species of migratory birds and
butterflies these species often Nest
here or use the area during their cross
hemisphere migration
routes through adapted farming and
conservation practices there are
increasing points of Hope new data
suggests that the level of nitrates in
the water has been declining in recent
years the key is to look at current
practices with an eye toward historical
conditions and practical conservation
strategies around 12,000 years ago when
the first humans appeared in North
America the Upper Midwest was mostly a
glacial landscape when the glaciers last
receded they left behind a fertile soil
glacial lakes and Wetland depressions
called Prairie potholes the effects of
the last glacial event are still being
felt on the
land we're in the prairie pad hole reg
region which is mainly Glacial Hill um
placed here pretty much the topography
and everything you see is placed here
pretty much by glacials um coming over
the land and then receding especially
the receding part where they gouged the
landscape and and made deposit deposits
in different
areas this is an open landscape uh
dominated by grasses and and wetlands
glaciers came through this area and dug
out these depressions uh the climate uh
has provided the moisture necessary to
maintain U the vegetation the grassland
vegetation and the wetlands um
interacting with with the climate and
the physical factors uh
glaciations uh our disturbances such as
grazing and uh and fire which have
maintained um the Upland system in a
very early successional
stage we're at kind of a major boundary
in Southwestern Minnesota we're sitting
on the Marine of the last Glacier that
came into this region and a marine is a
linear Ridge of Hills this one Trends
northwest southeast and to the east of
this line is a landscape that is very
young geologically it's um the drainages
haven't been integrated yet you have
Rolling Hills a lot of wetlands Lakes
sloos to the west of this Ridge is a
much much older glacial landscape the
difference in ag is 14,000 years to the
east 400 to 600,000 years to the West so
there has been a lot more time for the
drainage system to develop west of here
this difference in age of the two
Landscapes on either side of this Ridge
has to be appreciated when you're
talking about Land Management because on
the West Side you have this well
integrated drainage system every single
low spot on the land surface has been
drained has been reached by headward
erosion of a stream of some size and so
the whole landscape is connected with
the dend dritic drainage way on the east
side of this line nothing is connected
yet this landscape is poorly drained and
it will become drained in the long run
and so there is going to be the creation
and erosion of streams and that's a hard
thing for people who are managing the
land to appreciate they want it to kind
of lakes to stay looking like the Lakes
they always have been they're reluctant
to see Lakes fill in become marshes and
shallow water environments but that is
going to be the natural progression of
this
landscape the biggest change we see now
that the state is fighting and doesn't
understand is the Min Minnesota River
was deeply downcut during glaciation
10,000 years ago all its tributary
streams which reach into this area are
still adjusting to that down cutting
event and so they had waterfalls
initially created at the at their
Junction with the Minnesota and those
waterfalls or Nick points are migrating
upstream and in some cases are only 5 to
10 miles from where they join the
Minnesota River so you have these deeply
ins sized drainage ways that meet with
kind of a sluggish looking Upland stream
well eventually that gradient that that
step in the gradient is not going to
persist for the long run it's going to
be evened out and so there's a lot of
erosion there's a lot of gullying um
banks are caving into the river there's
High sediment load in the Minnesota and
its tributaries and a lot of that is
natural um farmers do contribute some of
it when they ditch and tile but the bulk
of it is a is a naturally vent and it's
something that is still adjusting after
10,000 years when the first Europeans
viewed this area in the late 1600s they
found the land covered with a waving sea
of Tall Grass Prairie roaming herds of
bison and migrating tribes of Plains
Indians those Native Americans left
subtle yet lasting marks upon the
[Music]
land after the Civil War agricultural
production hit full stride here and
within 100 years came to almost
completely dominate the landscape most
of the wetlands were actually drained at
about the turn of the century maybe up
to about 1920 the mid or so people had
to realize that Iowa and much of the mid
Upper Midwest here the prair pothole
region PE people had a difficult time
even living in this area because of
water they had trouble even getting
around in Iowa we had probably about 2
and A2 million Acres of wetlands that
disappeared because of drainage
so
people
historically didn't like wetlands and a
lot of people still don't like them
today because were a real problem with
people making a living off the land when
they had to farm
it
and the people's attitudes I think have
changed somewhat because they realize a
lot more now what the values and
functions of wetlands today producers
and land managers here are starting to
look for ways some of that original
ecosystem might regain function the
focus is on a few small patches set
within the agricultural landscape one
may still find a small remnant of
prairie or wetland in original condition
these areas serve as models and Seed
sources for restoration work elsewhere
generally down here over 90% of the
original wetlands have been drained and
are now uh used for
farmland for the Tallgrass Prairie I've
heard uh various percentages but
generally it's well less than 1% of the
original Tallgrass Prairie Still Remains
and I've heard as low as you know a
tenth of a percent so depending on what
area you're looking at Tall Grass PR is
very rare we do have some Tall Grass PR
behind me we have some on uh some of our
other waterfall production areas and we
use that as this seed source uh in order
to start planting uh those types of
plants in our new areas so this is a
Skipper and this is one of the species
of insects that we use to talk about the
quality or the health of a prairie the
Skippers are incredibly specific because
they're they're lay they lay their eggs
on grasses and um despite the fact that
it's not very showy of a species uh they
really do tell us quite a bit about the
quality of the Prairie this Prairie is
also a very valuable resource because
when you look at Iowa and the changes in
the landscape that have happened over
the past couple hundred years uh Iowa
used to be predominantly covered by
wetlands and prairies and now we have
less than 1% of the Prairie uh covering
the landscape that we had 200 years ago
so this is an incredibly valuable
resource this this site because of the
genetic diversity uh and the species
diversity of plants as well as other
organisms that live here like
insects one of the other important
aspects of this Prairie particularly is
that it shows quite a diversity of
microhabitat TS we have the Uplands here
we also have lower Wetland areas there's
a a high diversity of topography and the
different vegetation communities that
are associated with that so it's
important when we think about Landscapes
and we think about areas to either
restore or preserve it's important to
think about getting the whole complement
of these different kinds of habitat
types and in many cases there are plants
that are tightly associated with for
example the lowlands like the wetlands
uh and there are many other species of
animals wildlife that are associated
with each of these different micro
habitats so this 160 Acres on kalor
Prairie uh is especially important
because it has this diversity of
different habitat
types well first of our our farming
operation is a corn soybean operation so
it it has to be economically profitable
uh our whole family is
conservation-minded so that part is is
pretty pretty easy to work with the
family on um but it has to be
economically viable for our total
operation before we can do
them uh my parents were older and of
course uh participated in a lot of the
drainage of the farm and when we stop a
tile and and that type of thing it has
to be something that works with the
total picture of the farm that's kind of
how we look at it uh big picture-wise
we're actually in the De Moine River on
the that Watershed just a few miles
north of us we go into the Blue Earth
river system which goes north into the
Mississippi and uh through the Minnesota
River
so we're kind of on a tabletop there but
even our small Watershed we I don't know
that I want to eat the fish out of our
River when I when I see what comes down
it one of the concerns that I've had is
watching the scour erosion on this River
and watch the channel change and and uh
in my lifetime we've owned this
particular farm for 34
years uh there's been a terrific amount
of tile Upstream increase it's about a
30 m Watershed and uh the velocity and
the speed the water comes down to us now
is greatly enhanced so we're seeing more
scour erosion on the on the banks and
that's one of the things that I'd like
to see kind of slow down and it by
establishing the grasses on these Bank
edges is really really working in the
right direction in this immediate part
of the of the uh Great Plains the
northern Tallgrass per Eco region I
think that we are something like
97% uh privately owned this landscape is
97% privately owned and and something
like
85% engaged in cultivated
agriculture so any sort of public policy
that has intentions of improving water
quality or bird nesting success I think
has to has to include uh the land that
is privately
owned one of the most ambitious programs
that work here focuses on establishing
conservation practices on private land
the Minnesota conservation Reserve
enhancement program or Crap seeks to
place 100,000 acres of marginal cropland
in a conservation easement one of the
most significant issues that we've been
working on over the last several years
is is trying to clean up the Minnesota
River it's one of the most polluted
rivers in uh United States it's in a
primarily dominated agricultural
landscape it uh runs from the Western
edges of Minnesota actually into South
Dakota all the way into the uh
Minneapolis St Paul area where it joins
the Mississippi River it's one of the
principal it is the primary tributary to
the Mississippi River and it's sought to
be the number one pollutant to the
Mississippi River uh in the state of
Minnesota of course from Minnesota's uh
agricultural landscape the Minnesota
River probably is made up of all or
parts of 37 counties it's roughly a
watershed of 10 10 and a half million
acres of land in this particular River's
Watershed and roughly 10 million Acres
of that land is under intense
agricultural uh cropping so it's an
extremely intensified agricultural it
certainly includes probably uh the most
significant cropping areas in the state
of Minnesota are found in this this
particular Watershed certainly we can't
turn the clock back to prior to to
European settlement we know agriculture
is critical to the state of Minnesota is
trying to find that balance between
conservation and agriculture use and we
think crep has been a great great
selling tool for the state of Minnesota
uh particularly in trying to achieve
very significant benefits to the
Minnesota River Wetland Restorations are
the types of eligible crop lands that we
are trying to enroll in this program and
and the reason for that of course these
are the lands that uh if we can get them
out of crop production we can get a
conservation practice on those uh
parcels and protect our future resources
from uh you know reducing soil and water
erosion sedimentation nutrient loading
into the Minnesota River and also be
looking at improving and enhancing fish
and wildlife habitat you know one of the
reasons that we're here of course is
trying to enhance our Water Resources as
well as our Fish and Wildlife Resources
with within Minnesota and in order to do
that we have to look at trying to
improve and enhance the Watershed in the
Minnesota river which then subsequently
will benefit the Mississippi River and
on down the river down to the Gulf of
Mexico and and uh issues related to
hypoxia as an example at the mouth of
the Mississippi in the Gulf of Mexico
lies an area known as The Dead Zone or
the zone of
hypoxia here excess nutrient runoff and
pollution from up River have created an
oxygen deprived body of water no marine
life can exist here in improving water
quality in the Upper Midwest can help
alleviate The Dead
Zone additional connections extend
across the hemisphere Minnesota and Iowa
form critical links in a migratory chain
for countless bird species some of the
species Nest here some use the area to
reproduce others continue their journey
through here to the Arctic and then back
into South America when you look at this
landscape I think one of the key things
that are gained not only by the producer
but by myself being a taxpayer and all
the other taxpayers is the fact that um
this system that you see impacts people
further further down the river I always
think of the um my parents that live on
the Mississippi that's where I grew up
um this if I had more knowledge of this
at the time when I was growing up as a
kid I would understand better the
landscape but this thing has an impact
on that Mississippi River it has an
impact of uh further down when you get
to the G of Mexico removal of
nutrients um maintaining the flash flood
system that sponge effect the wildlife
habitat benefit on the migratory species
are all just a benefit to everybody in
the community as well as farther down
the Watershed Community for me um in my
present position as a wildlife biologist
for
nrcs uh all of this uh is uh connect it
uh from you know from the headwaters um
from the potholes the management of
Uplands uh through the uh flood plane uh
repairing systems to the coastal marshes
all of this is is connected so these
areas get used by a a wide assortment of
wildlife uh some of which stay around um
for extended periods and rear their
they're young either on the wetlands or
in adjacent areas others which uh only
occup these habitats very very uh
temporarily uh in route to uh breeding
areas uh
elsewhere uh this time of year you see
um use by uh transient Birds um that you
know may have bread up in the Arctic and
um such as Shorebirds and you know you
see the mud flats out here which uh uh
provide them access uh vegetation free
access to to feed on the invertebrates
that are in the in the shallow uh wat
which uh would allow them to complete
their migration down to the gulf uh and
eventually down down to South America
when we bought it it was all grassland
since then we've put the basins on it
that are that are here today gradually
over a period of time my wife Jean and I
are are very much interested in in uh in
Wetlands for a number of reasons for the
the wildlife of course comes with it
once you put the once you put the water
in the in the Wetland you have the the
the wild life following and the the
natural vegetation that comes along it
is extremely advantageous to to not only
the immediate neighbors but the the long
range Downstream neighbors are
benefiting from this too because of the
filtration effect of the uh of the
vegetation and the the mere existence of
the Wetland uh between here and
downstream at some point the prie
pothole region in the Upper Midwest in
Canada is the most productive area in
North America for producing waterfall
ducks and geese the birds that are going
to stay here locally for waterfall are
primarily malards blueing
teal U shovelers Gad walls many of the
uh other uh waterfall that migrate
through here
the uh buffalo head a lot of the diving
ducks
scalp canvas back redhe heads they'll go
farther north and and nest in in some of
those uh prey Wetlands farther north
Iowa has currently has some hot spots as
far as nitrate contribution to that
whole hypoxia problem and and uh part of
our uh solution to that problem is to be
able to position our wetland
Restorations within a wated or a large
landscape and position them to the point
where we get the maximum uh filtration
value out of our Wetlands uh Wetlands
placed in a watershed anywhere are good
but if we can strategically place those
wetlands in a position where they do the
greatest benefit um everybody comes out
ahead up here in the Upper Midwest one
of the big issues that's come up over
the last few years is the hypoxia issue
and that's mainly uh having to do with
nitrogen U extra nitrogen that's in the
system of the uh Minnesota River and in
the Mississippi of course they dumps
into the
Delta and anytime we can with our
buffers and with our filter strips up in
the Upper Midwest we definitely can have
an impact on removal of some of that
nitrogen before it becomes a problem in
our streams while I'm sitting in the
tractor cab planting on ridges or or
cultivating or
harvesting I often think of myself as
being uh just one farmer within a wated
or within a Flyway or within the
northern Tall Grass per Eco region and I
try to think of my role I I love of
course as all farmers do to think of big
yields it's just great fun to get big
yields and that is what really matters
to my success but I
also
uh get some sort of reward from feeling
that the birds that are making their way
from from in some cases golden Plover
they passed through usually while we're
planting corn and they I think that
they've been in
Argentina and I think that they're
headed for the very very
northernmost parts of North America and
I think of their trip when I'm moving
really slowly across the field in in the
tractor and and I'm fascinated and I
want really want to do what I can to
make their trip as as easy as
possible I like the idea of of giving
the really delicate and fine-tuned
attention to what I'm doing on this Farm
to so that that so that that golden
Plover finds what it needs on its way
through but then I also want to be part
of a network of information and research
so that I can learn whether or not what
I'm doing is creating any sort of
advantage to the to the entire Flyway or
the entire Watershed I would like to
believe I would like to know that that
this Farm is not contributing to the
zone of hypoxia in the Gulf of Mexico
farming with the mind on the larger
ecological issues leads to new practices
on the land small changes and tillage
methods and timing can have a great
effect on the landscape's overall health
this Farm wouldn't be recognizable from
the road passing by as being different
in any way to an untrained eye from
other Farms but there are a number
of changes and practices that I've
implemented to try to create benefits
for water quality and Wildlife I've
manipulated and tweaked the cropping
system a little to try to make room for
bird nesting success small mammals and
and our greater diversity of of of Flora
and Fauna to exist while at the same
time hoping to achieve maximum yields
maximum economic
yields I'm really enjoying in my
professional life trying to design a
corn and soybean cropping system that
facilitates bird nesting success
we can use these implements to get 170
Bushell per acre corn yields while at
the same time leaving a 45-day no
re-entry interval in our cropping system
to allow ground nesting Birds to rear
Broods of young in our Ridge till
cropping system the practices of the
past of broadcast applications of
fertilizers and herbicides are almost a
part of the past we have applier
fertilizers in a band 7 in deep and in a
very stable form so that the fertilizer
that we apply is used by the crops that
we grow and doesn't end up as pollution
in in uh surface water flow leaving the
farm we apply our nitrogen our our
nitrogen fertilizer at at uh uh the
point in time when the corn needs it the
most with with this rrop cultivator we
just make a few littleit uh
modifications to it and we band our
fertilizer in typically in late May and
we do nitrate nitrogen soil testing
before making our fertilizer
recommendations so that we are pretty
assured that we're not applying more
than we need and that combined with the
leaving the the fields un un tilled in
the fall and hopefully including the the
understory crops we're really hoping to
keep all of our our fertilizers right
here on the farm since we've changed
cropping systems and since the arrival
of some new technologies that allow for
the that allow us to leave this large uh
no re-entry interval in our cropping
system it allow us to
leave un touched uh uh residue corn corn
and bean stocks through the winter where
we're finding that Upland sandpipers
regularly nest and rear Broods right in
our crop fields and I find this really
really exciting and really
rewarding other rewards come when agency
managers link up concerned producers
with appropriate government programs
such as the Wetland Reserve program and
the Minnesota KB when land is set aside
through these programs the ecologic
function may be managed using some basic
conservation strategies by restoring or
preserving prairies and wetlands and by
establishing riparian buffers or filter
strips one of the things that we're
trying to think about when we look at
these prairies is how in a fragmented
landscape how can we reconnect the
pieces how can we uh make this a better
landscape for the species that we're
trying to preserve in the Prairies and
one way of doing that could potentially
be uh by adding reconstructed prairies
another way of uh putting this landscape
back together could be by creating
buffer systems that would connect these
prairies the site that we're looking at
here now is a is a glacial glacial
Remnant uh this is a a prairie that was
U never been had never been cropped in
this case this land owner hadn't done
anything to the land and so we're able
to come in do some burning on it uh we
broke the tile lines uh The Nature
Conservancy actually owns the fee title
on this now and we have the the easement
permanent easement on it and so we're in
a process of um of restoring the
ecosystem for this particular site as
far as connectivity goes of this site
with other sites if we're talking about
a larger area we address it here in Iowa
a couple of different ways in specific
programs like the wetlands Reserve
program and those and related easement
programs we add extra points in for
sites that are that are in proximity uh
either they get the most points of their
touching an application is touching an
established site like this or it's
within a mile or two miles those types
of things and we try to bring try to
bring those groups of easements together
because we can get a a more valuable
package for for wildlife and for water
quality and all those types of things if
there is a segment and it's all in one
land we would try to try to get a a
buffer strip between this site for
example and a and another one that's
maybe a quarter mile away we would try
to try to get that person in maybe in a
CRP buffer strip and plant that down to
Native grasses and Forbes and so it
becomes this this uh passageway this
buffer between this site and another
site maybe there's another land owner
that has a has a representative site too
and and try to connect them all together
so becomes a very connective ecosystem
although it's segmented in smaller
pieces than what it was naturally these
alleys that are wide enough so that
they're just not a carnivore trap but so
that their their their uh Wildlife can
actually uh can actually produce in
there and can actually U pass through
and safely uh we would try to get those
done to have a have a good um connected
um Wildlife Area the way we see Wetlands
at the planning phase and all the way
through it is that they're just one of
the opportunities that we can use to get
conservation on the land early on when
we do our preliminary planning for these
projects we rank them for water quality
for restorability for cost of
restoration and in this case U this
Wetland set in a position where it
created a string of wetlands U over 30
mil long where it fit into that chain
and U created a situation where you
cannot drive more than two miles in this
chain North and South in the potholes
without uh coming upon another restored
Wetland or a or a prairie system
so we use that as the ranking we
emphasize that and we also emphasize the
fact that that we took Approximately 80%
of the drainage area in this particular
area and filtered it through this
Wetland so it had some big water quality
benefits these conservation buffers that
we have out here today the riparian
forest buffers that are planted uh here
in the river bottoms of in the flood
zone areas and we're hopefully creating
a practice here that will be absorbing
nutrients that are moving underground in
in the crop Fields here where we pick up
a lot of nitrates that are picked up off
the corn fields and and come through the
underground streams we're also creating
a lot of wildlife habitat down here and
these are very fast growing species and
and we're going to create some habitat
that uh for the
Wildlife the forest buffered uh trees
are going to be creating shade habitat
over the stream for the Fisheries here
in in the southwest Minnesota Tall Grass
Prairie particularly uh for instance the
northern pike which is considered to be
a lake species in a lot of cases in most
cases in Minnesota but they are known to
migrate up in these streams at certain
times of the year uh anytime you can
create your Banks a little bit more
stable but also create some shade over
in pockets and pools you just create a
little bit more uh fish fish habitat for
those migratory species where we're
located here with this riparian Forest
buffer is situated at the bottom of a
landscape that's kind of steep for years
it had had been tilled some uh it's
protecting what used to be a feed lot up
there that's uh could have had runoff
coming through we're protecting that you
got a corn crop that's being raised down
here and of course in this part of the
country it takes a lot of nutrients
particularly nitrogen to raise that crop
of corn and and and with the intense
rainstorms we get we get can get some
leeching down into the roots zone so uh
that's going to be moving towards the
stream which is only a couple hundred
feet away and so anytime we can absorb
any of that nutrients through a crop
like the crop of grass that's located in
in the buffer here it's going to be
absorbing that out and taking that out
of the
system land owners and land managers in
the Upper Midwest are faced with
challenges both social and economic in
addition the byproducts of an otherwise
successful farming operation are
threatening the ology of the entire
Basin through appropriate conservation
and farming practices however some
solutions are being applied to this
complex problem as nrcs employees we
don't make the decisions for the
landowner our responsibility is to
provide to that landowner Alternatives
resource alternatives for for those
acres and then if there's programs
available whether it's USDA programs
whether it's uh um interior programs or
or local uh Soil and Water Conservation
District programs uh those types of
things lay those programs out so land
owners can can fit the the right
decisions with a program to help them
Implement those those decisions but as
far as us making decisions we don't we
provide alternatives to the land owner
land owners that make the decision when
you look at conservation planning on
this site you may come out and see your
eyes may focus on a basin per se but
when you can look beyond the Basin and
into the perspective of what the system
is requiring do we need a filter system
to help keep sediment and nutrient load
out of uh water flow can we do that not
only with one landowner but with several
and when you look at uh a basin per se
like this the question would be is what
is on the other side of the fence what's
on the other side of the hill and how
does it connect with one another and can
you as a conservation planner make that
connection happen by providing um
information assistance opportunities for
land owners to get together and complete
conservation practices that not only
function on their land but also work
within the entire system as we work with
one landowner then that information can
go to another land owner as we work in a
neighborhood in a in a group setting and
and collectively then these these good
decisions result in the resulting in
multiple Acres large blocks of Acres
being treated properly
[Music]