hey everybody rob greenfield here and
today I'm gonna share with you some of
the most easy and abundant foods to grow
for those of you that are in a colder
climate so this applies to people across
much of the northern United States
northern Europe and around many climates
around the world so if that fits you and
you want to grow a lot of food in your
garden and have a lot of food on your
table then this is definitely the video
for you a lot of you know me for my year
of growing and foraging 100% of my food
we're literally everything that I ate
for a year was either from my garden or
foraged but I did that in Florida in a
very hot climate where I could grow food
year around a lot of people saw what I
did and they thought oh you can only do
this because you're in a warm climate
but the truth is warm climate called
climate as long as you work within your
region you can grow an incredible amount
of food and a lot of the most
self-sufficient people that I've ever
met live in cold climate places like
Wisconsin or Ohio or New York so there's
so many foods that you can grow it's
just about growing what grows well and
abundantly in your area so when I'm
talking about easiest and most abundant
easiest means they grow really well it's
hard to kill them even if you have what
you can Center a black thumb there's a
good chance you'll be able to grow these
and walk away feeling like you have a
green thumb and then abundant means that
they produce a lot of food but there's a
second part to that and that is that
they produce a substantial amount of
food on your plate and that they'll
actually be able to fill yourself up and
fill your pantry up to get through the
winter because that's the key in the
colder climates if you want to grow a
large portion of your food it's that you
produce as much as you can during those
growing months during the growing season
and then you store it in jars in
freezers dehydrating it and such in
order to be able to make it through the
winter
with the food from your garden so these
foods are gonna help you drastically
reduce the number of times that you need
to go to the grocery store and
drastically increase the nutrition and
the abundance that you're getting
straight at home or on your farm right
where you are I have to start with the
potato one thing that a lot of people
have the hardest time with is calories
now I wanted to show you this potato in
particular it might look crazy too a lot
of you but this is a potato that has
been stored in the pantry for about six
or seven months now I'm in southern
France and it's mid-may and this was put
into the pantry in around October or
November
so these store for a very long time so
as far as your calories go potatoes are
gonna be one of the most calorie dense
producing a large bulk of your food and
they store really well so this knocks
out two really important things and the
potatoes that are left over that you
don't eat this one right here
could be planted to produce more so that
is the wonderful potato the second one I
want to share with you is pumpkins and I
am in love with pumpkins not just the
ones you see that you make
jack-o'-lanterns out of there's many
different shapes colors and sizes of
pumpkins this is just a beautiful one at
the farm that I'm staying at pumpkins
are amazing because they store a really
long time again it's May and this is
from the last season and it's just as
good as can be and you can also eat the
seeds you can eat the skin in a matter
of fact I will take the entire thing
except the stem and blend it up into a
soup so pumpkin and different winter
squashes they provide a lot of
sustenance nutrients and a lot of them
are very easy to grow grow the ones that
are adapted to your climate now next I
want to share summer squashes so
zucchini this actually is more of a
winter squash but it looks kind of like
a summer squash so I'm using it now
zucchini
these are truly amazing I've traveled
through Washington through Wisconsin
through New York all across the northern
United States and people tell me that
they have so many zucchinis that they
have to try to give them away but they
can't because everybody has so many of
them they get huge you can eat him when
they're giant or you can eat them when
they're small if you want them to be
more tender so zucchinis are a a must
for a huge amount of sustenance and
being extremely easy to grow the next
one I want to talk about is beans and
beans are truly incredible you can
either eat them fresh right off of the
vine or the bush there's there's pole
beans and there's bush beans you can eat
them fresh you can wait for them to dry
on the vine to have dried beans like you
would buy at the store like your pinto
beans or your black beans or your
lentils or you can can them these are
canned ones for example and another way
to store them is freezing them so the
freezer is a really great way to store
food it generally costs only a few
dollars a month to run a deep chest
freezer and you can store a few hundred
pounds of food so again one of the most
important things in the colder climates
is storing the abundance canning is one
way to do that
freezing is another and then there's
also drying as well and then jams I'll
show those as well there's also the
pantry for things like potatoes and
carrots that can store in the pantry so
there's a lot of different ways to store
your food and that's the key beans are
very easy very abundant and I also want
to mention peas which are kind of my
runner up to beans but very easy to grow
for a lot of people some people have
problems with them and they're not
nearly as filling as beans but peas are
another really great crop as well all
right the next one is carrots this is
definitely a favorite for me although to
be honest I just love all foods that
grow really abundantly and easily I mean
so this is a great video for me to be
filming because this is my passion
but carrots now these carrots have been
stored in boxes of sand in a cold pantry
again these have been stored for about
six months so they're not your fresh
super crisp ones but let me give this a
bite that's still pretty crunchy and
these are about six months stored well
it's actually uh Wow they're even sweet
still nice not as flavorful is some
carrots that I've had but sweet so these
can be stored they can be canned as well
I love to make carrot juice I mean
that's one of my favorite things so
carrots that's an important one and I
want to mention with carrots beets now
for a lot of people beets are super easy
some people beets have been a challenge
so I don't necessarily consider them the
most easy but I have to mention them
because they can be very abundant for
some people they're very easy but if you
grow beets you have to eat the greens if
you're wasting the greens
you're wasting some of the best
nutrients and taste they're one of the
most incredible greens if you ask me
they're they're absolutely my favorite
or one of my top favorite greens so
carrots and beets to continue on I want
to mention a few more root vegetables
and that would be radishes and turnips
so radishes are one of the easiest foods
to grow and you can actually harvest
radishes in about 30 days the small
radishes they're one of the fastest
growing crops that there are and you can
grow daikon radishes which get really
huge and I grew a lot of daikon radish
in Florida and then turnips turnips can
be pretty easy to grow as well they are
a nice root they go really well with
potatoes and beets and carrots baked
together
I love baked turnip living off of your
garden doesn't mean living without
flavor in fact it can mean a really
delicious garden full of flavor this
food can be grown right here and you can
harvest it within moments before you're
putting it on your plate so you can get
some of the most
delicious foods that you'll ever eat but
I really like in order to have that for
me there's some key ingredients onions
are one of them herbs are as well which
I'll get into pretty soon now onions can
be extremely easy I want to say that you
might have a hard time getting those big
giant onions that you would get at the
store that's not something that every
gardener or beginner gardener will be
able to get it's more likely that you'll
be able to be successful with small
bulbs and the other thing that's really
one of the easiest is bunching onions
and you can eat the greens now you can
eat the Greens of all onions as well and
actually if you eat just the right
amount you get a crop of green onions
and then a crop of the bulbs as well so
the smaller ones are generally easier
for beginner gardeners another one that
I want to mention is garlic now garlic
is super important to me it's a
wonderful medicine it adds an incredible
amount of flavor for some people they
found garlic to be super easy it's a
little bit more of a challenging one
because you plant it in the fall and
then harvest it in the late spring it
sits under the snow for the winter so
that makes it not quite the easiest it's
a little more challenging especially for
beginners but it can be pretty easy with
garlic this is a clove pop that in the
ground starts to sprout and then you've
got garlic now if you're not successful
with the bulbs you can grow it just for
its greens and you can get really really
productive abundant greens out of garlic
and they're very strong that was quite
strong just like garlic so onions and
garlic those are also extremely
important for preserving food when
you're canning and adding to soups
those really fill out the meal and add a
whole lot of flavor I want to talk to
you about greens now and greens are
where you get a lot of your nutrients
they're one of the things that makes the
most sense to grow locally rather than
having them be shipped they take up a
huge
amount of space and they really are just
one thing that does not make sense to be
shipping long distance so this is kale
right here and some of the beginner
greens that are really easy would
include kale arugula lettuce mustard
greens Swiss chard spinach and amaranth
those are seven of the easier ones to
grow
amaranth what's really special about
that is it's often self seeding and once
you get it going you'll have amaranth
coming back time and time again so
greens are one of the most nutrient
dense foods out there and if you can eat
greens every meal you are you have the
ability to change your life if you're
not eating healthy and they make a huge
difference
now greens are generally what you're
going to be eating during the the months
during the the growing season a lot of
people don't preserve their greens so
much you can and one of the greens
that's easiest to preserve is sauerkraut
so this here isn't exactly sauerkraut
this is more like preserved cabbage
sauerkraut though comes from cabbage and
you can store away jars and jars and
jars of sauerkraut it's just salt
cabbage and not even water and then you
can add in other things if you want like
herbs but literally just salt and
cabbage stores easily for through the
winter and it's delicious add so much
value to your meal the fermentation of
it through wild fermentation actually
increases the nutrient value of it
so cabbage is one that grows pretty well
stores and makes a really value-added
food to add to each of your meals can't
say enough about sauerkraut and if
you're interested in wild fermentation
check out Sandor Katz's book called wild
fermentation it is a must read if you're
going to get into the storing and
fermenting of foods alright next I want
to talk to you about herbs these add
incredible amount of flavor to your
meals you can make teas with
and they are often one of the absolute
easiest things to grow so some of the
herbs that I'm gonna mention are basil
dill cilantro oregano rosemary thyme and
mint here is basil this is being grown
in a greenhouse to get it started I want
to mention one thing about basil and
that's that it likes heat so this is
more of the peak of the summer if you
try to grow this while it's cold in the
beginning of the year you're gonna have
a really hard time and that's an
important thing growing the right things
at the right time of the year now
another herb that I want to mention this
one is just I mean for a lot of people
it's a problem because it's so
successful and it reproduces so well
that it takes over a garden so when I'm
talking about easy and abundant mint is
the picture plant for that it reproduces
through these roots and they just spread
through the soil so all you have to do
is take some roots from a friend's
garden put those down and those will
produce mint so mint is is definitely
one of my top recommendations and it can
end up being a problem so if you do
plant it I mean for me when I was a
beginner gardener I said any plant that
becomes a problem is a friend of mine
and I still generally feel that way one
thing I want to mention about herbs and
that is some herbs grow really well from
seed like for example coriander cilantro
these are really great to plant from
seed now on the other hand mint is a
difficult one to start from seed so for
the ones that are difficult to start
from seed I would recommend buying those
as already started plants from your
local nursery or another gardener or a
plant sale or something of that sort so
herbs galore there are so many I just
named seven but there are a lot of other
easy herbs to grow as well now I want to
talk to you about fruit trees which are
totally different from a lot of these
crops most of these are annual crops
that you have to plant again and again
each year if
you can invest in fruit trees you're
investing in your future you can plant
fruit trees and now the thing is you are
investing in the future to start getting
a lot of apples might take a few years
before you get your first apples and
five years before you start to get a lot
but you'll have apples for decades to
come
so fruit trees that I recommend apples
pears plums mulberries and cherries
those are some of the easiest ones to
grow in those more northern climates
apples can store just like this through
the winter you can freeze them you can
make jams there's so much that you can
do with your fresh fruits and you can
also just enjoy incredible amounts of
them during the season so fruit trees
are definitely a must
you can plant those around the edges of
the property and make use of that
vertical space with fruit trees it's
starting to rain here in the garden so I
got a cruise through these but we're
getting towards the end keeping along
the lines with fruits I want to mention
some berries raspberries and
blackberries generally are the easiest
and those can go crazy and become a
problem for a lot of people blueberries
on the other hand need acidic soil so
for a lot of people they are not a
beginner strawberries also can be pretty
easy however generally raspberries and
blackberries are more abundant than
strawberries so raspberries and
blackberries are my two biggest
recommendations for berries but I just
want to say there's a lot of other ones
out there gotta mention June berries
also called Saskatoon or service berries
are really great one as well right here
I am holding black berry chutney and
jams are an incredible thing to make out
of your raspberries or your blackberries
you can store lots and lots of jam so
that is a really really great thing
about those berries okay next thing I
want to mention is tomatoes tomatoes
grow super abundantly for so many people
and with tomatoes you can make huge
amounts of sauce I've just realized how
many times I've said huge and abundance
over the last 20 minutes or so but
that's what we're talking about plants
that produce a huge amount I just said
it again so tomatoes one that I
absolutely recommend in abundance at my
friend's house this weekend we just
planted over a hundred tomato plants for
a family of four it's a lot of tomatoes
but tomatoes are I mean most people love
them hot pepper is another one this is
something that can often grow in huge
abundance and be very easy
I took one seed from my friends serrano
pepper plant and that produced over a
thousand serrano peppers just from that
one seed another thing that I want to
mention sometimes this is a little bit
harder but cucumbers for making pickles
alright I've got two last ones for you
and these are perennials and with that I
want to mention that I really recommend
perennials these are plants that grow
for a year year after year after year
rather than things that you have to
plant each year like carrots so rhubarb
is one of the most incredible perennials
you plant rhubarb and about in a produce
for about twenty five years really
recommend rhubarb and then lastly we're
gonna finish it off with Jerusalem
artichoke also called sunchokes and
these are another one where if you don't
contain them they can spread through
your garden and they can become wild as
well they produce a huge amount I just
said huge again they produce an
incredible amount of food and they're
very tasty and I cook them basically
like a potato so there you have it that
is about 40 of my top recommendation for
the easiest and most abundant foods to
grow in your garden I just want to say
there's a lot more out there
I picked a lot of the common foods that
people have a lot of experience with and
and recognize because it's easier to get
started with that rather than plants
that you might never heard of like
gooseberries which grow well in northern
climates are like Moringa kale and
America took and Chaya which are more
southern climate so I just want to say
that I did kind of pick things that are
more known but there's
a lot of unknown foods that grow
extremely well I want to say try your
best to get your seeds locally locally
adapted seeds will grow much better in
your area because they are adapted to
that area and then buying your plants
from local nurseries that are using
varieties that have been grown in the
area for decades helps a lot
also for support join a community garden
if you you know feel like you have a
black thumb it would be incredibly
helpful to be around other people and
then also volunteer at farms and Gardens
that way you can be learning and you can
be helping at the same time and the
amount of knowledge that you gain by
volunteering at gardens and farms is
pretty priceless I hope that this video
has really inspired you to grow a lot of
food this year and the years to come
start small don't feel like you have to
grow all 40 of these crops this year and
add on each year as you start to get
better and better I'm excited for you to
get that there and start grow up some of
your own food if you enjoyed this make
sure that you subscribe to the channel
lots more to come
comment below and also like this to help
this get out into the YouTube world and
inspire more people to start growing
their own food I love you all very much
and see you again soon