you know it's amazing that we've
actually expanded to a bigger space in
ekkenov
where we partnered with the tlc
children's home and we've managed to
form
an agreement with them to use their
farming space which is about nine
hectares
[Music]
welcome to the farming podcast my name
is your host um once again right here on
the private property
channel
today we're joined by a friend of the
podcast who has been on the show before
and we spoke about hydroponic farming
rooftop farming because she had her own
rooftop farm in johannesburg cbd but she
joins us today on a different level
where she's going to tell us about her
agribusiness online platform that she
has started with the women's
organization and that promotes
and showcases
agribusinesses regarding hydroponic
farming and organic farming so if you
are interested in hydroponic farming how
to diverse into organic farming i
believe this conversation would be quite
beneficial to you because she is a
farmer herself and so she knows a thing
or two about hydroponic farming and so
yeah if you have any questions please
feel free to comment like and share
subscribe to the podcast and reach out
to our guests over an abava conversation
today because this podcast is for you
and we're here to help you learn
everything about agribusiness so i'm
getting into the conversation right now
i'm joined by ooh
how are you doing and thank you so much
for coming on to the podcast once again
i'm blessed thank you my sister bali and
it's actually a pleasure and i'm really
grateful for the opportunity to share
with fellow farmers the developments
that have taken place
and in building these communities that
we are surrounded with because we always
say we want to be the ones that see the
change in our communities and we go all
out to actually make sure that we impact
communities absolutely so let's just
start off by
giving us a rundown of where you are
right now with your farming business i
remember the last time you spoke you're
farming in the rooftop is everything
going well and we also touched based on
um how covert had impacted you um in our
previous conversation so how's the farm
looking
are you harvesting any crops at the
moment
you know it's amazing that you've
actually expanded to a bigger space in
ekinoff
where we partnered with the tlc
children's home and we have managed to
form
an agreement with them to use their
farming space which is about nine
hectares so we set up in hydroponics
which takes now fourteen thousand
uh
crops
and we are also doing an incubation then
we set up a class and we working as a
group of five of us now in a
collaboration called african women in
agriculture okay so i've got four
dynamic women that i'm working with is
janus schechter agnes hawaii and i've
got veronica
aswany and we're also working with bia
at black so as the five of us we've
started that incubation now and also the
farming business and the platform called
i am citizen so it's been a great move
because now it has given us an
opportunity to now impact communities
surrounding the akanov area where we
recruit young women who want to do
hydroponics farming and do also organic
farming and we also give them business
skills
and
they're also
taken to a point where they're able to
start their own businesses using
farming as a way of of entering markets
because the challenge has been that they
say as young people farming hasn't been
easy so we said no you can join and see
that there's there's actually so much
that you can do within the value chain
of farming so we we we started with the
first incubation last year and then this
year we've got the second cohort which
we're doing up until july then july
we're taking the next intake
where we're encouraging them to go also
and impact their communities where they
come from and and we evaluate their
community projects we profile them on i
am citizen which is the online platform
digital platform that we have started as
aware yeah so tell me more about the
incubation that you formed with aria
how long does it take
and why did you decide that there's a
need for an incubation
with a current
situation where
most of the challenges that were faced
by women was access to land and access
to finance and also looking at how do we
make sure that we we empower them on
starting just starting because the key
thing is that people want to be into
farming but they're not starting so with
that nine hectares that we we
listen from the
children's home we're able to get them
to start and practice and also learn
from a space where we are set up and
then we also
assist them in incapacitate them to a
point of them starting up their own
businesses where they come from
so the incubation is actually on
incapacitating women to to be able to
start and farm and they have access to
having like trainings that they don't
have to do just online but they can come
and do practicals at the farm where we
are at the tlc children's home yeah and
how long do you train the woman around
farming um is it just a few months a few
weeks and then what happens thereafter
it's actually six months because the
first cohort we got them for the whole
year last year so this year we split it
into six months so we we we've got the
first call second cohorts that we
started in feb they're finishing in july
and then we'll take the next cohort up
until november so what what happens
there we train them on the practical
side of farming and also we we have
classes where we have personal
development we're also looking at
at training them on finances how to
manage their finances how to have access
to markets and then we invite guest
speakers on various topics in
agriculture to come and address them
so we understand that there's more
farming than just farming the land we
say you can actually be in in in any
value chain within the farming
sector so we encourage them to also look
at how they can come in we've got new
intakes that some of them are looking at
being retailers and starting their own
businesses where they will actually uh
be
acting as aggregators
to to to aggregate from farmers and then
supply the communities where they come
from yeah so am i correct in saying that
the incubation right now is purely
focused on crop farming and not
necessarily livestock
we we've we've included poultry this
year because we've had three intakes of
young ladies that want to do poultry so
we've we've included poultry and we're
looking at expanding also to piggery and
also looking at
sheep farming and goat farming and
rabbit farming because we interview them
and then they tell us what what space
they want to be in
we also
guest speakers on the various topics
like with poultry we had a young farmer
that has just opened an abattoir in
akinov to come and speak to them and
encourage them that there's more you can
do within the value chain of poultry
so thomas bong and it to be part of the
incubation do i need to be a farmer that
has access to land for example but maybe
need a bit of technical information or
technical skill in how to cultivate
crops etc and that is when i would apply
into the occupation stay there for six
months and then go back onto my land and
farm or can it be anybody who's just
interested in farming exploring the
different commodities that are available
in farming whether it's crops
poultry
even
adding a value add in terms of an
abattoir so can it just be anybody or do
i have to have land on or an already
existing business where i can up up
skill
and improve my knowledge in farming
we we're actually encouraging even those
who don't have land why because we're
saying there's lots of people who say
they don't have lenta they're not
maximizing the spaces that they have
where they are because there's a new
project also that will be starting very
soon in may where we're using pyramids
to show them how to grow in their own
backyards because with the current
situation of food shortage we cannot
leave those backyards to life fallow so
there's a friend of mine veronica who's
also part of the
of the women in agriculture she's
designed a a pyramid that you can use as
a vertical farm
to to plant in in a small area about 120
plants at a goal so we're pushing that
to train people on that and then we
assist you to get to it we give them a
fundable business plan
that they can now go back and use the
land where they come from
okay so now moving on to the online
agricultural platform you mentioned that
you're promoting businesses that are
doing hydroponic farming and organic
farming so just tell us a little bit
more about the platform and how it works
so this platform will work as a
community as well because we've got a
page where we invite communities to come
and learn and say
like for example ask an agronomist
and then there will be an agronomist
that will answer questions for people
who want to be informing but they've got
lots of questions that they're not
certain about and then we've got a site
where we do profiling of farms and also
profiling of of of stakeholders
like if there's uh your your your people
that supply
inputs
they will be profiled on on that i am
citizen so that people have access to
the full network of not just farmers
network of of also suppliers and also
stakeholders within the agricultural
space
when did you decide to
when did you develop and launch the im
citizen platform and what success
stories can you tell us thus far that
have come out of the platform
with the i'm citizen we started in in
and the success stories has been that
we've been able to build a network of
farmers but even the incubators that we
had for a year last year they're also
profiled on that when they're able to do
their business on that platform and
network amongst themselves we we
encourage them to say
you you need to collaborate and work
together because with farming you cannot
operate in isolation
so we're encouraging them to say please
work together and with the second
incubation that we have the second
cohort we've also onboarded them to say
do your business on the platform because
digital space you're not limited to
where you are you can actually network
with women from different regions
different places because we're going
global and we cannot be operating just
locally
and confirming uh that you did say that
the land that
uh the incubation and the platform is is
is is highlighting is for the farmers
who are being incubated in akanov have
you received any requests for people
who've seen successes in your incubation
program to maybe replicate what you're
doing in other areas particularly in
khao deng over and above the other
provinces
yes we we've had so many requests
because even now we we're basically
communicating with people in in the area
of
iguruleni they actually saying can we
replicate this in in in the east as well
because we want to take it within
communities we've been counting then
also we've had in
inquiries from the eastern cape
to actually replicate this ip in the
different areas right
and just summing up
engagements with with them so we're open
to to replicating this model
in different areas
yeah i i think a critical question also
to find out spoken is that how many
intakes can you take at a time
okay at the moment because we're in
partnership with idc and we we were
looking at 12
cohort which is six months we're looking
at 24 in in in in one year but now with
the other
portion that we've included we're
looking at using the the new isa vuno
which we've named as isi vunaway will
also look at impacting communities at
larger scale where we'll have saturday
classes for them to learn about this is
the new
one that we're doing where we are
training them on how to maximize their
spaces in the urban areas especially the
ones that
back gardens
and i mean on my back garden which is
20 by 20 i've managed to grow plants as
well so i always say to them there's no
way you can leave that land follow and
and then you say you don't have food
because we still have that project
called farm in a box where we we donate
seeds
to to to to communities to start their
own food gardens at their back yards
right you did say that the the the
incubation is a non-profit so what
happens to all the crops that you uh
that you produce part of the incubation
program do you sell that um with the
revenue do you apply it back onto the
farm or do you give the crops to nearby
communities as part of food security
yes on the on the
one for farming enterprise because
within the the area we've got the
farming enterprise which is the one
where we're planting the crops and we've
partnered with ebb and fresh they are
our off takers
they come and collect and sell and then
the profit is it's it's plowed back into
the area npo
so the the other one it's impacting like
the very same children's home they they
actually get produced from because when
we started we started with them and we
started as a food garden that we were
doing for them and then they saw the
way it was done and this that we've got
len that's available can you partner
with us and set up something in in in
the tlc children's home
so part of the impact that we make it's
actually ten percent goes to protect
of communities locally and then the rest
we we plow back into the npo from the
sales made with the partnership we have
with ebb and fresh who are aggregators
yeah it sounds like you guys have really
thought about it quite uh
extensively you know uh making sure that
you're covering all the blocks that
really farmers face as a big challenge
or a barrier to entry into uh the
agricultural sector um i know you are a
farmer as well and now you've
transitioned into a a a space where
you're helping other farmers teaching
them um exposing their businesses and
obviously
transferring skills to aspirant farmers
what have you learned um throughout 2021
and going into 2022
over
since you've started helping um all the
cohorts in the various stages of their
businesses
what have you learned from it from from
starting um your incubation program as
well as i am a citizen uh program what
have you learned around the farmers and
more so just uh um in general within
agriculture from a farmer's perspective
and wearing my head as a farmer this has
been
an amazing time because now as a farmer
we always wanted to start in isolation
and run your farm there on your own but
now with moving to african women in
agriculture where i collaborated with
five dynamic women
it it has actually opened my
eyes to a point that collaboration is
key if we want to build communities we
need to collaborate and the networking
that takes place as farmers has actually
grown to a point that i'm even
networking with women as far as the
northwest
because we we didn't leave it to saying
we are in counting we need to address
issues and how they it has actually
opened up for us to actually network
with with people as far as india because
i've just won the global award
for women in in in agriculture
addressing the sdg goal number two of
zero hunger and i'm finding myself
speaking to women in india who are
doing and how they
and this has opened up a door because
like i said with with with networking
we're not limiting it to the whatsapp
we're now saying let's work with apps
where we can empower each other
and reach other
actions and countries surrounding us as
south africa
well that's fantastic and
congratulations on your award i think it
definitely shows um of the efforts and
the work that you're doing on the ground
but before i let you go swangela what
three points can you give to aspirin
farmers who want to venture into farming
whether it could be crops
livestock poultry
what advice would you give maybe top
three things that you'd give to an
aspirin farmer who wants to venture into
agriculture
thank you my sister you know i always
say to to farmers that as a farmer you
must have the tendency to continue
despite all challenges that we're
currently facing
and and the second one is to actually be
there as someone who's a solution see
yourself as a solution what are you
bringing into the agrispace be a
solution in a community and also the
third one would be start wherever you
are what is the that's in your hand do
not limit yourself to say i'm waiting
until i have 10 million or i have a
funding from start as little as at your
back garden move on let your communities
know that you are farming in your air
if you say you are a farmer no one knows
where you come from that you are farming
it's a challenge so start
where you are and use as little
resources that as you move on and you're
speaking to other funders they always
want to know have you started something
where are you uh where are you currently
where are you moving to what are your
futures and don't be scared to dream big
i always encourage people to say dream
big don't limit yourself
i left my profession as an accountant to
do my passion of farming and i've never
stopped
i never stopped i started living with a
small garden at my backyard to actually
let me eat from the garden just outside
my house and then move on so i really
encourage people to say start where you
are and don't despise humble beginnings
because we always want to see
things happening at a higher level
without starting where you you you have
your footprint
wow so that's my my treatment to say
start where you are don't limit yourself
and dream big and definitely have the
tenacity to farm
thank you so much for joining us
we thoroughly enjoy your inputs and your
presence within the farming podcast and
thank you for the work that you're doing
in agriculture because a lot more people
need training a lot more people need
exposure into the realities that a
farmer faces every single day and thank
you for just you know
pushing those individuals and holding
their hand training them transferring
skills making them understand how the
whole value chain of agriculture works
and congratulations once again for
winning your award
thank you so much
my sister and stay blessed we're really
touched and thank you that you you you
taking these stories too because these
stories need to be heard by the next
generation i'm always looking at the
seventh generation because i'm already
with grandchildren
so i want them to know that we didn't
i would tell them
we were busy i won't be with this
farming it never stopped you need to you
you just need to take the dayton forward
yeah
so i'm really and
thank you and god bless you for for all
the work that you're doing thank you i
really really appreciate it that was
mongerella who's one of the founding
members of african women in agriculture
the organization is called aria a w i a
they're based in akanov where they are
incubating farmers
for a period of six months teaching them
how to produce crops how to understand
the value chain
and they're working with an aggregator
who's able to take those crops and just
show the farmers basically the basics
around farming what goes into farming
and how the valley chain works from a
spec requirement to an input perspective
and when you have to cultivate your own
land so they teach you how to formulate
a business plan
how to just get started and get going
and working with other farmers and just
understanding
the realities that a farmer faces each
and every day they're not only focused
in crop production but
have moved into poultry and have
aspirations into moving into rabbit
farming livestock farming as a whole so
i think if you are looking to start a
farm or just maybe grow
the area in which you're producing food
in i think uh the we are team is is a
team that you should get in touch with
so reach out to
and her team based in akanov and i
believe once they have their cohort
applications open you should definitely
apply uh if you have any questions
please feel free to comment um on our
youtube channel we make sure that we
could reach out to um too small on your
behalf and maybe share her contact
details as well but yeah that's it from
the farming podcast today's topic was
agribusiness online platforms how we
start agribusiness online platforms
incubating farmers teaching farmers
transferring skills and yeah i hope this
conversation was beneficial to you and i
will see you next time thank you
thank
you awesome
thank you my dear have a blessed day
you