[Music]
hey y'all let me start by introducing
myself my name is Wes white here at tick
Creek Ranch we're social media content
creators and we do all kinds of stuff
here on the acridge we operated on 192
acres and as you can see we got some
timber here on our land so roughly 2
years ago started working on a proof of
concept now here we are many months
later and what you see before you is
what we call the log Hopper I saw it as
an opportunity to hopefully design
something and maybe some would say
reinvent the wheel but it's a
combination of a skitter SL logging Arch
I feel that it really can help fill a
knead or a hole that's in the market and
for some of you folks out there now this
is by no means going to replace a
tractor if you want or need a tractor
I'm not telling you you should even
consider this this is a very specialized
piece of equipment for a very
specialized application where the
Genesis that this came from is that I'm
very ecologically and biologically
conscious whe whether it be our pastures
our cattle our horses or the forest
floor I Like To Tread really light I
don't like to leave any Trace if I can
so that's kind of where this all came
from we're going to go around and show
you the features and functions of this
and I love your feedback all right so
we're going to start with the heart of
the Beast here what we got here is a
mile marker 5,000 lb winch and it does
come with a full spool of wire now we're
going to send it out like that to
anybody purchases it but I would
actually recommend unless you plan on
yarding with this thing and if you do
that hat you're going to probably want
to add an external battery on top of
this unit I wouldn't want to rely on the
small battery that's on your ATV
four-wheeler side by side whatever you
got to be running this winch in a
continuous fashion for long pull so this
wire here I'll actually probably trim it
down to about 20 ft it'll give us less
wraps on the spool it'll make the job of
the winch a lot easier and you won't
have so much problem with biting and
pinching cable it'll be a lot easier to
Flat wrap so that being said this is how
it will come it comes with its own
wiring harness that you would just add
to your side by-side ATV and then you'll
be able to plug it in directly and run
off the battery of the machine that
you're pulling it with here we've got
some grade 7516 chain and you can see we
got three chain Keepers on either side
the chain keeper is designed for just
that okay I do not recommend don't ever
ever suspend the load or the log off
these chain Keepers the only reason I
say that it's not the Integrity or any
problem here that we would be worried
about it would be this so if someone is
rigging this up puts their hand in here
like this and the load comes loose it
will cut your fingers off this is a
terrible pinch point so these are not
for carrying load chain hooks boom
that's how you'll suspend your load okay
let's talk about what makes this machine
more unique than pretty much anything on
the market um this is not a new design
and I'm not intending to say this is my
own conception this is a very standard
mechanical feature on a lot of trailers
Andor military vehicles throughout the
world I think a lot of you would know
what a walking beam suspension is
especially considering if you ever been
around a logging truck a Hendrickson
suspension or the like so we've just
adapted that to a 3500 lound stub shaft
here these are 5/8 plate this is all
laser cut and these spindles which are
all greaseable mind you these spindles
are rated at 1100 lb the tires are rated
1,000 lb so we are giving this machine a
3,000 lb rating I don't recommend going
higher than that but I know how you guys
use your equipment you can see this is
pretty
self-explanatory we've got deflectors
and then we also got chain keep Keepers
on the side here now what will we use
these for well these are designed to be
able to create a cradle or or run a
chain over the top of your log so if
your log is butt heavy and you're
grabbing it from the top of the tree and
it naturally wants to lift the front of
the log when you pick it with the winch
well you can throw a chain over the
front and you'll be able to carry a butt
heavy log out you'll take obviously
weight off the tow vehicle and you'll
have to take that in consideration or we
can cradle we can throw the chain
underneath the log and just lift set the
front of the log reset our tongs and
lift the back l so now you're probably
wondering what this contraption is well
this is what we call our trolley this
machine is designed to run many
different features and functions you
should be able to yard with it lightly
you're going to also have the the
feature of a standard log Arch where
you're going to be able to cradle and
carry your log out and you're going to
be able to take and move Logs with
unlimited length you'll be able to move
pecker poles and tree length logs as
long as they're not heavier than the
machine can handle by using this Trolley
system so what we got here is a pin it's
got three
positions a different height you can run
it if you want to cradle your log from
the front and hang from there but this
operation is going to allow you to back
over your log connect this hook to the
choker on your log and as you pull
forward this is going to run
up stop at the back and then drag your
log out from behind you it works really
great on really long trees again pecker
pulls you know light logs I've pulled a
I've Dr around a 40ft log that was about
oh 16 in at the butt 18 in it can do
more uh that's just something I did with
it you got to make sure your choker
chain is tight enough and you don't have
too much tag in to make sure that the
log is high enough so when the machine
articulates and the log comes out at a
obtuse angle it's not interfering with
your tire that is another feature of
these really short tires people might
ask well why four tires instead of just
two well the walking beam suspension is
a class two lever allows you to Traverse
over obstacles much easier with a heavy
load so as you can see for any of those
that don't understand you'll see how the
lifting mechanism works here as I pick
up on this tire I will effectively only
be lifting half of the weight of this
unit cuz half will be on there the same
goes for when this crawls over a stump
or
log see how easy that is this unit
weighs just under 600 lb and I can
easily lift that so now you can
understand how little upward Force has
to be applied to this tire to
effectively lift this to allow the tire
to Traverse over set obstacles so on
some of our Prototype videos we had some
people say oh great now you got four
tires to get flats instead of two and
blah blah blah it increases your chances
of getting a flat in the forest well if
you're going to go by that addage you
might as well run a unicycle and get rid
of your car that way you don't have more
tires in the way any rate let's say for
instance we get a flat tire here well
how do we get out of the forest if it's
truly going to run off the bead well
we'll show you it's pretty simple go
ahead and remove your cradle chain here
and we can run it right around the axle
we're going to say that the back tire is
now flat this is just a demonstration
you're going to take said chain
and we're falling over well now your
Tire's off the ground now you can run
out on a single you're not going to run
this off its bead you can do the same
thing to both sides if you want to feed
this trailer in over a log in a really
hard spot to back into we'll repeat the
same process over
here all right so now both are off the
ground mind you now we just changed the
center of balance of this machine
because we moved it forward from here to
the center of this axle which takes
incredible amount of weight off of the
tongue so it becomes much lighter and
easier to handle and wheel around all
right so if you're not too good at
backing up you can always do
this trip on a stick while you're at it
and you could position this over your
log bring your machine in and connect
okay let's come to the front here this
is the really important part um put a
lot of time effort and thought into how
to make this work work to where is very
strong and very safe for the end user so
if you get an apparatus like this behind
you I'm sure you know as well as I do
you manage to flip this thing over well
if this goes over and it's connected to
the ball in your four-wheeler what do
you think is going to happen you're
going to roll and it's going to be bad
so what did we do here we created a
swiveling tongue this is greaseable here
you go your grease zert this is a 1-in
grade 8 shaft passes all the way through
Doom tubing that's quarter wall
thickness 3/8 here in the gusset plate
you can see you have a handle and then
obviously your power wire that is going
to run your winch and it'll connect to
back to your
four-wheeler beautiful so that takes the
safety factor and uh UPS it a lot you
know in the initial phases and testing I
was doing some really kind of radical
and dumb stuff right well that's R&D
driving as fast as I could and trying to
flip my trailer I never was actually
successful but it's possible and I know
there's guys out there that will take
bigger chances than me so this is for
that oh factor and it should keep
you out of Harm's Way we'll demonstrate
that later I'll go ahead and throw this
thing over on its side down in the
pasture so this takes us to the next
part this machine does not come with log
Tong well we opted not to do that
because everybody's needs for logging
tongs and sizes are very very different
so you might say well one size fits all
but that's not been my experience so
what I got here is I have a set of 25 in
and 18in I find I use these more but
when you need these you just got to have
them as you can see here's your throat
it'll handle up to almost a 31 in log we
call it 30 because you're going to need
a little wiggle room obviously you can
also see here we have deflectors so when
you're backing in and if your guide
liming the log which is probably you
didn't limit too well well you don't
have a sharp a here that just
slams into and stops you we figured that
one out real fast first limb stub that I
backed into and it stopped me dead in my
tracks well we added those so as you can
see we have almost triple the effective
thickness of that 5/8 plate that 5/8
plate has zero deflection zero measured
deflection when it's being operated so
major Improvement 3/8 plate 3/8 tubing
this is 3in pipe and then let's look up
in here Tristan last but not least we
have an anchoring point for a shackle
here you can run a snatch block on here
to take some load off of your winch if
you need to all right you can see our
wire passes through our upper tube comes
out all the way to the front so it's
direct shot no slices let's get this
thing hooked up and uh we're going to go
grab a lot
so we're here on the trail for
demonstration purposes it's kind of hard
out in the brush it's hot as hell and
we're getting covered in tick so we're
going to be babies and do it right here
and it'll be a lot easier to explain and
show this is an old southern yellow pine
log uh it was cut about a year and a
half ago so it has lost the moisture
content but it's still very heavy I can
assure you we've been using this through
the R&D process this is one of our
sacrifice our dirty logs we drug this
thing and beat it and everything
everything else so really yeah all right
so we're about 22 in by 24 it's a really
balanced log uh we use this so we
wouldn't be cherry-picking during the
design of something that was extremely
front heavy giving us a skewed idea of
actually how this would work so we
wanted the log to be balanced so we
couldn't say oh yeah we can carry 24t
logs because the butt was this big and
the top was that big right all right
here we got a 7t choker slip hook and a
needle now if you can't needle and feed
under this and you're not going to be
able to get it cuz you're on too
perfectly flat of ground which I could
right there and that works but if you
can't we're going to show you how you
would go ahead and feed that here for
demonstration purposes I'm going to do a
bad job of backing up as you can see it
just slips
[Music]
over now don't let the trailer roll your
leg over because it will pull
four-wheeler in the trailer back as you
can see so stand outside of your
[Music]
tires it's like 94 to million per
humidity we didn't come here to listen
to any
wi pull that I like to just drop that in
there
this creates a little bit of a pendulum
effect now I'm going to try first time
I'm just going to pull forward I'm going
to see if it's going to run up and if it
won't because we lose traction of the
log skids then we go to plan
B that works Dandy now I'm just going to
take this
pen drop it in the desired hole as you
get more used to this machine you'll be
able to eyeball it and know where when
and how which one of those holes you're
going to use
so there we go all right now you can see
the logs off the ground up front what is
that 8 10 in it's going to come up
higher and I'll show you why now we go
ahead and set our tongs
back okay so now we're scoped out you're
going to see as we start winching up
it's going to drive the log forward once
again standing out of the way of your
wheel so you don't get run over
[Applause]
all right so the other way we just go
ahead and stretch out our tongs hook it
on the
trolley cure up Dro your
[Music]
pen so go ahead and lift this guy
up stay very clear obviously you can see
these tongs are just barely holding on
so we don't want to be playing with that
remember never put your fingers in a
pinch point area so hang your trains
from underneath comes down hard on it
you won't get
pin PR it down you got
it all right Tristan my cameraman he's
going to go ahead and hold this tape
let's look at the length of this log and
see what we got so what we had remember
is 22x 24 on average both ends of this
log so we're going to call it a 23 in
diameter log by 16 to long let's go
drive this thing around and take it over
some stuff see what happens
[Music]
all right we're going to demonstrate
crawling over obstacles so there's an
old nasty St it's a pretty big one
[Music]
all right so I'm going to dump this
thing over we're going to see how that
swivel on the front works I don't give
myself a hernia
[Music]
all right folks well we appreciate you
sticking around if You' like any more
information go ahead and reach out to us
at ww w. tick Creek ranch.com or you can
always get us at our email at tick Creek
Ranch
gmail.com so that's it from us here at
te Creek Ranch and we'll catch you on
the next one
[Music]