hey folks aaron ida creek farm and bush
hoggingservices.com out here on another
job this weekend
opening up some trails and you can see
behind me what we have done
uh when we got started it was basically
fingertip to fingertip
along this trail and the owner wanted it
open up and it's a lot of this florida
scrub that you see behind me
and uh getting it done so it's been
about
about four hours so far getting through
it pretty quick
uh we got the bottom of light today it's
the only thing heavy enough to
get through some of this and here's what
uh
the bomb of light can do to some of
these trees you can see it's basically
shaved that in half it's not a mulcher
but it'll certainly cut that down and
allow you to pick it up and move it and
i'm not sure why he ran over that one
but he did
so i'm going to spin you around and
we're going to go back and take a look
at
the tractor in action with the
heavy duty bomb of light on there here
we go
this job ended up being more work than
anticipated had to put a lot of branches
on the ground
like over here back there came along
with the chainsaw
each of us took a turn and basically
whooped us
soaked to the bone uh from sweat out
here in the florida
humidity so kind of overcast today it
rained a little bit ago so it hasn't
been too bad
but with that humidity it's just hot so
about an hour on that chainsaw is about
any but
as much as anybody can take you can see
a peek at the bottom of light up there
let's take a break we'll be right back
all right mosquitoes and horse flies are
out today welcome to florida
the rainy season just kicked off
watch out he's probably backing up
this is the last bit we've done here
[Music]
we got lucky the owner added some work
to it
we made a couple extra hundred bucks for
clearing around the pond
you gotta be careful not to get near
that thing that thing will throw a rock
off yards
it's kind of like working with a
sledgehammer compared to a regular
brush cutter we had a tail wheel put on
it that was a fail
somewhere along the way it looked like a
pin got pulled out the tail wheel fell
out and he ran over it
dented it kind of jacked it up so we'll
have to try to repair it later
we have to get a new wheel just
disappointing i hadn't even really used
it yet
back right into those palmettos it won't
multiple meadow but it'll
it'll cut a palmetto stalk and uh unless
if it's the real fibrous piece it won't
it won't uh mulch it like
otherwise it will uh do a real number on
the palmettos
all this strobe that you see around here
like this stuff
the only time it gets difficult is when
the branches hang over
the field and then they get in the way
of the track to the cab
which is why we got to go out with a
chainsaw
ahead of the cutter and cut those
particular branches down so we can
move efficiently in the tractor
but we're gonna keep this video short
you need bush hawking services in cedar
key
chieflin bronson williston uh
crystal river areas give us a call at
bushlockingservices.com if you like the
videos like
like it and give us a thumbs up we
appreciate you and
hope you enjoy the videos
let's get out of here before we get run
over get a piece of wood
stuck in her skull