when someone talks about monster grass
one nation which pops up in anyone's
mind is China saves tradition or
religion bamboo trees Earth at the heart
of the agriculture sector in China in
both the traditional as well as
modernized farming bamboo trees are
amazingly cultivated by Chinese farmers
and the results are super amazing China
is blessed with the best geographical
location friendly environmental
conditions massive Manpower and varied
Innovative techniques all these factors
suit the best for cultivating bamboo
trees and masses amazingly China is the
largest producer of bamboo trees and
almost half of the 1250 species could be
easily found in China's Diversified
bamboo production interesting isn't it
what techniques are used by Chinese
Farmers to grow bamboo trees which China
is the best choice when bamboo
production is talked about let's take a
deeper dive to know how China tops the
list when the bamboo Plantation is in
the picture
why is bamboo highly preferred
cultivation by Chinese Farmers one
fascinating fact that not only amuses
China but the entire Globe is that
bamboo is highly strengthened elastic
and as wear resistant characteristics
once cultivated these bamboo grows
swiftly and it'll take almost three to
five years to get mature these bamboo
trees mature with high yields and
throughout the process of their growth
they need very little care and
management the next appealing fact about
these bamboo trees is that the end
product can be used for Endless things
by human beings this bamboo can easily
substitute wood in the long run and all
of us are aware that human beings are
heavily dependent on recognizing and
exploiting natural resources for
survival being said this not only China
but the entire world has the most
prominent agenda of harvesting in
utilizing bamboo in the agriculture
sector however the method of cultivating
harvesting and utilizing varies on the
quality as well as the end user of the
bamboo
you might be surprised to know that
there are about 1 250 species of bamboo
in the world some prominent bamboo zones
in the world are Asia the Pacific the
Americas and Africa nevertheless 80 of
the species of bamboo can be spotted in
East Asian southeast Asia now jumping on
to why is China the best area for the
bamboo Plantation the major benefit for
China is its perfect location it is
situated from the subtropical Zone to
the temperature zone and some of its
parts like Yin and Province are in the
tropical zone so these zones are
particularly within the reach of the
East Asian in Southeast Asian Monsoon
regions and hence with these super
geographical conditions in natural
environment most of the bamboo species
can be spotted in China so because of
this advantageous location an amazing
climatic conditions China is ranked as
the largest in terms of species as well
as the diverse growing area for bamboo
plantations widely named as bamboo
kingdom is home to more than 500 species
of bamboo and this is the first country
in the globe to cultivate such an insane
amount of fish species of bamboo which
parts of China are planting bamboo trees
not only natural forests but also
man-made forests have bamboo plantations
in China from the southern part of the
tropical Zone to the northern part of
the temperature zone which eventually
reaches the Yellow River Valley have
diverse species of bamboo plantations
beets Hills Plains mountains Alpine or
sub-alpine altitude every part of the
region has bamboo plantations and these
areas are spread in 24 provinces other
provinces namely Hunan Guangdong guangxi
and Hainan are situated in the Southeast
tropical Monsoon region and have mostly
sympodial types of bamboo plantations
apart from this majority type these
provinces of a gigantic bamboo forests
and in that giant areas you can easily
spot bamboo species like denzio calamus
bambusa shizostakayum and encephalos
takayum chymonic calamus giganticloa
trisostakis neocinocolamus and others
though coming to the Central and Eastern
parts of China from the yangte cover to
the subtropical region this region is
highly influenced by East Asian
subtropical monsoons and because of
these natural climatic conditions one
can majorly spot monopodial and symposal
bamboos when talking about Genera
philistakis is the majorly spot Genera
in this region counting the total
Reserve volume of bamboo plantations in
China accumulates to a massive 150 to
170 million tons the natural as well as
man-made forests that majorly have
bamboo plantations are a massive source
of income for the country the investment
is quite low and compared to its outputs
so by analyzing the current situation in
China it is pretty obvious that there is
a great potential for further
development in the country especially
for bamboo plantations being a major
producer of bamboo it's important to
concentrate on every step of the
cultivation of crops and we already know
China's briskly shifting from
traditional techniques of the
agriculture process to contemporary
techniques so let's Glimpse what are the
Innovative techniques used for bamboo
farming at the beginning of spring
season which starts in March and goes
into July seeds of bamboo plants are
threshed getting these bamboo seeds is
pretty difficult so from The Limited
availability of seeds Farmers tried to
propagate as many bamboo plants as they
can as these seeds are rare and
sensitive some extra care is needed like
preventing them from drying out getting
too much direct sun or from getting too
cold as well after this process the
seeds are spread on the farmland and
undergo a special watering process
within three months or so these seeds
grow up and now they'll be mature enough
to shift from the Earth to the Plastics
until they're strong babies it is
advisable that these plantations take
place indoors or in Greenhouse
cultivation for a few years for the best
results
at the stage these bamboo plants need to
be placed in Plastics as after growing a
bit more it'll be easy for shifting to
other areas and just in a few days these
saplings are big enough and in proper
shape to get cut after cutting and
cleaning one of the bamboo sticks and
then those remaining grown-up plants are
transferred into big plastic bags with
roots for further propagation the upper
part of the bamboo is slightly cut into
three different parts and in those three
different parts Farmers dig a hole in
that entire piece of bamboo is half
buried in the soil you might be thinking
why the pieces of bamboo have a hole the
reason is while burying the piece into
the land those holes are filled with
water to keep the soil and the bamboo
piece moist within just a few days of
proper care and management The Roots
grow underground and the plant grows
slowly and steadily the next method
which is usually used by the farmers is
to propagate bamboo trees by Roots this
might sound absurd at first but
surprisingly this is the most effective
method of propagation and yes this
method is traditionally proven and is
the most effective natural strategy to
grow bamboo the underground expansion of
roots gradually produces new shoots
which basically come out into towering
poles here the farmers need to be extra
careful as they need to figure out if
it's running bamboo or clumping bamboo
because both the types of bamboo have
different varieties of fruits take into
consideration that if it's running
bamboo then it rhizomes grow parallel to
the ground and outward once these roots
grow upwards they will send fresh shoots
and eventually a new sapling however the
method of growing Roots is not the same
as the clumping method and also at the
same time is not advisable more
preferable propagation method through
Roots is running bamboo the next method
for the cultivation of bamboo plants is
through a method of tree branching in
this method the knee butt and the
existing plant is slightly cut in a
plastic bag full of soil is tied with a
rope around the small cut
Now The Roots will automatically grow in
the soil and farmers will be ready with
a new entire plant once enough fruits
are grown that extra bud is entirely cut
down and planted in the plastic bag for
further process
this method is pretty easy and with this
farmers can get more and more plantings
from the existing bamboo the next method
China's Farmers prefers to dig the
entire cut out plant in the soil so in
this method some of the species of
bamboo also grow in a Grove once the
small piece of the existing plant is
cultivated in the soil it starts growing
roots and finally the farmer could carry
out the existing process for the amazing
successful mature bamboo plant since
agriculture is adopting modernized
farming one more Buzz technique is the
tissue culture method this method is a
scientific approach to growing bamboo
trees and the results are super amazing
even if the yield gained is reliable so
be it propagation of bamboo from Roots
bamboo cultivation growth through the
Grove or the modernized tissue culture
method one thing which remains constant
is China remains number one in the
number of species and the yield producer
bamboo no country at this point is also
near China when bamboo trees are in
consideration so these were some of the
interesting facts about China and its
bamboo cultivation techniques so what
are your thoughts in China and its
massive bamboo production is China
cultivating large amounts of bamboo by
some other method will this bamboo be an
alternative to what to let us know your
views in the comments below and if you
enjoyed watching how China is enhancing
its bamboo plantations with different
techniques make sure to like share and
subscribe to our channel for more such
exciting content See you in the next
video