do I need to spend the extra money for
flow control valves
my suggestion is you definitely need to
install flow control valves in your
sprinkler zones that use pop up spray
heads a typical situation faced by many
of our customers is one in which you
have multiple zones one with rotors and
a different zone with spray heads rotors
require at least 50 pounds per square
inch of water pressure in order to
properly function and spray heads work
best with about 30 psi of water pressure
when the 50 psi reaches your spray heads
misting will occur by installing flow
control valves in your spray head zones
you are able to provide the proper water
pressure to all of your sprinklers
resulting in adequate irrigation all
around your yard you can find more
detailed videos about controlling water
pressure and using flow control valves
spray heads and rotors on the videos web
page and remember sprinkler warehouse
has everything for your irrigation needs
so that your trees lawns flowerbeds and
gardens are lush and beautiful and if
you have any questions give us a call or
chat with one of our customer service
agents on sprinkler warehouse.com they
really know their stuff and they'll get
you squared away subscribe to our
YouTube channel for more how-to videos
and for more irrigation tips for
sprinkler warehouse I'm alfred castillo
your sprinkler warehouse pro
[Music]