[Music]
my little elves Chalmers tractor and my
bifold wheeler rake and
after I cut the Hey ladies in the field
flat like what you see down here and
down there's a little bit of fun raked
area a
rake out the field
take these rows that were cut and then
rate flips the rows over so that the the
underside of the grass is now exposed to
the Sun so that that dries and it also
merges it up into a room that's small
enough with the hay baler and pick it up
this is what we call window a great for
to help the underside of the roll dry so
you just flip it over and also merged it
together so that come in here later this
afternoon with a hay baler it'll pick it
up in daily you know what I'm doing here
is that now I rake when there's what I'm
gonna do on the ground so that
right here the leaves of the old fella
and the grasses don't all fall off they
get too dry and brittle and as you move
them lose all that leaf and you can lose
your own easily 2030 percent of the
biomass that you're trying to get into a
veil so right now then I have to wait
for a couple hours for it to dry I'm
still a little bit dry and still waiting
for the do last nights due to come off
it's all gonna depend on if we get
enough Sun the day forecast kind of
changed a little bit so you got three
fathers guys number one thing on drying
hay is the amount of sunlight in the
humidity so it won't pass today
usually below 50% anything 55 or greater
percent that's real hot muggy day high
dew point kidney and
everything goes around I'll be here this
afternoon
[Music]
[Applause]
so your round bailing today yeah this
personnel but weather forecast kinda
he's grateful to Chuck
well
you can cover a lot of ground
[Music]
[Applause]