drone AG was founded in 2015 by farming
brothers Jack and he ran using their own
Farmers of research and development base
they've supplied Agri specific drone
packages and first of their kind
specialist training courses to the
agricultural industry now based on the
experience and insight gained over the
previous years the brothers are moving
into software with a clear mission to
make farming more productive through
practical hassle-free drone automation
and AI technology there is a growing
need to produce more food with less
resources as farmers we need to increase
yield and we need to do it while using
less chemicals and be more efficient
overall in order to remain sustainable
and profitable as a business a drone AG
we have used many different types of
software systems to control drones and
process the data learning what is useful
in the farming setting and what isn't
we've been very much focused on how we
can help farmers use drone technology
through that knowledge by our training
courses and hardware know-how and we've
also been looking at how we can build
practical hassle-free drone technology
ourselves the industry is at the start
of the next major agricultural
revolution drones will form a large part
of this revolution with drones and
agriculture growing to four billion US
dollars by 2020 for building on our
years of experience we knew we needed a
system that saves us time provides us
data we can readily use we also wanted
to lower the barriers of entry both in
terms of cost and complexity so over the
last year we've been using drone
technology in a completely new way and
we've begun building our own software
system based on those principles our
Skippy Scout app is simple to use
taking affordable off-the-shelf drones
like this and automating them in the way
never done before Skippy flies the drone
around the field and at multiple points
it descents to only a few meters above
the crop and takes a photo these images
are collected from across the field much
faster than possible on foot and in a
much more detailed way possible with
mapping or satellite technology
and they can be viewed in near-real-time
once images have been collected users
will be able to view them in location I
mean right into leak level and Rai can
already identify crop cover verses we
cover and even nutrient deficient leaves
we plan to offer the software as a
subscription-based service with two
primary tiers one aimed at farmers and
the other agronomists the price point
will be a lot lower than current
software offerings as a farmer having
this information straight away means I
can confidently assess pest weed and
disease levels in the field and I can
make informed decisions to deal with
them quickly and accurately which
hopefully means less crop damage and
better yields the accuracy and detail in
the data also means that can
specifically target the worst areas of
the crop which helps save on pesticides
and labor thanks to our expert developer
with both experience in drone control
systems and app development we have an
early version of skippy Skerritt up and
running now and the next stage is to
implement the full user interface and
integrate green area index measurements
and we detection we plan to bring in
further expertise to allow us to develop
our AI and recognize different types of
disease weeds and crop growth stage
people have been using drones in
different scenarios with little effect
on a big scale the technologies been
there to be able to map fields and look
at images but there's not been a simple
way of putting it all together and
basically aiding people's jobs in terms
of the agronomist to actually do their
job quicker I think in the past the
software has been cumbersome and slow
and in the end you've stopped using it
because you haven't had the time to do
it
whereas this Kippy Scout will mean that
you'll be quite easily get out of the
card set the drone away and get the data
quickly
new technology can provide solutions to
the challenges ahead but for farmers to
adopt those solutions now they need to
be simple and practical Skippy Scout
optimizes crop management in real time
at leaf level all with just a phone in a
drone and we plan to take this a lot
further over the coming years using
automated drone systems and AI to
optimize the whole crop management cycle
from scouting and mapping through to
intelligent control of both manned and
automated farm machinery on the ground
and even drone sprayers in the air
growing to over 30,000 users worldwide
by 2025 we can help farming to become
more profitable and sustainable while
benefiting the environment as a whole
you