animal diseases can be spread easily
from farm to farm and across the
countryside when livestock and poultry
are transported dirty trucks and
trailers might carry pathogens down the
road onto other farms or ranches and
into facilities follow these guidelines
if you own manage your work at an
operation other vehicles will visit
designate one secure entry point for
empty trucks coming in post a sign that
provides a phone number to call or gain
admittance then either admit only
vehicles you trust won't contaminate
your operation or that you can examine
before they enter inspect the truck and
trailer before it enters your premises
if there's mud or manure ask the driver
to leave to clean the equipment
thoroughly or provide cleaning
facilities outside your premises keep a
log of when haulers enter and leave
contact information and what condition
their equipment is in when they arrive
and depart show haulers what route to
take on your operation and where to loan
before animals are loaded for transport
examine the required paperwork a
certificate of veterinary inspection
which is commonly called a CDI or health
certificate may be required or may be
optional if the animals are going
directly to slaughter this certificate
is required if livestock are transported
across state lines the rules vary
between states so contact your state
animal health official state
veterinarian or local vet to clarify
requirements a certificate of brand
inspection may be required to confirm
that cattle have brands on them for
proof of ownership a bill of lading
describes what's on the truck typically
the number of animals in each class a
bill of sale confirms a change of
ownership like a receipt make sure
truckers have clean Footwear and
coveralls when loading and any time
around animals before animals are loaded
make sure clean outs are closed on
trailers this will keep manure from
being released during the trip confirm
that the transporter has clean and not
reused bedding on the truck examine
animals as they're being loaded don't
load
or injured animals instead sort them out
for examination and possible treatment
when done loading double-check the
paperwork to confirm the number of each
class of animal loaded and make sure all
gates are closed log when the truck left
your premises and any other information
that should be recorded if new animals
are being brought to your farm or ranch
set up your unloading equipment and pens
before they arrive have the area clean
and ready to receive the new animals
prepare a quarantine area in case it's
needed before animals are unloaded from
transport examine the required paperwork
these may include a certificate of
veterinary inspection certificate of
brand inspection bill of lading bill of
sale before or while animals are
unloaded verify and document numbers and
classes of animals for example the
number of cows guilts or use and
possibly each animals identification
such as ear tag or ear notch when
animals arrive don't just unload them
and mingle them with existing animals
evaluate them for signs of sickness
disease or injury if an animal looks
sick separated from the others as soon
as possible the new animals could show
illness at or shortly after arrival and
infect on premises animals with a
contagious disease keep the new animals
quarantined as recommended by your
veterinarian provide fresh water and
feed for the new animals carry out your
animal health protocols for examinations
and vaccinations after the new arrivals
have had time to settle down if possible
after unloading have the transporter
moved the transportation equipment to a
cleaning area where it can be hosed down
to remove manure before it goes back on
the road or to another farm or ranch if
not possible encourage the transporter
to complete a thorough clean out as soon
as possible so whether new animals are
arriving at your operation or being
transported off your premises these
procedures will help you keep the
animals healthy
[Music]