[Music]
thank you
that's
good
okay so we're going to tell you all
about these products right here that I'm
promising you every single one of you if
you own a tractor or not if you have a
trailer
a zero turn an ATV four-wheeler whatever
it is you're gonna want this product
folks how we doing welcome to Good Works
tractors we've got a special guest here
today Rick Percy with multi-seal you're
looking at a tire right here that has
over 300 holes in it but it's still
holding air how's that even possible
[Music]
foreign
pair using multi-seal you need weight
centrifugal force and air pressure and
all we have in this tire is air pressure
but you can still hear it seal the tire
hey Rick question for you can a guy like
me sure give this a shot sure all right
I mean it looks like a really good
stress relief sure what I got to do just
whack it yep okay right there yep all
right let's see how this goes
foreign
[Music]
boy
I'm afraid of busting my knuckles
you gotta whack it hard
[Music]
there you go all right was that good
enough that's good okay that's like a
half inch right yep this stuff is only
good to is this a three three quarters
yep look so that's uh near the max so
just kind of turn it yep
I'll spin it for you
that's it sealed
it's cool that's some good stress relief
right there
very cool all right Rick so I guess
layman's terms what did we just see
happen here well we had this tire
pre-treated with our product multi-seal
Pro HD 2500 and it's a true preventative
tire sealant additive that goes in the
tire ahead of time to help prevent flats
and what happened was the liquid accent
carrier takes our synthetic fibers to
the wound one of them being Kevlar fills
that void immediately almost like a
beaver dam or a blood clot it makes it
permanent repair
within one or two revolutions of the
tire okay so you know I've I've seen I
guess like the tire Slime type products
on the shelves before use those I know
that my dealer over in Matawan does not
like to service a tire that has that in
there but your product is different it
seems like yes
our product has uh all synthetic fibers
in it
we do not contain any glues or adhesives
of any type it's all water clean up
water washable one-time application
lasts the life of the tire and we do not
contain any organic fibers in there at
all that will break down over time well
so my experience I guess with the other
products though is that it's if you get
a leak and you're tired then you're
going to use that and fill it up whereas
multi-seal is meant to be more
preventative correct it's a preventative
sealant to be put in ahead of time to
help save the customer farmer trucker
whatever downtime so for me what I'm
looking for is a product that that saves
that annoyance that comes up years ago
Chris was doing a delivery for me
brand new trailer tires nonetheless and
he had a flat on the side of the road
you know we've been out to our other
property you drive a half hour out there
you want to hop on your tractor and get
work done and you see a flat tire right
there we've had them on our Gator you
know the tractors and the trailers all
zero turns everything has had flat tires
so the point is you don't want to have
that frustration that anger that you
can't get your job done so you get this
kind of product installed ahead of time
okay so Rick so I'm looking at this tire
just seeing all these holes and and I
guess just air pressure in general is
kind of on my mind I mean how does this
relate to air pressure and how does that
work it's a great question a multi-seal
remains a liquid the entire life of the
tire and by doing that It Coats the
inside of the tire like an inner liner
it'll minimize air loss by the porosity
the rubber uh bead leaks and valve stem
leaks keep the tire running the correct
air pressure at all times a properly
inflated Tire deflects more objects than
it receives so the tire will perform
better like ninja is designed to perform
and they'll get less Flats when a
properly inflated tire so do you have to
worry about this product freezing at all
no we've got our product rated at 35 to
40 below zero fahrenheit okay not around
here at least
okay so a question I had when we first
started talking probably the first
discussion was is this something that I
can install myself or do we have to make
a special trip to a tire shop to get it
done no certainly we do have a lot of
tire service providers that are dealers
for us but no an end user consumer can
install this it's real easy to install
just right to the valve stem with the
different tools that we have provided
for you all right so I think it's time
take us through what we have here I know
you've told me a little bit already but
I want to go through it again so let us
know what products are we looking at
sure start out with closest to you is
the flat out that will seal up to a half
inch puncture okay once again all
synthetic fibers water cleanup no glue
no adhesives can be installed right
through the bottle right through the
valve cap there's a hose that pops out
installation is real easy okay and so
again this retail version includes
what you need to hook up to your tire
yes and start it into your tire yes
there's an easy dispensing cap at the
top it pulls straight out because the
valve core newer built in there remove
the valve core stick the tigon tubing
hosing on your valve stem and squeeze
the amount required for a specific Tire
okay so nothing else required all in one
kit right here and good for something
like a set of boat trailer tires or one
ATV tire okay one ATV tire so and you
said something who who keeps this in all
their kits the US military Special
Forces that's pretty cool I think that's
a sign that this is a a pretty good
product here then we have our Pro HD
2500 which is what you consider a
Workhorse majority of our sales for
pneumatic tires use that product that'll
seal up to three quarter inch puncture
available anything from a one gallon
clear up to 275 gallon tote the one
gallon uses a one ounce pump dispenser
that screws into the top the five
gallons use a five gallon hand pump to
install our product move on to the hydro
1500 Hydro 1500 is made for any liquid
ballast Tire what about rim guard yes
rim guard is one of our
partners we use the product with it
mixes it a 1 to 10 ratio regardless of
what kind of ballast you're using adding
from calcium chloride to water to
windshield washer fluid and rim guard
okay hey real quick on this so this this
version here the hydro 1500
for liquid ballast all right like rim
guard Channel sponsor thank you but
can it be installed only at the time
does it have to be mixed in with the
water when you're installing it or can
you already have liquid ballast in your
tire and installed this after the fact
the answer is yes to both you can okay
mix it right before you install it not
not way ahead of time but immediately
before you install it you can mix it or
your tire is out there already has
existing ballast in it you move your
valve stream to 12 o'clock install the
product and it'll mix automatically with
the product our 3500 is our true
industrial heavy duty sealant it'll do
up to an inch and a quarter puncture in
a high ply tire to go over it again the
hydro 1500 will seal up to a half inch
puncture the Pro HD 2500 three-quarter
inch puncture and the armor 3500
into their quarter puncture all right so
there's really not a whole lot of math
that goes into this because multi-seal
takes care of that for you but let's
take you through some real world
examples here so you can figure out
exactly what you need for your tractor
so Rick we went and took a look at that
Summit tractor we have back there we
kind of used that one as the initial
example we have the tire sizes on the
front and the back it's two different
products right we have rim guard and the
rear tires so you only use the hydro 15.
this there's no other products that work
with the rim guard or liquid ballast
it's just the hydro 1500 yes and then
you have a separate product for the
pneumatic tires up front correct the Pro
HD 2500 is from pneumatic tire okay so
we had uh 12-16 and a half tires on the
rear of that Summit tractor filled with
rim guard
about 30 gallons total of rim guard
between the two tires it's a one to ten
ratio so we need three gallons of hydro
1500 okay so that takes care of the rear
tires three gallons of the hydro 1500
the fronts
over the 23 and a half 23. I forgot but
uh the fronts are 23 8 and a half 12
tires and we looked up on the chart
there those take 52 ounces per tire okay
so we have a 104 ounces that we need so
a little bit under a gallon yes to take
care of the front tires correct and for
that we would use well actually we could
use this right here a gallon of the Pro
HD 2500 right yes we take care of those
two front tires okay all right so that
takes care of the product that we need
now tell us about the pump motor Shield
makes three different or provides you
three different hand pumps that can be
used in our five gallon pails on all
three of our pumps every full stroke on
the pump is eight ounces so you just go
to your app tell you how many ounces it
is divided by eight that's how many
strokes you'd put in each wheel position
the one gallon bottle of our product has
a pump available for it for a separate
charge but if you already have your five
gallon hand pump on one of our three
products you can literally take this
gallon bottle and pour it in the five
gallon pail and pump out of that it'll
be a lot easier for you multi sale also
can provide you a injection cart pump
that's ran off your air system that has
a 15 gallon Hopper with two graduated
cylinders down below that you can
install your product using your air
system it makes installation quick for
larger fleets so Rick what can this
product be used in our product can be
used in anything
off-road regardless of air pressure size
or weight
over the road three-quarter ton trucks
and above multi-seal does not recommend
the use of our product in any Passenger
cars or light duty Vehicles due to the
TPMS systems okay so basically I can use
this for anything here I have in my
Homestead besides my truck my
four-wheeler my tractors
my trailers
my Zero Turns
all that stuff yes correct very good
okay so we use our calculator really
easy to do on the Polaris Ranger you
just measure the height and the width of
the tires and it tells you what you need
so we needed 150 total ounces for the
rear tires and then 126 ounces for the
fronts oh man
276 ounces I think however however that
comes out in gallons what is that a
little up two and a half about two and a
half gallons yeah yeah okay so a little
over two and a half gallons for this
again that's all pneumatic so we would
use the 2500 or the 3500 in here 2500
2500 is the right application for this
okay okay our Kubota M4 71 700
horsepower tractor eat about six gallons
per tire of hydroseal of hydroseal so
the 2500 1500 oh sorry yeah there we go
the 1500 here we have rim guard inside
here okay so 1500 goes in these and then
on the fronts the Pro HD 2500 yep 152
ounces per tire yeah 300 ounces total
300 ounces there okay so yeah this
starts to add up a little bit when you
get the bigger machines out yeah okay on
the 1025 this could be a Kubota BX
anything similar you know they're all
these sub compacts they're all basically
the same size give you an idea at least
so uh we have rim guard and the rears on
here one gallon of product per tire yeah
two gallons total of the 1500 the hydro
1500 to mix in with that on the fronts
combined it was a half gallon of the
2500 needed so you can get a gallon jug
of it and it's got an indefinite shelf
life right correct okay so it's not
going to go bad and keep it on there for
a couple years whatever else okay very
good okay so a trailer this is a
different application anything that's
high speed over 45 correct okay is a
different application so you don't need
to use as much of the material so one
gallon of the 2500 is going to to take
care of all four of these tires and in
fact this is the same trailer that Chris
had that flat tire on years ago I think
I had two other flat tires on here I
ended up replacing all four of these
tires down the road just because
but anyway one gallon that's all it
takes to take care of all four of these
tires pretty cool all right Rick so this
has been a lot of fun something I just
actually noticed I love it when I can
see this this seal right here made in
the USA that's awesome we try to get as
many made in the USA products on this
channel as we possibly can but what else
should we know about multi-seal the
multi-seal's been around since 1981
family-owned company I've built a
company 24 years our motto is seeing is
believing so folks I have been looking
for a way to fill the holes
in my equipment offering so to speak so
I'm really proud to start working with
multi-sealed so if you are interested in
placing an order head on over to
multi-seal's website there's going to be
a link down below and a link on our
website that'll take you right there if
you don't know where to go you're going
to enter code GWT to save five percent
off of your order and they'll pack it up
and ship it right to you so Rick a big
thank you for coming by my pleasure I
mean he's spending his whole day this is
like a four and a half hour drive to get
out here just to hang out with us and
show us what this product's all about so
I really appreciate that so again if
you're looking for this product go to
goodworkstrractors.com or of course we
sell tractor attachments all over the
country if you enjoyed today's video
we'd love to have you tag along hit that
subscribe button right down below I want
to thank you for taking time out of your
day to stop by and until next time stay
safe we'll see you soon
[Applause]
[Music]