hi everybody it's Jim from cornbread
hemp talking to you about part of our
organic farming practices here on our
organic farm in Central kentucky a lot
of people ask what makes organic
certified organic CBD better than
conventional CBD products and part of
that is about our organic farming
practices and one of those commitments
is that we don't use any pesticides ever
in any of these fields and that includes
natural insect control and that's
bringing in insects along the food chain
that are carnivorous to the potential
pests of these hemp plants ladybugs and
praying mantises we import thousands of
them into this field to control the
insects that might attach themselves to
these plants so from Farm to label
cornbread hemp is certified organic and
that's a huge part of our commitment to
Quality for you I'm Jim from cornbread
hemp nice talking to you