wear Extra Protection when mixing and
loading pesticides use an apron over
your protective equipment you need to
wear protective eyewear too carefully
open paper and cardboard pesticide
containers if you rip them open dust can
fly out and get on your skin and into
your eyes your mouth and lungs instead
put the pesticide container on a low
flat surface use a sharp knife or
scissors then wash the knife or scissors
with soap and water before using them
again and use them only for opening
pesticide
containers follow the label directions
to find out how much pesticide you need
and then measure it
carefully pour liquids carefully to
avoid splashes be sure your face and
eyes are well above the container while
you are pouring