uh welcome to the first beef and lamb
new zealand north canterbury farming for
profit event for 2021 really cool to
have a few of you along uh i'm your new
facilitator for the program sarah
o'connell and i'm now working at the
agri-business group
based in lincoln where my main role is
facilitation
so tonight's webinar it's all on working
dogs
um and we have got with us
laurie linning who is a vet through vet
life
in alexandra and she has been involved
heavily
in the teammate program um
right from its get-go almost which was
way back in 2003
the teammate program is a combination
and a team a team work project really
through
massey university and the working dog
center at massey university
and vet life but um laurie will go into
that in a little bit more detail she's
been the lead
veterinarian for the program since the
very
beginning of it so she's got plenty of
information to share with us
on the topics that we've worked on this
evening
so we're going to look into general
health
such as housing and vaccinating and
worming
feeding dogs so looking at what's the
best
type of feed to feed your dog is the dog
that you've
got does it need specific feed for the
kind of work that it's doing
and so on and then what are some of the
ins and outs around buying a dog
so laura's going to share her knowledge
wisdom and insights
around all of that information for the
evening
so um i've just seen a few additional
people
have jumped onto the call since we first
started so welcome everybody
um just a quick reminder keep your lines
muted
if you have questions pop them into the
chat box function
um and we'll get those answered as we go
through so time to crack into a wee bit
of content
now so i'm going to hand over to laurie
and laura you can introduce yourself
uh introduce their teammate project a
weebit
and then we'll get into our content
topics um
or starting with uh general dog health
yeah good evening everybody my name is
laurie lenny and i'm a veterinarian in
alexandria i've originally from canada
i've been
in new zealand for over over 30 years
and one of my biggest passions certainly
is
working dogs i was a large animal vet
for quite a few years before i
ended up being um i became a
really really interested in orthopedic
surgery so with that comes lameness
and all sorts of activities that involve
our working dogs so
from that we decided to look at
um setting up a program give us a little
bit more information of the
general health and what exactly was
going on with our working dogs because
if you look
at the information that we have
available to us
on the general husbandry and management
of new zealand working dogs
it amounts to about one small box in a
warehouse
so we decided to set up a
basically a five to six year program
that was
um looking at just about everything we
could with working dogs right from
feeding vaccination worming
um what they were fed how they were
housed
what kind of animals they worked with
how many how many stock interactions
they would have
so basically we did full on recording
for
six rounds so those animals were
hands-on examined by a veterinarian um
six times over the course of those years
um about four years from 2014 to 2018
and we ran an embedded parasite study as
well as
we used hay rex monitors for about 18
months
and recorded some information there now
there's been a lot of
information come out of it there's still
an awful lot more to come
um so it's pretty exciting it doesn't
seem like it's
um earth shadowing for some of the for
some people but
um it's going to be referred to as a
baseline project for
for many years to come so um
without further ado we might head into
the first topic which is basic general
health
um so the working dog project was
126 owners involving about 640 dogs we
sort of had in our heads we were going
to look at about
300 but it soon morphed into something a
bit larger so
it was pretty interesting so
um part of our big things with germa
health is
vaccination so the core vaccinations
that we would look at
are the vaccinations that we have
available to us for
dogs the core vaccine which is
parvovirus
december adeno2 virus or endovirus ii
which
is hepatitis and there is one also that
um is involved in one of the viral types
of kennel cough
and and para influenza which is also a
respiratory virus
kennel cough vaccinations which usually
are either entering a nasal or
subcutaneous injection are mostly
for the bacterial component of kennel
cough and that's bordetella
bronchosceptica
we're currently um in most of our
regions are undergoing
or experiencing an outbreak of kennel
cough
right from christchurch south um
with there is i'm sure there's a world
further north from that we don't pay
that much attention to it
but uh certainly in the southern part of
the south island we're certainly
experiencing lots and lots of kennel
cough both in pet
and working dogs
um the last one on that list is
leptospirosis we don't tend to worry
about it too much in the south island
because it
um doesn't tend to be much of a clinical
issue
that does become an issue if your
animals go to the north island
and require vaccination for that
so general recommendations well best
practice recommendations would be
that you vaccinate for with the core
vaccine
and your big big one is parvovirus i'm
sure that everybody knows
about parvovirus that causes hemorrhagic
diarrhea
in puppies and can have quite a high
mortality rate um very infectious and
lasts a long time in the environment
now that those core vaccines they should
be started
at between six to eight weeks and be
vaccinated
every four weeks until over 12 to 16
weeks
and depending on what type of
which vaccine you're using and what the
recommendations are
the current world small animal
veterinary association
recommends that your last vaccine be
after 16 weeks of age
to get over any residual maternal
immunity that
some um puppies might have that means
that
that immunity that they get from the
colostrum will interfere with their
ability to mount an immune response and
they do recommend
um that their last happy vaccination be
after 16 months
so after they have their set of puppy
vaccinations they are usually vaccinated
again at six to twelve months and then
as an adult
every three years as far as kennel
cough goes that's um generally
you can start whenever you like it only
takes three days for intranasal
and um 14 days after two
injections to mount an immune response
but those need to be boosted
annually as does leptospirosis
so those are the best practice
recommendation in the real world
well that doesn't tend to happen that
much
uh through our study we found 45
of dogs were vaccinated only as puppies
so they had their
course of puppy vaccinations and then
they were vaccinated i
never vaccinated again after that and
another 12
were never vaccinated and then the
remaining
um 40 odd percent were
um had some or variable
types of vaccinations and um
different vaccination intervals but
working dogs are a little bit of a
different
situation compared to pet dogs in that
they're usually
living in fairly um you know
areas that are far away from big
populations of dogs so they don't tend
to come in contact with a huge number of
dogs except in a certain situation say
of the shepherd who may move from
property to property those dogs in
particular are more likely to spread
disease than the ones that live on the
same farm for their entire lives
um i think where we probably have to be
very careful with those puppy
vaccinations
primal vaccination um is the one that
probably caused the greatest
incidence of disease in our working dogs
and certainly uh that's a very good
vaccine it has
a really good protection against the
disease
and so usually if they have one to two
vaccinations with carbo virus
vaccination they if they do come down
with the disease it's usually a mild
form
and certainly is often protective for a
very long period of time
um how long exactly those vaccinations
are protective for while the drug
companies you
as adults give you every three years and
they don't have
um haven't gone beyond that to get the
data
um to prove how long those vaccinations
last
uh simply because it's a money related
issue
now the other thing i guess you can do
or that is being done overseas is that
people are
doing um titans anybody titles to see if
their dogs need to be vaccinated
in new zealand that's cost um really
cost prohibitive
it's just cheaper to vaccinate than i
suppose um but certainly there are
people who
don't want to vaccinate any more than
they absolutely have to and that um
that can be offered but so for your
general
working dog don't please don't miss
those core vaccines as puppies
um it's a way way easier
thing to do to prevent the parvovirus
than it is to treat it
certainly a hang of a lot less expensive
um
certainly distemper and hepatitis we
don't see too much of any more there is
a little bit tinkering around but
the amount of evidence that's in the
population isn't really
that significant
um back from that we go to worming of
pups and adults now this probably seems
pretty pedestrian to a lot of people but
it's amazing
the variation in um
husbandry that we found with worming um
through a lot of people you know we
would ask people
generally you know do you worm your dogs
yes we were my dogs and
it was every combination of how often
and when
and certainly the sheep measles um
treatments
were something that really amazed me oh
measles has been around for
years and years and years and you think
that everybody sort of
would know how to sort that one out but
but indeed um a lot of people just
weren't aware of of how often
and when you should be treating for that
so starting out with pops
pups should be wormed starting at two
weeks of age
um you know it's heartbreaking to to
have a puppy brought in
for a post-mortem and have it full of um
for the worms that have a gut rupture or
obstruction
simply due to the fact that it's got
massive
aspirin loads or
blood out due to footworm infection so
again something that's
that's pretty easy to prevent um
certainly in the the parasite trials
that we
did run we we did found that they've
um that the couple of wormers that are
commonly used
in dogs um don't tend to look like
they're causing
um resistance still effective and um
you know not an issue to continue on
with what we have so those pups
start at two weeks of age and then um
continue on every two weeks until
they're 12 weeks of age as they get a
little bit older they do develop some
immunity and certainly have much less
reinfection rate
um as at after 12 weeks we go every once
a month
until they're six months of age and then
as a as an
adult we'll talk about down to that down
below
um certainly use a broad spectrum warmer
make sure you're using something that
treats
the biggest thing in puppies is round
worms astrid's
um as they get older tapeworms are
are more important but um certainly use
a broad spectrum warmer in those puppies
um as far as your adults goes there are
two trains of thoughts there some people
treat for shape measles and some people
don't
if your dog never has opportunity to
um come in contact with either untreated
offer or mate
then there probably isn't a huge
infection rate and those people believe
that
um because of those the way they
manage their fee that they don't need
that uh we
i still come across dogs that have
tapeworms
um every now and then so i think still
an important issue
so as an adult if you're not going to
worry about sheep nasals then
for their own health they should be
warmed once every three months with a
broad spectrum
warmer that's to get both roundworms and
tapeworms
most people still use still treat for
sheep nasals and sheep measles needs to
be treated
every 30 days that's the the length of
time it takes for infection
so um basically you're looking to treat
once a month
with a tape warmer and every
third month with a broad spectrum warmer
to get you back into those
um roundworm treatment for the animal's
health
so again if you look down below there it
says month one use a broad spectrum
warmer and then the two months in
between you just need to use a tapeworm
they're tapeworm medication by itself is
much less
expensive um and certainly an easier way
to go
financially than treating with broad
spectrum warmers all the time
um part three of general health i guess
we're going to talk about housing and
that was
that was an interesting thing that we
that we got to look at
lots and lots of kennels um there was a
lot
you know a big variation of materials
and types of kennels
um some people are are getting pretty
swish as far as what they're getting
into with
heated insulated kennels in some aspects
in central attack where we can get
off the cold in the winter time down
into the to the
um you know low 15s and 20s
and it's um staying cool for those guys
out there with
without much protection so basically
your housing
will affect the energy requirement and
quality and quantity of sleep that your
dogs are getting in at night
um and so that affects how much you need
to feed them
and also affects how
much recovery your dog's going to get
overnight
and how tired they're going to be the
next day and i guess i always
i don't think it's a big jump to believe
that um you know a dog like a person if
you get a poor night's sleep then you're
going to be more likely
to be not paying attention at work and
cause yourself injury
during the day um so i guess the things
that we maybe need to think about
are um shelter and position of kennels
so putting them in a place where they
can get some sunshine on them in the day
take them up
and out of the wind if at all possible
and certainly in some places
um in central otago it's pretty tough
because the wind comes from several
different directions certainly in
canterbury we know that to be a fact
but there are ways and means of
providing them
wind protection especially in the
wintertime when the winds are really
really cold
being some people would
put carpet that they wrapped around the
outside of the kennels
so it broke the wind and that made a
huge difference to the
the warmth of the kennels themselves um
removable doors or flaps so the dogs
could go in and they
had a chance to let their own body heat
kennels up especially if they were
uh insulated doesn't take an awful lot
to keep them comfortable um
bedding there was um about 44
of the people that we we canvassed used
some
type of bathing and that varied from
um straw to sex
stuff with wool or straw
actual um burlap beds that
that are pretty popular nowadays to to
proper bedding
carpet in the bottom um and you will
always come across dogs that
their very favorite thing to do is to as
soon as you put that bidding in they
like to
tear it all out and those dogs become
can become a bit of a problem i did come
across
one fella locally and he just kept
trying different
options until he found something that
they that they would leave
and most dogs um he said he could get
them to figure out that actually they
were better off with betting them
without
uh but he did have one dog in particular
that there was no way
that he could keep betting in his kennel
and sometimes you know you might leave
it for a week and then have a tanty and
then throw his toys out of the cough and
have no bedding is killing it again
um insulation is starting to be more
common there's about 14
of people that look at insulating their
kennels
be it using bats or
styrofoam especially under the floor
that's where we tend to get a lot of
grease coming through may have
nice tin walls but those floors are
always flattered and they tend to let an
awful lot of cold air up and in through
the
with the dogs actually sitting um
and then we look at coats and there was
24 of our people that used coats and
probably
quite a few more people used coats by
the time we were finished than
than when we started um they were only
just beginning to sort of becoming
involved
around about you know early to 2010
and certainly becoming more and more
popular again you do come across some
animals that
especially puppies that are quite happy
to take their quotes off
but the more common story we hear is
that
the dogs line up to have their coats on
it at night when they hold them open
they run in and you know they run
straight into the yolk of them
to be strapped in for the night so
there's a lot of people that are using a
lot more people now using coats
than they did before now we have had one
question
come in and i came up with the question
myself
um so does drontel cover sheep
measles yes it does so brontells um
got protection against both round worms
and tape rooms
so dronta will do that's your one that's
the broad spectrum warmer the one that
you would marry up with that in the
months in between would be drum set
which is just tape remember by itself or
there's
uh variable ones available out there now
um called t you know they've your
veterinarians will help you guide
through those they've all stopped
different ones we tend to
i think there's there used to be an
anchor tape warmer there's another
it's just called tape warmer but that
that tends to
to cover what you want so drawn tall is
a broad spectrum drawn foot is tape
warmer only
cold thanks laurie uh so the question
that i
had was also in relation to to worms and
it was worms and puppies
and my query was kind of around where
did those puppies
get those worms from so
rounds are pretty clever um if you want
to if you want to reinfect a puppy then
the most sensible thing to do would be
have your
uh larva sitting on the teeth and that's
exactly what happens
so the eggs pass in the mother's feces
and those larvae
get um sit around the teeth puppies
latch on
and that's how they become infected they
can't have direct fecal
contamination but generally that's
that's where their
um their infection comes from and
so certainly that are worming your
mothers very very important that
you know in the just the weeks up to
leading up to when your is going
to have puppies
that you should be wearing her to help
decrease that warm burden that she might
have
uh another question that has come in um
what do you recommend to use for pups
yeah so um round rooms are your are your
big concerns
so you just make sure that you've got a
product that's
that's going to cover that um there used
to be some lovely
suspensions that we don't have available
to us anymore
you can make suspensions or get them
made
for you by by crushing tablets up and
um injecting them you know just
instringing
them into their mouths and you just got
to be careful the doses that you're
using
based on the kilogram of coffee that
you're you're treating
because getting a getting a worm tablet
down a puppy of two weeks of age ain't
that easy
cool so how do you know you've got the
right dose
uh that'll be that's basically um most
worm tablets are
are based on a on a per kilo basis
so you weigh your puppies and goes to
your heaviest puppy
and you know if you're having
trouble figuring out your amounts if if
you're thinking of making a suspension
make sure you talk to your battle sorted
out for you it's not a problem like we
make up
um you know we'll crush a 10 kilogram
tablet and and suspend it in 10 mls of
water so it's
one mil per 10 per um kg so if you've
got a
puppy that weighs 500 grams and you give
them half a mil
so there's those ways but please if
you're
not really happy with your math get
someone to help you out with that thank
you lori
really awesome um you did a fantastic
job
and uh awesome amount of knowledge that
you've got
all right thank you thanks very much