[Laughter]
[Music]
yeah he's five years old and he is a
meat
you know
guys how we doing welcome to good works
tractors today we are at the butterfly
girl
photography place right the farm so we
have a
lot of projects to tackle out here we
have a berm that we have to move all the
dirt
the sand out yeah okay okay everything
away from the house we got to take and
put it out behind the barn
then we got to tackle some bushes good
chance to use the stump wrecker
now the biggest challenge might be what
you see right here i'm going to do
something i haven't done before i saw it
before on youtube
i think it was hometown acres used his
box blade to rip up and cultivate and
prepare for a garden so we're going to
give that a shot here
i don't have any tillers to use right
now so we're going to see what happens
it's springtime the garden's got to get
planted
now in some ways i am risking my life
today there are honeybees out here
there's a killer rooster there's even
coyotes roaming in the woods
but we're gonna get the project done one
way or another this could be a two-part
series so make sure you stick around
guys i'm proud to be sponsored by borah
wheel spacers today is the first real
opportunity in the field to try them out
and see how they help with the stability
we're gonna give it a shot if you're
looking for a stability solution for
your tractor make sure you check out
borah wheel spacers
order direct from them they make them
from one inch to six inches wide
aluminum steel a lot of options for you
made in america too and if you like what
you see here i'd love to get a thumbs up
from you
hit that subscribe button right
underneath the video and if you're
looking for cool tractor stuff
read through that description underneath
the video or head on over to
goodworkstractors.com
[Music]
[Applause]
okay so first thing we're going to do is
tackle these small garden strips here we
have one more over that way as well
i don't have a tiller like i said so i'm
gonna really pitch this box blade
tilt it forward by shortening the top
link and i'm gonna lower down those
ripper teeth as far as they go
i don't want to use the blade on the
back of the box plate at all i just want
these teeth to dig down
and scrape and cultivate the ground to
prepare for planting i found this on a
forum somewhere i know you guys have
done it before
my first time adding some weights right
to the box blade
i have 70 pound weights hanging on the
inside four of them so it adds an extra
280 pounds
these smaller box blades don't weigh all
that much so i wanted to have some
additional weight we have about 70
pounds with the spiko we have the loaded
tires too so
this should be pretty solid then when
i'm using that front end loader but this
is going to be a good project for you
guys you're going to see this box blade
in action
we're going to use the heavy hitch tooth
bar as well going to use the brush
crusher after we dig
out some shrubs up by the landscaping
that we're going to be ripping out
and of course we're going to use that
stump bucket too
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
so
[Music]
all right guys i am going into the
danger zone you can see that beehive way
back there
i got a till with this thing right
around it so
fortunately we had a a full body suit
here
so there was an actual honeybee inside
here when i put
put it on though so hopefully that's the
only one but here we go
[Music]
so
[Laughter]
my
[Music]
so
so we just got done tilling all three
areas with the box blade mainly
you know with the scarifier teeth the
shanks that we had all the way down
i won't say it was ideal you can't get
super deep you know part of the
challenge with a small tractor it's very
light so
i have a four foot box plate on here
it's a good reason why you would not
want to have
a five foot in my opinion because when
these shanks are all the way down
you can see that the wheels just sitting
there spinning it doesn't have enough
weight to get enough traction to be able
to pull
anything further so constantly had to
raise up and try to feather it and
you're going over an uneven surface and
so the box blade is
reacting to whatever all four tires are
doing and so it's kind of bouncing
around so it's definitely not ideal
but if you need to do something in a
pinch i think the results are plenty
good
to go ahead and plant with what you have
out here but overall i still prefer a
[Music]
[Applause]
tiller
[Music]
so
okay so didn't think about bringing a
chainsaw or hedge trimmers
so we're going to try to tackle this
without first asking our customer
to see if we can borrow a chainsaw from
them i could always head back home and
grab one but
i figure what the heck we're right here
we're gonna give it a shot we're gonna
see if we can knock these out
without going that route
[Music]
[Applause]
now
[Music]
so number one it'd be a good idea to cut
these down just to prevent
branches from whacking the house we've
been lucky so far but
that's the first thing i would say about
ripping up the shrubs near the house
number two you gotta be able to attack
it from other angles so i might have to
get this bush out
to get the banks out of this one there's
a couple big rooks back here
these front couple were easy but this
one's kind of buried underneath that
timber
and a lot more soil back here without a
good way to get to it
proving a little more difficult
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
for those of you not familiar with the
brush crusher grapple this is the only
type of grapple you can get that doesn't
require any additional connections
besides just hooking it up to your front
end loader so there's no hydraulics
no electric that's required you just put
it on and you get to work
so then you may be wondering how does
this system work without any third
function hydraulics
i'm going to show you right now so pay
attention to this stop
right here that's on the back side or
the bottom side of the loader arm i'm
going to lift up on this bottom jaw
just to illustrate this point so when i
lift up
on it you can see it's not touching
there so that stop
is going to prevent any further motion
of the bottom jaw so this is essentially
where that bottom jaw is going to live
you'll see there are some different
positions so you can tweak
the angle or the you know the the
levelness of the bottom jaw
this top jaw is going to be controlled
opening and closing
by your curl roll function on your front
end loader so if you're going to dump
out a bucket full of dirt or scoop up a
bucket
this is going to be that same function
that controls the open and close of the
grapple this is going to be the model
bc4215 it's for the john deere quick
attach
there's also the model bc 4200 which is
not going to have
the center teeth there's going to be a
heavier duty bc 4255
not gonna have the center teeth but
built a little beefier for the larger
compact tractor
those three are all for the john deere
quick attach there is going to be
another version the bc
4300 for anybody that has a skid steer
quick attach it's going to be gray in
color
doesn't have the middle teeth again it's
built a little beefier similar to that
bc
4255 it gets confusing i know but all
the information is on my website good
works tractors
we can ship these all over the country
we do it all the time but if you have a
skid steer quick attach
on kubota mahindra coyote ls the list
goes on
look for that bc 4300 so you'll see i do
have those third function hydraulics
right up front i want to
give you guys examples of all sorts of
equipment in action so
just pointing this out that i don't have
anything hooked up here that's the
beauty of the brush crusher is
90 or more of folks don't have these
additional hydraulics so you get into a
grapple functionality without the
additional cost of the hydraulics or
electrical connections or anything else
however if you're dead set on getting
some additional functionality on your
tractor
i'd encourage you to watch our videos on
the summit hydraulic solutions both the
diverter kit for the front end
the hydraulic multiplier for the back
end the best part is you go to summit
hydraulics you order from them
you use code gwt and you're gonna save
five percent off your order
[Music]
so
you
[Applause]
[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
do
[Applause]
now
all righty guys we are wrapping it up
for today day one we gotta
we got all sorts of stuff done i should
say with the three-point hitch have the
box blade on here
a lot of stuff on the front we had three
different attachments on the front today
the brush crusher
the regular bucket here with the heavy
hitch and our stunt bucket as well so
you can see
all sorts of different applications for
these products make sure you stick
around you're going to want to get a
tour
of all the wildlife all the farm animals
that are out here we're going to finish
up moving those berms
get all this dirt piled up out here get
some more spread out in front of the
barn as well
my job was no longer there
everybody wants out
sister found this place she lives on the
next road
okay and she's like i found it i found
the perfect place when i walked back and
i saw the barn and i saw the property
and
no animals had lived in this field for i
don't know how long but it was like lush
and pristine there was no dirt it was
all grass
the barn was perfect and i was like this
is for my horse
i wouldn't want to live anywhere else
now like this is the perfect place and
then we just kind of
accumulated that alrighty guys we're
back out here day two
we were all here a couple days ago skip
today because of the rain back out
friday morning now to finish up you can
see we've got one section of the berm
moved already
gonna keep working our way around the
house just keep pile by pile taking it
back through a couple of fences back
there
have to have somebody man in the gate
just because all the animals want to get
in and out but
that's the destination for the dirt
we're gonna get to work
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
uh
all right you guys well the amount of
time i had available has expired we got
a lot of work done between the first day
and today i don't know six seven hours
worth of work and a couple different
periods
uh some gardens tilled up and worked up
for planting
got all these shrubs there were some
massive old shrubs that were standing
here that we got dug out
really quick with the stump bucket
timbers out with the tooth bar
you know these berms i'm not even sure
how many yards of dirt we moved but it
was a lot
so a lot of you are curious on how much
to charge for different jobs you know an
hourly rate maybe by a project
it is helpful if you can come out and
walk a project but for me that's not
really
an option i just don't have the time to
do it and with bids all over the place i
know a lot of you guys don't either so
you know i would typically charge
somewhere in the 120 to 150
an hour rate for something like this for
all
inclusive work so it's going to depend
on your geographic location as well the
amount of competition you have
the type of work you're doing so this
gives you a good idea though of the
different projects you can knock out
within a
short amount of time if you have the
right tools with you i have an important
question though because i told sheila
that i was going to charge her for this
job i was going to give her a discounted
rate because we're shooting video
but i have something that i really want
instead of cash money so
i have not asked for this yet we're
going to see what she says
all i want is just a little bit of that
honey after you get your
are you serious oh yeah after you get
your first uh first batch
will that work
i would love i love some fresh eggs too
yeah all right
see you guys know me i love food so if i
can get some food out of the deal
i'm feeling pretty good
yeah for sure all right well good there
you go guys the first batch
that's right so you can get your payment
in honey or eggs or other food as well
it's up to you it's totally optional
anyway thanks so much for stopping by if
you like what you see here i'd love to
get a thumbs up from you
hit that subscribe button right
underneath the video and read through
the description underneath the video as
well
or head over to goodworkstractors.com
thanks again for stopping by and until
next time stay safe we'll see you soon
so hey i have chicken i have
duck and then did you want wanna