jeremiah jones pioneer field agronomist
kelly robertson granular csa with
precision crop services
so kelly in your updates you talk about
goal so what is go gold g-o-a-l that
means get out and look get out of the
cab of the tractor the sprayer
get out the field
look at what your tillage tool is doing
look at what your planter is doing look
at your seed depth
you know all of those things don't rely
on all those monitors and fancy gadgets
we've got in the cab
uh or or looking you know six feet above
the ground from a glass bubble thinking
you know that everything's okay you need
to get out and look it also means get
out of the pickup
yeah so if you're driving by a field and
something doesn't look right stop the
pickup literally get out and walk across
the field yes
so planting depth i know
you know everybody's got the old timer
pocket knife they pull out and that's
how deep they plant or you know the old
knuckle method that's how we d deeply
plant or we use our digging tool about
our planting dev so what else can we do
about checking planting down so if you
want to look at your
your planting depth and you want to look
at sidewall compaction or how your row
units are doing typically what we use is
a is a measuring tool like this
and you get out here and you start
digging around well when you're doing
this
you're disturbing a lot of what has
happened
as a result of the planter or the
tillage tool going through the field so
you don't get a good idea of that so one
of the things we are going to use today
is just this leaf blower to just start
kind of blowing the loose soil off of
where the row unit went so that we can
look at the the job the row unit was
doing what the closing wheels were doing
and how the seeds placed in the seed
trench so
[Applause]
so here's an instance where we could see
several different things going on in the
in the row unit so right here you notice
after we blew the the this off that we
noticed this line here and that's where
his two by two uh nitrogen is going next
to the uh
next to the row
uh here we have the seed trench as you
can see
so we've got a little bit maybe just a
little bit of sidewall compaction but
notice it is loose for the most part it
didn't blow out with the
with the leaf blower but it is loose the
other thing that you can notice if you
look really closely as you can see where
the spike closing wheels
have ran
down through this unit so
overall we've got about a two
inch and a half two inch around two inch
planting depth
um
not seeing a whole lot of information
here or evidence that shows me that
we've got much if any compaction
happening
but i mean this is a good way to look at
what your role units are doing
and the conditions that you planted into
to determine what kind of compaction you
might have
that concludes this pioneer agronomy
video podcast visit our page on
pioneer.com and follow us on twitter and
facebook for more agronomy insights