hi I'm Melissa Sakura and BSU Extension
agent agriculture and natural resources
for sergeant cabbage today I'm going to
be preparing my garden for the growing
season with a few simple steps if you
haven't taken a soil sample in a few
years it's recommended that you do so so
you know you're available nutrient
levels in your soils and yes you
Extension has a video available that
walks you through the process of taking
a sample if you have questions once you
have your soil test results you'll be
able to determine if a fertilizer
application is needed or not
when preparing my garden I want to make
sure to remove any old plant materials
from the sterile surface removing these
plant materials will help reduce my
chances of spreading diseases that may
have overwintered when determining if my
garden soil is ready to be worked or not
I'm going to look at the soil moisture
about two to three inches deep so now
I'm going to take a sample look at the
moisture
the soil here is easily crumbling apart
then it's ready to be worked if it stays
in a ball and doesn't fall apart easily
you'll want to wait a few days for the
soil to dry out if you work your soil
when it's too wet it's going to form
clumps and it's gonna be really hard for
those seeds to germinate and establish
in that soil before working your soil
you may choose to add compost which will
help with nutrient and water holding if
your soil is ready to be worked you can
kill your garden to provide for a nice
seed bed perhaps you have a smaller gun
area or a raised bed and you can also
use your shovel and rig to provide a
nice seed bed to go many gardeners are
also choosing no-till as an option when
planning for my gardening season I want
to make sure I have enough space between
rows so I get until throughout the girl
named season to kill the weeds if needed
I also want to make sure I plant enough
space between my plants for them to have
adequate room to grow and I want to plan
for my crop rotations so I'm not
planting my tomatoes in the same spot
every year I like to use a garden
journal when planning for the season
that way I can plan my rotation my
available space and I can also make
notes in my journal throughout the
growing season and which varieties I
liked and didn't like and reference it
from here to here if you have any
questions about preparing and planning
your garden contact your local NDSU
Extension agent and they'd be happy to
help