good morning modern standards this
morning's video is going to be all about
starting our tomatoes and growing our
tomato plants in soil blocks in the
house we've been getting a ton of
specific questions about our growing
system and how we're doing it so I'm
excited I am encouraged to share how
many people are growing their own or
getting ready to start their own inside
that's very encouraging and exciting
we'll be eating BLTs with a lot of
modern stutters the summer so let's dive
in and let's talk a little bit more
about our Tomatoes and how we're growing
them there's been a lot of people making
comments about our lights being too low
they weren't lower but I was leaving
them low to let the little guys catch up
a few of them here and here yesterday I
raised the lights up believe it or not 2
to 3 inches and there was room between
the light and the plants and they have
grown immensely what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna raise our lights up to links
Believe It or Not yesterday and the
plants are already touching the lights
again mister Figueroa you're making too
much noise with the chickens over here
it's hard for us to hear the grow light
that we're using here on these tomato
plants is a regular fluorescent shop
light setup with t12
grow light bulbs and over here we have
our LED strip lights I have not been
sitting my plants right away what I do
is I let them grow up a little bit and
when I find one plant that's better than
the other like this ones growing nice
and straight and the base on this one
doesn't look as nice so we're gonna get
rid of that one
over here it's kind of a 50/50 it's not
a lot healthier but it is I think by
pulling this one out now
that one's going to grow a lot faster
but I hate thinning I'm too soon just in
case one of the other doesn't make it
the grow light setup that we have is not
the most expensive setup it's just the
most affordable setup that I can find I
know that stronger lights out there but
I don't want to focus our plants on
growing up inside the grow lights are
just to give them a good start and that
way we can have a good healthy plant
started inside so I'm not gonna you can
go out and you can spend hundreds of
hundreds of dollars on good high-quality
lights if you want these are not them
these are strong enough lights to do the
job that we need them to do let's talk
transplanting these seed start we're not
gonna be putting these seed stocks
directly into our garden from these soil
blocks you can do either one or two
things last year we bought these bigger
pots on Amazon see if I can find the
link farm if I can I'll put them in our
store on Amazon then we put the soil
blocks in here and added more soil and
they had all this area to grow and our
plants wish I had pictures of them this
year I need to get better with taking
pictures of things and saving the
pictures I'm gonna say our plants were
is good 12 to 24 inches tall when I use
thick stalk the pots works good when we
took him out of the pots they were brute
bombs they could have believe it or not
used to have gone to a bigger pot so
this year what we're gonna do this
winter I made this large soil block
maker you want to watch that video see
how to make when you sell I'll put a
link for that video right here but what
we're gonna do is we're gonna transplant
our medium soil blocks into a larger
soil
that we're gonna be making but a lot of
people been asking how do you know when
your plants are ready to go into the
next size container a soil block so the
way I determine if my plants are ready
to go to the next soil block what's
these ones are believe it or not see all
these little root fibers that's all the
roots growing out of your soil block so
this is telling me all right the plant
has used up the space inside of this
soil block and it's time to go to the
next one the other really cool thing
about the soil blocks and seeing the
roots like this is now our plant is
ready to go to another soil block or go
to the garden and get directly planted
and whatever we're planting it in and
these roots are going to just keep
growing where if they're in a pot like
this the roots get stuck when they hit
the wall of the container they turn back
around and they get roof on they call if
you look it's almost like a ball they
get balled up and they'll grow into a
circle so the roots don't grow out
easier and when you that's what you have
sometimes you have the transplant shock
is the plants are in new soil but they
don't know hey my roots can grow they're
still bound up where the soil block let
ends come to the end and they grow out
and sometimes they'll grow into the
other soil block sometimes they'll just
grow into the tray but that's good so
when we go to transplant them they're
gonna have to be ready to take that new
soil on the new nutrients from the new
soil and they just grow amazingly I'm
gonna need to transplant our tomato
plants I'm not gonna do it in today's
video sometime this coming week we're
gonna be transplanting these and finally
being able to use the large soil block
maker so I'm excited for that so keep
your eye out for that video rather to
show you one other trick to encourage
your roots to grow down let's go over
here and I'll show you now this is one
of the reasons we use the plastic trays
without holes as we can flood the tray I
know you normally when I'm watering you
see me what
sprayer somewhere spraying the top of
them that's when they're small and when
they're just starting to turn into
plants once they get bigger if we flood
the tray Colton's flooded and I mean
flood the tray that water in a matter of
minutes
is gonna be Swick up by our soil blocks
you can see it's basically just in the
grooves when I flooded it there's about
a half inch of water in there same with
this one what that does is it makes the
soil blocks wick the water up from the
bottom so the pot that's gonna have the
most water is the bottom and that
encourages the plants roots to grow
deeper you want that for a few reasons
you want to have good deep roots and if
you're just missing the plant the water
staying up high mostly something's gonna
seep down low but the majority of the
water and the wetness is gonna be up
high so it's not going to encourage
those roots to grow them deep it's gonna
encourage surface roots which is it a
good thing especially if you garden with
a deep mulch back to eating garden you
want to encourage deep root growth and
there's few reasons for that one is it
makes a stronger plant the second is it
makes the roots grow down deeper it
encourages a better growing plant but
less watering and you don't want to
water your plants the more you water
your plants the more the roots are gonna
stay up high you might be watering your
plants May but might be looking good and
healthy but you're not encouraging the
roots to grow deep and the deeper the
roots go the more nutrients those plants
are gonna have because they go in deep
down to the soil going down to the
resources and pulling up what your soil
has down there for and then sucking it
up putting it into the fruit whatever
the pot is that you're gonna eat and
then in return giving us more nutrients
so if you do deep bedding back to eating
garden or just mulch your garden you're
gonna get that and you're not gonna need
to water your garden what's just amazing
so if you have a drought you don't have
to worry about it you might look at the
dirt and go oh it's dry but deep down
it's damp there's moisture down there
and your plants are gonna grow
so like starting our plants this way and
teaching the roots to grow down and
encouraging that from the beginning it
gives you a better plant and a better
garden and more nutrient-dense food it's
just amazing I'm gonna talk more
upcoming videos of how we're gonna plant
them but I'm gonna touch on it real
quick so I know there's a lot of people
that are in a growing zone that they can
be planning their garden sooner than we
are so two more things I want to touch
on before we end the video one is you
want to plant calcium in with your
Tomatoes when you plant them in the
garden so if you have a good source of
quality eggshells you can start saving
up your eggshells and baking them in the
oven to dry them out then you can put
some eggshells in each hole where you
plant them in your garden and they'll
have a good source of calcium while
they're growing you could also do
oysters shells that's another good one
so just be thinking about that how am I
gonna get calcium to my tomato plants if
you have tomato and rot or blight most
of the time that's due from an
insufficient source of calcium so if you
can start the whole off with calcium the
plant should have the calcium while
they're growing and then you'll have
less battles you're fighting throughout
the growing season the other thing you
bring you in close hopefully I can get
the camera to focus but you have these
little knobs on your tomato plants when
you plant your tomato plant you should
plant them so you bury the first Leafs
or right up to the first leaves all
those little nubs will grow roots and by
planting your tomato plants deeper in
the ground they're gonna have more roots
the plants gonna get stockier and harder
so the winds blowing it's not gonna blow
the tomato plant over I'm just gonna
make for a stronger plant right from
beginning
I hope the chicks haven't been too noisy
boy yeah in the video right over there
fingers crossed we'll be getting those
outside this coming week exciting times
here in the homestead come springtime
hope you enjoyed today's video
I didn't answer all of your questions
leave them in the comments down below
and we'll see you right back here
tomorrow at lawmakers a guy the modern
homesteading self-sufficiency and
freedom
[Music]