[Music]
swam prha digital India educated India
let us start uh this lecture with a
thought
process that all of we are here to learn
right learning is a
process and uh we should have love for
learning so I always feel that love for
learning lessons the labor pains of
learning today learning is a very
difficult process for all of you
right because you people are occupied
with several other things
and therefore it is very important you
should develop a love for it and and
learning is a part and parcel of human
life uh let us recall what we learned in
the last lecture we basically looked at
that why we need to go for uh
agriculture as a basis for our growth
right and why because uh you know like
we are having a naturally Endor with the
resources which are very
conducive and uh you know for the
agriculture or the farming and later on
we looked at like uh what are the
processes involved in
agriculture and how this modern
agriculture being implemented as of
now right and today we'll be looking at
what are the problems we are facing with
the modern farming and you know like uh
in 19 uh 50s or the 60s you know like we
are having Green Revolution people are
very much where Gaga about it and today
also some of the you know intellectuals
are very saying that we need to go for
second Green
Revolution is it really Revolution or
not that we'll see and I will I will put
forward or I'll show you uh some data to
it but let us before that let us look at
what the problem in the modern
agriculture we use more fertilizers and
more pesticide for
what because more fertilizers we give
the growth will be better and then you
know production of the crop will be
higher and more pesticide we have to
give because the pest are the are more
increasing at a
number because uh as a result that we
are more profit Maniac you know we are
want to have
more greedy greed greediness has come to
our mind too much right and there's a
whole world not only in India across
because of this is what you call
materialism like as I told earlier
Market materialism makes a man Maniac so
we became Maniac you know like for
profit man for grabbing all those things
are going on in our mind that is a what
we call uh Det of mind power to think
which is right which is wrong getting s
away so therefore that is the problem
and then it is thrust upon us and we are
just not thinking about what and paste
and diseases are part and parcel of
nature keep in mind that because one
person will be relying on other right
and they
balance and so also disease is the thing
to Decay and then you will be going so
this is the part of nature in ide
system Natural Balance between predators
and past are to be maintained so that
you know each are connected with each
other these are all philosophy what are
embedded in our uh you know uh
traditional knowledge system in our
ancient
wisdom and which we need to understand
basic things what we are talking about
here you need to understand the basic
laws of nature and then work accordingly
not going against and you know uh
imbalancing or doing something that
balance will be broken balance is
important because we cannot really look
at only small micromanagement the whole
big picture we need to look at it and
big picture are very order and then it
may be looking like a disorder but
actually as I told that our civilization
order in disorder and that is natural so
that has to be looked
at so chemical control that's why we
want to have a control over this
uh diseases and also the past so that
last 40 years you know insecti use have
increased
10-fold while the crop losses from the
past damage have double losses are
increasing and you are increasing that
also right insect so one has to look at
that why it is so and as a result the
safety of the
people 1 million cases of poisoning by
pesticide each year around the world and
up to uh 20,000 of these results in debt
this poisoning because of and this
number may be more I mean like you know
and dates occur in tropical countries
where chemical piz which are banned in
Europe and other Western countries like
USA are still being used in India right
I mean there are several examples I am
not going to look at it and you can see
your for example DDD and then some other
thing even Ura people are not but we are
using it here in this country so uh and
cost of farming increasing at alarming
rate and as a result food prices are
also being increased very much around
300% in last 10 years and if look at we
are having a people who are hands to
mouth living like hands to mouth
laborers and where they will get the
food because the food price are now is
comparable to the global global market
and earlier days food was very cheaper
in this country whenever I visit other
country I feel oh we are safe we are
having at least food a common person can
get today it is not because of
globalization and you know right and
problem with the industrial agricultural
practice I have already discussed me
just uh highlight some of the points
I'll be highlighting more again because
I want that some of the things will be
repeative in nature but keep in mind
these are important we need to
understand that then only we can take
characteristic as I told that
monocultures basically the single kind
of crop they use and that erods the
biodiversity among both plants and
animals it is not only with the plants
only because all are connected so
therefore that is
creating
and uh if you look at the nature is
always multi layer or you know various
things it's not heterogeneous it's not
homogeneous we trying to make it
homogeneous because in engineering we do
that you know but that is not that is a
wrong it is not easier to handle the
heten thing you make it homogeneous
therefore you say that no it nature is
other way around it is your limitation
that you are trying to push forward or
the you know thrust upon the people but
you must understand that nature is not
like that and there is a strength in
that synthetic chemical fertilizers are
being used
blatently which
pollute the soil not only the soil water
and air all whatever the environment we
are getting spoiled because of this
blatent use of chemical fertiles I'll be
showing how it is so and both
environment and although not only the
human health but also the animal health
plant Health all are being
connected so soil which is the soul
of infinite lives right and that is
getting uh spoiled you know much faster
than it can be
replen and taking with its land's
fertility the whatever the fertility
nutrients the land land the soil is
having it is going
away and which are very important this
fertility and nutrients are very
important for the growth of the plants
and those things we eat as a food but
those are been getting away you know
I'll be showing you later on like what
are the things and I'll also give you
data how this most of the civilization
got
extinguished got spoiled because of soil
quality is going down at that time we
need to keep that and maybe in the next
class I'll will show you some data and
water is consumed at unsustainable rates
in many agricultural areas because water
being used too much and it is also uh
helping to take away or leeching out the
what do you call this fertility and
nutrients which you are adding to the
soil artificially and also the natural
one all are going away so you know you
are using because of too much use of
water so effect of pesticides on
environment if you look at chemical P
can kill useful insects there's a lot of
you know microorganism insects are very
useful pollination for pollination we
need but they are not you know and if
pollination won't be there then you
can't have a food production you may
have very big plants but you don't have
now in Western country people are using
artificial pollination you know like why
you will do that and cost is in will be
increasing which at the past leading to
the imbalance in nature whole mother
nature is in imbalance you are cutting
the limbs of and you know fingers or you
know if look at a body my fingers are
being cut my you know hand being removed
from the mother nature you know Mother
Nature if you considered as a body that
is not the way so therefore you need to
look at it
and uh as I told earlier artificial
chemical can stay in environment in the
bodies for a number of years right even
if you won't use it will stay for in
your thing for Generation to generation
and you cannot really afford to do that
and causing problem for many years it is
not for your generation it is for the
next maybe 5 10 generation will have to
suffer because of you have used the
chemical fertilizers and which are not
good for the health so therefore we need
to understand insect past are very
quickly or over a fear of breeding
Cycles they become resistant to
artificial products they also try to
resist the thing and develop a hormones
and other things so that they can
because that is the nature nature is
intelligent you know they are working to
go suppose somebody will try to hit you
you will have to protect yourself right
find out ways and means use your mind
use your body use your resources use
your power to do that they are also
doing that way okay and are no longer
controlled by the label of chemicals
what we we were using earlier days I'll
be showing you some data as well so if
you look at fertilizer consumptions you
look at this in
1960s we are having fertilizer
consumption is very very low if you look
at this is the color orange color that
bound is very very low million tons
maybe you know like one or two million
tons and it is goes on increasing and so
also China and then we are because we
want to grow at a faster rate than the
other
people and that is the bigger problem
but if you look at America which is a
very intelligent people you know like
they have grown this a higher increase
from 1960 to maybe 80s they realize
these are not good and they are almost
remaining constant and sometimes going
negative and I do not know the data last
maybe 6 seven years
but I'm sure that they might have
decreased it so if you look at we need
to do that we'll have to cut off and
then the whole business you know they
are sending their multi company to here
to Swindle us and users and then spoiled
we will be intelligent and we should
understand this and then do that so uh
and if you look at we are as we are
using more fertilizers and more
pesticides and other things we are
spoiling also the groundw
I was told of course this may not be the
correct but you please check don't go by
any data I'm giving please correct it
check it and then accept it uh in some
newspaper this thing I learned that 60%
of groundw in China are not drinkable in
India you think about it my guess is
around maybe 20 to 25% of the at least
in kpur I know there is some area where
the water has gone ground water has gone
bad deadly bad
so therefore we need to and uh worry
about that because that sustains the
life and if we spoil the ground letter
and which are interconnected how we are
going to uh what you call correct it or
how we are going to um huh replenish how
you do that can you take it out by the
pump and again put it is it possible all
are connected you know like
interconnected right so how will uh you
know uh take care of that polluted water
so therefore we'll have to worry about
and if you look at the fertilizer
conception I know nitrogen is there is a
phosphatic type and potass potassic type
it is all are increasing know in 1991
where something 80 in lxs tons you know
this is in lcks of tons 80 LHS tons now
one in 2007 166 and today maybe it will
be something 175 or maybe 80 I do not
know okay okay you please look at it all
are increasing we should decrease it we
should at least stabilize it you know
because we know it is they are harmful
but still because our people are
illiterate and then so also the thing
and the people are using advertisement
and other thing to uh what you call Le
them for this for the more production
and more profit as a tool to em them you
know right lure them but all our we are
spoiling the health let us look at how
is the food production related to F
fertilizer consumptions right so uh if
you look at that this is I've taken the
data from 70 to 2002 it's a little old
data but let us look at the trend this
blue color is fertilizer consumption
rate it is going up sometimes in 75 it
is gone up above the red line that is
corresponding to the million terms of
food production and then if you look at
it is uh food production is lower down
at least 95 onwards and the fertilizer
consumption is
increasing and let me tell you last year
I had gone to some nearby Village in uh
kpur where people are you know and then
I inquired with the farmers I told what
are the consumption they're saying that
we are using almost double the
fertilizers what we are using 10 years
back for get getting the same you know
tonage for acre kind of air crop see
look at what we are doing that means the
soil fertility has gone down and you are
adding more and more and then it will be
spoiling right so therefore the farmer
committing suicide because the cost of
farming is increasing at an alarming
rate than the what price they can get in
in the you know uh what you call
Market as a result you know they are in
debt therefore government of India is
you know uh what you call uh um taking
away their dat in the sense giving the
what you call subsidies no not subsidy
it is M like loans waving waving of the
loans they waving of the loans but that
is not the solution solution has to be
found out looking at what are the causes
of it and then look at fundamentally and
solve the problem and there all of you
uh who are listening to these lectures
and then you'll have to come into
picture and educate them and also
educate the government about these wrong
policies of using these Concepts because
you know we are democracy we should do
that and uh the growth is I mean we are
all talking about Green revolutions and
other thing we want to have another
Green Revolution people are talking
about genetically modified crops and I'm
afraid one should not venture to that
of course there are several reason I'll
be not talking about why you need to but
you'll have to if you are interested get
into that and find it out yourself so
the growth rate of the crop production
let us look at what happened in our uh
the green reol let us look at that uh
this 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 in this diagram for
the wi we are talking about preg Green
Revolution something 1951 to
1968 we are having something 7 you know
is the tons of this so uh this I have
taken the data from the draft of 12 plan
document Delhi Planning Commission and
2013 right so let's say this is the
percentage you know what you were having
then it has been decreased in the Green
Revolution period 69 to 81 okay and then
it is again little bit increase up and
then going down and then down again this
thing then again people are increasing
because of in the seventh plan and that
is true with if you look at this point
you know for the rice for the wheat and
then pulses for oil seeds of course oil
seed has a little bit gone up I mean
corresponding to this 1951 and uh the in
the today kind today means 11 and
12 but uh wheat and rice and pulses you
know it is lower than that what it was
there in Pre this thing so therefore you
can judge from yourself and this data I
have taken from this thing that look
this is is a myth that we are having a
Green Revolution okay because the crop
we are putting lot of pesticide lot of
fertilizer and this thing but we are not
growing I of course there is a various
fluctuation depending upon your what we
call your uh climates and there
depending upon other parameters you know
that is there so one has to look at data
and analyze it and then only we can say
that look there is a green and beside
this we are paying price for the what
for this use of this chemicals
fertilizer pesticide spoiling soil air
and everything we'll be talking about
what are the problems of chemical
fertilizer let us understand
that and there is a
micronutrient imbalance because of
utilizing the chemical
fertilizers because we know that
chemical fertilizers contain nitrogen
phosphorus potassium which are
micronutrients these are the
micronutrients you know you can think of
and excess use of
fertilizers during the farming causes
micronutrient imbalance because the soil
you are giving artificial if we giving
artificial you know soil will be
imbalanced maybe you are adding more
than what is required so excess of
anything is bad right you need to know
that what are the things and there will
be also imbalance because of
root will be taking and then it will be
not taking all the thing it will be
remaining I'll be talking about later on
about you know like uh root how they
take and what will be the size of roots
if we use chemical fertilizer if you use
natural farming all those things I'll be
talking about a little bit later on
particularly when I'll go to the Natural
farming excess isop part affect the soil
fertility adversely and also the
productivity as I told just now that
which my own experience talking with the
farmers nearby the Cano area they're
saying they're using large number of you
know large amount of fertilizer for the
same amount of crop production in the
same land right over the years and that
is true that you can see I mean you can
ask anybody and you are having also data
nowadays internet you can get the data
and uh maybe from reliable source
because internet one has to be careful
about data right you can go to the
government sources some other things
then you can find it out what are the
conceptions you know I have shown you
already that so there is a nitrate
pollution like excess nitrogen
nitrogenous fertilizers Lee deep into
the soil because you are using a lot of
water also irrigation you know like and
there is a groundwater you are using
using the pump you know power right
electricity and then Diesel and the lift
irrigation system has now come up right
and you just press a button and then
water will be spread over this thing so
and it is sometimes I have seen at least
in the nearby kpur area that is they use
a lot of water unne and that can
contaminate the ground water also and
that is happening in lot of areas and
other water bodies nearby is being
spoiled by the in know nitris fertilizer
and if the concentration of nitrate in
the drinking water exceed 25 mgam per
lit it affects mortality rate and the
low weight of the newborn babies which
is basically these uh you know low
weight and thing known as a blue baby
syndromes right and which is showing
I'll show you a diagram maybe uh next
slides that um and blue baby syndrome
refers to at least two situation one is
Coptic heart means you know there will
be heart arteries which will be you know
big thicker and then will be thinner
that problem will be there and this memo
glob Mia that means like an you know
like blood will be less and then now it
will be little bit different than that
so this causes a problem in the blood
itself so you can look at this term I'm
not uh you know sure about that but you
look at that so what is that I mean this
is causing problem which will be with
the baby itself you know then where
you'll go right so these are very
serious problem of the blue baby
syndromes and there is another problem
which come
eutrophication utopic app basically when
you use excess
fertilizer that can pass to the nearby
water bod bodies okay and as a result
this there will be over nourishments in
this uh pond water bodies and which is
known as UT
tropication because the over Nish if
overnourishment will be there then what
will happen that the algae you know
there will be lot of growth in algae at
the faster rate and then they will grow
very
rapidly right and then again they will
die and then as a result because their
life is sought and they die and pollute
the water affecting the Aquatic Life
adversely that you might have seen that
in your you know observation if you are
having good observation see the cause is
this one so therefore these causes and
that is the
problem if you look at this pesticide
there are two kinds of pesticide people
use First genertion pesticide use sulfur
arsenic lead and mercury to kill pest
look at these are all you know dangerous
you elements on should have it but we
are using the second generation of
course the DDT what is dor dile Tri
chloro ethen used to kill pasts and
these P organic nature of course but uh
P protect our C from severe losses due
to pest but they have several side
effects you know you can think of there
several side effect it should not be
used as such and side effects of pite as
I told that basically that of non-target
organisms suppose you want to kill X but
now you'll be killing y j and you know
other things and which are beneficial so
several insect kill not only the target
space but also the several
beneficial and organism which are not of
Target and as I told that after you know
use this P past several time the people
the those are also living organism they
try to resist and certain Pest of course
certain things may not resist properly
but certain pests that could manage to
survive became highly resistant to all
kinds of pesticides you know and though
these past are called as super pest like
super man you know they become super
past so and biomagnifications is another
thing most P
nonbiodegradable right it's not it
cannot be deg ated by the soil or other
things so get into food chain which is
known as bio accumulation it will
getting
accumulated and these pesticides in BIO
accumulation form are harmful to the
human beings and as I told it will
remain for your body chain you know
chain chain food chain for several time
also in your own body right and it will
be transmitted you know various forms
and surface and groundwater pollution uh
you know like toxicity to Aquatic
wildlife and human through drinking
Waters right all those things risk of
cancers like uh pesticide enhances the
risk of getting cancer in two way it
acts as a carcinogen also and it
indirectly spoil the immune system you
might be aware that is a train known as
cancer train which is originated from
Punjab you are aware all of you there's
a train all cancer patient will be
coming you know that's why people call
it cancer because in Punjab Arana region
they're using this pesticide and
fertilizer to larger extent they can say
the rice what we call wheat bow or the
food bowel of India but they are really
spoiling their own health and giving us
food and that is also not of good
quality so I'll will stop over here and
we'll be looking at
the uh what you call disadvantages or
the of the using this modern uh farming
in the next lecture and later on I will
tell about like what is the quality of
food we are using
and then we'll be looking at basically
why we need to go for the ancient
technology for the agriculture thank you
very much
[Music]