[Applause]
hey everyone today we're planting garlic
I'll be using both store-bought garlic
and 12 cloves of elephant garlic from
this year's Harvest we'll be planting
them in two different types of garden
beds one is a no dig bed and the other
is hul culture we're going to compare
which method works better so what's the
difference no dig gardening is exactly
what it sounds like no digging instead
We Lay compost and organic materials on
top of the soil to build it up naturally
protecting the soil structure on the
other hand hugle culture is a raised bed
technique that uses decaying wood and
organic matter as the core of the bed
the word hugle culture comes from German
and means Mound culture this technique
helps retain moisture and adds nutrients
over time as the organic materials break
down I'm planting the garlic on
September 28th 2024
sewing each clove about 4 in deep and
spacing them roughly 7 in
apart normally I'd water them in after
planting but today the ground is already
quite wet so I'll just rake over the
soil and leave it as is now it's just a
waiting game to see how these two
different methods perform will the no
dig bed do better or will the hul bed
come out on top only time will tell make
sure to subscribe so you don't miss the
Harvest and comparison video thanks for
watching and I'll see you in the next
one
[Music]