um and i like how you just mentioned the
technicalities around sprouting
and on the fact that we also need to
farm potatoes with irrigation because
you know without water farming does
become a little bit tricky especially
with high value crops such as potatoes
so you know we've had a lot of rains
around december january february period
and um with with your knowledge and and
maybe
the farmers that you've worked with how
have they
mitigated the risk
[Music]
good day podcasters thank you so much
for joining the private property farming
podcast bringing to you yet another
episode of the farming podcast
discussing all things agriculture um as
i always mentioned on the show is that
if you have any topics comments
questions that you want to share with us
please do reach out to us right here on
the farming podcast you're catching us
live on youtube and we're happy to
engage with you and obviously explore
topics that you want to hear hear about
let us unpack it with our experts guests
and um this is what the podcast is for
at the end of the day so today we have
mr andrei dutoy
joining us and he's the manager at bayer
crop division our topic today we're
going to be focusing on potato farming
you know pro how do you make profit out
of potatoes um how do you farm potatoes
the pros and cons of farming potatoes or
maybe broadening it a little bit um into
venturing into vegetable farming uh if
you don't know about bayer um i guess
you should take out your laptop your
phone and just google them they're a big
international company
that deals with crop protection
pesticides a lot of varieties and i
think andre is going to be able to
unpack some of their services and what
they do particularly in his portfolio
and let's just tap into his expertise um
just to learn more about potato farming
the pros and cons around vegetable
farming how do we make a profit out of
it how do we grow our farming
enterprises to become profitable over
and above the pressures that we as
farmers face and maybe tap into the
valley chain as well so if you have any
questions like always to mr andre please
feel free to comment um let's get
straight into it and introduce andre
andre thank you so much for joining us
how are you doing
uh thank you very much now i'm doing
well
yes uh just uh thank you for that
introduction
um my title with buyer is the go to
market manager
for potatoes and vegetables in south
africa
so yes um i'm glad to be on your show
today
happiness happiness so firstly maybe
just explain to us what does bayer what
does the company bear do um and
specifically when you're saying you're
the go-to market manager what does that
exactly mean
molly is a very big company a global
company we are in pharmaceuticals we in
[Music]
seed
and we in crop science as well so yes my
responsibility is
the development of strategy and
alignment of uh the sales people
in field
to
uh
to to to align with our strategy uh for
the future and and so on so yes
they the go-to-market strategy leader or
is is somebody that is very
knowledgeable in the field of of his
expertise and he
or her
um
sort of show the way for the future and
that is in short my responsibility uh
with bayer at this stage
fantastic so um today we mentioned that
we're going to talk about potato farming
because i believe that it's also your
area of expertise so maybe just break it
down to it what you know if one wants to
venture into potato farming um what type
of land size should i be considering
what are the best regions to farm
potatoes
and how does one make a success out of
potato farming
in bali yes potatoes in south africa is
planted
right through the season right room from
summer right through to winter there's
always somebody that plant potatoes and
somebody that always fresh potatoes so
we in a fortunate position that
you know there is certain areas in south
africa that they plant potatoes like in
the halting area western free state and
kozulu natal and they are in the western
cape okay you ask me what is the
important thing about potatoes say for
instance if you want to start with
potatoes
the first thing is that you have to do
your research
raw potatoes fit
into in that area is it suitable to
plant your potatoes in that area
is the soil suitable to plant potatoes
what is the
the pest and diseases that can attack
your potatoes
and lastly uh is also the end of the day
you have to send your final product to
the fresh produce market or to the
processors or
one of those markets so you have to
investigate
those markets
the
because the end of the day you have to
make money to
to to to produce uh to do plant potatoes
potatoes is very expensive that variant
from a hundred thousand rent eight
up to two hundred to two hundred and
fifty thousand run the hectare so it's
very very expensive so you can't afford
to make a mistake so my first
uh to answer your question first of all
do your own work
see if it will fit into your rotation
fit in your form and another thing is
with potatoes we always say you need
the
the the implements you need you have to
have a plant you have to have irrigation
you have to have a lifter you have to
have a sprayer and lastly you have to
have a sorting space where you can sort
your potatoes
so it is a high input cost
the second
do secondly i will say
start small
and grow into it so that if you
if you make a mistake it's on a smaller
scale
and you don't have a you know
you you you you manage your risk on a
smaller scale as we if you open the
gates and you start and you plant big
hectares
you know the risk is just too high and
your input cost is very very high in
potatoes yes and then there's quite a
few things other that you can make use
of
this a lot of expertise in the field
um
you know your
your distribution companies that
distribute chemicals and
and fertilizers and so on they have very
knowledgeable people in the specific
areas that will
guide you
to
make a success if you want to start the
plant potatoes
another thing is what a potato grower
mistake in consideration is remember you
plant seed potatoes and that is a tuber
that is produced by a seed grower
and always buy
certified seed because there is a
guarantee on certified seed
uh that you also as part of your whole
process of manage
risk
uh at the end of the day
okay and then lastly is potatoes is
economical of scale
you have to have a high yield
a high youth
and high quality of potatoes
market at the right time at the right
market to get the right at the the best
uh price for your or for your potatoes
these are it sounds very technical you
know everything that you're saying about
um yes your advice is to say start small
so that you know when you do fail at
least you don't lose as much in your
investment as opposed to going big um
and i like how you just mentioned the
technicalities around sprouting around
the fact that we also need to farm
potatoes with irrigation because you
know without water farming does become a
little bit tricky especially with high
value crops such as potatoes so you know
we've had a lot of rains around december
january february period and um with with
your knowledge and and maybe uh the
farmers that you've worked with how have
they um mitigated the risks or still
kept their farm businesses in survival
mode rather in survival mode with all
these climate change um
different variables happening in various
parts of the provinces in the country
molly yes um
the the potato farmer uh he must watch
the weather
because potatoes is very acceptable in
chains of weather patterns
and if you just look at the spray
program and if you see there is a coat
from coming in of a lot of rain
you must
spray preventative
for
certain diseases
and my advice to a farmer is
do not wait until the disease or the
pest is on the farm
create or develop a spray pro program
that is preventative
a good measurement is
what you do before flowering determines
your
your success hour after flowering so yes
okay in bayern we have quite a
we have a very nice portfolio to a
microvision for all the
different pests and diseases that you
can
pick up during the growing season if i
can just start at uh
when you plant it at planting
there's a big problem with two
things that you must keep in mind first
of all is
nematodes
so we have a product with the name of
villam prime that control
nematodes
and the second one there is uh imester
solvers one of our new uh products that
we will launch we're busy launching it
and that cro
uh control raza
those two
uh products play a vital role in the
appearance of your potato that you want
to sell to the housewife
the potatoes as well research it after
products as well research
and if you use it according to the label
uh you will have good results okay so we
covered the the planting and what's
happening under the soil
and secondly when the potatoes start to
grow
then there's a fungus fungus diseases
that can attack your potatoes and there
is certain insects that can attack your
potatoes and therefore we have um a good
portfolio we have uh folic
nativo infinitu for the fungus
diseases and then we have dieses buddha
can belt to control your moth
diseases and there's other companies
that also supply
products to control
for instance leaf miner
we can't we can't supply everything to
them to the potato growers so you have
to make use of other companies that
that support a spraying program during
the season okay come back to your
original question about the weather and
and and so on yes weather is a critical
factor if you have too much rain
you your fertilizer
reach out and your blonde come under
stress and then they develop them
certain diseases and so on so you always
have to measure what happened with the
weather and what you're gonna do during
the growing season so if you look at the
growing season of potatoes it's anything
between
three ah four to five months that the
potatoes grow and you have to
make provision for your pests and your
diseases every seven to ten days you
have to spray and that's part of the
input cost
at the end of the day
okay
the weather
is also
important especially in the eastern free
state where there is quite a bit of uh
dryland uh plantings that uh taking
place so those farmers depend on rain
okay again they don't have irrigation
where you can just switch it on and say
there is water so the depend for water
that we blessed in south africa yes
that's a risk
so
my advice is to eastern free state
pharmacists
you know you form you know where your
best lens is and you know also what is
the water capacity in your land use them
for potatoes
due to the fact that you manage the risk
the whole time
yes
to conclude
from buyer we try
to advise our farmers to
look out
uh look at the weather and make a
management decision in connection with
the agents in the field to prevent
anything that can happen during that
time where the weather chains or you
have lots of rain or all those things so
yes
we try to advise our farmers to be
successful
fantastic and sticking on to that advice
andre
at the start of the production season do
you go out do you work with the farmers
to say this is how your soil analysis
looks like maybe instead of planting a
plant population of a hundred thousand
you need to maybe do 80 you know or
maybe go to 120 do you also assist the
farmers with the growing program around
pesticide management
yes
we in bayern we specialized in in crop
protection
there is
some other companies like your
fertilizer companies that do the soil
analysis and then they recommend the
correct fertilizer and blend and
and and so on for the farmer
uh then there's the seed companies that
advise the farmer which seat and which
cultivar to use and every area
let's call it a set of rules
where you know that you have to plant
your plant population have to be
that so many plants per year and then
you will
produce a a very high yield
from buyer's side
for us is that we
give a lot of training
for our agents in the field we empower
them with knowledge and we give them
uh access to sell our products in the
field that they can
with the
hope of of the assistance of uh
of our area managers in in the different
areas that knows the area knows exactly
what to look then they developed a crop
protection program
for the farmer but it is not cast in
stone remember what i said about the
weather so you have
you have something that you can work on
but you can change your indecision as a
certain
problems arise and and you have to make
provision for certain things
and that's the role of buyer in the
production of potatoes
yeah tell me andre do you guys work with
industry associations because as you're
talking i also was reminded that oh
there's a potato south africa uh
association do you work with the the
industry association maybe to bring in
um maybe with your partners like the sea
partners good varieties do you guys
engage with the association to say these
are the right pesticides you know for
the season maybe from your research and
development because i know that
organizations like yourselves pride
themselves with the quality of inputs
that you sell out to the market so my
question is do you work with industry
associations like potato south africa to
give them expert advice on how to
successfully grow this commodity
bali yes potato south africa and potato
certification
services is a very very important
partner for us due to the fact that
we
use their plot platforms
to
introduce new
innovation
we introduce our new chemistry we
communicate with uh our farmers uh
but we
um
we in a partnership that we use their
platform or we sponsor platforms that we
can
can communicate to our
farmers out there
another important part is what potato
certification and potatoes at africa
play is that
they have
information available and as a strategic
manager for me is important to
if you don't measure you can't manage
you know so we use
the
the platforms where i publicized on on
on patellar south africa where a website
or certification website we use those
information to manage um
in south africa
you asked me about seed
potato seeds we don't have anything to
do with potato seed in south africa
these other companies
that specialized in that
um
one thing that the
potatoes at africa have
certain work groups in different areas
and we
use those work groups
to demonstrate
cypher instance a buyer product or by a
spray program or
new innovation
and the information that we gather on
on on on workgroup level
is fantastic for a farmer because it's
information that he can use
in his area and he gets specific answers
for his problem and he can
manage risk with those information that
we
we we
collect
in in this
this is not a strange relationship but
everybody
make use of this
those platforms and work groups to
communicate with our client the end of
the day and uh client is our farmers
absolutely absolutely as i let go of you
andre i think you've just you know
unpacked this specific commodity quite
technically um and it's not a it's not
it's not a conversation we have every
single day and you've literally
displayed the intricacies around potato
farming and i guess this is the reason
why there's not so many players farming
potatoes because yes it is a big staple
crop it's a very important one around
the south african landscape but also
it's very difficult to master so maybe
leave us with a fun fact you know um
from your knowledge uh do you know how
big uh do you know any big potato
farmers in south africa you don't have
to mention their names but maybe just
give us a fun fact of the biggest potato
producer is producing one how many uh
hectares of land
sure
yes
that is uh
we have very big seed drivers in the
western free state area
they produce a lot in high quality of
seed and then we have
very big potato growers in the eastern
free state ryland
growers that produce um
anything between 300 and 400 to 500
acres at a time
and then in the group we have
pharmacy
between 200 and 408
as well that produce
potatoes
for south africa but
my message to
anybody that
eat the potato is
have respect for that potato because
there's a lot of uh work
and knowledge and
and
and the risk and input costs that go
into produce a potato
it is such an is such a fantastic
commodity
and it gives for so many people in south
africa jobs and and and so on it is just
a very exciting industry to be in
and
for my for my potato farmers the the one
thing that i can tell them is
all the best for the growing season
my provision for the
things that you don't know what can
happen uh prevention is always better
than care
and uh
you know
your success is our success and
from by your side we have a big team
or a very
knowledgeable team in the field that can
assist you so that you can be successful
the end of the day
absolutely thank you so much andre for
your time that was a a fantastic
conversation and yeah you've left me
with that note to say now we must all
have respect for our mashed potatoes our
sweet potatoes and more so our chips
that we consume um
for for for consumers around the country
so yeah it's a different message that
you've put out there but trust me next
time i eat a chip i will think of that
farming mind
thank you molly i really appreciate it
and i really enjoyed talking to you
likewise that was andrei dutoy
the go-to market manager from bayer
crops crop division and we were
discussing and maybe slightly unpacking
down the potato industry basically um
getting to know from his uh um advice
how many hectares one should start with
and he mentioned also besides land it's
cricket it's critical to have the right
equipment the right mechanization to be
able to plant your potatoes um weed uh
the areas around your potatoes and more
and more importantly harvest the
potatoes because it's quite a delicate
crop it needs special care and attention
and he mentioned that the rough or
average um input cost per hectare is
about a hundred thousand and it can all
go all the way about about up to 200 000
per hectare so you have to make sure
that if you're investing in such a niche
commodity make sure that you have your
ducks in a row reach out to the bayer
team who could assist you from a
pesticide management perspective um and
also work with your seed reps um work
with your chemical ribs to
really help you uh come up with a very
tight growing program that will help you
also mitigate your risk once you start
your production that's it for me like i
said if you have any questions please
feel free to reach out and continue to
like subscribe in our youtube channel
and continue to support the farming
podcast see you next
[Music]
you