that's been one of my biggest fears
since we've had this house out here is
like a cow's gonna chew through an
electrical line and kill himself and
then i gotta deal with that
grow your guard and find your tribe let
your hearts
[Music]
hello everybody and welcome back to the
terraform homestead today we're coming
to you with a new series all about our
solar system this is not a how-to video
this is not an in-depth detailed
demonstration of exactly what we've done
if you're looking for that there are a
bunch more resources out there on the
internet that are much more educated and
detailed than i can be in this video but
this is what we did to get our system
set up in a series we set up our systems
uh one for ourselves one for our camp
and with that enjoy this episode
today
i have been
uh procrasti working all day which
basically means
procrastinating on the project you're
supposed to be working on
by working on another project
so you don't feel bad about not doing
anything i was supposed to be cleaning
the rv uh we've got a couple people
showing up in about a week um i think
i'm pretty sure
work wires you never know um
so i was supposed to do that today but i
just did not feel like it worked way too
hard the last couple days
and wanted to do something more fun
so
i spent the morning planning and
researching and designing and all that
kind of stuff
and spent about three hours at home
depot today
um and got all this wood
got all this wood
and
got
this
new electrical system i'm really excited
about this we got our
second
tesla battery delivered yesterday
so that will put us at 500 amp hours
which is really cool lithium ion
batteries awesome stuff
and now that we will be having not just
the tiny house
but the rv
and then our pump house
um so we'll have to be running
electricity way way out there um to run
that that well pump decided it was a
good time to upgrade to what our
electrical system will be
finally like done done eventually this
will hold this whole area will be a
workshop um so we'll end up building the
workshop around the electrical box
[Music]
got it into its spot
and up on blocks we have termites out
here so anything
wooden has to be elevated off the ground
so that's why with the cinder blocks
and in addition to that i've got
some of these uh pieces of rebar cut and
kind of hooked
that i will be driving
into
the ground here and then i have these
long carriage bolts and then i just put
a washer in here um to kind of help
further anchor this bolt in then now i'm
going to fill these four with concrete
and this will be locked into place one
of the things that
don't really think about out here in the
desert it's got these black hinges
and they've been sitting in the sun so
now they're literally too hot to touch
um so i gotta get my gloves
to get these guys on
doors are in and look at that so now i'm
gonna get
the roof in the floor in
and the backboard in to mount everything
i'm very upset right now with this cloud
this cloud
was
over there
and it's been raining the entire time
but it decided to go around behind the
mountains
and then over here
so we got no
rain whatsoever on the property
nice windy hot day great for filming um
i have got in
our line and i'm about to start
trenching
so going from the tiny house to the
electrical box um and that's going to
make it so they don't don't have these
janky extension cords going everywhere
that's been one of my biggest fears
since we've had this house out here is
like the cow's gonna chew through an
electrical line and kill himself and
they're not gonna kill that so
[Music]
today is the hottest day we've had so
far i think our high is 101 today
so this little cloud is providing just
the tiniest bit of relief
so it's 101 out and then i'm just on top
of this motor basically and it's just
it's hot it's hot out here in the desert
no one ever told me that getting my
grounding rod driven in
this is no joke in hard soil
i feel like the soil is the bait of my
existence with all the electrical and
plumbing that we have to do out here
okay we've got
almost all of it done just got this last
little
bit here by 10-15 feet
and then we'll be done and then
get to what i'm good at laying pipe kind
of how it's gonna be i need some more
parts before i can finish this out um as
always
never get everything in the first run
but
this is going to run
all the way down there
there's that post running some big gauge
wire um i think i got eight gauge wire
i'm pretty sure that's gonna be way
better than this janky ghetto fire
hazard that we've been living off of
the 30 amp plugs go in here
i got this this wire big enough
that or the conduit big enough that i
can run six eight gauge wires through it
and so i'm gonna have a tee off here
and then
not right now but once i get the ditch
witch trench here
to this little spot
and then kind of
45 it out to the water tanks here's the
makings of the electrical closet so this
is our second tesla battery
um
the other one's currently being used uh
with two of them there that will give us
500 amp hours
at
24 volts which is plenty and should be
hopefully enough for the big house and
everything we want to do out here
so eventually this whole area right here
will become my workshop
and then i'll mount the solar solar
panels on top and
kind of thought about right in here
doing a like a covered garage kind of
thing just so we can get a little extra
rainwater but that's probably a little
ways out so the solar panels right now
they're
terribly mounted
not oriented right but eventually
they'll be mounted on the roof here
coming into the pv box
that will go to the charge controller
batteries inverter breaker box and then
breaker box goes to everything
[Music]
i've got everything
mounted and now it's starting to wire
everything up
be a quick tour so
we'll have an inlet here and i still got
a drill
that will go to this which is a pv
combiner box that basically takes
all the panels and then combines them
into one cord
that goes into
our charge controller here
that splits off and goes down to our
batteries which these are two
250 amp hour 24 volt
tesla batteries
these will be connected um so we'll have
500 amp hours worth of power that goes
into
our inverter 4000 watt
pure sine wave inverter that goes to our
breaker box here okay so i've got
everything hooked up
[Music]
there we go
and we'll flip this guy
and i'm gonna run over to the tiny house
and see if it's working
it would help if i plugged in the tiny
house
and we have electricity to the tiny
house that's not a ghetto uh extension
cord
super excited that this worked the first
time we are set up we are pulling about
800 watts right now in
uh so i've got
over here a string of 600 panels or 600
watts worth of panels
and up there there's another 600 watts
worth of panels those guys come in and
plug into these two slots here
uh it gives me another four slots to put
in um
and i've got
on order about 1200 more watts worth of
panel to plug into this the power
stations pretty well finished up i've
got
everything hooked up here everything's
live everything's working added on
a outlet up here so i think i'm going to
build a bench right here as a work table
for a little bit until i get something
to get the workshop more built
we have out here and see maybe our
percentage and then this is a cutoff for
the inverter so
that way i can turn everything on turn
everything off from the outside and not
have to worry about getting into
the locked cabinet if i need to shut
something off quickly really excited
really happy for this um this is a big
upgrade from doing it the other way
[Music]
i hope this was inspiring to you solar
is becoming so much more accessible and
diy friendly for those of you interested
in maybe getting involved with us and
getting some off-grid experience some
diy experience learning how to use some
tools learning how to build a house um
please check out our link below for eco
residency program we're gonna be ramping
up our summer program very very soon and
are starting to take some applications
spaces are very very limited so be sure
to get that application in as soon as
possible
thank you guys for watching i hope this
was inspiring go build something cool
[Music]