all right guys uh welcome back to this
channel
uh if you are new to this Channel please
end you subscribe to this Channel and uh
click on the Bell notification icon uh
to get lot of videos on profitable Pig
farming and this channel will bringing
to you lots of great videos on
profitable Peak farming well uh in
today's video I'll be talking from the
business side of peak farming I want to
talk from the business side of peak
farming of course I understand uh
that pig farming for many is a passion
is an interest uh there is a probably an
enthusiasm towards it you enjoy doing it
but uh again in the in the end what
really matters is uh how profitable is
your Venture how profitable is your
business so let me quickly share some
tips with you today on uh how to make
more money from the Pak farming business
uh several farmers are not making profit
from Pak farming me I could prove that
to you because uh from my own experience
moving around I can tell you already
that several farmers are not really
making it in P fing and that's not
because P fing is not profitable it's
really profitable but because of certain
mistakes and that's one of the reasons
why this channel exist to share with you
lot of great uh content to educate you
to Enlighten you on certain things you
need to work on to ensure you get your
farm much more profitable all right so
uh let me let me talk to you about about
certain things uh from a business point
on uh Pak farming and how you can
enhance your business how you can make
more money from Peak
farming all right uh
now there's one thing that uh we all
need to understand in in business
generally business is about buying and
selling of product and buying and
selling of certain items in this case
selling pigs so depending on whatever
model you are doing
one thing that makes you to be in
business is that you have a product the
pigs and you are selling them to a
customer to your final consumer or
whatever you have there so now you have
product that you want to sell
out if you are able to sell at the right
price to the right customers then you
are in business and if you can continue
that for a while because the pig farming
business is not just for a day or for
just one set you're not just doing this
for maybe you just buy 10 PS and you
sell them and that's all obviously you
are continuing a process uh you can be
in pig family for 10 years for 20 years
so obviously you need to have a
continuous um sales of your product and
that brings me to the very first key the
very first tip for you to make more
money in P farming and that's number one
have a very good reputation have a very
good reputation you see it's an
emotional business you know business is
generally emotional and I believe you
have probably heard this saying that
people don't buy product people buy
state so uh some someone will decide to
buy from you because they like you
because they trust you because they
believe in you and they will not buy the
same thing the same price from someone
else so people buy States and if you
understand this uh log this psychology
to business then you understand that you
want to ensure that your customers have
the right uh interest as as the right
relationship with you so you want to
build great relationship with your
customers you want to ensure that you
are very honest you're very credible you
want to ensure your credibility is on
the highest side that you have great
reputation when it comes to dealing that
means number one for instance let's say
you are selling um breeders to Farmers
you want to ensure that you have
all if you say this breed is a t breed
it's a it's a t breed if you are calling
this breed a Duro it's a Duro you want
to have great credibility if you want to
say this pig is pregnant then this pig
is pregnant you know I heard of someone
a farmer that bought um pigs from
another farm and uh he was told that if
the pigs were pregnant but on getting to
the farm after 2 months the pigs are not
pregnant the P the pig was not pregnant
and in calling that farm back the farmer
is not picking picking up the call do
you see exactly that that farmer do you
think that farmer is going to get to
that farm to get any other thing or is
going to make any referral to that farm
no and that's already a very bad thing
for his business because nobody if if he
knows anybody going to that farm he will
caution the person that that guy is not
credible so you want to ensure you have
the best credibility when it comes to
any business and which include the Pak
farming business anything you are going
to if you're going to talk about their
medication you are going to ensure you
giving them the proper medication the
the Waring and everything you're not
going to sell PS that are going to be uh
I'm going to call turn to casualty when
it get to the other Farm because that
will kill your credibility and once your
credibility is dead the business is a
very small world the business world is a
small world everybody in town
understands that that person is not
credible they don't come to you anymore
and if you can't sustain your Market if
you can't keep selling your product
you're not in business so you won't have
the ability to expand when you don't
have the right customers coming to buy
your product so you want to earn honesty
is a very important currency in this
business so that's one key that you must
have to ensure that you keep making
money in pig farming you must be
extremely honest great reputation they
know this person is like this and they
know you you you would not lie about
what you're doing that's very very
important now I talked about the
external customer but let me quickly
Channel this discour to also the
internal customer customers a lot of
people forfeit the interest and
importance of their internal customers I
call the internal customers their
workers now if you don't have the right
credibility the right reputation with
your workers you should know you are a
you you a dead meat if I permit me to
say that because your internal customers
are the ones that sustains your business
so if your internal customers feel you
are fraudulent you don't pay them their
wages you don't pay them their salaries
or you are not faithful or you treat
them like like uh like uh they don't
exist like they are unimportant then you
are writing letter to failing in your
business because they are the ones that
keep your business going somebody said
you don't make it a duty to impress your
customer but make it a duty to amaze
your customers and I'm talking both your
external and your internal customers I
for a person now I can tell you one
thing that uh permit me to say this and
to talk about myself when it comes to
reputation it's really there I have
people that will vouch from here
anywhere and it's it's just that way
even without me being there a worker
will tell a worker that that person uhuh
is not like that he's a very faithful
person I would not uh deny my internal
workers of their uh right of what they
are supposed to get I would actually do
much more and go further to impress them
to amaze them to make them worthy to
make them interested and that's the
reason why you will see how passionately
they do the work I'm they given to do
there's a guy that works for me uh he
works in certain ways that you'll be
surprised you will think I pay more than
what I pay you know but because of the
fact that he understands there's
faithfulness in this person I'm not
going to you're not going to do a work
for me and I'm going to try to Swindle
you or to scam you no what I I I do as
much as possible to ensure that you are
also making it in life and that's what
must also do if you want to keep making
money in pig farming ensure both your
internal and external customers are
doing very well and you have great
relationship with them great reputations
with them and that's uh that uh once you
have that believe me the the it's it's
uh it's very certain that you can have
great profits great money make good
money from your pig farming business
well that's not all I will also talk
about this one is something I've spoken
about uh in a while I've been speaking
about this and that's getting healthy
stocks getting if you want to make money
from your pig farm from your pig um
business please get l stock please get l
stock be very careful of not just don't
just get stocks from any Farm I think I
have said that uh very often here make
sure the farmers you are getting your
stocks from are very credible they have
the right reputation thems so that you
can easily Trace their genetics if they
tell you they're selling to you a large
white you know it's a large white you
are buying don't buy stocks from just
any Farm be very careful when you are
buying your stock uh ensure they have
the right medication being done on the
farm ensure they have the right genetics
ensure that they've taken their high on
injection when they supposed to have
taken it because I was one of my friend
um he told me he was telling me recently
that he suspected that the reason why U
some pigs he got some while ago while I
think all of them died or something was
because of probably uh the fact that
that those pigs probably did not take
their iron injection when they supposed
to they are farmers like that that don't
care about many of all these things they
don't they don't maintain good uh
medication on their Farm if you get un
Peaks from that farm they may be good
while you are looking at them right
there but once you shift them away from
that farm to your own Farm then they
start having problem so make sure you
get the right genetics and you ensure
that they have taken all their
medications and they the right breed you
are you intended to buy so number two is
for you to make sure you buy L stocks
please if you really want to make money
from because this your a pig can stay on
your farm for at least 5 years and keeps
giving you uh piglet so you want to
ensure you are buying the best uh um in
short PS in the best state so please uh
make sure you buy Heth stock number
three is take the peak farming business
very serious take it incredibly serious
many people are I I you know I can I I
cannot tell you what I don't know I can
only tell you what I know from my own
experience in watching Farmers around me
I've seen that several people don't take
the farming business very serious uh if
you ask many
farmers to show you their records on
their Farm many don't even have anything
called a farm record if you have a far
if you're in business and you don't have
the right records how then do you
monitor your profit and sales how then
do you uh monitor what's going on on
your farm how do you monitor the amount
of money you have spent so take your
fing your business serious the right
time to feed them the right medication
the right um cleaniness the right
management everything you need to know
to everything you need to do to ensure
the business is is done well is moving
forward please do it take it very
serious take it like as if uh your life
depends on it because it really does so
you want to pay attention to it
immensely you want to put in all your
all effort to ensure it goes very well
don't um be like those people that come
in the morning feed the pigs and that's
all they go away they don't check on the
P they don't check if they okay they
just go away and uh they don't give them
Dew they don't dearm them they just put
them there expecting that somehow
somehow the pigs are going to be okay
please take your farming uh your pig
farm very serious pay attention to every
detail be extra uh involved in your
business and then the last but not the
least is for you to invest in knowledge
if you really want to get it right in
Pak farming you want an expert to be
around you because anything can happen
at any time it's as much as uh you may
you may have been doing well for a while
you could wake up one day and disc
discover certain things may happen on
your far and that's why you need an
expert around to be able to walk you
through what you're supposed to do on
how you are supposed to handle it so
that will bring me to the end of this
video how to tips to make more money in
pig farming once again if you're new to
this Channel please Ure you subscribe to
this channel lot of great content on
profitable fing will be brought to you
right on this channel thank you very
much bye-bye