if you have a look at this cut over here
it is 45° to the angle of the branch
what that means is the oins and the
hormones are being centered around this
corner over here which is the tip and
just below the tip is a bud that's the
bud I want to stimulate to grow and this
brings me into the Angles and the bud
locations there's a bud on the very top
over here now if I were to cut here this
bud is going to go straight up so if you
cut it at the wrong location you got
this nice 45° angled branch which you
are now sending into a vertical you've
just lost a whole bunch of good work but
if you cut it on the bottom outward
facing node this branch is now going to
grow that way it's not going to grow
inwards and up it's going to grow
outwards and up