[Music]
so we're here in buber today delving
into the depths of the online soybean
manual we're here with agronomist and
Growers really looking at the whole
soybean production cycle so the online
soybean production manual is a really
effective tool for both agronomist and
Growers just looking at all areas of the
soybean production system it does
include lot of updated information to do
with both diseases storage every
different section of the soybean
production
[Music]
process the consumption of soybean and
the processing of the soybeans in
Australia has changed back in the um 80s
whilst we had a crushing plant that was
a main focus but from the demise of that
sort of plant there was a more focus on
the edible type Market the edible Market
being the Asian influence of tofu and
also the introduction of soy milk as a
dairy alternative those two sort of
products have sort of paved the way for
additional high-end edible sort of
qualities uh the baking industry is is a
major sort of consumer of soybeans as
flour as an additive in the baking
process through improvers soybeans in
Australia grow from the the tropics all
the way down through into Victoria
uh your main production areas are
concentrated in the Southeast corner of
Queensland where the major manufacturers
uh and processors are situated there is
still plenty of demand in the
marketplace in Australia we're still not
producing enough soybeans that's going
to meet all the market demand that we
[Music]
have so soybeans are a rotation option
in our Shan farming system so are really
a key pillar in in maintaining soil
Health in our Coastal farming systems
initially in the early days it was we
wen't promoting it initially as a grain
crop it was just to get Growers familiar
with it as a rotation crop in in the in
the sugar system so a lot of guys were
just green manuring it but then it
became very obvious that we could grow
it for
grining I was humbled at one event where
one grower stood up and mentioned that
you know unless he had grown soybeans
for grain as part of his his farming
system he still wouldn't be a cane
farmer today because it got him through
tough
[Music]
times in my role we're really looking at
how to store the soybeans most
effectively and trying to incorporate
that extra Avenue into farming
businesses in the
region storage in these sorts of regions
can be a bit tricky we often see them in
coastal or Northern regions and that's
where the relative humidity really comes
into play we often see that the
conditions can be a bit challenging for
storing soy beans so we really look to
go to a bit more uh technology in these
sorts of regions looking at automated
aeration controllers to really try and
overcome some of the issues with manual
aerations the manual itself came
together in about 2012 so I was due for
a refresh and now uh so it's been
reviewed refreshed brought up to date
and having it online it's an easy
mechanism for Growers advisors or
anybody Al like just be able to access
that most current up-to-date information
it's great that there's been a renewed
push from grdc and the Queensland
government to promote soybeans and I
think there's a real opportunity there
for other farming systems to consider
soybeans not just cane and it's the kind
of crop that people should be thinking
about using when they're changing
farming systems as a bit of a cleaning
up the padic so to speak but the benefit
is that you can also earn an income from
it I think it's just a win-win all
around I think it's a great crop I did
access the online manual before I came
to the workshop it sort of helped me
decide whether I needed to come or not
and I saw that there was plenty of extra
information and more detail that perhaps
hadn't been in older Publications so I
was really pleased with that and I
thought the online manual was quite easy
to
[Music]
use I found the workshop today and
yesterday absolutely brilliant I mean
some of it I sort of knew before I've
heard before of course but a lot of it
was is a great refresher some of those
little gems of wisdom that you sometimes
forget uh but also because the speakers
have been given plenty of time to talk
they've gone into quite a lot of detail
of their various subjects which has been
brilliant because often when you talk to
them it's on the fly or they do a quick
presentation at a field day whereas this
has been a lot more in depth and then
we've of course got their great notes to
refer back
to glob
soybeans are a new crop for me so it's
been awesome to see like the whole
picture of soybeans right from planting
all the way to marketing at the end of
the season yeah it's been
fantastic the online manual is really
good it's so easy to get through and you
can see all the modules really easy just
there click on them and go through all
the information it's great
[Music]