easy to grow a Wonder in the kitchen
tender fruits are nearly round mildly
sweet flavor creamy texture plump and
variably ribbed there's a nice poetry to
Seed Catalog descriptions but there's
also a lot of technical terms in there
so we're going to talk about the meaning
of some of those words and how they
relate to your garden there's a few
different types of seeds that you'll see
advertised organic is one so organic
seeds have been grown in organic
conditions on a farm so that means no
chemical fertilizers pesticides or
herbicides as well as a whole host of
other variables this one's listed as
USDA organic certified whereas this one
just says organic lettuce seed another
thing you'll see is non-GMO project you
are not going to accidentally buy any
genetically modified or GMO seeds those
are highly regulated they're very
expensive and they're for agricultural
producers if you find something that
doesn't say non-GMO project certified
doesn't mean it's GMO it's not something
that you have to worry about hairloom
seeds is another thing you see listed
hairloom generally refers to plants
different types of cultivars that have
been grown for a long time some people
say before the 1950s some people say 50
years I'm not sure that there's an
actual rule but often they have a
historical or cultural significance to
an area which is why they still are
grown you'll see some seeds listed as
treated seeds I actually have some here
that I ordered by accident you can see
these PE seeds are pink so these are
treated with a fungicide this will just
keep them from rotting when they go in
the ground pelleted seeds are not the
same as treated seeds for smaller seeds
like lettuce seeds what they are is
they're actually a small clay coating
that turns it into a seed that is about
the size of a radish seeds so you end up
with something that's easier to handle
that's easier to plant out it's not
necessary if you're not planting out a
whole ton of plants but if you're
planning to save seeds from your garden
it's important to know if the plant is
open-pollinated or if it's a hybrid so
open-pollinated plants you could save
the seeds from and then they will
produce the same seeds the next year
they pollinate naturally in whatever
mechanism the plant uses it's different
for all different types if it's a hybrid
plant it's been more specifically
crossbreed by agronomists who have
picked out certain traits from A couple
of different cultivars and put them
together that plant will not produce
seed that will produce a new plant the
seeds may be sterile or they may just
produce something totally different than
the plant that you started with so you
don't want to save seeds from hybrids
hybrids are also often more expensive
because of the technology that goes into
them and you want to just make sure you
notice how many seeds you're getting in
the past I've ordered pepper seeds that
were hybrids and then realized I only
got 10 seeds in my envelope another word
that's related to that is parthenocarpic
or self fertile you're going to see that
listed in association with growing in
green houses if you're growing cucumbers
or tomato in a greenhouse there may not
be as many pollinating insects around
and so something that's parthenocarpic
is self fertile they'll often grow
without seeds and they don't need to be
fertilized by another plant in order to
produce fruit seed cataloges will give
you a lot of information about timing as
well DTM days to maturity how many days
it will take between when the plant is
either directly seated in the ground or
a transplant is put in the ground so I
use them as a comparison point just to
understand if I'm looking for something
that's fast or something that's slow
otherwise I'm not going to really take
that information and assume that it's
going to be true in my garden any
perennial plants that you're ordering
will also say Hardy till Zone 2 to 4 or
Hardy to zone six it'll list them in
there note that the USDA zones are
different than the Canadian zones so
check which zone you're in and then
check which country your catalog comes
from so that's how cold the plant can
get over the winter so you'll also see a
lot of growth habits listed on here so
these are different ways that the plant
grows and it's good to match these to
the conditions that you want in your
garden you'll see different things like
spicy Bush basil is does well in
containers as well as the garden the
plants are small and Dome shaped so
they're small dwarf semi- dwarf climbing
those are words that will be used
another big distinction here is between
determinant and indeterminant those
terms are usually used when talking
about tomatoes Det perent means that the
plant will grow to a certain size and it
will produce fruit and seeds but then
when it's produced enough seeds that
it's sort of finished its life cycle and
thinks that it's passed that on it will
stop and it will die indeterminate they
will continue to grow fruit and they
will continue to produce seeds until the
weather conditions change around them it
gets too cold they dry out then they
will die the days get too short
something like that word you'll see a
lot is resistance so there's a few
different types of resistance you'll see
these parlees say that it has
intermediate resistance to dowy mildew
resistance to uh diseases is very common
you'll see that a lot in tomatoes
sometimes it will say something specific
like resistant to Tomato tobacco mosaic
virus sometimes it will be General it
will say good resistance package that's
bolt resistance is another one that you
see often something that can grow as the
weather gets warm without going to seed
if you've ever grown cilantro I find is
an especially common one it'll grow
really well in the cooler weather but as
soon as you get a hot spell it'll just
send up a giant amount of flowers and
the leaves are not as good to eat also
crack resistant Tomatoes uh will often
crack especially if they get too much
water if it's a wet year at a certain
point in time when the fruit are forming
the skin will actually crack so crack
resistance just means that it's less
likely to happen um they've been bred to
have a thicker skin and more of an
ability to to take on that excess water
field holding how long something can sit
in the field without needing to be
picked maybe that's important if you
want to grow you know a whole bunch of
head lettuces and sort of leave them and
pick them one at a time growth rate is
often said Slow versus Fast growth rate
intermediate growth rate grows well
early grows well late likes heat likes
cold you'll see all of these descriptive
terms uniformity I often see so that's
good if you're doing some preserving
projects where you want beets that are
all the same size or if you're selling
them in a market and you want them to be
a similar size and shape and then
there's all the other
words perfectly compliments strong
handles holds color unique coloration
weight speed and crunch these are the
fun ones and then you've got all kinds
of words that have to do with the
flavors rich flavor tarte flavor sweet
flavor maybe a little bit arbitrary but
also pretty exciting to think about have
a good time reading catalogs and
hopefully this will help you understand
what they're talking about I'm just
going to go back to the Poetry now
attractive dark green Savoy leaves on
tall upright
heads good sweet
flavor