[Music]
the following is a production of New
Mexico State
University this is a story of two
successful agricultural entrepreneurs
Louisa and Jim who want to expand their
business by winning a contract from a
new demanding buyer their story
illustrates some of the benefits and
techniques for initiating good
agricultural practices
but is no substitute for professional
consultation from public sector advisers
or private
consultants in addition Government
research has shown that consuming fresh
fruits and vegetables offers important
health benefits this video is designed
to help make the nation's already safe
fresh produce Supply even safer the
events portrayed in this video are
fictitious and are for educational
purposes only
[Music]
hey Jim this is an exciting day can you
believe we got an appointment with this
Chef this is a big deal for us today
absolutely but I hope it doesn't take
too long because my wife and I have to
be salsa dancing by 5:30 okay well I'm
not the one holding us up let's get
going okay
this is a big day for Jim and Louisa
business partners in a small fresh
produce Farm over the past decade they
have had their good years and their bad
years they even almost went broke a few
times but they have always dreamed of
expanding their operation and buying the
adjacent Farm to make this dream come
true they must expand their Market to a
new type of
buyer today they have an appointment
with one of the Region's top chefs will
see you their dream is actually within
their reach but as with everything in
agriculture it will take planning and
[Music]
work what Jim and Louisa will hear today
from Russell is what many producers
across the United States are hearing
from buyers of fresh produce how
seriously they heed the advice Russell
gives them could make a big difference
in their hopes for the
future as the fresh produce market
becomes more competitive and buyers more
demanding producers across the US are
looking for ways to make their good
farming operations even better it is
beautiful lettuce but I like to add you
my list of prar but we only use
certified Gap process
Gap what's that I've never heard of that
before I'm not the expert but you can
ask Dean Okimoto he's one of our best
produce suppliers okay yeah actually I
know Dean's in the call up with me and
so yeah maybe we could give him a call
and go out to his farm and and find out
how he does it to meet your standards
Russell I want to thank you very much
for your time today I think we can meet
your standards and we'll be in touch
with Dean and then we'll be in touch
with you hopefully give me a fall great
excellent thank you thank
much thank
you well we got it today Louisa and
Jim's potential buyer said he would buy
from them only if they had a gap program
but the problem is they don't even know
what gaps or good agricultural practices
are when Jim visits Dean he's at first a
bit shy asking for advice from a
competitor but Dean puts him at ease Jim
it's the responsibility of all of us in
in in the industry to to be aware of of
good agricultural practices and to make
our industry which is a safe industry to
begin with even safer right so it's
important for all of us to understand
these things and to learn it and it
protects all of us that way Dean
explains that gaps involve a detailed
process designed to prevent or reduce
microbial contaminants from entering the
fresh produce production system
following gaps is not always easy but
for demanding buyers like Russell it's a
requirement so I see this is is
everybody's responsibility like you were
saying I mean I I could be responsible
for some of these problems I need to
figure out ways to mitigate them so how
do I learn about the actual ways of to
cleaning up my farm well Jim you know I
know it's a lot to handle and with our
busy work schedule and everything what I
did as I hired a consultant although
Louisa and Jim decided to use a
professional consultant your local
extension office and many universities
are staffed with qualified
[Music]
advisers hey Jim what are you up to hey
Louisa um I'm going over this poster
that Dean gave us and wow there is just
a lot to do and I can see that we're
going to be spending a lot of money
Transforming Our Farm yeah but you know
what I think we know a lot of things
that are on this poster already right
but I mean where do we start there's
just there's just so much and you know
what I'm worried are we ever going to
get a payoff well a payoff as you call
it well I think it's just going to come
in different forms you know expanded
markets and you know confidence in our
product and you know what get this maybe
in the future hopefully in a couple of
years a profit you know what when we
start selling to high-end buyers we
could probably see some money coming in
okay but you know what I don't think we
should start spending that money just
yet uh I just don't I don't know where
to start there's just a lot to do it's
not difficult it's just I'm a little
confused where to start well I think
you'd agree with me it's about our
reputation we want to be growing and
selling the best Clean safe healthy uh
produce maret absolutely yeah well I
know your fears and I think since you're
here and I'm here why don't we take a
look at this poster and let's pick out
several things that we can start doing
together you know take small steps
towards um getting it all together good
idea well you know I'm looking at this
insecticide area here they show kind of
a bad example that that kind of looks
like our farm I see where we got to go
and so you know what I'm going to pick
this one for now and start on this what
about you okay well you know how I've
been feeling about having to go behind a
tree and our workers having to go you
know out in the field what Jim and
Louisa have found is a simple road map
to move their Farm toward APAP
compliance in order to meet the demands
of a new
buyer they decide to make some
critically important improvements
[Music]
immediately Louisa says she will start
with worker hygiene and Jim is going to
tackle their use and storage of crop
protection agents it won't be easy but
the payoff will make it worth all the
hard work believe this how many Louisa
has always been concerned about some of
the workers common hygiene habits
although the workers are welcome to use
the toilets at the Farm office in
reality many just take advantage of a
nearby Bush Louisa knows this means they
are not washing their hands properly she
intends this to stop
immediately Louisa gets worker hygiene
regulations off the web to comply with
state and federal requirements now she's
ready to go shopping for toilet
facilities Louisa is surprised at how
many units really do not meet her needs
they all have toilet paper holders
inside but she's looking for units that
will hold lots of toilet paper running
out would be bad
news next Louisa looks at the
handwashing facilities first she wants
it to be outside not inside among other
things this will help ensure that all
workers actually wash their
hands in addition loua is looking for a
large soap dispenser she needs a paper
towel holder that dispenses single use
paper towel trash here she also wants
attached trash cans for the used paper
towels Louisa checks to be sure that the
tank can keep the water clean and
sanitary and that it is easy to clean
and sanitize on a regular basis it she
also wants to be sure the used water
never runs onto the ground but instead
is caught so it can be disposed of far
from her food
crops once she finds the ideal unit she
signs a contract that covers delivery
cleaning supplies and maintenance
this relieves her of a lot of
Maintenance headaches and provides
written documentation that she rented
enough toilets for the number of workers
she has and that everything including
cleaning and restocking is up to
standards Louisa has ordered the unit on
Wheels so she can always have it close
to her workers and post signs to remind
workers to wash their hands after using
the
toilet Louisa knows these new toilet and
handwashing Facilities will make her
workers much happier and will also make
improvements towards the safety of her
produce she realizes this first step
wasn't really all that
[Music]
hard Jim wanted to start on the crop
protection agent guidelines because he
was trained by the University's
extension program and received his
applicator
license he's proud of the crop
protection agent file he maintains
complete with copies of labels and
material safety data sheets or the msdss
he always records the agent mix ratios
and Equipment inspections he's proud of
his written
records Jim has been careful to document
that Harvesters observe the legal time
between his last spray and worker
re-entry to protect his workers Jim also
follows the approved Harvest interval to
help ensure that no illegal residues
remain on his crop but in reviewing his
class notes Jim realizes he needs to
double check that his workers are
calibrating the spray equipment fre
frequently and recording all their
maintenance H I'm not quite sure about
this maybe a checklist will
help Jim reminds the workers to check
the calibration before each spray and
makes Dennis responsible for record
keeping and periodic inspections because
you know Dennis this is really important
to do this you're doing a couple things
for us you're saving us money you're
controlling our p and we're keeping out
of the trouble of having illegal
residues so it's really important that
you're doing this and you're doing a
good job so thanks for this calibration
will save Jim money crop protection
agents are
expensive well Jim has put off his last
stop as long as he can he's going to
inspect his crop protection agent
storage area Jim always knew his storage
unit was cluttered but looking at it
objectively he can see it could be a
source of future contamination if he
doesn't act
now he knows pesticide containers
shouldn't be sitting on top of product
shipping containers he also knows all
crop protection agent should be
organized separated and locked up he's
just been too busy and this looks like a
big job but Jim remembers his Farm's
commitment to provide consumers with
safe produce and to protect his workers
at the same time he wants an operation
he can be proud of so he decides today
is the
day in less time than he would have
guessed Jim has a good system for the
Farm's crop protection agents complete
with good
documentation Jim feels pretty good he's
solved a problem that's been nagging him
for some time he's eager to share his
progress with Louisa and plan their next
[Music]
steps hey Jim I just passed the storage
it looks terrific you did such a
great job thanks Louisa you know I'm
feeling actually pretty excited about it
myself once I got going it was actually
pretty easy and and now that we have it
organized I think we can insist that our
employees keep it clean well fortunately
we have good employees all we have to do
is get a system in place we have to
train them and then it's just going to
be part of our routine I just love these
gaps well you know I wouldn't get all
that excited just yet I'm still
reluctant you know we're spending all
this time and and I'm I'm worried about
whether or not we're really going to be
able to get the payback from people like
Russell and others I just don't know
okay I'll admit it too I've been a
little bit concerned about that um I
wondering should we get some
professional advice what do you think
maybe someone to keep us on track
because otherwise we're just going to
lose their Direction and I don't know if
you and I have the discipline to keep
doing this well Jim and Louisa chose to
get coaching from the private sector
there are many universities and
extension offices that can provide
quality advice also depending on the
size and disarray of your farm coaching
may not be necessary
[Music]
shortly after they talked to Dean Jim
and Louisa started getting professional
guidance from a private consultant
specializing in gap
certification other nearby farmers are
using qualified government University
and Industry resources but Jim and
Louisa were so busy they opted for a
private consultant and they're glad they
did in any case the advice this
consultant gives Louisa and jeem can
benefit any producer wanting to
understand good agricultural practices
so let's
in a very methodical way and that's what
we want did the mitigation checklist
that I gave you help you going through
the process Craig it sure did it made
the process so much easier yes and we've
been actually incorporating good
agricultural practices into our standard
Farm procedures to meet the requirements
of more particular buyer such as Russell
and Jim and I are excited to get this
process into action that's really great
let's take a look at what you've done to
date and see what else we need to
do the three talk about what hard work
it was to get ready for this Farm visit
today and all they learned about their
own farming practices in the
process Lisa took on the challenge of
learning the history of the land they
were planning to buy so they could
expand their
operation before they invested in the
land next door Craig told her to do a
title search and detailed investigation
of the prior land use she checked the
public records and the prior owner
records to be sure the land was
historically used only to produce food
crops and not used for industrial
purposes or to raise livestock such as
cattle or chickens it's an easy
transition thankfully she discovered the
land was only used for food crop
production for over 50 years and there
was no history of chemical and microbial
contamination to be concerned
about Jim took on the task of detailing
what the land surrounding the plot they
hoped to buy was used for he started
with an accurate map and marked what all
the land around it was used for at first
Jim didn't understand why a neighbor's
land use could really affect his
cropping plans but when Craig told him
to map out the direction runoff water
flowed from the neighbor land and how
hard and which way the wind blew Jim got
the
picture Jim's cousin out of New Mexico
had to adjust his plans because of a
neighbor's existing land use he wanted
to grow fresh leaf lettuce but then
realized that the wind and runoff from a
nearby Dairy might carry pathogens onto
his Fields so today Jim's cousin is is
earning less than he had hoped growing a
nonf food
crop luckily Jim found no major problems
with their land but just to be sure it
stays that way he's improved his fence
to keep the neighbor's horse from
wandering onto his
land well let's talk about fertilizer
and compost next and Louisa that was
your task that's right Craig and let me
tell you everything about compost I'm
the person now I know it
all she was responsible for the
fertilizer use records on their Farm she
discovered that the compost they buy
follows a tested and certified method to
reduce microbial
contamination Louisa actually went to
the supplier to inspect their process
for herself she learned they carefully
controlled the process including the
time temperature and number of turns
used to make the
compost the owners then tested each lot
at a certified lab to assure that it did
not contain pathogenic bacteria Louisa
established a farm policy to only buy
compost that has been tested and shown
to be free of pathogenic bacteria Jim
and Louisa buy commercial soil
amendments and fertilizers only from
reputable manufacturers who follow their
industry's best practices with Craigs
help Louisa set up fertilizer
application records for each individual
field she added the manufacturers
certified analysis of their product and
set up a weekly time to update her
records Jim and Louisa are learning that
running a top quality operation is only
half the task they must also document
all their efforts before they can be
audited and
certified Jim and Louisa have also
learned that while the entire process
may seem overwhelming by working on
little steps every day it really doesn't
take that longs and along the way they
continue uncovering ways to make their
operation more efficient in many
unexpected ways Jim and Louisa told
Craig that their cheapest source of
water was the stream that ran through
their property they wanted to use it if
testing proved the water was safe at the
same time they tested the well water but
the test results showed the stream
contaminated with ecoli so the farm
would need to rely on the well water for
food crop related water needs you know
now Farm policy tells workers to only
use wellwater for any operation where
the water will come into contact with
the edible portion of the
crops after all these months keeping
records has become second nature to
so he made a folder for all his water
test results and has established an
annual water test as Farm policy this is
all part of their Farm
gaps Louisa worked with Craig to develop
worker training and hygiene policies for
their farm and set up regular employee
training
sessions this allows her to update them
on New Farm policies to improve the
sanitation of their
processes the farm now has a written
policy that all workers must wash their
hands after eating going to the bathroom
taking breaks and anytime they return to
harvesting or handling the product she
insists that sick workers are either
allowed to go home sent to the doctor or
temporarily assigned to tasks where they
do not have contact with the fresh
produce at least once a month Louisa and
Jim schedule a time to update workers on
new safety regulations and procedures
and to reinforce the gaps especially
those involving cleaning and
sanitation they document their ongoing
program to keep workers trained and
reminded of critical points that affect
the safety of their product thereby
helping to protect the reputation of
their farm and the
industry if a cut happens on the job and
there's any chance that blood touch the
fresh produce all potentially
contaminated produce is thrown away Jim
and Louisa have worked too hard to
endanger their good reputation over just
a few dollars worth of produce in the
short run it hurts but in the long run
they know it is a small price to pay for
a top
reputation Louisa also established
written policies that all Harvest tools
are washed and cleaned with portable
water and rinsed with a food quality
sanitizer the farm now has written
policies that are enforced to ensure
that all washing and packing areas are
kept clean dust free and
sanitized here Craig shows Jim how to
measure the strength of his washwater
sanitizer all the bins and Trays holding
the fresh produce are sanitized and only
new bags and boxes are
used all packing materials are stored
off the floor and away from
chemicals the storage unit is set up to
ensure contamination from Birds rodents
or insects will not occur and just to be
sure Jim sets out non bait rodent traps
spaced at recommended intervals and
makes a map of the numbered traps he
then establishes a schedule to
frequently check and change out the
traps
packed product is kept in a clean
well-maintained cold room at the optimum
temperature to maintain post Harvest
quality and to reduce microbial growth
Jim and Louisa have worked hard to
produce their crop and maintain high
standards for quality and safety they
have labeled every box with tracking
codes to allow for Trace back in the
event of quality or food safety problems
they have also set up systems to
maintain these standards through the
last phase of their process
transportation to the
buyer Jim once thought he was saving
money by hiring discount shippers to
take his produce to Market started doing
then he talked to Dean again we have a
checklist that we go through that'll
tell you uh the cleanliness of the of
the van and the temperature that we want
to ship our produce at so it's a whole
checklist and if you check for those
things if you use another shipper then I
think you'll be
okay over time Jim came to agree with
Dean's logic and adopted the same
policies now he follows a pre- shipment
checklist for all trucks and uses only
trucks that are clean and have
pre-tested refrigeration
equipment and this is a big day for Jim
and Louisa their first shipment of fresh
produce to new client Russell see you is
on its way okay so Jim are we ready to
go we are just close it up over there
and let's get them on our way
wonderful looks like a good shipment
absolutely finally all their hard work
is paid off
they're selling more lettuce and other
produce such as Tomatoes than they ever
did and they have a reputation as a
preferred
supplier Jim and Louisa know this is no
time to relax record keeping work
training and process monitoring will
always continue but now that the system
is set up and they can see the benefits
of their improved marketing position Jim
and Louisa are determined to maintain
their reputation as one of the best
producers in their industry
[Music]
the preceding was a production of New
Mexico State University the views and
opinions in this program are those of
the author and do not necessarily
represent the views and opinions of the
NMSU Board of Regents