[Music]
hey I'm Joe Watts plages barber County
here with gardener gun one of our 4-h
real gardeners family farm
tell me Gardner how many acres do y'all
have here ten thousand ten thousand and
hot what all do you grow here cotton
soybeans peanuts and we that is amazing
what we're gonna be talking mostly about
cotton today so come on with us to go on
our cotton adventure we drove about ten
minutes
on bumpy dirt roads through acres and
acres of corn that was planted earlier
this spring gardener explained that
Indians used to live in this area and
after plowing he can find pieces of
broken pottery in the fields here the
farmers are changing out the seed to try
a different variety farmers sometimes
experiment with different seeds to see
which type grows better the hoppers are
the yellow plastic bins that hold the
seed while they're empty the farmers
check the seed brushes which clean off
debris from cottonseed right before they
are dropped into the soil
[Music]
the farmer is better than the cotton
planner to another field and doesn't
have to travel on any main highways but
sometimes he has to next time you're in
a vehicle traveling slow behind a large
tractor like this you can be patient
because the farmers doing us a favor by
growing something we all need
did you know cotton is in the same plant
family as okra and did you know that
cotton has been grown in used for
thousands of years this spray is a
pesticide to help fight bugs and a
fertilizer to help the cotton grow this
planner plants twelve rows of the tongue
depositing two seeds every 13 inches it
will take around two months to plant
four thousand acres of cotton which will
be ready for picking in six to eight
months
[Music]
the plant will bloom with a white flower
that changes to pink as the bloom dries
a hard ball or a bowl is formed the soft
cotton emerges when this bowl cracks
open now it's time to pick the cotton
which will take about three to four
months with a great big huge machine
this is gardeners favorite piece of
equipment the cotton picker it won't be
used until the fall when the cotton is
ready to be picked these yellow
triangles cover up barbed spindles that
rotate quickly to pick the cotton the
black tubes blow it upward into the
basket when the basket gets full the
cotton is dumped into the back module
builder which presses it into a round
shape the cotton has been bailed and
wrapped the farmer decides when and
where to drop the module a round cotton
module can weigh six thousand pounds
that three tons are as much as an
elephant the modules will be taken to a
local gym to be separated into seed lint
and trash it will then be taken to a
warehouse and sold
[Music]
we asked gardener what is his favorite
part of living on such a large farm and
he said that he likes having plenty of
space to goof off with his buddies
you