are several types of small fruit and
berries that are produced in pop culture
in greenhouse an outdoor production
those crops include things such as
strawberries raspberries blueberries
crops like that
the ideal growing media for all the
various types of small fruit will depend
on basically the grower preference the
container size and the cultural
practices that they experience so
there's and the nice thing is with our
Pro mix product line we offer products
that can cater to these different needs
as I mentioned there are several mixes
that can apply to the specific needs of
a customer it depends on what your
specific needs are for instance if
you're looking to use a mix that you can
app inside the greenhouse for smaller
containers maybe gallon size or smaller
product that would probably work out for
you either the pro xvx mycorrhizae
which is combination of peat perlite and
vermiculite or the pro makes LP 15 which
is combination of peat and perlite both
products have high water high of high
water holding capacity so they don't dry
out very rapidly so they're great to use
during the summer months but they still
have good aeration they're lightweight
so they're easy to handle and for trent
and easy to transport now for still for
indoor production in small containers up
to much larger containers and especially
outdoor production we would recommend
some of our bark base growing media we
have two Canadian products the pro mates
BRK and PRK 20 as well as two products
from our plant in Matawan in Virginia
which would be our pro mix BK 25 in BK
55 all these products are peaked bark
based with perlite added and the idea of
having the bark in there is it gives a
little bit extra drainage so it's ideal
for transitioning not only for
greenhouse crop production but also for
the outdoor production of fruits and the
extra weight from the bark will also
prevent the pots from tipping over
especially in the wind so between the
bark and the perlite providing extra
drainage they're actually good mixes to
use even for the winter months as well
now bark mixes in general do tend to
draw a little bit faster than the bx and
even a little bit faster in the HP did I
mention
for so little so this will help minimize
any issues with diseases bark also is a
great material used for long-term crop
production another reason why it's good
for pots are larger than gallon size
because the bark itself doesn't shrink
in the pot or decomposes quickly another
option if you're looking for a
greenhouse mix or even an outdoor mix
that has very high water retention we
recommend our promix HP CC this is a
combination of peat chunk coir and
perlite and the chunk coir itself likes
to retain a lot of water and give it
back to the growing media as a crop is
growing so you don't need to water the
product as often so it's ideal
especially for summer growing in larger
containers especially indoors or
outdoors for organic production of small
fruit we recommend the pro mix MP MP is
a combination of peat core and perlite
it's ideal for year-round production of
small fruit and gallon sized containers
are smaller it does have a higher water
attention very similar to our B X and L
P 15 so there's less so it doesn't need
to be water quite as frequently
there is no compost added to this
product so you don't get that plugging
up the pores which kind of limits oxygen
to the root system so you get an active
growing root system which helps produce
faster growth and a faster crop time
now however what does make pro-mix
unique is not so much the different
types of mixes but the but the active
ingredients that we can add to it
the active ingredients are essentially
natural organisms that have been
extracted from the soil they're not
genetically modified so the first one we
offer is our mycorrhizae mycorrhizae is
a vesicular Arbus killer endo
mycorrhizal fungi called Glomus enter a
disease it will colonize small the roots
of small fruits of all plants except for
blueberries now in that case the micro
Zee doesn't cause any problems for the
blueberries the blueberries just simply
don't utilize it but for all the other
plants you're gonna get increased uptake
of nutrients because essentially once
the mycorrhizae colonizes the root
system it grows out past the root system
where roots are not present to bring in
water and nutrients where the roots are
not available therefore it more
efficiently mines out the growing media
for nutrients and for water so think of
mycorrhizae is kind of an extension of
the root system so what how does that
benefit you well first of all because it
can acquire the nutrients of water more
efficiently it delays the onset of
nutrient deficiency symptoms as well as
it delays the onset of wilting it also
increases resistance from environmental
stresses in addition to that and as a
result when you're transitioning maybe
from a smaller container size to a
larger size you don't see the transplant
shock delay that normally occurs and on
top of it you also get faster plant
establishment you get better initial
growth and better sustained growth
especially if there's stress involved
bottom line larger plants will produce
more fruit
the second active ingredient is our bio
fungicide it's a bacterium called
bacillus subsys it colonizes the root
system of all small fruit plants and
it's present throughout the entire crop
cycle of that plant it basically will
suppress root rots caused by the fungal
pathogens Alternaria Fusarium Pythium
and Rhizoctonia it will reduce fungicide
drenches by up to 50% so that's great
news whether you have to drench him
inside the greenhouse or if you're
growing them outside
in some cases that completely eliminates
a need for the fungicide drenches
because the root system is healthier so
the bottom line is you save money on
those fungicides they also helps to
reduce plant loss so obviously the lower
your plant losses the more plants you
have to sell and therefore you can
increase your crop production simply
from that fact alone and third would be
the combination of both the bio
fungicide and the mycorrhizae together
so there you will get the benefits of
both organisms in one product
you