hello everyone welcome back to the
channel in this video we're bringing you
the best Amazon garden tools and
accessories and these cool Tik Tok
videos will make you buy them if you
like the content please make sure to hit
the like And subscribe buttons as usual
you can find the links to all the
products in the description
below loan
away my new compact leaf blower has so
many uses in the garden but this one is
my favorite
[Music]
eight years of being a dad and his dad's
skills have peaked
[Music]
hello everybody today I'm going to show
you my favorite garden tool and how to
use it the one side has a serrated edge
the other side is a straight flat Edge
has measurements on the side so you see
how deep youin shovel down and I'm going
to show you how to use it first put our
gardian
gloves can't do that and so with the H
hor knife it's really nice to dig and
plant bulbs you can see that there are
inches so you have 1 2 3 4 5 5 six and
if you need to get a specific depth like
I need to dig 4 in you can easily go
ahead and do that dig up where you need
to
be and then you know your depth is 4 in
if you have rock out soil you can use a
straight edge and cut it up you can also
can cut weeds down really easily and
pick branches and get those cleared out
real quick are you tired of spending
endless hours pulling weeds like this in
your garden and having these same weeds
take away water nutrients from your
veggies and fruits I have a solution for
you this is called a sturup hoe some may
call it a hula ho I will show you what
it does follow me take a sturup ho just
drag it across the surface Yanks to weed
right up along with their Roots so if
you want your garden weedless like this
bed right here then get you a stpo save
you a bunch of time hit that plus sign
on the way out thanks for
[Music]
watching never forget to water your
garden or yard again how with a smart
hose timer like this orbit beehive it
connects to your phone or tablet so you
can water automatically at set times of
day you can even start and stop it
remotely without having to go out into
your yard best of all it'll use your
local weather data to not water when
it's raining saving you money it even
works with Amazon Alexa and Google
Assistant for voice control and all of
this functionality costs just 60 bucks
follow along for more cool smart home
gear and if you need help with your
smart home check out my concierge
service at the Lincoln bio today I'm
going to show you how to use the best
garden tool that I have in my backyard
this is called a tapener it's used to
tie up
plants all right so it's really simple
to use you just push down and it
extracts the tape you put it around
whatever you're trying to wrap up
squeeze and it Staples
it so it's got a refillable tape
dispenser and the stap going here and
it's really easy to
use and you can use it for anything from
cucumbers to
Tomatoes All right so I hope youall
enjoyed this tip and y'all can pick this
up on
[Music]
Amazon if you have a yard or Garden or
know someone who does you need to see
Grandpa's weeder this incredible tool
allows you to pick your weed standing up
eliminating the stress on your back and
knees this tool has been removing weed
since 1913 I could not believe how easy
and effective it was to use instructions
are right on the real bamboo handle
center of the weed press and lean its
unique head design grabs the weed and
pulls it out it's genius if you're a
weed puller and don't have this you'll
be saying where's this been all my life
incredible I love birds so I bought this
window bird feeder and filled it with
seeds and meal worms it took a while for
any bird to come but I stayed hopeful
and kept refilling the feeder and then I
managed to capture this special moment
these Stallings now visit
daily wordss started to build nests in
my window bird feeders but they all were
abandoned after they were nearly done I
guess it was to open or they got scared
off but not this pigeon she built a nest
not even half the size of the smaller
birds but said monay she late eggs
welcome to your new home for the next
couple months new
friends hey have you tried out this
amazing solar Fountain it is cordless
solar powered and has a built-in
submersible water
[Music]
pump it even has a backup battery to
store power and six bright LED lights so
it still works great at night
here's an amazing tool to use to weed
your garden this is called the hand
weeder here my mother-in-law is weeding
a Thistle and it's going to get the
whole root which is what you need to
really get rid of the weed so this tool
is great because it gets deep enough
into the
soil and the bend on the tool helps you
pivot and leverage the Earth to help get
the weat out and the fork at the end of
the tool helps grab the
weed this is an awesome tool must have
throw away that blunt hands
saw and try this portable electric
pruning
Shear it is cordless and lightweight and
will definitely make cutting your Lawns
tree branches a
breeze pair it with a compatible
extension pole to make cutting hard to
reach branches super easy
don't want to ruin your nail
varnish then this pair of garden claw
gloves is perfect for
you it's waterproof and has a breathable
design ideal for digging and quick
planting order yours in Amazon
now this t one garden naer and seat
works as both a garden naer and a garden
seat making it super convenient for you
to kneel down in your garden without
hurting your knees or back turn it over
and it becomes a perfect seat no
assembly required opens and closes
quickly easy for storage and carry holds
up to 300 lb get yours now link is in
the
description this tool is perfect for all
the gardening enthusiasts out there it's
the twoin one grafting tool pruning kit
perfect for fruit tree grafting it can
handle both can and rootstock it even
comes with with an extra set of blades
two paraffin tapes and a grafting knife
so get
grafting hey
there do you prefer to watch the clouds
or the
pruning order your very own trimmer now
on
Amazon Link in the
description I'd love you to watch again
and comment which is better the clouds
or the
pruning so which do you think is cooler
the solar fountain or the electric
pruning Shear comment down below if you
like the content we'd really appreciate
it if you can just hit the like And
subscribe buttons it's only going to
take a few seconds and it's totally free
but it helps the channel a whole lot
thanks and see you on the next video