hey Geto guys it's Wayne Perkins here
we're at the ataga Field Days uh in
ataga funny that and it's it's a cloudy
day but we're here with the Sol water
pump the react pump and um it's pumping
well it's done about 22,000 l so far for
the day we got two panels set up behind
it uh just want to give you a little bit
of information about the react pump um
it's capable of pumping up to about
10,000 l a day maybe a little bit more
depending on what we do with it on and
on the height so that's that's a pretty
good quantity and it's capable of uh
pumping to about 150 M head we can go
higher than that but the standard model
here will pump up to about 150 M head
that's kind of based on the amount of
water is based on how high we need to
pump it uh few options with it we
basically this is the two panel system
we can put four panels on it or six
panels which basically maximizes the
amount of water you can get out of it uh
so the the two panel system it'll pump
um it'll pump that 150 M head but it's
going to struggle on the cloudy days or
days that aren't so good
uh so with with the four Panel System
what we're doing is we we're giving you
more water on the good days but we're
giving you a lot more water on the bad
days we just got a lot more we can grab
a lot more power from the sky so hey
look if you're interested if you need to
get water to your stock on your farm or
whatever um you know Keen to have a chat
to you just give me a call love to hear
from you and we want we want to go
through and we want to talk through the
process with you we we're going to want
to know how high you need to pump the
water we're going to want to need know
over what distance and on on average per
day how much water you need and out of
that there we'll start working with you
on figuring out whether this pump or one
of one of our other pumps uh we'll do
the job for you so um if you're in the
market for some clock water and you
haven't got any electricity give me a
call love to hear from you