chicken you're not coming in the house
uh admiring modern status help these
chickens don't trip me man they're awful
pushy in the morning wanting in the
house let's say another beautiful one
out this morning 50 degrees and it's
supposed to be 87 for a high tomorrow
Figaro didn't want to come in last night
but I think I am yeah at the door this
morning good morning mister you pulled
an all-nighter
[Music]
[Applause]
mixed so you don't get any strings
[Music]
I can hear the goats Livi's they're
calling yeah
you just never know what you're gonna be
doing on a farm
one minute you're cooking banana bread
[Music]
now as long as we have this covered up
or mixed in with enough wood chips wood
shaving straw hay carbon you're not
going to smell anything and it's going
to compost nicely
is it nice over here links on a nice
cool spot yeah
now pigs like to go to the bathroom in
one spot which is good and bad it's easy
to clean up it's nice to get stinky in
that area if you don't keep carving
there that you can pick up and haul off
[Music]
I gave you a fresh bedding to play with
that stuff you're supposed to go to the
bathroom on one of the great things
about having pigs and chickens is when
you're empty a refrigerator for the week
haul when you're baking and cooking with
real food you got all your food scraps
pigs and chickens you guys are so noisy
there's enough for you to be able to
have your own side of the pile but they
want to be right next to each other or
you like them banana pails
[Music]
good stuff huh
they smell good don't they well I try
setting up an area for the goats to go
run around in while we're home but they
can eat brush and clear up this area for
us what are you thinking the chickens
sausage you like Calvin right there so
if your marriage can withstand putting
up an electric ultra netting it can
withstand anything here hey this is not
pain in the butt to do that's what I'm
trying to say you see a struggle
[Music]
put out
what do you need me to do just be
patient
[Music]
right here
the heart spar there
the Huq of this made out of cement
sunspots the arts and sponsors
[Music]
good luck nice life
I don't think you are supposed to be in
here do you think they're supposed to be
in here
I don't are they getting in your
territory huh I leave your territory huh
you don't care you're a happy pig I do a
happy pig huh
all right we got it fenced in all the
way around through the grove of apple
trees they got some raspberry bushes in
there your interesting to see what it
looks like after they're in there for a
few days we're only gonna let them out
when we're home and we don't have time
this afternoon to let them out
unfortunately but tomorrow we'll be able
to let them out and see how much fun
they have right spaghetti
[Music]
they fly do they they fight on to the
feeder hey guys where'd you go hey guys
lazy butts I'll call wake them up way
down here sleeping on top of each other
what are you girls doing
we're piggies there you go
well you think you're a goat and you
guys stay inside the fence you girls
need to stop playing with your ball the
race it's got some cucumbers peels for
you oh she likes it
willow gets it all you want to try a
possum nope
willows too fast this is where we gotta
end today's video tomorrow let the goats
out and see what they do with all the
brush and shrubs under the apple tree
and we'll see you guys right back here
tomorrow
[Music]