[Music]
my name is Arrow Rella and we're at
nessen kig Farm in Lichfield New
Hampshire Southern New Hampshire this is
a mixed vegetable farm uh 35 to 40 acres
of uh vegetable crops and it's a
certified organic farm and I've been
here 17 years so the vegetables uh that
I grow here primarily uh direct sales to
restaurants and uh specially food
purveyors that sell to restaurants and
hotels a lot of culinary herbs salad
greens uh more exotic things uh relate
to uh Asian crops because most of my
workers are are Southeast Asian
basically cover crops are the foundation
of the farm an organic system one of the
ideas is to feed the soil that if you
take care of your soil then you're going
to have healthy plants that are going to
come from that here where this Farm is
in Southern New Hampshire uh found that
the best way for me to add biomass
organic matter into my soil to feed my
soil comes from utilizing green manure
crops we don't have access to animal
manur in this part of the state I'm
using two different
uh GRE manure crops and and uh they're
used a little
differently um start out in the Spring
areas that either I have bare soil or
it's winterkill crops from the previous
year I couldn't get into a fall seated
cover crop I put in peas and oats and
and peas and oats is is quick growing
cover crop for the current growing
season and um and then starting in
August and September as I take pieces
out of production and vegetables that
were seeded that year then I'll seed
fields to uh uh winter rye and hary
vetch as soon as I can get on the ground
I'll seed uh fuel peas and oats spin it
on and then lightly Harrow it in and one
of the things I really like about it is
that also brings in early income my
earliest income in the spring because uh
the young peash shoots are very popular
with the restaurant trade and also with
uh Southeast Asian our Asian Chefs and
usually within about four to six weeks
of seating I have something I can start
to harvest that's a really good starter
for the
springtime the P tendrils or PE shoots P
tips different names for it it's not
something you can sell tons T and tons
per acre I have tons of it in fact
that's one one of the reason I'm growing
it for is the biomass of the nitrogen
that the peas are fixing that so that's
but um on a normal year I probably can
realize grow sales between uh say8 and
$110,000 on uh five to 7 Acres that
might be seated to fuel peas and oats
so what we have here is a strip that I
started uh it was a strip of Harry Veet
and Rye I started turning over probably
uh mid April and everything was broken
down enough that I was able to
transplant my tomato plants probably
about the third week in May and um
meanwhile the Ryan vetch on the beds
next to it we're continuing to uh to
grow
just about at this stage is the point
where you want to knock it down what I'm
looking for is for the vet to start to
go to flower or the the ride to be a
pollen stage and what I like to do
ideally is to culate once with my
tractor and then I'll knock it down with
with the mower and then once it's down
we'll use the straw as a mulch for the
tomato plants and then we'll bring in
some uh some steaks and do a basket weed
system to bring uh you know trellising
for the tomatoes up out of the mulch I'm
utilizing the uh Straw from the strips
to start with the mulching process but I
try to have a block of of uh Ryan vet
nearby as you can see behind here and
I'll mow that down as I start to mulch
these I'll have a good uh a good close
by area where I can bring in more mulch
without taking a lot of Labor removing
mulch from one area another area of the
farm I look at the cover crops as as
biomass I mean two things that are very
important for the farm is nitrogen from
the fixing of nitrogen and the legum
that's part of the GRE manure and
biomass is very important so I want to
maximize my biomass which is bring it to
full maturity strip system was Harry V
and Ry overwintered and then cutting
strips in the in the springtime I use it
for wide space crops or crops that I
choose to grow in a wide space and that
may not traditionally be grown wide
spacing but uh pumpkins and winter
squash easy to plant and 10-ft centers
that work works very well and so I can
have 5ft wide beds with uh the adjacent
5ft wide strip of the Harry Veet and Rye
Tomatoes I have wide spacing so I can
get a good air flow for uh for
disease what we're doing here with green
manure cover crops is I'm using them to
uh confuse Colorado potato beetles I cut
strips plant the potatoes I try to do my
uh weed cultivation and healing so that
the potato plants are are well
established and then at that stage I
knock down the Ryan vet and usually by
then it's late June early July and
that's the first the potato beetles even
come into the field I don't need to have
a big Mulch on the ground like I would
put on the tomatoes I just want to have
some contact with the straw on the
potato plants with this
method uh I've never had to spray more
than twice and uh for potato
beetles and and and at best it's a spot
spraying I don't spray the whole field
because good portions of the field there
won't be any potato beetles at all it's
usually on an edge of where they'll come
in to the end of the rows or an edge of
where a field of Sol acious crops were
the preceding year and they'll find a
few a few rows
this is my sper which is the uh primary
tillage tool on the farm I use it for
incorporating pretty much all of my
cover crops it uh needs to operate at
slow speed and so that's you know one
disadvantage is that when you're
bringing that organic matter in the soil
and that I can't move very fast because
it's a lot of biomasses chopping in
there but once it's in the ground and
I've made a couple of passes then I can
go in with a Fiel culator and do a very
rapid pass make a nice smooth seed bed
and then I'm ready to
go it's like a number of shovels and
just cuts clouds does a good job of of
chopping the straw into the soil but you
get nice clouds in that and and then
over time that they can break down
slowly so it's much gentler on your soil
structure and doesn't oxidize all that
organic matter you're trying to bring
into the soil when I first came here
there was a rototiller so that's what I
learned on for primary tillage but uh I
really didn't like what it did the soil
really beat the soil up like an egg
beater and I and I heard about uh spers
being much better for soil structure and
better at incorporating biomass not
oxidizing it so this seemed to be a much
better Implement for improving my soil
quality and that's really you know
important for me is is uh doing the best
I can for my soil