this is sweet potatoes that we had just
planted okay um we planted some of them
a week ago and then the ones that are
being irrigated now we planted yesterday
okay and it's very important if you
don't get rain after you're planting to
to if you don't have irrigation it's it
makes it real difficult for the for the
plants to get get established after you
PLS so this is a pump
see how far you got a dig Bill before
you get any moisture not even hitting it
yet so that rain is really critical
right now very critical
so some people go to Las Vegas to gamble
and you choose to farm I guess huh
that's exactly
right well so here's the potatoes that
we get at the farmers
market nice
tell me a little bit about then what
you've done what you've done here since
the last time I was out here um actually
all we've had to do is cultivate them
several times okay and um that's to get
the weeds out and along with getting the
weeds out it pulls the runners from the
sweet potatoes so they don't set down
okay and it gives you a better set under
the hill okay so there's two benefits to
cultivating getting the weeds out along
with pulling the runners back in so they
don't if you get a lot of Runners it's
set down then it takes size away from
the sweet
potatoes so this is called a potato
Harvester that's a potato Harvester and
how does it work um it just it runs on
hydraulic rather than rather than PTO
it's got a hydraulic pump and does it
have does it go down dig or yeah you
just set it whatever depth you want okay
and with sweet potatoes as you see once
we get digging we have to go rather deep
with it okay all right so they don't get
skimmed up
okay so these are the ones for tomorrow
yes there'll be for Saturday market for
Saturday
market you wash them before you put them
in the
crates
wow
okay do you have any to wash oh this is
where you wash them right here right
here don't have one of those fancy
washers you do this all by hand oh yes
this
and then we'll dump them back
in
okay so these are all sweet potatoes yes
and then where where will these go
they'll go into that uh storing uh
trailer behind the shed okay and they
this is just how they're stored right
right Donald store them cure them and
then store them for the winter
you
oh
a