again historically drainage was just
thought of as getting rid of water as as
uh quickly and as efficiently as you
could uh to make the the crop ground
more productive but more recently with
some of the more climate streams that
we've seen where we still have those wet
intense uh Springs with intense
rainfalls but maybe the drier Summers
where we're actually seeing some crop
stress and yield loss due to not enough
precipitation uh we're looking at more
of a multi-purpose practice of drainage
water recycling where we're still
draining the agricultural lands but
instead of just draining all of that
water Downstream we're C capturing some
of it and storing it uh in a pond or
reservoir uh and then later on in the
season in the summer when it's maybe a
little drier and the crop uh needs more
water the land owner can then utilize
that captured water to irrigate it back
on uh to their Farmland so this is a
really exciting uh new type of project
um that we're seeing a lot of momentum
in