pest risk analysis is the process of
evaluating biological or other
scientific and economic evidence to
determine whether an organism is a pest
if it should be regulated and the
strength of any phytosanitary measures
to be taken against it
[Music]
it is a science-based process that
provides the rationale for determining
appropriate phytosanitary measures to
protect the plant resources of a
specified area
pest risk analysis is one of the
available tools for agriculture trade
food security and the environment as it
helps countries to protect their plant
resources from pests and fulfill their
international obligations
pest risk analysis is conducted to
evaluate and manage risks from specific
pests and internationally traded
commodities it identifies and assesses
risks to agricultural and horticultural
crops forestry and the environment from
plant pests
[Music]
it impacts all aspects of a country's
plant protection or plant quarantine
program because it provides the
information needed to determine an
appropriate course of action in a given
situation
it can be regarded as a process to
answer these questions
is the organism a pest
what is the likelihood of the pests
introduction establishment and spread
how much economic damage including
environmental and social will it cause
what can be done to mitigate
unacceptable impacts
pest risk analysis supports various
types of national or sub-national
programs including surveillance programs
eradication programs establishing
pest-free areas and supporting exports
of agricultural commodities to other
countries
however the most common application of
pest risk analysis is to establish
appropriate import requirements to
prevent the introduction and spread of
regulated pests
pest risk analysis is a useful means of
evaluating and informing various types
of policy to predict likely outcomes
evaluate efficacy or provide other
insights into policies and programs
administered by national plant
protection organizations
these should adopt international
standards for phytosanitary measures and
pest risk analysis as a key part of the
decision-making process when it comes to
establishing phytosanitary measures and
regulations for plants and plant
products
national plant protection organizations
use pest risk analysis for a variety of
reasons
analyzing risks associated with pathways
including commodities
analyzing risks associated with specific
pests
[Music]
providing analytical support for new or
revised policies
much of the work that a national plant
protection organization must carry out
can be supported by pest risk analysis
from making decisions on how to spend
resources to deciding on phytosanitary
measures for imported commodities
visit the international phyto-sanitary
portal at www.ippc.int
to find resources on pest risk analysis
such as guides training materials and
more
access the fao elearning academy at
elearning.fao.org
for free e-learning courses
[Music]
you