[Music]
my name is Angela Fraley I'm an agent
associate at the University of Maryland
here with my colleague Carol Allen who
is the other agent associate at the
University of Maryland and we are both
food safety educators so our job is to
provide all the growers in Maryland the
education that you guys need and want
and the technical assistance that you
also need to be able to navigate these
murky waters of food safety both in
audits and in the federal regulations so
today hopefully I'm going to be
demystifying some parts of this and
giving you some updates from the work
that the Maryland Department of Ag and
we have done in the last year to get you
ready for the produce safety rule so has
anyone gone through a third party audit
process in this room one got a GAAP
certification couple okay a couple
coughs education has anyone had a PSR
inspection this year from MDA okay is
anyone a little bit confused about how
those two things are different the PSR
and the gap okay good good all right
well not we're hopefully I will give you
tips and tricks to try and negotiate
both of those things and it is kind of
hard to think about what the differences
are between the two because at their
core they try and get at one they try
and address one issue right so both of
them outline practices for you to
minimize the microbial hazards on your
farm but there are a lot of differences
between the two one is a voluntary
process that you could undergo and one
is a federal regulation so in this talk
we're going to start with kind of
looking at the differences between the
two then I'm gonna get a little bit into
how to negotiate the audit process if
you are interested in getting a GAAP
certification this year then we're going
to transition and talk about what's been
going on in terms of the produce safety
rule this year how we're getting farmers
ready what we're seeing on the ground in
Maryland and just as to let you guys
know you
they're doing really well so far MDA is
really pleased with how farmers in
Maryland are farming and how they're
getting ready for the produce safety
rule so both of them require similar
things
they both outline different ways to
minimize microbial hazards on the farm
and they're focused on the farm elements
that we know affect your product quality
and safety the most so that's all the
workers that interact with your product
that's the water that you use to
irrigate your product and wash your
product and cool your product if so
that's also any soil amendments that
you're using on the farm that's how you
clean and sanitize the tools that you
have on the farm and the equipment that
you have on the farm and it also
outlines practices for how to deal with
wildlife and other animals on the farm
because we know that all of those things
are really important in terms of your
your finished product quality and safety
and so you might be thinking in your
seat right now okay well if they both do
most of the same things why do we need
both or why do we need either so why
would you need either right having a
formalized food safety plan and food
safety culture on your farm is not only
helpful to minimize those microbial
risks but it also opens up market access
for you guys if you formalize the plan
and get a GAAP certification and then
furthermore we do know that a lot of the
practices that we do from food safety on
the farm are also really good
horticultural practices too so they also
not only minimize your microbial human
pathogen risk but also in some cases
plant pathogen risk as well so it's
always good to double dip now why both
so as I had mentioned before the gap
program is a voluntary program the FISMA
PSR is a mandatory program buyers right
now are only focused on the gap program
because that's the only thing that gives
you a paper certificate that a buyer can
see and it's very unlikely in the next
few years that buyers are going to go
with anything food safety without a
paper certificate attached to it right
so the GAAP certifications are the only
thing that's going to give you a
a paper assurance that you can hand to a
buyer and that allows you to open up
market access to different buyers but
it's also why both is also important
because if you do gaps and you follow
good agricultural practices you get you
get a third party audit it's very likely
that you're well on your way to getting
ready for the produce safety rule so we
like to say that the GAAP certification
is like a stepping stone to the produce
safety rule and in some cases depending
on what sort of GAAP audit you want to
target if you are following all of those
all those standards in that particular
gap audit you're actually already
completely aligned with the produce
safety rules so when you can double dip
please do so because we don't want you
to duplicate efforts in any way so a
little bit into how they're different
this is only going to touch on a few
things of how they're different if you
are interested in reading how the GAAP
audits and the produce safety rule
inspections are really different
University of Maryland extension and the
agricultural law education initiative
came up with this really great handout
that goes into a lot of detail into the
differences in the similarities they're
available I have them here I'll have
them in the back table across the wall
over here if you would like to take and
read some more they're also available
online because there are a lot of links
associated with this table as well but
as I mentioned before number one the gap
audit program is a voluntary program
dictated by what your buyer market wants
and the produce safety rule is mandatory
under the produce safety rule also a
Maryland Department of Ag is rolling out
a registration for growers so every
grower in the state of Maryland is going
to have to register with the Maryland
Department of Ag and that's just so the
Maryland Department of Ag can kind of
figure out where they need to put you in
terms of when you're gonna be inspected
in the produce safety rules so if you're
a grower that's growing under five
hundred thousand dollars worth of
produce you're going to be inspected
either this year or the next year
but if you're a grower who it has not
been inspected yet and is growing over
five hundred thousand dollars with the
produce once you get registered you're
going to be put up in the priority list
for an MDA inspection and
not scary at all we'll get into them at
the at the end of this at the end of
this at the end of this talk so covered
produce so again because the GAAP audit
is a voluntary program you dictate to
the auditor what sort of products you
want gap certified so if you are a
farmer and you have apples and you have
kale for pick-your-own and then you have
sweet corn you can choose to just get a
gap audit and a gap certification just
for the apples so that the auditor only
goes out and takes a look at what the
practices are with your apples that's
different from the produce safety rule
the produce safety rule MDA
inspector is going to come out and take
a look at your practices that pertain to
all the crops that are eaten raw on your
on your property so in that same example
of having apples and kale and sweet corn
they're gonna look at the apples and the
kale because both of those are eaten raw
and they're not going to be as they're
not going to look at your practices
regarding sweet corn so exemptions to
this rule the next part down here under
the voluntary program you can be exempt
based on what your buyer what your buyer
requirements are so there I know I do
know some buyers in some grocery stores
will allow you to start selling to them
if you don't have an audit yet but with
a written assurance that you're going to
get an audit in the next year so so you
could kind of work with your buyer on
the expectations they have with you
exemptions on the produce safety rule
because this is a federal regulation the
exemptions are real complicated and real
murky and every single one of them has a
record associated with it so I'm gonna
just briefly talk about it here but if
you think that you might be exempt or if
you think that you might be qualified
exempt to talk to me after this talk or
we could talk to Carol as well so if
you're a farm that's growing under
27,000 dollars worth of produce a year
you can be exempt and there is a
registration associated with each one of
these right so there's registration
associated with if you're growing under
twenty seven thousand five hundred and
twenty eight dollars of produce it's
adjusted for inflation each year which
is our job to keep up on so we can let
you know if you if all the produce on
your farm is all going to further
there's a specific exemption for that so
let us know if you're growing all you're
growing is spinach and it's getting
canned let us know we can direct you to
the right registration form to fill out
for that the last one is if everything
you're growing on your farm is just as
not eaten raw so if you're just doing a
whole farm full of winter squash for
some reason then you can be that crop is
rarely eaten raw and there's another
potential exemption that you can apply
for for that okay so those are the
exemptions if you are a farmer that may
find yourself in the category of selling
between twenty seven thousand dollars a
year in produce and five hundred and
fifty five hundred and fifty one
thousand dollars 550 550 one yeah
mmm-hmm that that one is important so if
you're between twenty seven and five
hundred and fifty then you could
potentially be under a qualified
exemption that you could apply for a
qualified exemption so in addition to
your produce sales if you're in that
bracket you're going to also want to
roll in any other food sales that you
have so that involves any livestock that
you're selling any jams or jellies that
you're selling as well so you roll in
all the other food that you're selling
and who that food is being sold to so it
gets very complicated we're not going to
go into it at this talk but if you think
that you are between 27 and 550 of
produce and you think you want to apply
for a qualified exemption then come talk
to me afterwards we'll get you all
situated basically what you're going to
have to do is keep sales records of all
the food you're selling and who you're
selling it to to maintain to MDA that
you are still within this structure to
be qualified exempt and you'll have to
keep those records for three years okay
or you can just choose to be fully
covered and you will be in the bank of
farms that MDA will come out and inspect
if you don't want to go through all that
all that record-keeping you can choose
to do that as I mentioned before
with with the voluntary audit you are
gonna get a paper certificate of
compliance and this is what buyers
really like to see and there's no sort
of paper certificate of compliance
associated with a PSR inspection other
general differences if anyone's familiar
who is familiar with the food safety
plan who has written a food safety plan
okay cool
all right okay so for your GAAP audits
you have to have a written food safety
plan that an auditor will come and take
a look at what sort of practices
policies and procedures you have in
place on your farm and for the produce
safety rule it's not really required to
do that but it's recommended because it
just keeps everybody more organized and
it keeps the inspector on your farm for
a shorter amount of time if you have
everything organized into a written plan
for trace back and recall some of the
audits outline that you should have a
trace back and recall plan so this means
that you have a lot system for your
products and you know you can trace it
back from where it was in the field and
trace it forward to where it's going to
specific buyers so some audits require
that the MDA gap audit does not which is
the baseline type of audit that you can
get it's it this is also not required
for the produce safety rule unless
you're doing some on-farm processing
like making ciders or jams or jellies or
something like that the record-keeping
is various between the two there are six
required records for the produce safety
rule and we'll get into what is needed
on those records in a little bit and
when we get there I would recommend that
everybody take a look and just add the
things that are required for the produce
safety rule on whatever record that you
are already doing so that you don't have
to create two records for the same thing
right there are some easy ways that you
can comply with the produce safety rule
with things that you already have and
then just kind of rounding us out the
produce safety rule is just focused on
microbial hazards it doesn't talk about
chemical and physical hazards
however in audits you're going to have
to want to keep a record of the
pesticide applicator license and other
Burbidge about how you're mitigating
chemical and physical hazards
okay so into the different gap audits
that you can pursue if you would like to
depending on if you want to open up
market access to different buyers and
different wholesale opportunities they
range from less intensive to most
intensive and the different the
intensity of the audit kind of just goes
with how many more paper records you're
gonna have to keep the practices are
very very similar among all of these as
I had mentioned before they all outline
practices around workers fertilizer
water quality maintaining and testing
water quality your cleaning and
sanitizing schedules for your tools
equipments and your building how you're
inspecting different trucks that are
coming onto your property to haul
produce temperature controls and
monitoring for animals so if you have
not done a gap audit before and you
would like to get into this world of gap
audits I would really recommend starting
with an MDA gap
it requires the least amount of records
in the least amount of time to get you
started it's very likely that you're
already doing most of these practices
that is outlined in an MDA gap audit you
just got to write it all down in a way
that an auditor can take a look at and
give you a passing grade on right and
there's also some records required to it
getting getting used to starting to put
records together is is a bit of a hurdle
but once your rips once your started
with records it's a lot easier to keep
going with record-keeping if you're
interested in some of these more intense
audits they're going to include
different parts and a produce safety and
a produce safety plan some of them
require written risk assessments so how
you know when you're going out to a
field it's ready for harvest some of
those audits require a record associated
with I know my field is now ready for
harvest again it's things that you're
already doing the auditor just wants it
in paper form now which is quite
laborious I definitely understand that
they also want things outlined like
different defense plans corrective
action plans so again something that
you're probably already doing you
probably already have a plan in place
for if a port-a-potty falls over or if
you see a worker who is just not washing
their hands ever right what the plan in
place is that you're going to go over to
that person and retrain them right and
in these different
audits they're there in these more
intense audits they're just asking that
that's written down and formalized in
paragraph form which Carol and I can
help you do if you are interested in
getting an audit so MDA can come out and
perform any of these audits here there
they're not going to come out and
perform the global gap on it but MDA can
come out and perform all these audits
and in 20 the twenty twenty year is a
good time to get an audit done because a
lot of those because of MDA has found
funds for them to be either free or for
you to get reimbursed so the MDA gap on
it is free if you'd like to get an H gap
on it there's 100% reimbursement on that
audit so it's also free you can get cost
share for any group cat op group gap
audits you're looking to get and if you
are interested in the harmonized gaps
there is a reimbursement for the first
four hundred dollars of certification
and seventy-five percent of costs over
four hundred dollars so this year is a
good year to pursue this because I'm not
sure if these funds are going to be
available in next year's so now is the
time to do it
um the stars over here go to the fact
that some of these audits are fully
aligned with the produce safety rule
meaning that if you're completing all of
these things for this particular audit
you're also aligned for everything
underneath the produce safety rule and
then also for those bigger farmers if
you are selling to a larger grocery
store like Wegmans or Walmart or if you
would like to sell internationally there
are audits that MDA can perform for you
that are global GFCI equivalent global
food safety initiative equivalent so
that's available to you alright so if
you're sitting in your seat and you're
saying okay this is all well and good
but I don't know what the steps to
actually get this done are the first
thing that you're going to need to do is
designate it be someone's job on the
farm to be a food safety officer and
that person is going to be record man
number one unfortunately or fortunately
if they like records right so and then
we
you go to a food safety training you
have that appointed person go to a food
safety training there are multiple
throughout the state of Maryland that
we're doing this year we do them every
winter however if we get a quorum of
farmers who are like we would like a gap
class in the fall we would also hold one
in the fall it's based on availability
and interest so you'll go to a food
safety training you'll start writing
down the guts of your food safety plans
as I mentioned before these are all your
written policies they're gonna be your
records they're gonna be any SOPs that
you have and they're gonna be any risk
assessments that you're making and any
plans that you have in place in case
things go wrong so that is all included
in the guts of a food safety plan you'll
keep things like your pesticide
applicator license in there you'll keep
things like your water testing report in
there risk assessments as I had said
before then what you're going to want to
do is start trying to see how what you
wrote down is actually aligning with the
practices you do on your farm because
auditors will the audit goes off of
based what you're writing down that
you're saying so if you're writing it
down you should do it and if it's
something that you're not doing on your
farm don't write it down because that's
a way that an auditor will ding you
right they've grade you off based off of
what you're saying you're doing it's
also a good idea to have a day where
you're a mock auditor yourself and you
go out to your workers and you see if
they're following the practices that
you're you wrote down that you said
you're doing and it gives you a little
bit of an opportunity to kind of self
evaluate and augment the plan or your
records or anything before an auditor
comes and then you want to schedule and
pass a third party on it when can you
call Carroll or myself to help you
through this you can call us during
almost every single part of the process
we cannot be the auditor for you
unfortunately we would love to be but if
you have any questions about how to
develop SOPs if you want second eyes
reviewing a food safety plan if you're
not sure how to write a food safety plan
please get up with us we can definitely
help you because it's having a written
food safety plan is a great way to grow
your business so you can get a bunch of
templates online for food safety plans
the MDA has a template food safety plan
that's a good plug and chug
there's also for those growers who are
interested in h gap a more stringent
type of gap audit there's a template
from the well there's a handbook on how
to write your plan from the carolina
farm stewardship Association there's
also a good plug and chug template from
the produce safety Alliance that I can
send to Mike and he could send out to
people if they're interested that's
another really good plug and chug one
hmm
yeah yeah that's pretty safe do you like
well yeah it's Cornell the Cornell gap
program yes Thank You Carol as I had
mentioned before keep it simple and easy
to follow structure it based on what the
auditor how the auditor is gonna go
through your farm so there are different
scopes that are required in each of the
the audits and just have your verbage
structured exactly like that because you
don't want that person on your farm any
longer than they need to be use tables
liberally like when you don't have to
write a paragraph you don't need to you
can use a table if it's easier and other
sort of conventions like bolding as I
mentioned before it's not a wish list so
just write down everything that you are
doing and things that you're not doing
don't write it down and make sure even
with these if you're using a plug and
chug that you're erasing the things that
are not happening on your farm or if
they cover a different type of crop
you're making sure that it's tailored to
the crop that you are writing the plan
for so this is a great way it's an
example to put verbage in a food safety
plan that covers many different phases
at once into paragraphs and feel free to
take a picture of this I got this from
Penn State and it talks about animal
control so if you see here they have a
couple of elements that I think are
really nice all in two paragraphs they
have the written policy about what they
do for animals we do all that we can to
keep up domestic and wild animals out of
the fields right so that's a check check
mark off that they have a monitoring log
they reference a monitoring log in here
right we routinely monitor the growing
area and the results are recorded in our
monitoring log they have because this is
off of a more stringent audit this is
not often
MDA gap audit they have an allusion to a
written risk assessment again if you're
going for an MD a gap audit this does
not need to be in here but they talk
about that they include an inspection
for the presence of animals during your
pre harvest risk assessment and then
they also outline the plan that they're
going to enact in case something other
than something non normal happens so if
they find significant evidence of poop
in the field they outline that what they
do is mark off the area with a buffer
and they don't harvest crop within that
buffer and it's removed so this is a
really efficient way to get all of the
elements of a food safety plan in
paragraph form and I would really
recommend working off this template
because it's it's just the easiest way
to do it and care a lot Carol and I have
experience in this it can help you help
you move through this kind of on records
as I mentioned before take a look at all
the records that you have right now and
we would recommend just making them
produce safety rule compliant and to
make them produce safety rule compliant
you're just going to have to add a
couple of these little elements here
you're going to want to add on all of
your records the name and address of
your farm all the records have to be
done at the dated at the exact time that
they're done the date is sufficient they
also go to in in different things like
cleaning and sanitizing produce safety
rule records want you to outline what
methods you're using so you in this
example it is writing out what the
method is but we all know we don't have
time for that so what you can do instead
is you could reference an SOP up top
here and you could just reference like
everyone was trained in this specific
way to clean and sanitize things
reference the SOP and this could be a
check mark you could say clean and
sanitizing harvest knives SOP right the
other thing that produce safety records
need is that they are at the end of the
record you know you have your worker
signing them and at the end of the
record the food safety officer is going
to want to review them title them and
date them alright so what can Carol and
I help you with well we can help you
write your food safety plan we can help
review your food safety plan we
take a look at your practices that
you're doing on the farm you can have us
out we can take a look and prioritize
what different things you're going to
want to target for this year and your
food safety goals we can help you
interpret water test results or get your
water testing program started if you
haven't already started it and then
furthermore we can also help you devise
a cleaning and sanitizing program for
different tools and equipment on your
farm so if you're not sure what things
you should be cleaning and sanitizing or
how often you should be doing it or how
you need to be recording it or if it's
effective let us know and we could come
out and help you with that there are
also a bunch of resources both around
the country and in Maryland that you
could take advantage of to help you with
your food safety goals as I mentioned
there's a template for pretty much
anything you could ever want there are a
lot of signs that we made and some of
these signs suffice the recommendation
or sorry the requirements for the
produce safety rule there's a visitor
sign so especially those of you who have
picked your owns I would recommend
getting one of these signs so this
outlines the policies that a visitor
should be following when they come to
your farm it talks about not picking one
stick not bringing their pets not
bringing food and drink into the field
washing their hands and farm kids safety
I think it says on here plants are not
toys which I really like so I have these
available out here I have like six
available and we can order more so
they're all free for you for taking if
you would like to have one we have other
signs as well also we have worker
training supplements so the produce
safety rule not only wants you to show
the Cornell video to have all your
workers trained in hygiene but they also
want your workers trained in doing their
specific jobs so Maryland Department of
Ag actually came up with four
powerpoints and videos that are in
English in Spanish both for harvest
training post harvest training working
with animals and general food safety so
you can show these to your workers and
that will suffice the other requirement
of training for the produce safety rule
and then we can also provide the
resource of trail tailored training to
your needs that's where the the survey
comes in so the our survey is the yellow
one in your little booklet
we really appreciate if you fill this
out this lets us know what types of
training topics you would like to have
in this area and we're in this area is
most convenient for you for us to come
train so please fill this out I'll be
collecting these at lunchtime all right
back with the PSR compliance dates for
the produce safety rule so if you're a
grower that's growing over 500,000 worth
of product expect that the MDA will be
calling you soon to get an inspection if
you're a grower that is growing between
two hundred fifty thousand dollars of
product and five hundred thousand
dollars a product this year is the year
that you're going to be inspected and
then small businesses between 25 and 250
you've got till next year again as I
mentioned in the top if you think if
you're someone that's between 27,000 and
$500,000 worth of produce and you think
you might want to apply for this
exemption I would recommend start
keeping sales records now of the food
and produce that you're selling and who
it's getting sold to because MDA the
Maryland Department of Ag is gonna want
to take a look at those records next
year so what is MDA and Carol and I
currently doing to help everybody get
ready for the produce safety rule
we're holding PSR trainings so the
produce safety rule trainings these are
a federal requirement that were every
food safety officer in a farm goes to
one of these trainings we have one
coming up in McHenry Maryland which is
all the way west so that will be the end
of these trainings for this year but let
us know if you would like one over here
in the late fall we could start doing
that for you or when else would be
efficient and effective for you guys to
get a training we are conducting on-farm
readiness reviews so an on-farm
readiness review is a confidential
program that Maryland Department of Ag
and the University of Maryland is doing
where we come out to your farm and we
take a look at your practices and we can
let you know where you're already
aligning and things you need to
prioritize to align better with the
produce safety rule it's completely
confidential and we don't take any
written notes off of the farm we keep
them all with you and on the whole
Maryland's been doing real
well with these 86% of Maryland farms
only needed to have minor changes but
before they were completely aligned with
the produce safety rule and those minor
changes are usually red tape things like
the stuff on their records and doing a
water distribution assessment writing
that down so again a lot of formal
things but on the whole you guys are
doing really well and we really commend
you for keeping food safety in the
forefront of your goals as I mentioned
before MDA is inspecting the largest
farms this year they are only none of
these inspections are unannounced
they're always gonna call you up unless
you are not returning their calls then
they might show up but they have not the
only thing that they're citing to the
FDA are any egregious conditions that
they find on the farm and they have not
found any egregious conditions in the
state of Maryland which is great they
are providing you a summary report
that's a non-federal document and that's
just a report of things that you can
work on this next year and that's just
for people who are getting inspected
what's been happening so I was able to
get this information from one of the
inspectors Alec lenka from the MDA and
he let us know the different things that
need some work in general in Maryland
for this next year so common
observations that he saw when he was out
doing produce safety rule inspections is
that just to keep in mind we really want
you to be aware of all your tools and
equipment that our food contact surfaces
and we want you to devise cleaning and
sanding tips cleaning and sanitizing
schedules for those tools and equipment
and it doesn't have to be after every
use this is at this is a schedule based
on what the frequency you determine is
so it can be every month it can be once
a season it's based on what works for
your farm different cleaning procedures
we're still feeling seeing a lot of
people just spray sanitizer on a dirty
belt and just say that that's what their
cleaning procedure is and we really want
you to follow a four-step process of
cleaning with a detergent and then
sanitizing and then completely drying
the piece of equipment drying is
essential we are finding in the research
because of microbes we're never
there is water present microbes really
like to get into that niche and grow so
drying whenever possible your equipment
is really important soil amendment
applications so if you're applying
manure to a sweet corn field and you
have melons within like 15 feet of that
sweet corn field just be aware of the
different risks associated with that
sweet corn field if there if there is
any way that runoff could happen and how
you're gonna mitigate potential risk of
any runoff as I mentioned before visitor
policies and that sign that I have can
show you up on this visitor policies
thing making sure that we have a plan in
place for when wildlife comes on our
farm and having workers trained for
knowing how to deal with animals on the
farm as I mentioned before Maryland
Department of Ag on their website has a
training that's an English and Spanish
for working with animals so I highly
suggest getting to that website and
showing your workers this from the h gap
if you're if you're a grower who wants
to get one of the stringent audits for
the h gap there are a couple of other
things that Alec was noting in his
inspections this year again a lot of
these some of these are piddly things
some of these are red tape things like
securing chemical storage makes sure as
was said in the last talk whatever sort
of sanitizer or pesticide or whatever
you're using follow the label
instructions that is the most important
thing and then you could take a picture
of this I think for time I won't be able
to go through it all the way but there
are some things that you can prioritize
that will cover a PSR requirement and a
harmonized gap requirement and that is
making sure the records have all the
required things on them protecting your
water source from source to spigot
keeping your harvest totes off the
ground and I know this is a hard one and
research is still diving into the actual
risk of harvest totes in contact with
soil but if you have the ability to use
a sacrificial tote when you're
harvesting or if you could put a piece
of cardboard underneath the tote that
you're using to slide around the ground
we really recommend
doing that if you can if you're
employing any sanitizers for water
treatment activities make sure that
you're able to monitor monitor the
sanitizer with a pH or ppm strip you can
get these pH or ppm strips from brewery
supply stores or restaurants supply
stores I have got one from Amazon and it
did not work so I would caution against
using the Amazon once and then if you
are using a cooler just be aware of
what's going on with cooler condensate
we want best-case scenario is for the
product any product that you have don't
store it directly underneath the cooler
but if you are storing it directly
underneath the cooler I would recommend
that you cover it with a plastic sheet
or something so we don't have any
condensate hitting the product
alright so things to think about now we
just want to make sure that everybody
realized that food safety is an
iterative and continue to process
continuous you're not going to get all
your food safety goals done in one
season if you are thinking of where to
start we always recommend starting with
worker training program because they
affect your product quality and safety
the most because they're touching it all
the time and if you are interested in
going to a gap training this year we
have a couple of advanced trainings
happening March 28th nope February 28th
and March 4th and these advanced
trainings we're gonna get more in-depth
into how to look at your piece of
equipment for food safety risks how to
develop cleaning and sanitizing
schedules and if you're doing any sort
of on photo on farm produce processing
how to how to know if you're edging into
a different type of Food Safety
Modernization Act rule if you want more
information on how to write your plan we
are hosting two basic gap probe
workshops where we're going to be
actually writing plans so if you think
you're ready to do this but you just
don't know how to write the thing we've
come to one of these programs you'll
leave with a plan almost done go ahead
and take a picture of this these are
references for further reading all of
the Maryland registration forms that I
talked about are available here and you
can talk to Carol or myself to kind of
navigate you through which form you need
to fill out if you need to fill out one
and there are also resources from the
produce safety rule as well oh yeah go
ahead did you get it
okay good and then if you have any
questions please reach out to us and
I'll take any questions you have great
question so they're still trying to
figure out how often they're gonna have
to come out to give you a an inspection
some smaller states are able to come out
to their farms once a year it's quite
it's gonna be unlikely that MDA is going
to be able to come out to you every year
I think they're thinking maybe I don't
want to give you a number but maybe
every three years and it's gonna be
based on priority they're thinking too
so it won't be an annual thing that's a
great question so we hear this a lot the
wildlife is a real challenge especially
on the Eastern Shore especially with all
the deer we have and I think that all
the regulator's and the auditors know
that we're not going to be able to keep
all of the animals outside of an outside
space right so this one is mostly a due
diligence thing on you it's it's you're
writing down that you're trying to
monitor for them and you're trying your
best to deter them from your production
areas but we know that wildlife are an
integral and also beneficial part of a
farm so we're not trying to give you a
prescription to get rid of all the deer
right and we know that it's a challenge
and that's kind of one of those things
where you do your best and you write
down what you're doing and that's all
you can do
two three four clapping that's exactly
right yeah and I just think yeah
wildlife will always be a challenge and
it's a good thing that the MDA auditors
and inspectors they know that so they're
not they're not as persnickety as
someone else in Rhode Island would be
unfortunately fortunately if you went to
choose one yeah that's a great question
so the question was which animals should
we mitigate for most right should it be
the deer should it be the geese and I
think you can think about this two ways
you can think about it as what sort of
animals you most likely see and how many
of that sort of animal do you most
likely see so if you notice from your
monitoring because you're just looking
at your you're looking at your
production area all the time you notice
that deer is the biggest problem then
you're going to want to try your best to
control for deer if you know that you've
got a flock of geese and a flock of deer
it's kind of down to like well who's the
bigger problem who goes into the field
more often then I would prioritize that
way it's just doing your best they're
animals they're out there we're not
going to keep them from our delicious
food you know
are we are we seeing any feral pigs nope
okay well let's hope not you're gonna
want to have to do something you know
you can do something you could bury it
you could just flag it you could remove
it the the buffer is up to you you it
doesn't have to be three feet it doesn't
what you can say that but then what
you're gonna want to do is follow up
that your workers know not to pick it in
subsequent picks like if they go into
the field again so you can write down
and that's where the kinds of
flexibility comes into play you can
write down whatever works for your farms
just as long as you can like back it up
with worker trainings right and in that
instance someone will ask a worker be
like how do you know if you're coming
into this field a second time what to
pick and what not to pick right and if
they know and if they can tell the
inspector like oh I know then you're
golden makes sense okay thank you
[Music]