well welcome everyone uh thank you for
joining us and
we have
we so this is the i think the third of
the series i think there's one more
after this
and today we're going to be talking
about grain drying storage and farm
safety
so i'm sam markell i'm the interim anr
director co-interim anr director for a
probably pretty defined short period of
time here since we're interviewing two
candidates um we have two people with us
ken hellevang is a professor and
extension agricultural engineer
so ken
has been a specialist for 42 years so
he's got a lot of experience he also
took one for the team as uh as a
department head for three years and a
few months as an anr director before
muhammad and i so he's done a lot of
service work in there we really
appreciate that
he also for those of you at big iron the
what was they can the best small indoor
exhibit award i think that's right yeah
so
ken was involved with that angie was
there the whole time too so so ken will
talk first and he's going to talk about
some harvesting and drying for maybe 20
25 minutes we'll have a q a and then
we'll switch to angie and angie was a
county agent for seven years and now
she's the ranch
farm and ranch safety coordinator did i
get that right angie yeah so then she'll
talk about some of the safety issues
that we face again maybe you know 20
more minutes or so and have another q a
so that's that's what today will be done
we we will at 11 15 we'll stop promptly
or shortly before depending on the
questions so
ken if you wanna and scott swanson's
with us so if you have any technical
issues scott's your guy
so ken why don't you go ahead and take
it away
okay
well
good morning everyone and
as hopefully you can see my slides i've
been a good extension person i say that
i can't talk without slides
so we're going to focus
on kind of the harvest and drying
situation
for corn soybeans and sunflower
and
i've titled it october of 2022
i frequently will tell farmers and
others that when i'm doing presentations
that i like to cover the fundamentals
because each year is different
each year gives us
challenges and so
if we look at
this year
as of
the crop and report yesterday
things are moving along
i always watch the
crop report
as we go through the growing
season because i try to
use that then to give me a signal of
what i need to be covering
for harvest and drying and storage
and then it gives me
an idea of where we're at particularly
this year with our late
planting
but because of the warm temperatures we
pretty much caught up
so
what i've got on the slide is
this year's september 2022 versus the
five-year
average and when we look at corn
maturity
we're about 26 percent uh
pretty close to normal
soybean leaf drop 57
versus 72
for a five year average
but soybeans will will change quickly
uh and then if we look at sunflower
uh we're at about 30
versus 34 so again pretty typical
conditions
but i always
say that reaching maturity is is just
the first step in the process
uh corn for example has about a 35
moisture content once it reaches
maturity
and of course we don't want to be
harvesting 35 percent moisture
and so then we start thinking about what
is the dry down
and for soybeans that's not as big of an
issue typically
because they drive fairly rapidly
as long as we have decent drying
conditions actually
there's potential for it to get too dry
and we'll talk some about that
so what's
what are we looking at uh i always look
at the
weather forecasts uh trying to look at
what what are we going to
be dealing with is it a dry harvest is
it a wet harvest and it can start out
wet and get dry or vice versa
the 8 to 14 day
temperature outlook is in the top left
corner
uh up in this area here
and it looks like we're going to be
above normal temps and even if you look
at the
the
10-day forecast that the weather service
and other places
put out
looks like we'll have no trouble
reaching maturity
as we
finish off this growing season
but when we look at october
we're continuing to be
it says potentially above normal
temperatures
the central part of the country is got a
much higher probability
but
probably but their guess as of
right now is that october is going to
continue the trend
that we've had
when you start looking beyond that then
we get equal chance of
above normal normal
conditions
and so
that always worries me a little bit that
as we get to november
that things might be turning the other
way and that's why we start seeing
a change in that pattern
if we look at precipitation we're going
to continue to be dry
for the 8 to 14
but as we start looking into
october
then we're at equal chance of being
above or below which i say ends up
putting us pretty much at
a normal probability and that means that
we could be wet we could be dry
and
that's
the challenge and if we start looking at
even the the seasonal which is october
november december we're trending to that
equal chance again
and so even though temperatures are
looking pretty good
uh precipitation
as we start getting into october
is less certain
okay if we get normal temperatures and
conditions uh
how rapidly will will the grain dry down
and we'll focus first on corn
uh and this
table
uh includes a number of different
factors related to that dry down
uh we'll skip september and just look at
october
if we're looking at
the first column here uh it says
16 moisture so that's the moisture
content
uh that would be
potentially the the ending moisture
content if we had good drying conditions
so that's favorable
number of
primarily
agronomy-focused people look at growing
degree days and try to make a prediction
off of that i just was on and
looked at a pioneer for example
they have where they say it takes about
30 to 45
growing degree days to take off a point
of moisture
if you look at that predictor
that would only say we would drive four
to five percent during the month of
october and that's not reality and so
i've if you hear people talking about
growing degree days and how it
correlates with with dry down
i wouldn't listen too intently to that
iowa state university has put together a
calculator
that's on the web
you just do a search for
iowa state university dry down
calculator
and it
has you put in
the moisture existing moisture content
and the
date
and it'll calculate a prediction based
on
weather
conditions
over historically weather conditions
and if we
use that model it'll show that we would
expect
maybe about a 14 moisture reduction
during the month of october
so if we're starting out at 35 that
would say that we would be at about
moisture at the end of october
i've used a prediction where i go to the
north dakota agricultural weather
network and look at potential
evapotransportation
transpiration
which is what we use to calculate
irrigation needs in the summertime
it takes into consideration
temperature wind
solar radiation relative humidity etc
i think it's a good way of making a
prediction
and depending on
year and where you're at in the state
we're probably looking at
about three inches of water removal
based on that p-e-t
that would then translate into drying of
about 11 to 12 percent not quite as
optimistic as the iowa state one
and i'll say we're looking at maybe two
and a half or at most three
percentage points of moisture removal
during the month of october
so
likely unless we're harvesting very high
moisture corn
a lot of corn is going to need the whole
month of october to dry
as we shift to november unfortunately
we look at the equilibrium moisture
content or that field moisture
increasing
the amount of moisture removal is almost
nil
we'll maybe pick up a point a week
and so
my typical recommendation is that we
need to be planning to harvest
corn the latter part of october early
november as pretty much the drying is
done at that point
if we look at
following that moisture content we're
going to be using a moisture meter
to
measure that grain moisture content
keep in mind though that the meters are
calibrated for 15
moisture corn and as the
moisture gets higher
it's more in air
so if you're checking 25 moisture corn
uh it's probably
as much as a point or more off at that
point
also we need to be adjusting for
temperature
we start harvesting corn in november
when we have temperatures
that are
below 40 degrees
most of the meters are not going to
allow you to take a reading
or
will give you an inaccurate reading
below 40 degrees
also they are sensitive to moisture
variations across the kernel
so i really encourage people to take and
and
do that initial moisture measurement put
the
corn in a sealed container like a ziploc
bag or something
give it 6 to 12 hours to equilibrate to
room temperature
and then recheck that moisture content
just to make sure that we're getting an
accurate reading
i don't anticipate a lot of use of bags
this year
but if if some are using
the poly bags for corn storage
that corn needs to be dry if we're in
the 25
to 35 percent moisture range that corn
will go through the
the in sylene silage making process
which we don't want for most of our our
corn
in the 15 to 24 percent moisture range
we're gonna have heating and spoilage
uh unless we're at winter temperatures
if we
can consistently stay below 30 degrees
then we may get by at those higher
moisture contents
but essentially the corn or grain needs
to be dry
going into the bag if we're going to be
safely using a bag
[Music]
in addition to moisture content
sometimes we'll get people thinking well
it's a sealed container and so
that will prevent mold growth
or
prevent insect activity
both of those are false
we recommend running the bags north and
south so that we get
even solar
heating on the two sides
and
keep in mind the
the
temperature of the grain will be
whatever the average outdoor temperature
is
so the bags work well for winter storage
but if we're storing into spring it
really needs to be dry
there's
lots of variations or options for
high temperature drying
and i've just included a
collection of different dryers
on the slide
there is a presentation on my website on
the different types of dryers and i
could if someone has an interest
i could do an hour presentation just on
the different characteristics of the
different high temperature dryers
one of the things though that that
frequently comes up is what is the
cost to dry
and if we're strictly looking at the
energy
most of our dryers high temperature
dryers drying corn
we'll be looking at
about 2500
btus of heat required to evaporate a
pound of water
and
we can then use that information
to calculate
what that cost would be
we take
the multiplier of .022
times whatever the propane price is
and that gives us the cost
per bushel point of moisture removal
some of the newer
dryers that include
the more energy efficiency features
might be down closer to 2000 btus
and then that conversion factor is .018
but for example if we had a dollar per
gallon propane we take that times
point zero two is kind of an in-between
number between the two
uh and that shows us about two cents per
bushel per point
and it's a straight linear relationship
so
if propane is two dollars a gallon
uh we'd be looking at four cents per
bushel per point of moisture removed now
that's strictly just the
the cost of the propane it doesn't
include
all the other associated costs that are
involved
if we look at
trying to calculate how much propane is
actually being used
there's a fairly simple formula for that
as well
again .02 times the bushels that we're
drying
times the point of moisture removal
so if we're drying a thousand bushels
and we're taking off 10 points of
moisture
that amounts to about 200 gallons of
propane
so one of the things they've been
talking about for this fall
is that you make sure that you have
your propane
contracted or
available so that when it comes time to
do the drying
maybe in in
late october early november
that
we know how much propane that we're
likely going to be using
particularly in some of the newer
areas where they're growing corn for
the first times
guys will try to get by with using
natural air drying where we're just
moving the air through the bin
if we're doing that the maximum moisture
that we can handle is about 21
moisture
we need an air flow rate of at least one
cubic foot per minute per bushel
uh and i'll show you on the next slide
that that works okay in october but not
november
so typically what we're doing is cooling
the corn
and holding it wet over winter and then
doing the drying in the spring
and we'll
normally recommend when outside
temperatures
are averaging above 40 degrees
is when we start that
natural air dry
lots of numbers on this
table
what i want to focus on is your the the
november
roll
that
because of the cooler temperatures
we start looking at very little moisture
holding capacity in the air
and we're looking at 70 days of fan time
to do the drying
uh and even if we start adding heat a
lot of guys think well i'll just go out
and buy a heater and warm the air
and if we heat the air 10 degrees
it does shorten that drying time a
little bit
but we also end up over drying the corn
we're now down at
12 and a half percent moisture and it's
still taking 51 days of drying time
so pretty much i say that
natural air drying just does not work in
november
spring drying works very well again like
i said starting when temperatures are
averaging
uh 40 degrees and warmer
we're still looking at
40 to 50 days of fan time
but it will dry that corn down
as long as we're starting at that
20 21
percent moisture
every year uh we have a few bin roofs
that
they are damaged
because as the air goes through the
grain it picks up moisture
if the temperature
is at or below freezing
it'll ice those uh gooseneck vents open
over the screens and those just uh
seal up tight
so anytime we're running fans at
temperatures near below freezing i
recommend leaving the fill and axis door
open
as a pressure relief valve otherwise
it's just going to pop that bin roof up
and damage it
let's shift gears and talk briefly on
soybeans
optimum moisture is about 13
moisture
one of the characteristics of soybeans
is that they change moisture very
rapidly
and so
everyone is familiar with
it might be 15 moisture
in the morning and by
a warm dry afternoon we might be down to
and the amount of breakage that occurs
the damage to the beans
and the field loss shelling in the field
uh go up as we start getting moisture
contents below 13.
so
the farmers really need to be
doing whatever they can to harvest as
much as they can
at that 13 moisture
if we get into a situation where
we get rain showers coming through
some years it it's very difficult to get
the
soybeans dry out in the field
we can run them through a high
temperature dryer but we have to limit
the drying temperature
and we're still going to end up with
some breakage and damage going through
the dryer
the other characteristic of soybeans
are that we have a
significant fire hazard because the pods
and other trash
that it goes through
the dryer tends to become lodged and
then over dried
and becomes tender
and so
they need to keep the grain flowing we
need to keep the dryer clean
we may need to be
monitoring that dryer continuously
and cleaning it
maybe a couple times a day
those that are familiar with sunflower
know that the sunflower fires are
part of drying sunflower
too many times though people think it's
related to the drying temperature
again it's a housekeeping issue
it's dependent on the
cleanliness of the dryer
and so maybe with sunflower we need to
be
cleaning that dryer
two and even three times a day
we need to be monitoring it to make sure
that
that the flowers are continuing to flow
through
if a fire does start shut the fan off
use an extinguisher to
attack where the the fire is
and then
empty the dryer to make sure that
any of the embers that might still be
glowing
uh are removed we got to keep in mind
that
sunflowers are an oil product and both
with
soybeans and particularly with sunflower
we end up with an oil fire
some again try to use natural air drying
i really discourage anything over 15
percent
moisture
and again it works well in october as
long as we have adequate airflow
and this comes out of my
publication
natural air low temperature grain drying
and you can see
different air flow rates and drying
times required to get it done in october
but as we look at november
same kind of table as before
we shift into november and all of and
our drying times become very
excessive and
we with sunflower
with just a little bit of heat we can
successfully dry in about a month
as long as we have
adequate air flow and so
a little more optimistic
conditions
for sunflower
well getting it dry is just part of it
then we have to manage it
and the types of things that that we
need to do
our monitor temperature moisture insects
mold
i recommend at least every two weeks
except during
the extreme cold of winter
and
manage means to direct with a degree of
skill
so we need to have some expertise on how
to manage the bin
we need to be
controlling
temperature moisture and insects
many years ago i put this visual
together to
show
the
temperature bands for insects
the curved line is the
average monthly temperature in north
dakota
we recommend aerating the grain whenever
it's uh
10 to 15 degrees cooler outside
and then
we
end up
trying to keep it cool as we go through
the summary if somebody has questions
or wants some of these i still have some
of them on
and
lots of technology available to help us
manage that grain
but it
is a tool
that we don't want to replace
going in and checking the grain
there are lots of hazards associated
with the grain
this is kind of a lead-in to angie's
portion
the one that i will touch on a little
bit on the moldy grain
for years i was telling people you need
a mask that has two
straps
as a way to really
indicate the n95 mask
one of the things with covid is
everybody knows now what an n95 mask is
but that's
excuse me that's what we need for
for keeping those mold spores out of us
like everybody else just do a search for
ndsu grain drying and storage
and you'll find my information
and i think it's yours angie
awesome thank you so much ken you had a
great uh great segue into
i mean our work goes hand in hand
together
in terms of
the
the safety precautions that that we need
to consider when we're looking at
working
around grain handling equipment and so
for those of you on the call
my name is angie johnson as
sam shared i am the ndsu extension farm
and ranch safety coordinator i've been
in this role for just about a year now
and so
um
i have one year under my belt but still
so many um so many more opportunities
and much more knowledge to gain and so
it's been great to
to work with ken and and learn a lot
more and understanding of of what farm
safety positions look like across the
extension service system in in the
united states and so it's been it's been
a really good opportunity and i thank
you all for your support and your time
this morning to learn a little bit more
um
i'm going to go ahead and just get
started some of you may have
seen bits and pieces of this
presentation i've i've done a recording
or two
for you to have available during
pesticide training season
as part of a component
within your training materials but also
for fumigation
working with andrew thostenson our
pesticide specialist here at ndsu and
focusing on on how we
work safely around grain bins when
applying a fumigate product
and so
any time
i i give a presentation or i work with
with staff it's really important to take
a just take a moment to step back
because
the topics that i get to talk about are
they're not easy
they're really hard conversations to
have
nobody likes to be told that they're
unsafe not that that's what i do at all
right i that's that's not our goal we're
not we're not enforcement we're
prevention and education
but the reality is is taking safety
seriously
can be a challenge and it's not that
people don't want to be safe or aren't
acting safe it's just we become so
comfortable with what we're doing that
we take for granted the seriousness and
honestly the hazardous conditions that
we do work in and so it's really
important to just take a step back and
for any of you out there
um i i can only imagine that that some
of you have been touched in your life by
someone that's been involved in some
type of farmer ranch-related incident
and so i always encourage growers or or
any any audience members out there that
need to take a step back because of this
heavy subject to please feel comfortable
to do so
because taking care of yourself is
priority number one
i like to start off with showing this
humorous little clip or meme whatever
you want to call it because i think it
gets all of us to start thinking and
being realistic with ourselves that
for for those that i mean
you can just
go to the local elevator or during
harvest time you can see the long line
of semis uh that are at the elevator and
so
um you know i don't always wait in line
at the green elevator but man when i do
it makes me want to build one more bin
and and many of our growers have
experienced that and
um my point being is that the grain
industry has
has changed we're not just dealing with
5000 bushel bins anymore we're dealing
with you know commercial facilities that
have over a million bushel storage
capacity whether that's
not just grain bins but other confined
spaces that they're using structured
domes and whatnot
but our handling equipment you know
we're using semis semi trailers pup
trailers
um you know we can hold a
a semi can hold a grain cart load or
more and versus the single axle trucks
of of yesteryear and so just keeping in
mind about how the grain industry has
really has really changed and how
farmers are handling their storage
and with that change comes comes
problems right unintended
um
unintended
issues that
we need to address but but it's a
challenge and so
one of the the reality is
and why we're all here is to understand
a little bit more about the problems
that that come with working in confined
spaces such as grain bins and one of the
biggest questions that i get asked and
asked often especially by the media is
well
what what's our number one
you know farm-related injury or or
fatality and and the reality is folks is
that it's it's not that simple there is
no formal reporting
um
you do not have to report if if you have
a farm injury or incident on your
operation there's no federal mandate
that requires you to to report that
injury
and
what that means is that we don't have a
great database or and we don't have a
great understanding in terms of what
we're actually seeing out in the
countryside commercial facilities
absolutely 10 or more employees they
have to follow osha regulations the
occupational safety and health
administration so any time there's a a
near miss incident i mean it has to be
legally reported
and some of the best information that we
can get is is from purdue university dr
my colleague dr bill field
he has been
working with a grant for for many many
years that really focuses on
trying to understand and get an idea in
terms of what's going on with confined
spaces out in the agricultural workspace
and
they have been collecting this data
since 1962 and so it's a very very large
data set and i just i'm not going to go
through the details of these numbers
with you but i think it's important to
put into perspective
that grain storage facilities are are a
big big problem when it comes to
injuries and fatalities
um and and what his report does is it
looks at both commercial and on farms
and you might be wondering well
angie you just told me that we can't you
know there is no
reporting system we can't monitor
farm-related injuries
and the reality is is
what our
industry isn't the right word but what
our
what our team does is really look at
news releases media reports social media
posts
um there are a couple networks out there
that that is literally what they do is
they scour
and keyword search
different terms in order to kind of get
an idea of what accidents or excuse me
incidences are happening based on what
the media is reporting and i think all
of us on this call realized that well
just because a farm injury doesn't make
the news
um
doesn't mean it's not serious because
not all farm-related incidences make the
news you know typically
if
if it's a
fall or if if there's survivors it may
not even make the news it usually has to
be a very tragic scene in order to make
local media and so just to kind of give
you some framework of the reality of
what we're dealing with we're
we have a really really good
estimate and and some data but it's not
concrete and it's not solid
and i've been talking a lot about a
confined space and and i don't want to
make the assumption that we all know
what a confined space is that's that's
not fair and because there's many
different types of confined spaces when
you get out into our our large feedlot
operations whether that's cattle or hogs
or or whatever a find space working with
livestock we've got manure pits as well
and and they classify as the confined
space and so just setting this narrative
that
when we're dealing with a confined space
we're dealing with a space that's not
designed as a regular workspace
like a grain bin is not a shop you know
this isn't a place where you can go in
and grab your welder and or or get out
of the rain i mean if this is not
designed as that type of structure to be
working in
um a confined space also is very limited
there's there's not a lot of exit or
entry points and as you'll notice in
this photo
they are small okay it's it's not meant
for quick access it's not meant for
quick escape it's it's very very small
it's meant to serve the purpose of
storage of storing grain
and then a confined space also really
looks at the physical and toxic hazards
right and so ken was talking a little
bit about molds earlier okay
we can also have fume issues
in terms of
when those molds are happening they
produce toxins that that get into the
air and you breathe in
and can cause some serious health issues
later on and so just kind of giving you
a background of
you know what this is what we're dealing
with in a confined space and for most of
us here in north dakota our confined
space is is related to grain bins
uh this is just going into the deep
nitty gritty to give you a even deeper
view of of what a confined space is and
and really looking at i just wanted to
showcase this to get deeper into the
hazards because most producers don't
think about oxygen content when they're
working with grain bins i mean oxygen
can be a huge limiting factor and a
problem right anytime we're dealing with
with too low or too much we we've like
ken talked about earlier with dryer
fires we can actually have green
excessively heat up within a bin and get
so hot that it'll it'll combust it can
start on fire and so just looking at the
different the different true dangers
that i think we take for granted um and
and don't always get an opportunity to
shed a light on because we just work
with grain bins so much we're around
them so much that we don't realize you
know in most cases we think of
engulfments but really um
some people can be overwhelmed with the
air quality once they make that choice
to to enter a grain bin
this is looking deeper into the weeds
because i think it's really important as
as agents i know i loved seeing
um some numbers and i it really hit home
to me when i could see a little bit more
about north dakota you know where does
my home rank and this is just looking at
confined spaces from that purdue report
and if anyone's interested it's
available online or i can certainly send
it to you
but i always i like to showcase this
2020 report and for some you're going to
say angie that's so outdated but just
hang on with me bear with me
so in 2020
there were 64 total cases of confined
space incidences okay
of those 64
confined space incidences
35 of them were grain entrapments
because remember grain bins are not the
only source or are not the only type of
confined space so there are a lot of
other mostly manure handling facilities
our other confined space
but just kind of giving you an idea
of some of those detailed numbers
and i want to ask you
where did north dakota rank
so when you look at this map you're
going to see
the map of united states of course but
then you're going to see boxes within
each state you're going to see a gray
box and that box is going to have a
number that lists the total number of
confined space incidences
that they have been able to report and
record since about
1962.
that white box right next to that gray
box is going to be the total number of
20 incidences that occurred in 2020
within each of those states so when you
look at that white box you're actually
going to see that north dakota and
minnesota tied for second in the amount
of confined space incidences in
okay keep that in the back of your mind
i promise i'll i'll dive into it a
little deeper
and and this is a this is a serious deal
and and that's why you're all here today
to to learn a little bit more and i want
to give you some confidence to be able
to talk about grain bin safety when
you're working with your clientele and
so i get this really cool
opportunity to work with the stanford
health trauma center here in fargo um
many people don't know this but the
trauma center in fargo
is the only level one trauma center
between minneapolis seattle denver and
omaha nebraska
that's a that's a that scares me and and
it should scare all of us because the
reality is is if we
need trauma-related care we need
critical uh our our individuals are in
critical care they need help now
emergency surgeries um these are the
only level one hospitals that they're
that are able to handle that and so i've
gotten the opportunity to look at
agricultural related farm incidences
from some of the data from stanford and
between 2010 and 2020 there have been
292 farm injuries
okay and of those 17 of them were
related to grain bins
okay
and 10 of those occurred between 2019
and 2020 alone
that just for for me in in this field
that blows my mind and is is a jaw
dropper for me and
the reason why i keep bringing up 2020
and showing that
is how many of you remember that harvest
okay
if you go back and look at end on data
that was an or if you have good
long-term memory
that was a really really really wet fall
and that caused a lot of harvest
challenges
and this is why ken went first in the
presentation because
we want to talk about if we want to
prevent grain bin related incidences and
fatalities it starts with the condition
of the grain going into the bin for
storage and so during that harvest
period with that excess um
plant moisture
within those within the kernels of
whatever crop it didn't matter whether
it was corn or whatnot
it caused some serious storage issues
moving forward and so hence when we had
storage problems
there was more need to end up going into
the bin
and
digging deeper into that data
something that i think gets taken for
granted and i've talked to ken a little
bit about this and we featured this
topic at big iron is talking about slips
trips and falls
and so a lot of times media reports only
look at or talk about grain engulfments
that's what makes the news and and
rightfully so it's a tragic tragic event
and extremely serious
but but we take for granted slip trip
slips trips and falls are just as
serious you know we're talking about
platforms that
are
my goodness
20 plus feet you know over and so
it's it's very very serious and and can
have life-altering effects and also
cause fatalities
and so of that data from our our staff
samford trauma center 13 of those were
related
uh 13 of those injuries were related
from falls either falling from the bin
into the bin or
falling inside the bin and this is just
i'm not going to go through all these
numbers but just to give you the
severity of what happened and i think
it's really important to note that this
data i don't want to say it's limited
but you'll probably notice there's a
piece missing is that this does not talk
about fatalities our stanford data only
really looks at those that made it to
the hospital and were able to survive so
this does not include those that didn't
make it
and again just giving you some more
demographics that it's not just one age
that's targeted we had
any individuals from 18 all the way to
81 years of age and so
um it's you're not people are not immune
to it age age doesn't matter it's it's
impacting the all of the producers as an
industry
and so now that i've got you thinking a
little bit about slips trips and falls
because it is something that we don't
hear in the news we we don't hear of
those reports often but they're
happening
more and more than we realize
um what can we do to prevent that and um
one of
one of my favorite ways to do this and
and ken and i can go back and forth on
this i'm okay with that but utilizing
ground opening lids uh being able to
open that bin directly from the ground
is is huge i've got a hopper bin system
that this is this is the platform that i
have installed on all of them because
i do not feel comfortable climbing that
high nor should i expect my
father
to have to take on that endeavor if i
don't want to do it and so using ground
opening lids
has been a huge
has been a lifesaver literally for for
us in our operation do they solve
everything absolutely not because as ken
mentioned earlier you still have to
manage you still really need to be
able to take a peek inside those bins um
but this gives you an opportunity that
when you're climbing the bins the lid is
already open you don't have to try and
hang on to your fixed ladder and also
open that bin hatch at the same time
this is the piece of safety equipment
that we featured at big iron i
absolutely love it love it love it
because it it it helps growers
um
actually have a safety mechanism in
place to be able to climb a fixed ladder
system so a fixed ladder is just like i
just like it's now uh pronounced is that
this ladder is bolted it is fixed onto
the side of that green bin and this
allows a cable and pulley system to be
attached to a class 3 harness and and
lifeline a fall protection so you're
able to climb that bin
and for some reason if it's
if not that you should be climbing a bin
on a frosty morning but we all know
frosty mornings they can have that frost
layer on steps which is extremely
slippery and so if you're make make that
choice to climb and you slip and fall
you are only going to fall as far as
that fall protection will
the length of that fall protection so
this is a really really cool
um
design that that folks can have
installed on their bins in order to
actually have some safety protection in
place when when making those bin climbs
stairs i get a lot of conversation about
stairs which i think are fantastic but
the problem is is that stairs do not
come equipped on all grain bins okay
usually they are
um an additional add-on purchase and we
all know with inflation and and the
lovely situation our world is in right
now that
especially any any metal iron you know
in this case uh what we're dealing with
with bins it's gonna cost more and so
that will be a deterrent for people to
install stairs is just because of the
sheer cost to add it on
and you'll also notice uh in in the
photo on the right
so the stair takes us up to to the roof
of the grain bin but how do we get to
the top okay you still have to climb a
fixed ladder to get to the very tippy
top and so that's again where you could
have a
a ground opening lid installed at that
point so you're able to open up that lid
um right at the the top of that
staircase there and you could also have
some fixed ladder fall protection
installed as well again the down play is
everything costs money but at the end of
the day
putting a price on on your safety in
your life it shouldn't even be a
question but i realize
um it it it gets it gets expensive
the other piece that we featured at big
iron and this is something that i would
like to work with with agents more
because i think it's a very very
simple but such an effective program is
utilizing lockout tag out
lockout takeout
is it does not have to be complex so
basically um i know i've got a really
busy photo on on the left side so so
just bear with it but the goal is is
to really shut down all of your power
sources before you start doing any
maintenance or or working on your grain
handling system like ken mentioned a lot
of there's tons of dryer options out
there and there's also so many different
auger system grain legs sumps bin sweeps
a lot of them are mostly powered by
electrical controls and so
taking the time to
completely shut it down get to that
breaker box power it down
use that lockout clasp in the middle of
your screen
to to go through the loop of the breaker
box
uh on and off switch and then actually
taking a lock a physical lock or a
physical little tag
that has you can write your name on it
your employee's name on it whatever it
is and
and lock it or zip tie it in that clasp
and what that locker or tag represents
is you it represents you as an
individual that has taken the time to
power down that equipment and nobody can
unlock that lock except you when you are
ready to turn on and re-power that
equipment so it's to help prevent
someone from unintentionally coming over
and say geez no wonder why this doesn't
work it's off and then somebody turning
it on while the other person is working
on it
and um
it's something that what i like talking
about lockout tag out because it's not
just
a farmer ranch related piece this can be
used for for homeowners in in houses and
and especially with young children
around not that they should be around
breaker boxes to begin with but you just
you just never know where where kids and
children can find themselves and so
lockout tag out i think is a really
really good tool that we can do a better
job helping producers be able to use
that tool
and this is just an example when i was
in the county i had a producer that they
utilized lockout tag out when it came to
maintenance of their equipment so that
tractor
you'll notice there's the the
the tag that is attached to the door
handle of the tractor
that tag cannot be removed by any other
person than than
who's listed on that board and in this
example would be trevor or scott they
have drain there's no hydraulic oil
because they're fixing the axle seal and
so if someone were to didn't know that
and where to hop into that tractor and
start it you're going to have some
serious mechanical issues moving forward
and so they practice the lockout tag out
system
to protect their equipment so somebody
doesn't unintentionally go in
and operate that machine and so if
you're if
i think about it this way if you're not
going to do it to protect yourself start
out by thinking about that equipment and
and keeping that safe i think it's a
really good way to
to ease into it and to you to see and
showcase the benefits of using it even
if you're working by yourself
we always don't remember to pull the
keys if we've changed the oil but if i
take time to tag out and put a tag on
that cab i'm going to remember instantly
when i see it that yep that's right i
can't drive this i need to i haven't put
oil back in
shifting gears a little bit um and just
being cognizant of time here
i always
this role has been interesting because
i've always said this and i will stand
firmly behind it in the fact that my job
is not regulatory like i am not here to
hammer down rules on you to tell you
what to do
um
and and so people get really really
really really anxious and i can see the
hair stand up on the back of their neck
when i say the word permit
and the only reason i i bring this up
because
i feel that and i might not explain
myself in the best way so bear with me
but i feel that
there are already amazing
tips tricks fact sheets whatever you
want to call it there's you call it
regulations there's these amazing
resources out there that really outline
the hazards that are
that are present when working with grain
bins so how can we help producers
utilize the checklists the fact sheets
that are already there and i'm not
saying physical paper that's not my
point but just being able to go through
and realize like oh my gosh
these are things that i never ever
thought of because how many how many
people are ever taught
on grain bin management you know you go
to your grain bin manufacturer they come
and install it and then it's your job to
put grain in into it you know there's
there's there's no training so you you
learn by doing i mean a lot of people
they've they've worked with ken and
really setting up their system and and
so nobody's ever been taught and i think
just bringing awareness to those hazards
and talking about them so then we can
help people mitigate that risk and so
you know having that mindset you know
what
i'm not gonna make a green bin entry
decision without really going through my
my checklist now that i know what these
hazards are have i locked out all the
energy sources do i know what's going on
with the air quality in the bin
do i have a safety harness and a
lifeline and i've put an asterisk by
that because
there's there's two it's two separate
issues having a safety harness versus
knowing how to use it are two completely
different issues
and and i could have a conversation on
that all day
but the other thing is is you know what
type of lighting do we have because
remember
i hope this is familiar but these are
all
signs
pointing to we're dealing with a
confined space okay
um and
uh the part at the bottom talking about
having
basically having that what i call a
buddy system
and guys will think well jeepers i have
i have a buddy with me
they'll be able to pull me out
and for all of you out there on zoom
land the reality is and and this is
gonna sound harsh
but the reality is is that buddy is not
there to pull you out that buddy is
there to call 9-1-1 and and because
you will not be able to react fast
enough to
to grab a hold of somebody that's
becoming engulfed in green um and what
ends up happening is that second person
try ends up becoming the victim as well
because they try and go in and and
rescue that first person and so as cruel
as it sounds
that buddy system you need to have it
but the reality is is they're there
because they need to be ready to call
9-1-1
if
i shouldn't say if it happens it's it's
when it happens okay
um and going back just just talking
about grain bin entry this is just
specifically looking at entrapments now
earlier we looked at all total confined
spaces this map is is again from my
colleagues at purdue university really
looking at the number of entrapments in
2022 and again
north dakota ranked second
and really contributing to that that
high moisture crop that was going into
the bin um during that really awful wet
wet fall um and again not going to do
detail but just showing you some some
different demographics of that
a lot of times i'll get questions all
right angie like it's just corn right i
mean i don't have to worry about it i
raise you know i raise flax or whatever
it's not my problem right
and let's be real here
grain entrapments can happen with any of
the crops that we're dealing with
whether it's corn soybeans i mean any
any of the crops that you see on your
screen it can happen
and the truth is of of the documented
cases that we have remember documented
there's a lot of cases out there it's
estimated about 30 percent of of
farm-related cases are not reported
over 50 percent of those documented
cases have involved corn and that's
because it's been out of condition as as
ken had talked a little bit about
earlier those those pieces that lead to
that so i think it's really important
when you're working with your growers
that
sometimes it's
it's i don't want to use the word
oblivious but just realizing like it
happens more than
than
than just a cor people that are storing
corn and bins
these are the different types of
entrapments again this could be a whole
powerpoint on itself so i don't want to
get caught into the weeds of this some
of you have
have heard me talk about these before
and if for those of you that would like
to learn more i'd love to sit down with
you and we can talk through these but
just wanted to go through some of these
pieces and i added to this list storage
bags um i know a few years ago in kitter
county i believe as ketter county there
was a very very uh dangerous
incident that happened with the the
suction power of that that poly grain
bag those storage bags and so
ken mentioned them earlier as well but
but they are definitely a risk for
some entrapment situations that can
occur as well
this is just briefly going through
you know looking at a flowing grain
scenario and i hope when all of you see
that picture i hope deep down inside you
got really or a little bit angry because
that person is making a horrible
horrible horrible decision in in doing
what he's doing there's no fall
protection you can see clearly see the
funnel cone shape of grain that's going
down and um and and and that grain is
horrible i mean you it is in sheets and
so
um any of the
any different collapses or there could
still be some open
hollows or caverns underneath because of
that crusting we just have a serious
itch situation on our hands and so with
flowing grain i talk a lot about how
the there's a suction action right and
and that ac that suction is so strong
that you physically cannot swim out of
it you know swim your way out of it to
try and pull yourself up um and you
can't you can't walk or climb yourself
out
and these are just some clips from
from ken's publication on don't get
caught in the green just showcasing the
reality of how many seconds it can take
to become engulfed and fully buried and
so that deals a lot with um
the the grain demo that we got to make
at fall conference last year and so if
agents are on this call that are
interested in learning more about making
your own demo talk to me i've got some
supplies left over
and this is just looking at um
the the sheer amount of force you know
gravity takes hold in those engulfment
situations and so when you're buried at
certain levels at certain depths within
the grain this is showcasing how many
pounds of force it would take to be able
to pull that person out and and i know
how strong sam markell is but there's no
way sam would even be able to pull um a
person you know using over 1500 pounds
of force if they're buried that deep
into the grain so just kind of a really
good picture to help
reiterate the fact that that second
person that's on scene
can become a victim really quickly if
they try and and pull that other person
out
this is just looking at bridge grain
where we have that crusting on the top
and and that hollow center and we try
and break that crust and once it breaks
we can easily become entrapped into the
remaining flowing grain that's taking
place
sidewall collapse i usually think about
this like an avalanche
actually at big iron last week we had
some students come through and they they
claim to me that there is no way that
can happen in a bin and i said yes
absolutely this can happen in a bin it's
because you get really really high
moisture moldy corn that's starting to
solidify essentially into this wall but
you'll still have free-flowing pieces
that once you break that crust layer it
can quickly avalanche
and now you're going to see a scene out
of a playground i'm getting close to
wrapping up here i promise but
you know it's all about perspective okay
i show this slide because to all of us
looking at it it's a pretty innocent
slide right it's a pretty innocent
ladder um we take kiddos to the park all
the time and a lot of times these these
are the different pieces of equipment
that kids get to play on so to to a
child this is this is a playground but
then i ask you well what about this how
is this different and so it's all about
perspective and making sure that not
only are we concerned about people going
into the bin but then also what are
those hazards um
when when we have kids on the farm
because a lot of times
our our farm yards are not separated
from the house it's it's all or nothing
it's a whole entire yard and so taking
the time to not only
um
you know not go in the bin but to help
put aids together such as on the right
side you're gonna see this panel door
which simply is just you know a piece of
sheet metal or a piece of tin that that
they've locked in front of that ladder
to prevent people from
and even kiddos from climbing and going
in
and so just to kind of
give a quick summary
you know really like 10 ken talked about
and i talk about all the time it starts
with really good grain going in the bin
um if you have poor grain going in the
bin that doesn't get dried properly or
has issues to start with it's not going
to get better over time that's a huge
misconception is that oh if i leave it
in there it'll work itself out it's
that's not true
i always say have a plan in place
and
you know ultimately
i don't want any i don't want i don't
want producers in the bin but i realize
that's easier said than done um and and
that's why having a plan in place and
and talking with you as agents it is
really important to hash that out and
figure out what that looks like
um and then making sure that
you
you're ready to go that fall protection
is ready your observer observers ready
lockout tag out and then realizing that
if you make that choice to go in
every action you choose has a
consequence to it all bets are off the
table
the minute you make that choice and so
to to finally uh follow up i i guess i
ask you and i ask this to the producers
you know what's what's your biggest
asset on your farm and what's it worth
you know is it that beautiful shiny john
deere combine if you're a green fan
how about any quad track fans out there
that that piece of equipment's pretty
awesome
for those that are loving livestock like
me
you got this million dollar bull that
sold a few years ago that's a pretty big
asset to own i think i'd be scared to
own that
and then for any of you or if it's just
me out there uh sheet producers you know
a couple years ago we had a seven
thousand dollar ram sell at the hedinger
ram sale and so we've got some pretty
big assets and and a lot of our farm
yards they have entire
commercial elevator systems now it's
it's not the days where your local
elevator was the only elevator most most
farm systems now have an entire elevator
themselves and so we're looking at
millions and millions of dollars of
equipment here but the reality is uh the
correct answer is the biggest asset on
your farm is is you
you're the one um
that that needs to come home safely
every night and there is no amount of
equipment or livestock in this world
that is worth more than you and your
family
and and how are you going to protect it
and and that means taking some time to
plan
invest in safety
and so with that um i will stop and and
take on any questions or comments from
the crowd
what people are thinking i'll just add
that not only can that avalanche
of grain cover you in the bin
uh we have had one fatality in north
dakota
where the farmer was standing outside of
the door
and the corn
come rushing out the door and covered
him up knocked him down and covered them
up
so
surprisingly
you're not even safe outside the bed
yeah and i mean it's just realizing the
the hazards that are there i mean we
unfortunately it takes it takes a
casual
a bad situation for us to learn and that
can totally be prevented with more
awareness and education
so folks if you have questions please
reach out to angie and ken they've got a
lot of great resources a lot of great
experience
and i would take advantage of that
you