is are you rolling is this rolling is
this are we on TV right now is this live
this broken wire right here is totally
my fault but this is small potatoes
compared to this other gentleman that
emailed me recently he's got a broken
tractor for sale so this guy here that's
my problem okay so I installed a summit
diverter on here a few years ago and um
I don't know what the heck I was doing
but I did not strap that thing up and
kind of secure it the way that I should
have and so that cable that wire was
hanging down and at some point recently
they got snagged and it tore right off
so I've got a repair job to do on the
1025r and so this is a crazy one of
those things that just happens that
you just can't plan for this kind of
thing right and so this gentleman emails
me and says hey
I've got a tractor ran away down a hill
rammed into a tree both the rear axles
are broken off of it
he was able to get a brand new tractor
and take his loader and swap it out to
the brand new 1025r he still loves a
1025r
but now he's got a tractor that's kind
of in pieces and shambles only 280 hours
on it you know and I've had some of my
own pain over the years especially back
when I I bought and sold a lot of used
equipment I I've mentioned this story
before the John Deere 2320 and you know
I own that machine for like an hour's
worth of time on it and you know kind of
went through checked everything out
everything was good to go a customer had
come and actually handed me a check and
purchased that tractor but he couldn't
pick it up for a while like a week or
something until he was in his new place
or had a trailer or whatever it was so
anyway I was just moving that piece of
equipment around to get it out of the
way when all of a sudden it stopped
working
if you know the 2320 and a couple other
models as well that U-joint back there
on the on the drive shaft will go there
weren't um instructions on how to grease
that or that you needed to grease it uh
there weren't zerks on the earlier
generation of the earlier model years of
that and anyway catastrophic failure
sheared off inside the transaxle housing
about a 4 500 repair a thousand of that
which was parts and the rest was Labor
to disassemble and then reassemble and
so for me I weighed both options I
weighed paying the 4 500 to fix that and
then sell it and get whatever I could
out of it or discounting the price down
and selling it as is and and kind of
fingers crossed hoping for somebody I I
positioned it in a way that is this is a
great deal I made it enticing enough to
be a great deal for somebody who is
Handy and has the time to pay just a
thousand dollars in parts and then
there's that Gap there right there's a 3
500 that's kind of
flexible right how much is your time
worth and and so essentially I lost less
money selling it in as is condition
versus if I would have
had it all fixed and sold it in fully
working condition I just disclosed
everything folks really quick if you
haven't done so yet hit that subscribe
button down below if you are enjoying
today's video we want you to tag along
and if you own a tractor then you need
attachments we'd love to help you out
check out goodworkstrractors.com we sell
and ship all over the country every day
of the week and so this was fairly
recently okay and so just so you guys
know if you want to reach out and
contact me anybody that's interested I
told them I kind of help him
um get rid of the the broken tractor on
however he decides to sell it now if I
don't respond to you and it's down the
road in the future sometime I mean this
is going to sell pretty quickly okay
whether he sells the whole thing off or
sells it in Parts but so don't take
offense of that this is this is a end of
2022 time frame right now so if you
email me in 2024
it's long gone okay but anyway
his repair unlike mine that was forty
five hundred dollars was eleven thousand
five hundred dollars
three pair the rear end of this tractor
eleven thousand five hundred dollars I I
almost can't believe that and I don't
know the breakdown between the parts and
the labor but um
that's like
that's like I don't know 70 or something
the cost of the base the base tractor
itself uh
that's outrageous anyway so you know he
asked what what he should do right just
looking for just looking for people's
opinions and so I said well I mean the
easiest thing would be to sell it just
as is when one lump sum and to sell it
off and explain what the issue is and
what the estimated repairs are and if
you can get a breakdown on the cost for
parts versus labor then again you can
kind of do what I did and maybe we can
minimize your losses there I think if
you wanted to maximize the amount of
Revenue he could get out of it he could
scavenge the whole thing right just
separate out the wheels and the tires he
could even take the hood the seat the
three-point arms just what is this a
public PSA
three-point arms okay if you guys are
buying a used John Deere one series with
a backhoe on it make sure you get the
three-point arms with it because they
are a
they're a fortune to get if you have to
get Replacements so they're not going to
be on the three-point hitch if you have
the backhoe on here they come off so ask
whoever you're buying it from if they
have the three-point arms that go along
with it and if they don't
find out how much it currently costs and
negotiate that into the deal but anyway
most folks don't want to go through that
right they don't want to have to deal
you weren't planning on you're not
looking to become a junkyard right and
scavenge things off and sell them on
eBay or Facebook Marketplace one by one
so that's what I would do but I thought
it's worth talking about number one
because I don't really know where
there's many tractor graveyards around
there especially for newer
you know I don't know I mean 2000 year
2000 and newer tractors I don't know if
there's enough of them that are out
there because most of them are probably
still in existence you see you know the
old stuff right you know from the 30s
40s 50s 60s all that kind of thing but
the new stuff you don't really see any
of that but if there's if there's a
location out there or multiple locations
that are great resources for folks to
find replacement parts
you know it's a new wheel from a scrap
yard from something that got rolled or
whatever that'd be great information for
folks to know so leave a comment down
below well anyway I figure I I suppose I
should tell you what happened and so I
had to ask him to get more detail and uh
pretty pretty simple story really he
says we were blowing leaves with the
tractor the operator backed up to align
with the Royal to use and when he went
to the forward pedal the axle broke and
away he went like down the hill I guess
I am curious if he was sitting on the
tractor this whole time that would be
really crazy he says I wish I could have
figured out why this happened or what I
may have done to cause it he sends
another photo showing the oil trail from
the point of failure when the axle broke
so like up on top of the hill one of the
axles broke off at that point
went down the hill whacked a tree and
the other one broke off folks we are
proud to be sponsored by rim guard
Solutions a liquid ballast weight it
goes right inside your tires completely
hidden we're big on safety on this
channel these tractors are just too
light and Tippy right out of the factory
not only is it going to help with safety
keeping those rear tires planted on the
ground it helps us loader efficiency and
traction too the benefits of rim guard
include being the heaviest all-natural
liquid ballast weight on the market it's
not going to corrode your rims like the
old calcium chloride it's not going to
freeze and it's available at over a
thousand dealers Nationwide find the
dealer near you at rimguardsolutions.com
anyway so to sum it up he says this
tractor was serviced regularly as stated
in the owner's manual and was in great
condition with 280 hours oh it was a
2013 model year and it does have a 60
inch mower deck with it as well so I
actually look to see if it might have
had wheel spacers on it because that's
always an interesting topic of
conversation on you know how much the
the spacers really stress the rear axles
there's no wheel spacers on that of
course it just seemed to be some sort of
fluke accident that happened there I do
feel like eleven thousand five hundred
dollars is
is Extreme I don't know maybe I I'm just
not up with the times right now but that
seems like highway robbery to replace
that rear end
um so yeah
take that for what you will I thought
that was a just one of those things that
happens right and I don't know maybe
Insurance hopefully insurance covered
that for him
good question for homeowners insurance
policies to to see what is covered on
there for completely freak accidents
like that that happen but again I'd like
to know
where do you go to find a new hood for
your tractor right I mean I I've seen
them on eBay I mean you can get you can
get them from Deer right but if you're
you're always looking for cheaper
alternatives and there'd be a great a
great demand for that I have to assume
out there if there was something well
known and Consolidated for folks to go
to but on that note if you do go the
brand new OEM route well then one of our
discount Club Partners 247 parts.com is
one of the biggest online John Deere
dealers in the world and you can save
money off your order with code GWT on
their website so that's pretty much it
for today folks but I I think it's worth
mentioning I I love the 1025r and and
this could happen to any tractor it
could be an orange tractor green tractor
blue Tractor Red Tractor whatever it is
freak things happen out there and
that's you know that's just part of life
right so you got to roll with it but I
hope you enjoyed today's video if you
want to see more we want you to tag
along hit that subscribe button down
below it is completely free and if
you're looking for something for your
tractor an attachment for the front end
loader or the three-point hitch but we
can probably help you out check out
goodworks tractors.com we sell and ship
all over the country every day of the
week I want to thank you for taking time
out of your day to stop by and until
next time stay safe we'll see you soon
[Music]
all right
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]