bedding is going to change with the
season and uh with cattle, at least a
lot of the individuals I'm working with,
we're feeding uh calves, calves in the
fall, maybe yearlings uh to get another
turn through there. Uh when we bring
them in in the fall, we're dealing with
smaller calves, probably start them out
on a a little bit uh less hot diet in
terms of nutrients and so forth.
Um it's normally dry. Um the bedding is
the highest quality we're going to have
each year. So that we're probably going
to start out with using utilizing the
least amount at that time. As winter
goes on, hopefully the calves are
growing. The quality of the bedding
still good. We will have the the
occasional snowstorms that come through
and big openings on our buildings will
allow uh some of that to come in. Need
to adjust and then increase the amount
of bedding when that happens. Uh
spring we're dealing now with bigger
cattle. Normally if we have some uh rain
or so forth, the bedding is going to be
wet. So part of its usefulness has
already been used up. We have that thaw
period and high humidity. So we're not
going to get the the evaporation and we
do get the frequent rains. So again,
we're going to have to adjust our
bedding upward.
Now, uh, the last one is summer. And I
put this on here for the people that
have changed
from a open feed lot to a bedded barn.
They tell me that the biggest thing that
was a aha moment in terms of it is you
use more bedding in the summer than you
did the fall and winter, which is the
exact opposite. If you beded in an open
lot, you beded during the winter, but
you never did anything during the
summer. With these facilities to keep
things moving, one, you've got great big
cattle. You've got hot conditions. The
cattle are drinking more. Some of the uh
feed ingredients we have may contain
some additional sodium, some additional
things that cause the animals to drink
more. more drinking is going to produce
more urine needs to be soaked up and
often at the very end of the feeding
period we're dealing with deterior
deteriorated bedding. It's pretty much
used up. So they'll often times use 50%
more bedding in the summer than they do
in the winter. And they did not expect
that to be um when they started out with
the facility.