there are farmers who get G bumps when
they hear the word tomato farming being
mentioned but there are also some
farmers who have made some good profit
and created wealth doing tomato
farming and New farmers ask themselves
what do they do that others that make
huge Rosses don't do where do they get
it
wrong is it from the variety select is
it the market or what is it well in this
tutorial we shall tell you everything
that you need to know on successful
tomato farming and especially how you
can grow good tomatoes and the best
timing for high
prices in this tutorial we shall cover
the following topics the Kenyan tomato
industry the best time to plant tomatoes
in Kenya the best place to grow tomatoes
in Kenya
the most profitable High yielding tomato
varieties to grow how to plant good
tomatoes the worst tomato paste and how
to control them tomato diseases and how
to control them cost and profit of
tomatoes
fing and finally the bonus tips so make
sure you stick till the end if you
really want to start getting good
profits from your tomato Family actually
at the end of this all you will realize
what separates those who makes profit in
tomato farming and those who make losses
and
remember we are dedicating this fashion
to those serious Farmers those really
fused farmers who need to start making a
living and money and profit from tomato
farming the Kenyan tomato industry
Kenyan Tomatoes most of them are sold in
the market though there is a small
portion absorbed by the industry and
therefore it is the mass Market that
determines the overall prices that
farmers earn now tomato prices in Kenya
can be determined by WEA Supply demand
and most of all the Brokers will and
greed how much brokers want is what the
farmer will sell simply because he
cannot sell his own produce and
therefore the inability of most Farmers
to access Market is what has empowered
Mercedes brokers who never Farm but I
eat the biggest pie of the Tomato
production selling tomatoes in krams
especially as how Industries absorb is
the most profitable way for Farmers
however
Brokers prefer using expective units of
measure such as hip crate or Pro box two
and abnormal
profits the best time that you can plant
tomatoes in
Kenya the perfect time that you can get
good prices at low cost is one that
coincides with low market
supply yes
planting your tomatoes in such a way
that you harvest them when there are Le
little market supply at least at this
time prices are high and even if Brokers
try to expl you will still get good
margins
and at this time especially when there
is heavy Lane most produce is destroyed
by the L the roads are inaccessible
therefore the supply roow and prices are
high remember tomato demand is always
there people will still continue
consuming Tomatoes regardless of the
weather where can you grow
tomatoes the best place to grow tomatoes
is one that has FTI well drained soil
and warm
weather warm weather p and fastens the
Tomato growth at low cost especially
when it comes to controlling fungal
diseases caused by cold weather doing
outdoor tomatoes in wet cold regions
increases the cost of production
especially in controlling
diseases compared to doing it in weather
in warm weather Legions the greenhouse
system is ideal in both hot and cold
regions as it enables faster growth of
crops the most profitable High yielding
tomato varieties to grow in Kenya in
order to make money in tomato farming
you must select the best tomato variety
with faster maturity high yield and good
tolerance to diseases all tomato
varieties are not the same they vary in
terms of yeld and resistance to
diseases the best two varieties that you
can plant and get good hydrates is
Terminator F1 from Royal seeds and also
F1 from seminis these are the best and
most profitable outdoor tomatoes to grow
in Kenya for Greenhouse Farmers Susanna
F1 has good shape good size and
therefore makes it the best tomato
variety to plant inside Greenhouse it is
a product of Royal
seeds now let's check what makes the min
typ one a good variety one it is a very
vigorous plant long determinate and a
heavy
yielder its fruit has deep color with
over
shape it matures with 75 days from
transplanting has a fruit weight of 125
to 150 g a yield potential of 40 tons
per
acre okay and those harvested fruits
they can stay up to 21 days fresh at
room temperature this what makes it most
IDE deal for buyers they want a produce
that can stay long after harvest
Terminator F1 has a 21 day Safe Life AA
can hold a plant population of around
8,000 plants of Terminator another cool
variety that you can do is answer for
from seminis
it is elongated Square loud tomato
hybrid it's best for open field
environmental condition it brings value
to Growers with overall fruit quality
disease package extended shelf life and
plant
y after
getting the best vary how do you plant
it here is how you can plant good
tomato in outdoor farming dig planting
holds on a spacing of 60 cm by 60 cm or
60 cm by 50 cm but for Greenhouse fing
you can do 50 cm by 50 cm simply because
you'll do the
pruning after that apply well decomposed
manure 2 kg precisely per planting hole
cover with loose soil and water then
drench with thunder inxite to kill any
cats and City shooter or optimizer
for removing any transplanting stress on
the
crop after
that you can transplant your seed drinks
in large scale farming suain seed drinks
is economical however for small scale
Farmers Laing your own seedings is most
economic and the variety is guaranteed
even for large scale Farmers if you can
manage to raise your own seedings it's
very very economical and also the
variety is guaranteed we've experienced
several cases where Farmers they ordered
or outsourced the drings but they were
not the variety that they were promised
given Farmers ress and remember you
could only realize this few months down
the line and it's irreversible there's
nothing much you can do Ling own SE
drings is guaranteed of quality and
variety after you've planted your
Tomatoes the next thing is feeding
feeding is what determines the yield
regardless of the variety if you have a
good variety and you don't feed it well
you'll definitely experience low
needs here is the tomato fertilizer
application
schedule the fertilizer that you need to
apply how and even the
quantity to breast with dap NPK 1717 and
fertilizers on the for 14th day after
transplanting 45th day after
transplanting and 16th days after
transplanting respectively what do I
mean I mean J planting you don't apply
the DAP 2 weeks after your seedings have
developed you can now come and apply the
DAP at this time the seedings would have
developed the roots and managed to
absorb the fertilizer if you applied
during the planting it may be easily
reached away and not end up helping the
crop after that 45 day equivalent to 1
and a half month after transplanting you
can now apply NPK 17 17 17 it has the
balance nitrogen phosphorus and
potassium this will initiate fluting and
flowering so you don't skip this one and
go to CN no this one will initiate
fruiting and flowering and give you high
number of fruits and flowers
after that then 2
months after transplanting you can apply
now the CA and fertilizer CN has the
calcium that will help in expansion of
the
fruit and that's why we usually
recommend it to be done 60 days after
transplanting you can supplement this
fertilization by applying nitrogen fol
fertilizers such as you can apply easily
grow vegetative on the first month that
is 2 weeks after transplanting and your
to blasting every week you do e grow
vegetative to enhance for your growth on
the second month after transplanting now
you apply the NPK FIA such as oo uh and
also Advanced K this one has more
potassium and it will help in floating
and flowering on the third month you can
now apply calcium Le forious fertilizers
to prevent blossom endro and
also these calcium Bon folas they will
prevent in fruit and flow
abortion after that we going to look at
the wor tomato paste and how to control
them imagine after selecting the best
variety feing then now what kicks out
all tomato fing it's p diseases we are
not going to allow this and that's why
we are now giving you the worst of all
and the best chemicals you can use and
how you can manage to apply them the
number one past that has run most
Farmers out of business is Du absoluta
or what we call Reef Miner it's the most
destructive paste in tomato farming due
to its infectiveness to most chemicals
caused by insect nature of damage
actually it tends to hibernate between
the layers of the leaves so that when
you apply the chemicals they are much
not effective to identify them very
easily you can see some marks as if H
kind of of snail passing by we often
call them broad shaped mindes on the
leaves L you find them on stems but you
can also find them there the best
control for Tut absoluta is applying the
best chemicals early so you can apply
belt for a male at the rate of 4 m in 20
L of water or 10 m per 20 L of water
these application should be done from
the third week after transplanting and
you continue at Le weekly weekly weekly
and when you apply you apply on the
leaves below the leaves and also on the
soil okay why do we apply on the soil so
that we can manage to kill all the eggs
ra on the soil below the leaves you need
to control it and also on top control
when you do this you will manage to have
a total control before it reaches the
last stage right like a
fly remember it goes the whole
metamorphosis so if you don't control it
before becoming an insect it will be
hard and this what has caused most
Farmers low yet you find fruits they
have made some holes and buas don't also
want to buy them no one wants to
buy a tomato with wols made of
insect so the best way ensure that you
you can use bed for a m per 20 L of
water or Emerald 10 m per 20 L of water
and apply early there is no shortcut
about
it the next Insight that has caused
total Destruction in crops and
especially Greenhouse Farmers it's white
fries this one has has drained most
Farmers white fries they are white stop
stacking insects and by doing so they
tend to promote growth of su
mod kind of extracted honey they cause
regular liening of tomatoes and can also
transmit viral pathogens like the Tomato
yellow lefal
virus to identify them you just need to
shake shake the plants a little bit and
you'll see white flying insects along to
control them apply profile at 30 m per
20 L of water or also Amon 10 ml per 20
L of water the application in it own
green houses should be done on the
midday if it's on the farm it should be
done on the evening you apply around the
farm and then you apply inside not
inside then you will finish with around
no spraying fast around the farm
contains the them and makes them easy to
be
killed after controlling the paste the
next thing you need to watch out is the
Tomato diseases here is how you can
control them
early the most destructive tomato
disease is
bright oftenly known as
Bida this one has drained a lot of
farmers and kick them out out of tomato
farming business tomato arite is a
disease characterized by brown spot with
dark conc drinks the disease spreads
rapidly affecting the Lees and the stem
and finally it affects the
fruits to control it apply my 72 WP at
the rate of 30 G per 20 L of water or
gold at the rate of 50 g per 20 L of
water the the best way to control them
is a application once they are affected
it becomes very very hard
remember the cells of the plant die so
and you cannot manage to revive them and
therefore the best way is to prevent
early when you've seen little
infestation you can first apply copper
Beast find St such as the green cop or
Isa cop and then after that you now
continue applying the normal fun sites
but most of all is ensuring that you've
prevented the
infestation and the best application L
is applying twice per week in cold
Seasons or heavy season or once per week
in hot
Seasons the next disease that has
destroyed a lot of tomatoes is tomato
yellow leaf spot
disease you find the leaves has black
spots okay the bright and Sport disease
are
different for sport disease you find
sports evenly distributed on the leaves
but for blight you'll find along the
margins as if they starting to
dry it it starts by affecting other
leaves with greenish yellow spots
begging from the top of the leaf
progressively the spots become dark with
infected Broms also turning black and
falling off the disease it also affect
fruits for Effective control you can
apply either Trinity gold at the rate of
50 g per 20 L of water or you can also
apply
skore yes at at the rate of 20 ml
per 20 L of water these two will help in
total control of Lea spot Lea spots and
bright these are the worst diseases that
will kick you out of tomato famine
imagine all that investment and bu is
where you come to or after all that
investment and then you let just because
of the carelessness you let your crops
be destroyed
by P P the tutor and also the white FES
actually we don't expect any farmer
listening to this tutorial to be ever
again stressed by this dis we've given
you toal
control and after you've done this now
let do the math how much are you willing
or high likely to make and how much are
you highly likely to
incur the cost and profit of tomato
farming in Kenya the cost of tomato
production in Kenya is
185,000 k Shing and you can find all
these
M on our previous article which you can
click here
above this often varies with season
location and management and good
management Ana can produce 300
crates if a farmer
Sals if a farmer sales one crit at
around 1,000 shs then a y 300,000
from 300 crat in one this gives him a
profit of around
115,000 however if he does sell the
similar crates below 800 500 and even as
it was in some months past at 300 Shing
per crit the farmer definitely make
losses so therefore the best means that
you can manage to get good profit is
selling your yield above 1,000 shs per
crit at least this way you'll get some
good
profit remember we promised as we begin
to give you the bonus tips we have the
very bonus tips how you can increase
yield then the second one how you can
speed the Tomato growth and also the
third one how you can get your tomatoes
to produce more
fruits now to increase yield and ESP
special tomato yield ensure that you've
planted with 2 kg of manure Ure that
you've toess with 100 kgs of D 100 kgs
of NPK 17 and 100 kgs of c
and you've done sufficient
irrigation don't forget also to control
the past and diseases once you do that
you will definitely increase your yield
the next one on speeding the Tomato
growth ensure that you planted in warm
areas Ure that you water very well and
you feed them P Tre and by feeding I
mean giving them the right fertilizer at
the right time not that you're giving
the DAP 2 months or you're apping C at
the beginning those one will not give
you the good results the third one how
do you get your tomatoes to produce more
fruits one you can spray
high potassium FIA fertilizers such as
advanced K this one will enhance
flowering and
fruiting and don't forget to combine it
with Boron Boron will prevent the formed
fruit and flouring from a boin and the
third thing don't forget to add calcium
it will prevent the Brom
andrs that's how smart Farmers would
grow tomatoes and make a Kill from it
I believe now you can comfortably begin
your tomato farming if you have any
question on tomato farming kindly let us
know in the comment section we are
willing to help you and we are willing
to help you get those 400 or even 500
crates you get about 40 ttimes yes
remember if you get high yield and at
low cost regardless sometimes of the
price you definitely get good margins
but if you have low Ys I you get low
prices you end up making losses and in
tomato farming there is no shortcut
there is no shortcut you cannot plant an
opv variety and you expect 40 tons you
cannot deny the crop CN or NPK and you
expect good plant you cannot skip weakly
spraying of chemicals to control T absor
white fries bright yellow spots black
spots you cannot escap that chemical and
you expect good years it doesn't happen
like that you have to be consist
consistent don't forget also to like to
subscribe and to share see you next in
the next tutorial