other than the 40 minutes so I'm Grand
butcher I'm cheering the session just on
the on on the loose in I have a
timekeeper here somewhere I think well
there you go Charlie good um can we have
the nord at ten to two your big stink
you do what you have to do but probably
everyone here knows Dirac anyway he's
extremely well known scientist based up
at Lincoln been there since 1996 and
he's the go-to man when it comes to
loosen and sub clover will touch on
subcriber but mostly talking about loose
in who hasn't heard Derek speak before
so anyway we'll get straight into it
we're going to have a 10-minute session
at the end but are you happy to take
clarifications all the way through we
have there's this little innovation here
if you've got a question put your hand
up or throw this at you you have to
catch it all right I won't throw it fast
we'll have so I'll hand it over to Derek
[Music]
thank you very much and thank you for
coming what I thought I'd do today is
actually I'm going to talk about loosing
but really what I'm going to talk about
is how I got on to loosen and what the
principles of it are and trying I know
that the audience here is not a true
Lucerne audience some of you are not
actually in areas that would be
conducive to Lucerne but the principles
that we talk about hopefully are
appropriate for all the farming systems
that we work with what I'm going to do
is give you some information so when I
operate what I'm doing are called on
station experiments so my postgraduate
students they do good research that has
great data integrity and farmers
consider their of low currency and
relevance so generally the results that
come out of a field experiment done at
Lincoln or done at Massey farmers are
all that's interesting but it didn't
happen on my farm it's that's the
tendency for that sort of thing so what
we're trying to do is well I actually
have to do
it and the students have to do that
because we want good quality data but
when it becomes more relevant is when we
get down here and we have some case
studies so case studies are often for
farmers what happened in the region or a
farmer - becomes of high relevance so
high currency and relevance here but for
me trying to publish in journals it's
got low data integrity so I can actually
talk to other scientists with those case
studies because they're not considered
to have really good controls so what
we're doing is scientist is trying to
operate from up here way down to here to
get things to happen no personal opinion
here has low currency relevance and low
data integrity so you may think you know
everything but actually unless it's got
some science behind it it probably isn't
that good and I'm not sure where we put
Donald Trump on that particular diagram
myths and legends maybe over here I
don't know and as I mind so what I'm
going to try and do is give you a little
bit of data to say look this is this is
what I base things on but then try and
give you a few case studies of people
that have implemented some of the things
we've talked about in some of the
results that they've got from doing so
this is me you can spot me here as a
callow youth look and I did wear shorts
and I don't show my students that but
that's pretty much how many of my
students look at the moment so I
finished I did some farming at Bell
Pluta for part of my prank
and I finished and I went overseas and I
was given a book when I left it was
called the village pub so we visited 87
village pubs in England my wife and I it
was fantastic got us off the main roads
but what I was doing it was actually
working on climate change and that was
2022 many years ago twenty to twenty
three years ago and at that time people
were just starting to measure carbon
dioxide levels and start to think about
whether climate change was going to
occur and as a young scientist oh well
I've not really heard much about this so
I did some investigation and thought
yeah actually I think this is real I was
working out whether we could grow wheat
and Spain or not anymore what was going
to happen in 25 years so that was what I
was you know doing my research on and
then I came higher
and I was given a brief one of the nice
things about the university is you given
a brief we don't care what you do
research on just do something very nice
brief to be given and that's what it was
and I said well if I put climate change
with farming actually in New Zealand the
predicted biggest impact is on the east
coast of New Zealand
it's from Central Otago through the
Hawke's Bay that's where climate change
is supposed to have the biggest impact
and more importantly actually they're
already coping with the greatest
variability of climate of anywhere in
New Zealand any way they cope with years
of rainfall no rainfall cold with the
whole lot so I didn't really talk about
climate change for twenty years and some
people I don't still don't talk about it
with them but I talk about trying to
cope with the variability that occurs
from farming on the east coast of New
Zealand and so that's what I did I said
well let's work on that the other thing
was there was no one really working on
anything but rye grass and white clover
when I came out 25 years ago so I
thought well I'll do something different
everything we do is actually on our dry
land website so if you're looking for
information from my research team that's
basically at Lincoln University slash
dryland and I'll put this presentation
there as well and it'll just have
today's date and go on it so you'd be
able to have a look at that if you want
to as well the first experiment I ever
did those of you that heard me speak
before will recognize this it was very
simple we've got a cocksfoot pasture and
we said well what actually makes plants
grow here's our normal cocksfoot
let's said all the water we can to it so
we've just bought $10,000 with a center
pivot irrigation
or let's add all the nitrogen we can to
it here all it said irrigation and
nitrogen here and so that's what we did
and we looked there was a nine year old
one a cocksfoot scheme so it doesn't
have a lot of leg in a minute and it was
pretty grass dominant but the results
actually have transferred when we've
gone and worked on Grimes and rye
grasses and tall fescue the same thing
happen that's pretty much what the
average growth rate for the dryland
pasture was was about six and a half
tons of dry matter that we got when we
just added water we took that to ten
tons
now if you've just spent a lot of money
converting to a dairy farm that's not a
great change in the amount of yield that
you get
what interested me was that one when we
gave those pastures all the nitrogen
they needed we went from six and a half
tons to sixteen tons so that highlighted
how nitrogen deficient those pastures
were the consequence of of that line is
that farmers recognized that water
wasn't their main limitation in
Canterbury now remember this is
Canterbury 20 years ago
all those dryland farmers being
converted into center permit irrigate is
actually the main limitation wasn't
water
it was nitrogen and so to produce 22
tons of dry matter that's what they
actually do is they add nitrogen and
water to get 22 tons of dry matter
that's pretty much what's happened if we
if we look at this graph and you look at
the blue line at the top this line here
has all the water it wanted and all the
nitrogen it wanted so the only thing
that's causing it to go up and down is
temperature and if I account for
temperature I can do that I simply
account for temperature and instead of
saying that today is Thursday I
accumulate how much temperature we get
today and if I do that I can get my 22
tonnes of dry matter and say that that
pasture grew seven kilograms of dry
matter per hectare per temperature unit
that I've accumulated okay so that's the
22 tonnes and I've got rid of the wiggly
line and this one here is the irrigated
one that had no nitrogen so which
produced three and a half kilos of dry
matter four that's the nitrogen gap
that's what was missing in those
pastures there was the potential yield
gap that we have in those dryland
pastures so what's happened to nitrogen
applied in New Zealand well that's
what's happened to nitrogen applied in
New Zealand because people started doing
this around here and recognised that if
I put water on I'm not really getting
much of response so we have increased
their nitrogen footprint and nitrogen
use quite dramatically in recent times
with their nitrogen production is a very
inefficient process so we produce a huge
amount of carbon dioxide it's an energy
intensive process but I'm not begging
nitrogen because without it we wouldn't
have seven and a half billion people on
the planet
that's a good thing or a bad thing
doesn't matter until the 1950s there
were about two billion people on the
planet after that with nitrogen
fertilizer it's allowed the population
to increase exponentially prior to that
the haber-bosch process which produces
the nitrogen if you looked at farming in
the 1920s it wouldn't have been much
different from the 1820s or the 1720s
it's really the advent of nitrogen that
allowed us to grow wheat crops it
allowed us to industrialize rice
production that has allowed the growth
of what people now call industrial
agriculture so that's what happens and
that's the urea use in Canterbury since
about 2002 it's gone up on average eight
and a half thousand tons per year every
year okay now you can shake your head
when you look at that but if you look at
the previous graph you can understand
why that's happened because they put
water on and nothing grew because
actually what was limiting their
production and what limits their
production all the time and what limits
every plant's production is nitrogen I
haven't got a nitrogen I don't grow so
what we now have is the difficulty of
we've still got yellow nitrogen
deficient pastures all over Canterbury
and thousand kilos are being deposited
from a urine patch causing us
environmental problems so there's a real
dilemma on how we deal with this issue
but actually we've still got in
deficient pastures and if you drive
around Southland in the spring and you
see those urine patches that's the yield
potential that you must say that's the
gap that's accurate one of the other
things that happens is we add nitrogen
fertilizer is we stop nitrogen fixation
so this is loosen and white clover and
what happened to them as we increase
nitrogen fertilizer application this is
the percentage of their nitrogen that
they derived free from the atmosphere
how much did they fix with nitrogen
fixation so all of it when they've got
no fertilizer and then it decreases down
as we increase the fertilizer rate so if
we put a lot of nitrogen on we suppress
the nitrogen fixation we also give the
advantage to the grass and we end up
with very grass dominant pasture
natural state of affairs and now the
dairy industry and Canada a lot of the
time it is when the cows leave the
paddock they call the arere truck in and
and I don't have an issue with that
because that's actually makes sense
biologically but what I was trying to
get at was this one do I really want to
be doing that or can I get the dryland
farmers to get somewhere between the six
and a half they've got now in the
sixteen that's possible by having
nitrogen on the system and the way to do
that if we look at sorry if we look at
that from a summer perspective I'll just
go back to that Griffith year you can
see in both of these cases we've got a
dry period through the summer if I count
for that summer while looking at the
moisture response what you find is
here's my seven kilos of dry matter
three cubed greasy day at my 22 tons of
dry matter in the spring if I've got
water and I have nitrogen in the system
that pasture that grew 15 tons of dry
matter is growing as fast as the one
because it's exactly the same it's got a
nitrogen and it's got water and then it
runs out of water now plants are not
that clever but if ever you've spoken to
them recently but they don't really talk
back that well they don't know they're
running out of water
so what they do is grow as fast as they
possibly can and then bang they run out
of water and that's why you've got a
flat line there so we ran out of water
and then the slope of verse is pretty
much the same of this life of this so
here's I can't do much about it but
there's huge potential for me to grow
feed and spring when I've got water and
in autumn when I've got water if I have
nitrogen in the system because nitrogen
is used at the same right water is used
at the same rate whether the pasture has
nitrogen or not so this shows you what a
bucket of water looks like here's my
bucket of water in its full this is
basically your soil profile on your farm
when you've got fuel capacity start
sweet and then we use the water as we go
through the summer period and then we
get dry and we've got a little bit of
rainfall happening so we come up a bit
but more
I'm full and then at the end of the
season hopefully we've filled the bucket
again it's a dry land
rain feed sort of system but both the
dry land plus nitrogen in the dry land
without nitrogen pastures used that back
in a water at about the same rate
because the use of water is driven by
physics it's driven by the humidity the
wind speed and the temperature and you
know the use of water because you've
heard that today we're going to lose
five millimeters vedepo transpiration
all that's saying is how much water are
we losing from the system we're losing
five mils of water and every day we lose
some water not five mils if you've got
nitrogen and two mils if you haven't
it's five mils that's what the
evapotranspiration is on any given day
driven by temperature wind speed and
humidity and that's what's going to
happen so they're pretty much says I can
use lots of water efficiently the same
bucket of water sorry efficiently or not
depending on with rahi being in the
system so what it means is this patch
here in this patch here are using the
water at the same rate that clear
alright so my philosophy was well if I
know that it can I get dryland pastures
to be more efficient than what they
currently are because we know we have a
limited water supply we know nitrogen
makes plants grow we know we've got a
meat animal demand particularly during
lactation and we know that we can grow
more feed in spring if we have some
nitrogen in the system we want to
minimize impact on a year in water be
productive and profitable and socially
acceptable and my answer was well I
think we can do that with legumes and it
wasn't that new because when I was a
student that was what I was taught it's
sort of changed a bit but well how do we
make the system actually operate so when
I started working there was I'd been
taught about loosen when I was a student
at Lincoln by a professor professor
Langer the late Professor Langer who
died last week
but I've been taught about loose and I
came back to New Zealand no one was
talking about it so can we use
soli games fix about 25 to 30 kilos of
nitrogen per ton of Liam that you grow
and that doesn't matter if it's beans or
it's peas or its course or its white
clover or its loosing or sub clover
about 25 30 kilos of nitrogen fixed for
nothing from the atmosphere for every
tonne of legume that you grow that's
what you get put into your system okay
and we also know that hive eating value
pastures look like that the leafy
there's not a lot of deep material
there's a lot of dicot a lot of liam in
there and a little bit of grass so
that's what we're looking for and we
also know that if we want to grow
animals fast and I had to grow them fast
300 grams per head per day or more then
I have to actually have an MA of 12 and
the only pastures that do their a mostly
clover pastures good quality loose soon
rate pairs ja or bidam that Mother's
Milk if I get the national average of
around 150 odd grams per head per day
really what I'm dealing with is average
rye grass growing pasture but he may
have a bear team now for my dryland
systems I've got a graph later but for a
lot of the people I work with they had
to get a lamb from birth to slaughter in
a hundred days because I've only got
three months of growth September October
November or October November December
and then it's dry so they either sell
stores and get hit by a store market or
they've got to grow animals quicker so
if you think about that if I have a five
kilo booth weight and I want to get to
thirty five kilo live weight to finish
I've got to put on 300 grams bahid per
day over a hundred days that's just the
numbers that's just what it says and to
do that I therefore need high-quality
pastures and we also know that animals
like to eat legumes given a choice
they'll eat 70% liam 30% grass so when
we put them on a paddock and there's not
very very much liam that's what they go
and eat so we constantly put pressure on
the lagoon
but I wanna he'll block constantly it's
the legging that gets eaten so over time
the he'll block starts to deteriorate in
terms of their production because the
thing they'll eat when they target and
particularly use they will target the
high protein they'll target that need
you so I asked around white people
weren't using leucine at that time and
got a few answers and so what I've got
here is a precis of some of the results
of the research that we've done in
getting the lucerne system operating now
I don't care whether it's a red clover
and plantain or its sub clover it's
white clover or what it is that might
work in your farm system the principles
are pretty much the same
it's a liam that will drive production
it's a league in that the u requires
just pre lambing and.and as their lemon
because that's when the greatest demand
is coming on and any animal that's
losing weight during that time as an
animal that's harder to put back weight
back on your to put more feed back into
them before you take them through to
toughing the following year so
high-quality feed is very important
through their early lactation period
from an establishment perspective
loosen'd does based on free draining
soils with same sort of pH and fertility
as rye grass white clover we saw about
ten kilos per hectare and we use peat
and occu lated seed particularly if
you're putting in lucerne stand into an
area that hasn't had one before then you
need the inoculant for a lot of our
legumes red clover white clover there's
actually the bacteria that will fix
nitrogen floating in the atmosphere here
now and if you sow them under the ground
they'll actually grow pretty well we
generally spring so occasionally we
autumn so and we generally cultivate all
direct drill now leucine can be
successfully direct drilled if you are
direct drilling anything if it's weeds
or it's looser whatever it is you should
be thinking about using something like
diammonium phosphate one of the things
that direct drilling does is it doesn't
mineralize nitrogen to give those plants
a kick off because you're not actually
turning the soil over so a little bit of
phosphorous is very important when
you're establishing a suede crop for
example particularly if you're direct
drilling it it becomes really important
the root system the more important the
phosphorus becomes phosphorus is the
energy source for plants because what
we're trying to do with a Lucerne stand
is grow a decent tap root and this one
is one and a half meters long after
eight months so you know it's growing
about a centimeter a day that one
actually came out of Pleasant point it
was sent to me by a farmer when they had
a flood there a few years ago and it
washed away a part of his paddock and he
sent me sent me through a picture of his
plant in Central Otago those you've
grown driven through there you'll see
there's quite a big change in that so
one of the key things we've done here is
autumn spraying really important if
you've got a weird autumn and you've got
brown top dominant pastures or you've
got California thistles you're trying to
kill that's the time to do it the autumn
is the critical time because the plants
are taking sugar down from the top to
the roots so that's an author the thing
that really happens every year and
pretty much but even some willow trees
over there
that's what deciduous trees do they take
the nitrogen out of the leaves and they
store it in the trunk or they store it
in the roots and they store nitrogen
because they can't make nitrogen but
it's the nitrogen that makes the leaf
green that allows photosynthesis to
happen so our deciduous trees actually
take that light region out of the leaves
the tune lovely yellow and red and all
sorts of colors but it's the nitrogen
they're storing and waiting for next
year so does the brown top so does the
Californian thistle if you want to
control Kelly thistles top them in the
spring we'd wipe them in the autumn with
a trans locatable herbicide that's when
they'll be taking sugars down so the key
thing here this is low rainfall
obviously is to conserve moisture and
killed the root mass seek and spraying
in the spring but these are really you
know did and this is just to reach
drilled so that's an autumn spray that's
then been seek and sprayed in the spring
again with some insecticide and then
drilled in the drilling here as the
loosens being direct drilled in here
seed plus fertilizer and that fertilizer
as the phosphorus phosphorus is what's
keeping you warm
the moment it's the energy source for
all of us and for plants it's the energy
source for them to do photosynthesis and
it's the energy source for them to do
nitrogen fixation so plants actually
need phosphorus that's why we do super
phosphate but here we're just talking
about banding at below the plant and
giving that plant a good kick off when
it gets going one of the other issues
that comes up is people get concerned
about carbon soil carbon everyone wants
soil carbon
I don't want soil carbon okay this is
organic Medus this is a fetch sitting on
top of soil I don't mind the soil carbon
down here but this carbon here actually
stops nutrient cycling so one of the
problems when you get a thick thatch of
brown on top or a buildup of material on
the top of your pasture is it's
difficult to establish in here you've
got to get rid of that I can't put a
seed in here and expect it to grow but
that's often the thatch we have when
we're breaking in new lands so we've got
to get rid of that thatch and we might
use a rye corn crop or something like
that to be able to do that that's one of
the reasons that these cereal crops work
so well when we're breaking in that
she'll and is that we put a seed and
what we're doing in that case is we can
put a rye corn seed at depth through
this I can't put a clover seed in here
and I can't put it down here because
it's too deep it won't come up but a big
cereal will go in there and it'll then
come up so the cereal crop in that case
is being used to break down that organic
matter and often farmers that put in
their rye corn crop or their oak crop or
whatever it might be find that the first
year crop isn't very good and the reason
that's not very good is because they're
generally putting nitrogen on to grow
this crop but the nitrogen is being used
well by the microbes to break down this
cabin because you've got to have
nitrogen in the system to get the
breakdown of that carbon so we lose some
of that nitrogen but then if we break
feed this through the winter we return
some urine and then that urine helps and
the seeking year crop is generally much
better so on a dry situation that's the
way we've predominantly been breaking in
it
sort of land from establishment in
cultivated areas and Canterbury will
sell in about October and we'll get our
first crop in December and we graze that
if it's weedy and then we start
rotational grazing we don't need it to
flower if it does that's great but we
don't need Lucerne to be flowering as
we're rotationally grazing it the key
thing is to be patient I'm not going to
go through all the technical details of
this if you've got specific questions
around this we can do it but in 40
minutes I can't give you how we do
loosen ABC I just wanted to give you
some principles some other principles
growth is what we call kilograms of dry
matter per hectare per day okay so we
need to understand that growth is about
catching light and one thing to keep in
your head is that light is instantaneous
if I don't catch the light today it's
not there tomorrow the soil moisture is
I can conserve that for tomorrow I can
consider the nutrients for tomorrow but
light is instantaneous you either
captured or you lose it so capturing
light becomes really important because
light is the driver of kilograms of dry
matter per hectare most of you think
kilograms of dry matter per hectare per
day what I like what's my growth rate
actually what you're talking about is
how much photosynthesis happened today
how much carbon was made how much sugar
did we make okay and then and to do that
you've got to capture light and then
development is when the plants flower or
when do they produce leaves and those
things are driven by temperatures
they're driven by the same sorts of
things and they're influenced by
environmental signals plants can tell
time and they tell it by the day length
how did the willow tree know to drop its
leaves because the days were getting
shorter okay so that's how they're
telling the time so that's our energy
capture device whenever I don't have a
canopy of leaves then I'm losing light
from the system one of the issues we
have in spring is we have our pastures
so short that actually we are losing
light from the system because if they're
completely short they're not capturing
all of the light that's available if I I
just wanted to illustrate that if I've
got
me too squid that area here and I've got
it completely covenant in the ground I
have what's called a leaf area index of
1 1 unit of green leaf 1 meter of green
leaf a meter of ground to capture all of
the available light I actually need
about three and a half meters of green
leaf for every meter of ground so I
actually need the leaves to be up a
little bit to be capturing and
intercepting the light because there's
generally more light available for us
than the plants have the ability to
capture so we're going to capture all of
that light what we found with the
Lucerne was that if we irrigated the
crop and we had a mean temperature of 12
and the spring it's growing about 60
kilos of dry matter per hectare per day
but in the autumn it's still irrigated
it's still capturing all of the light
but it's only growing 35 kilos of dry
matter per hectare per day so this is
these are it's got nitrogen because it's
a leaking so we said about trying to
work out why do we get this big
difference in growth rates between
spring and autumn so this was a PhD
students job at Lincoln and we had crops
that we grazed 38 days resting and four
days grazing were crops that we grazed
after 25 days 19 gave them three days of
resting the experiment doesn't matter
too much what matters is what happened
below ground so this is the start of the
spring and I've got about three tons of
biomass below ground because we don't
often think about what's happening below
ground but below ground the Lucerne
stand and I suspect the red clover in
the chicory have this mass of carbon and
nitrogen stored and then they use that
and transport it up and therefore we get
high growth rates hence we get those
higher growth rates that I showed you on
the spring and then in the autumn in for
the plants there's only spring in autumn
plants only register when the days are
getting longer and when the days are
getting shorter that's how they tell the
time and if they do that then at the end
of the season this crop had got back to
its three tonnes of dry matter and look
pretty good so it was doing very well
but
the consequence of that if I was only
measuring above ground was that this
that's being put under the ground makes
it look like it's got a lower growth
rate so the difference between these two
lines is that really the mean is about
here this is from stuff coming from
below ground up Californian thistles
exploding in the spring this is from
sugar being put under the ground into
the rhizomes and into the roots going
down that's when I put my herbicide on
the Kelly thistles and get them because
they're taking it down so Lucian is
doing that once we understood that the
same thing happening if we don't if we
don't look after the Lucian stand the
same thing happened in the second
treatment but we killed that crop in two
years because we never gave it a rest in
the autumn needs a risk to get back to
three tonnes to be breeding so what that
told us was we can be much more flexible
with grazing a loosen stand than we ever
thought we could be so we now graze
loosen stand I had people that are
grazing loosen stands that are about 10
centimeters tall in the spring they will
start when the first panic and the
rotation is about that big okay now I
used to be told when I was a student you
wait for 10% flowering sometimes the
crops with us but who's heard that he
was in flower okay that's what I got
told
and this set of data I've just shown you
is my scientific explanation for no we
don't we can start when the lucien is
quite small we can start rotational
grazing on that or we can actually we
have some people who made a low stocking
rate er actually set stalked on that
because they've got so much leucine on
their property if they didn't have some
animals on it during spring and when
it's just starting to kick off they'd
run in a room so we can graze before
flowers of d appear ideally with using
lambs the growing point is at the top of
the plant so once I remove that growing
point the growing point of a plant is
the bit that produces the leaves it's
also the bit that tells the temperature
okay so the growing point at the top now
with a grass that growing point is below
ground so pokes the leaves above ground
and therefore I can see it stopped
grasses because if I remove
the leaf another one will pop up because
the the point the growing point the bit
that produces the leaf is protected and
it's below ground with loose units at
the top of the plant so if I take it off
it has to start and produce it a whole
new one from from that crown of shoots
that it's got so that's why we
rotationally graze loose soon and we can
set stock grasses so here we're looking
at a stand pre grazing now I've got that
at 20 to 25 centimetres tall as being
the first paddock that we're grazing in
September we've now shifted this down
we're actually at Lincoln grazing often
the first week of September and we're on
to 10 to 15 centimetres okay so it's
then becomes a really viable option
because we're using it early in the
spring this one looks like it's 10 to 15
centimetres because the photo has been
taken on an angle but that's what a
grazing rotation looks like so this is
that first paddock it's got to be at 2
tons a dry matter second paddock we go
into third paddock 43056 panic because
we're rotationally grazing around the
paddocks that all looks pretty good and
I've come back here a top paddock one
two and three and about three town about
30 centimetres which is perfect for
going back in for the second rotation
perfect height to be going in 25 30
centimeters 30cm metres tall but look
these ones here gotta weigh on me so
they'd be paddocks that I probably
should be dropping out of the rotation
and cutting and carrying so what we're
in an experimental situation is very
difficult to do there but if I'd shifted
this set of lines down a bit which is
what we're doing now then actually all
of these come down a bit and I no longer
have to drop those out so I'm maximizing
the feed that's actually going in to the
animals so we're starting grazing at
about 10 centimetres tool in the spring
and that's about twelve use plus twins
per hectare is what we're starting on at
about that point so if I've got a 20 hit
deer block of low soon and maybe I've
got it split in into five paddocks
that's 20 times
12news plus 28 years that's 240 in a
mall so it'd make sense
you
would have been an absolutely no problem
start grazing 22nd of August that's a
month earlier than we were starting when
we first started doing this research I'd
be quite comfortable coming into the
sluicey understand now 22nd of August
okay so that's very that's for me at
Lincoln but it's a month earlier than we
ever were previously and then it grows
it continues to grow and we grew some
stuff that 60 centimeters tall and you
can't see a flower anywhere near it so
it's this big and there's no flowers if
I'm waiting 14% flowering what a waste
okay so the key message is let's get on
to the loosen and the spring and look
after it in the autumn triplets happily
grazing some malucia and grass here in
priority stock lamb beef deer we've got
dairy cows grazing lucerne now once
they're on it they should stay on it and
we want to stay on a rotation with those
with that mob of animals if you haven't
got loose in and you'd like to have it
about 20 hectares is a good amount to
start with because it'll take your
Hoggett mob for example five hectares
becomes a nuisance five hectares cut and
carry you know but if you're just
starting 28 years is probably what you
want to do and that'll give you the
opportunity of having five four here
paddocks and being able to work some of
us out and see see whether it's going to
work on your property high numbers for
short periods of time no more than seven
to ten days on any individual panic and
then they're off these bulls are quite
happily grazing with the ewes and lambs
and early spring in Marlborough but a
fibres out there for them to eat and
some salts available to them blue stone
stores salt or sodium in its roots so it
needs sodium to be available so it's
just a normal Salt Lick gets put out
whenever your grazing Lucy needs some
sodium out yeah one of the things that
Doug Avery started to do for those who
don't know Doug farms in Marlborough
it's pre grazed my when the Lucien's
really lush and the spring I have no
scientific evidence to say if this is
good or bad but it seems to work so
instead of
oops go backwards go big go big oh it's
not wanting to go back for me here we go
instead of having to put the fibery out
if you've loaned some strips the animals
will actually come in here and eat this
so that's the fiber and because whatever
we put out is hey is not going to be as
high-quality as the stuff and the
paddock the animals will tend to not eat
the hay you can't get every animal to
eat hay because it's not quite as good a
quality and they'll always try and
choose the highest quality feed but if
you have some strips like this then this
is actually just wilted for about 48
hours before the animals have gone in
and that deals with that lush lucerne
that can be a problem in the very early
spring and you can see the Bulls are in
here eating the loose and at the same
time in the autumn because we know it's
putting stuff under the ground we look
after the plant so what I'm trying to
say is I think Lucerne fits the breeding
systems really well we've got a lot of
animals coming in the spring it's
producing a whole lot of carbohydrate
coming up producing more feed than it
should based on how much light it's
intercepted but in the autumn we've got
to recognize it's going to slow down and
so in the autumn we've got to give it a
chance to build up those root reserves
and that means trying to leave it have a
flower or an extended period in autumn
as anytime between the second week of
January and the end of May that gives
you a pretty big window to get it right
and go here the stand needs a rest okay
and that way we can keep stands or wait
around for a while in terms of quality
the Emmy of the leaf is always above 12
the Emmy of the steam is always about 8
the reason we're trying to graze it
about 30 centimetres is because that's
about 3 tons of biomass if I grace 5
tonnes I've got two and a half tonnes of
leaf and two and a half tonnes of steam
if I graze
two tonnes I've got two tonnes of leaf
in no steam it's all highly palatable
there's a bear two and a half tons of
good stuff in a loose sense game which
is about 25 30 centimetres tall now if
I'm making hay I'll probably have to do
40 centimetres because I need that bit
of steam at the bottom to have hardened
off so I can actually cut it and so
that's why you tend to find hay crops a
taller
but from a grazing perspective actually
that's where we want to be and I don't
know what that is it's just that my
hands go there so you know it's that
that's what we want to go into a para
can eat about that and if it's Wayne
lambs probably about that but that's
about where we want to come under loosen
stand to maximize the quality that we're
eating we can't have animal health
issues so a vaccination program has to
be good and I'm not an animal scientist
but people tell me a seven and one is
the best option for a loose hoon
situation b12 injections for if you've
got a cobalt deficiency and we don't
flush on loosen if we can avoid it in
dull or wet weather because these little
spots here they cause a compound and
they loosen to rise and when it rises up
it's called chemists roll it actually
suppresses ovulation rate so you don't
get as many twins as you expect and we
may find that we get that this year cuz
there was a lot of wet autumn and if
farmers use their loosen and it may find
they're scanning and lambing percentages
are down a bit but this is some recent
PhD work what we found was if you're in
that situation you can leave them on the
loose in until two weeks before the RAM
goes out so they can be going through
the window if you go through the summer
putting on weight doing really well and
then two weeks before you want to put
the rear mirror they should be off the
loo soon and then you won't have a
conception problem okay once they're
pregnant they can go back on Lucy and no
problem at all it doesn't cause abortion
there's no issues with that
it's just that leaf disease from fungal
causes it some problems Reed got the
fiber that mowing helps in that
situation bloat we know about it can
always be an issue I'm not going to say
you won't get bloke people do get bloat
and it's devastating when it happens
okay sodium we've talked about because
we need we need you might see sometimes
animals go into a Lucy and panic and
that and the third paddock in the
rotation and they're just eating the
fence line it's often because they're
eating the weeds because the weeds have
got sodium in them because we haven't
they have any excess to sodium so start
well that's fifteen between us enemies
tool qualities maximized at thirty
centimeters the leaf and the saw
part of the high quality stuff dari
about the residual that's in a panic
once you've grazed it
it's of no consequence to the plant it
looks messy
so if you don't like a messy looking
stand you can go and trim it off but
otherwise it's of no consequence
drop out paddocks if it's getting away
what you should be doing ana-lucia and
grazing in the spring is I'm grazing
panic for and my six paddock rotation
what does paddock one look like I'm
grazing paddock five what does paddock
one look like because I want it in two
paddock one the second time when it's
about 30 centimeters tall so that's how
you should be looking at your stand
there's no defined number of days
grazing rotation nothing like that it's
when do I get back to about 30
centimetres and for us at Lincoln's
sometimes that's been after 28 days
sometimes it's been after 35 4 to 5
weeks has been what we've required when
we started that short one - when we get
back onto the first paddock again the
second time around we've talked about an
extended period of autumn growth and in
some areas if you've got a wet autumn
then use your grass for tapping not your
loosen and weed control the weather it
is then the weed control becomes really
important so that's sort of an overview
of loo soon and I'll take technical
questions later if people have got them
I just wanted to give you an overall
understanding of the plant and then give
you a little bit of case study stuff so
this is Doug average who's who Doug
speak a number of here Doug speak was
retired he's in town now I'm going to
visit him this weekend my own will still
live in Blenheim so I'm off to visit my
in-laws and I'll go and see Doug but
I'll see him in Teheran we'll have
coffee instead of me driving out to the
farm but phrase is still on the farm I
Gompers at Frazer this is the story this
is the graph that really turned Doug's
mind was when I shown him this one and
said you know what because of that
remobilize ation plus the plants never
nitrogen deficient in your limited
bucket that you get there at Vaughn
Avery and Marlborough in the spring you
can do about 30 kilos of dry matter for
every millimetre of water you've gotten
the soil whereas your grass is only
doing about 13 so all of a sudden
instead of producing two and a half
tonnes per hectare and spring you're
producing six tonnes per hectare and
spring because you've dealt with that
nitrogen deficiency that I talked about
by having the league game in the system
and he got that and he then started to
understand that what he really was is a
farmer of water and it's maximizing the
use of the water that becomes important
when we talk about five mils of
evapotranspiration what that means is
you they actually lost 50 tonnes of
water from a hectare you know the
process of photosynthesis is not about
saving water it's about getting carbon
dioxide into the plant to do that it's
got a little holes that open and the
water flies out you can't change that
that's biology but we can maximize the
use of that water by having nitrogen
efficient plants and the system
particularly in spring hence my desire
to have sub clover and because it's our
earliest growing medium that's 14th of
August so obviously lots of using lambs
around and one of the things that we
find is that you get hog at mating as
you put more weight because those new
Lambs oh go back again you lambs here
will get mums milk
so they'll do 300 grams per head per day
and then they'll get straight lu soon
and it's much easier to get them up to
55 kilos by the time they come around
and saved in your hog at mating and we
know that as you put weight on hog it's
you increase the percentage that you're
going to get out of them so the whole
system starts to spiral up because
you've got better grown you lambs wider
that from that first period of growth
when they're just born right through
they stay on the loose in and they're
looking pretty good by the time you come
to mating it's an example of them
growing and just another example of if
you this is October and he's still
cutting some strips in here because it's
been raining as a 550ml rainfall
environment on Doug's property he
increased the land area between 2002 and
2012 I stopped he gave me the figures
every year but I stopped in 2012 because
about then he started to lease a lot of
land and take another farm all except
when it became too complicated to try
and do a true comparison between the
systems but over a decade when I first
sort of met Doug he went from
1100 Heatley's to 1800 a sheet numbers
went up a bird about 12 percent but the
key thing was the performance so we've
got a 28% lift and lambing we're no
longer selling stores at 13.3 we're
selling 19 kilo lambs that are going off
prime so we've got a 43% increase here
in total lamb sold we've gone up almost
100% now I know we've got an increase in
area of about a third to a half but
we've gone up a hundred percent in terms
of lamb production now to pretty much
the same flock in the return obviously
being quite high and for those of you
that are interested then he's written a
fairly good story that you might want to
have a look at called the resilient
farmer one of the key things he says
about that is it wasn't playing sailing
and so I wanted to illustrate that
whenever you have a farm system your
farm system or whatever you're operating
on you know that system so you've
maximized that system and its operating
as well as it possibly can because
wherever your farm is after say five 16
years you've got it as optimized as it
can possibly be
so your ability to have to change it
becomes limited you already know where
the animals should be on any given day
or how much feed you're going to grow
you've optimized that farm pretty much
and so your system starts to plateau and
what we're talking about is how do we
implement a new technology like Lucerne
grazing well generally what we find is
things go backwards and Ford AG they
went backwards quite quickly but this is
you get a new car or you whatever it is
you do something different you start to
play squash and you've never played
before you know there's a damn period
here where you go backwards a bit and
it's always going to happen because
you're trying something new but what
you're wanting is look if I keep on this
path I'm going to stay here so I go
backwards a bit and then I've got
potential to increase my output quite
dramatically that's what we talk about
when we say transformational change
incremental change is a little bit
transformation is big output change what
agribusiness
there's a problem here and this is if
you read Doug's book that sort of when I
met him when he was down here you know I
and it took a bit to come out and
there's a risk you're going backwards ah
this isn't gonna work so we have to
minimize that and hopefully that's what
science agribusiness technology people
are doing that's their job is to try and
minimize that but don't be scared if
things don't work the first time you
grow on a rape crop or a plantain red
clover crop or whatever it might be that
you try you can't expect it to work as
well as what you've been doing for ten
years because you don't know the nuances
of that system so you have to learn how
to deal with that and our job is to try
and minimize this negative the output in
the risk of reversion from there maybe
the next thing is irrigation and you can
move to another I'm not sure most guys
that switch from a dryer into an
irrigation actually have a problem it
doesn't it's not plain sailing to fish
start putting an irrigator on there's a
lot of problem a lot of things to learn
keep an ID it keep it thought of that
process as I show you the next case
study this is Bob Roy 300 400 mill
rainfall and central in the Mackenzie
you know Oda Matata Dundee and Lisa
Anderson this is their property and what
happened is they had heard Doug's story
in about 2008 and they were driving back
from somewhere unless there was a fir
trip for Ravens down and she came into
my office because she was Aniak student
and she set my office and we she was
asking me some questions calendar and
what the questions were but Gandhi was
sitting there sort of a bit bored and he
saw this handout that I'd had from a
field day at Doug over his place and so
he grabbed that and he started reading
it and then he just took over the
conversation said I heard about this guy
and that was it and I don't know Gandhi
at all but he told me what he was trying
to do and I said to him well actually
your farm system your feed supply an
animal demand don't match you're trying
to produce a whole lot of animals in the
middle of January in February we don't
have any feed your for hundreds of
rainfall weren't your grazing your
loosen and that was about it that was
about the end of the conversation you
brilliantly from there from Lincoln
through to America he then just talked
to Lisa the whole way home about what
they were going to do and how it was
going to change so this is their story
after ten years there was their old
system see it stopped constantly chasing
grass hill country going backwards
because they're constantly up there
looking for every blade of grass
hundred-day supplementary feeding peak
demand and feed supply completely
misaligned so what we did was try and
implement what I call landscape farming
so we take the areas that are deeper
soils and we put some loose in and
because that's where the waters going to
run - why would I cultivate this it's
already hard and bony I'll let the water
run here and cultivate that area in the
first time they're using lambs went on
they got a phone call from the neighbor
the user lamb escaped and dear Lucy and
paddock because until high country was
traditionally cut and carried so you
know outside the box
getting started they had a little bit of
Lucerne but starting the grazing was the
big issue and in working out which bits
of our landscape can we put moose in
into and utilize loosen in there the
best thing Gandhi did was marry well
because Lisa was quite happy to cut
cages and get some idea of how much
they're actually producing she was a
numbers person and her training and
forced her to do that so they got good
support also Peter Anderson my things
with stock here and they recorded the
numbers so in the last 12 months or so
I've just being able to go back and look
at the numbers over time what they found
was kilograms of lamb weaned it was the
number of lambs you've got times their
weaning weight so that's the key period
we were looking for how much how many
kilos are you getting and that depends
on your scanning percentage your lamb
wastage and your lambing this is the key
thing that changed they decreased the
lamb wastage Marino's are not very good
mothers any of you there's no anything
about Marino's because they're generally
being starved so they give birth and say
thank God the parasites gone
and they walk away but if they feed well
then they might not walk so far and they
might actually go back and inquire as to
what that thing was that they just
dropped or maybe - look now we've got
two so the lambing percentage Liam
growth rate etc you can see the 2008
system producing about 90 to 90 tons of
weaned lamb and then starting to get an
increase from their grazing and then a
bit more and then a bit more near no
reversion I'd like to say that's because
they had some intervention from good
agribusiness and myself so they're
backwards but that's what happened and
you can see now the same property is
essentially producing 150 tons of weaned
lamb when it was producing 90 it's a 50%
increase and they've done that on a four
hundred mill rainfall environment and
there you use mated hasn't changed very
much initially so what you find is you
don't have to change your stocking rate
very much you're just feeding animals
better paths place are we all right okay
that's good because I am - putting the
two together you can see those steps and
stairs and that's the the change the key
take-home message they listen to advice
and acted on it that was the key thing
I'm just here the advice they actually
listen to the advice and acted on it
so the lucerne story has worked pretty
well it's defined a lot of systems
people are making money out of it the
sheep milk goat milk people they're all
wanting green chopped looser because
they know it's the highest quality feed
if you're making if your product is milk
out of sheep you need high quality feed
to do that and rye grass cab I'll flick
through that one except to say that part
we knew 5 to 35 kilos in 100 days the
other plant we've been interested in and
we're working on more at the moment is
sub fly though so this is the 11th of
September
Ashley Dean at Lincoln and what we're
finding is we're able to produce animals
that are growing 300 grams per head per
day very early and within a hundred days
I mean Ashley Dean is essentially a
grave all for those who don't know
it's a stone farm at Lincoln that they
put some soil in pretty much what the
dairy cows are on and most of the plains
there's not a lot of soil there but
within a three-month period we are
averaging 300 that's about 330 grams per
head per day and if you do that 300
grams per head per day the time to go
from 25 to 35 kilos live weight is about
a month or is if you're only doing a
hundred grams per head per day it's
three months so you've got to have
animals growing fast have to get 20 to
megajoules per day if I've got 12
megajoules from my Lucerne they need to
be out two kilos of loosin per day
that's what I need to eat to be able to
do that and then they're gone in a month
from a sub clover story if you're
interested in sub clover this is amol
broccoli team Paulo David and Joe Greg
and their staff is online on the beef
and lamb website and what they pretty
much did was all through grazing
management David learnt how to graze he
didn't even know he had sub clover on
the property when we visited he didn't
know it was there and he grazed it
properly get that sort of pasture in the
spring and his values here saying he's
gone from sixty to seventy six tons of
meat all they did was put in stock water
and fences so they could manage this sub
clover no seed introduced in that so if
there's any seed merchant to you but
they just managed what they had and knew
which league in was going to work in
their environment you can have clover
and sometimes that can be too short so I
just wanted to finish sometimes high
quality feed is not good enough by
itself there needs to be intake this is
too short and what you find this is a
sheep well then you may have a living
and a half but a decent intake so you
can get decent and take here depending
on what the herbage mess is so you can't
just have high quality feed there's also
got to be a
decent Amanda herbage so I might take
home heroes sometimes our pastures are
too short and it's not the quality of
pasture that's limiting our production
it's the intake you've got to have both
and that's why the lucerne works is why
the sub clovers work and there I've done
sorry
I'm around Moran til the end of the day
some people got questions happy to
answer them thanks Graham we looked at
our place because we were in the Waimea
Valley and I see that's got the greatest
change in climate and so you're looking
towards drier okay and I thought a great
idea we plant looser well then I looked
around and there wasn't a paddock that
didn't have fill tiles in it that
required some extra care with that help
bed is looser in field trials I'd put
the loose in in and find out
very brave I'll give you a ring so so
what we know is that it will find them
and it'll probably block them but the
advantage you get out of it I suspect
will be worth the hassle and I'd have a
go and I'd find the dryer of the
paddocks obviously north west face if
there's any slope at all any contour I'd
go under those contours first but the
benefits are so great that I would give
it a go
that would be my advice and if I get it
wrong well you've done a panic and I'm
sorry but at least unless you do it
we're not going to know how far no what
what is your the the highest rainfall
that you can suitably okay loosen it
rainfall is a misnomer it's when does it
rain okay so a lot of people think
they've got 1200 millimeter rainfall and
go you should be dairy farming but
actually it all falls in June and July
and August actually what matters is how
much rainfall do you get in October
November December January and February
if you have six weeks eight weeks of dry
then it's worth putting loosenin it's
worth having a go with a deep taproot of
legume that will give you some summer
production and you only got three weeks
of dry well most years you'll get
through there so the amount of rainfall
doesn't matter it's when it falls that
really matters
so yeah it's easy to say 400 mils and a
dermatology absolutely you've got to do
it but I've got people at a thousand
mils of rainfall that are still doing
loose in because they're back they've
got soil like this it's already fall if
they get another 200 mils of rainfall in
August and September not actually
helping that's when it falls that
matters
hm could I've got the nod for another
year you just do a few water tables at
20 meters and you're 20 meters yep and
you're your tip rates going down a meter
and it's you got Tim which is dry is is
it still beneficial and you're farming
on Gribble if you found me on gravel
what else you going to grow and I've had
situations and of people that sell the
gravel ringing me to try and kill the
elusive because at the end of the load
that going down to get the gravel they
were still loose in routes at six meters
so it won't stop at a meter it'll keep
going down as long as there is moisture
there now if the water table comes up we
don't know whether that will cut but you
know if you've got a water table that
goes up and down but if it's just down
there and you've got gravel nothing else
is going to grow on it so I know that
situation I'd probably look at all them
selling but we can talk about there at
morning tea because you're wanting to
stop there nothing to do you want other
people to bring this issue to a close
I've got people busting to get into the
door just like you to think Dirac please
and the normal sort of work
I don't it always a it's quite
remarkable you get the top-flight
speakers they make reasonably complex
sort of discussions quite simple and
easily understandable and Derek's a real
cracker at that and just an addition to
the round of applause you can drink this
on the aircraft on the way home it's for
you and that's for you as well and many
thanks again Derek so you mean a good
thank you
[Applause]