alright so here's my my solar setup that
I have going I have these 210 watt solar
cells got them both for forty four
dollars forty-four dollars for the two
solar cells pretty good deal but I still
have yet to be able to test them to make
absolutely sure that they're running at
10 watts each there any possibility i
can zoom in on this yes no okay fine it
says
it says that we've only put out a
hundred and sixty-seven milliamp hours
and I've been running this thing for
hours that's lame but uh okay i need to
get me to take out and put it in actual
direct Sun on a day that's not you know
I don't know patchy here and there and
ya want it directly at son I'll put its
own ohm resistor on them see if they
will actually give me 10 watts 10 ohms
10 ohms oh okay and it was at 12 volts
this is supposed to be 12 volt things so
12 volts 12 volts at 10 watts would be
eight hundred milliamps and we're only
doing five volts and 200 milliamps with
210 watt panels so whatever like I said
I've gotta do actual testing outside but
either way you know getting into the
soul of revolution is pretty cool I got
my my thing here you know show me how
much power is going in this thing is
keeping count of how much power actually
using this little thing down here is the
charger circuit for my battery this is
my USB battery so I'm charging up my USB
better right now and have been for hours
and when I got 167 milliamp hours in
there which is crap are 67 times five
that's that's almost 1 watt over three
hours not right bye peeps thanks