hey folks its Josh Stoney Ridge farmer
spring is finally in the air here in
North Carolina where I live in the
Piedmont of North Carolina we're
starting to get a touch of that warm
weather at that sixties and seventies
where we have a sense of urgency now
we've got to get out here and we've got
a prune our fruit trees okay and this
tree is a key for a pear tree so we're
going to give you a basic run around
here in the orchard and give you some
ideas some basic thought processes on
how we or I prune the fruit trees here
on the farm we've got about sixty five
fruit trees now here on the farm and
I'll pick the camera up and show you
we've got the beginnings of a beautiful
wonderful orchard for our family to eat
fruit off of for years to come this is
for homesteading this is not for
production this is for homesteading this
is for making our own cider making our
own vinegars making our own wine having
fruit here on the farm for us to eat and
plus when I ride down through here on
the lawnmower I'm grabbing a delicious
pear or a peach or an apple or plum it's
awesome so come on along today and we'll
show you a little bit of basic backyard
fruit tree pruning all right that's fun
[Music]
so first things first let's talk about
the trees okay now this is a pear tree
right here and I'm going to show you the
limbs that we don't want the things that
we don't want just give you a basic
rundown of information that you need to
know for pruning your trees and this
will pertain to pruning your trees in
the winter in the late winter you can
look at the trees now and tell that
they're not even starting to bud this is
the perfect time there are not a lot of
pests and the risk for the tree getting
some sort of infection or disease it's
pretty low this time of year so as we
look at the tree here you can see
several branches that are growing inward
we want to get rid of those and branches
that are touching one another that will
end up eventually rubbing one another
those are not beneficial branches okay
we also want to look at the angle at
which these branches come out we don't
want a very sharp angle we want the
angle to be somewhere near a ninety
degree angle the closer to a ninety
degree angle the better off it will be
so what you need to know is a wintertime
pruning promotes growth and a summertime
pruning [ __ ] growth so here we have an
example of a tree with the branches
coming off just like it should
coming out to the side almost at a
ninety degree angle this one's coming
out nicely the central leader right here
is growing good and if you go around the
tree you can see that this branch right
here may be a weak point but we'll have
to see as time goes on when you're
trimming major limbs off like this you
need to be thinking is this limb shading
the limb below it no it's not is this
limb shading any limbs no is this limb
shading any limbs well we've got a
little bit of an issue here so if we got
a little rot going on right here you can
see that right there so I think we're
going to take this guy out or at least
cut this one back because this one is
going to shade this limb and you can see
the deer have damaged my trees a little
bit here too now as you look at the tree
further you can see that this is growing
overtop of this guy and this one is
growing inward we want to open the tree
up and bring more light into this tree
so that we have more for
more light means more limbs means more
fruit means a better growing tree and we
want healthy trees these trees are all
within two to three years old or within
two to three years of planting coyotes
there's coyotes back here so guys have
been having a lot of trouble with
coyotes lately that rooster crowing
might have got him called in I got my
pistol with me today we've been having
some serious coyote problems they've
been trying to get in the chicken coop
at night the dogs are barking at them so
I hear I'm there
they're probably 300 yards away through
the woods but anyway let's let's get
back to it by the way a guy gave me this
this holster it's from Cold War
concealment it's a local company right
here in North Carolina
it's called Cold War concealment he
makes custom holsters here I'll show it
to you again
who makes custom holsters this is a
Smith & Wesson M&P 9-millimeter I like
it you can do all kinds of custom colors
anyway back to the fruit trees so
there's several different schools of
thought on trimming a tree there is a
central leader method where one central
leader goes up and then there's the open
center method where you're trimming the
tree back so that it is open in the
middle and shoots off large limbs kind
of curling up we really need to go to
the orchard and have the orchard guy
explain it to us but for now I just want
to walk you through what I'm gonna do so
if you're gonna trim your own fir trees
or a couple tools that you're gonna need
to take along with you we're gonna need
this little guy right here it's a corona
it's called a razor tooth saw and
basically it's for getting your larger
limbs I don't know that we'll need that
today because our trees are fairly young
and fairly new and also this is the
corona brand and it's really really good
this is the third pair that I own I keep
one in the Gator I keep one in the truck
I keep tools on the truck because you
never know when you'll need this guy or
this guy to get something out of your
way on a farm Road so I keep the tools
on the truck but this is a corona brand
also and these guys are just farm
essentials things to have I'll post
links down below to these tools
tried-and-true
trusted this guy especially is a very
trust
tool here on the farm that thing is
heavy heavy duty all right so let's get
busy and I'll show you
trimming a tree because that's what
you're here for right all right let's
examine this tree see these branches
these low branches they're just no good
for anything they're just energy sucking
branches so we're going to go ahead and
we'll get our cutters and we'll snip
those off okay we're gonna cut back here
see their growth rings right here and
that's where the hormone is the growth
hormone in the tree if you cut it here
that is going to cause new growth if you
cut it back here you get in that growth
ring and you cut off that new growth
now you're gonna think I'm scalping this
tree but if you look here you can see
there are three major branches one two
three and they're all coming off at the
correct angles that we want there's also
another one here but this angle this
crotch angle right here is just a little
tighter than what you see here okay I'm
gonna leave this guy this year and I'm
gonna take this one out because this
limb here will shade that limb so let's
cut him out now with these apple trees I
don't want a shoot shooting up to the
sky here I'm gonna be able to pick my
apples so we're gonna do a drastic cut
right here and we're going to get rid of
this guy we're gonna get rid of that
central leader right there because I
want this tree to bloom out like that
okay so that I can walk all the way
around it and pick my apples get rid of
these little dudes now I'm gonna cut
this one because the crotch angle is
just way too tight okay
I'm gonna cut him off all right then I'm
gonna go right above this little growth
ring area where the growth hormone is
and I'm gonna cut right there boom I
took that central leader off and we'll
also get this guy right here now look at
this tree it's really lopsided so let's
go on and get in here and take that guy
off and then this guy I think we'll be
okay and then that's appropriately
trimmed lopsided tree now here's an
example of a pear tree
that's just overcrowded look at this guy
right here
see how that's rubbing up against there
we got to get rid of that it's just
growing this actually comes up off and
grows toward the inside so we want to
get rid of this whole limb right here
okay we want to cut him way back all the
way back to here and these cutters
really do a good job yeah get that guy
out of there now see this guy he's
crossing over - okay go ahead and get
rid of this because it's rubbing right
there and we want to get rid of any
diseased or broken branches another
point to make if you're going tree to
tree and you don't want to spread
disease it's a good idea to have a rag
with you and basically you can take that
rag or take a coffee cup and pour some
rubbing alcohol in there and clean your
clippers in between so clean your
pruners in between trees if you suspect
any disease because if you don't and it
has blight on it you can move it from
tree to tree to tree let's look at
another tree look at how busy this tree
is look at how many branches we have
here we have a lot of growth in this
tree and we don't need that much growth
okay so we're gonna take out most of
these lololo branches and we're gonna
leave probably four or five of the major
branches with the right crotch angle
starting down low here get a little
sniffing going on something you need to
think about when you're doing your trees
in your orchard is this is your tree and
you have artistic freedom to make it
grow however you want it to grow so if
you wanted to grow out and go where you
can do that you can do whatever you want
to with your tree but you need to open
up all these branches we're gonna have
to take some out so we can open it up
and promote growth and get the tree to
grow the way we want it to grow
there's no real wrong way but you'll
learn over time what you did wrong and
hopefully you'll learn from it so the
next time you do your fruit trees you'll
learn a little bit more now I'll trim my
trees probably a little bit different
then you'll trim your trees and a pro
orchard guy will probably trim them a
little bit different I suggest you go
online and you watch a bunch of videos
ok pile all that knowledge before you go
out and you cut your fruit trees take
yourself some notes and get out there
and work and have some fun enjoy your
life be outside it's beautiful out here
today our beautiful orchard and I'm
really happy to share it with you guys
so the major take-home messages here are
when you trim trim the ones that have
the sharp crotch angle you're shooting
for a 90 degree almost crotch angle if
something is really tight it's gonna
make a weak spot and that branch is
gonna crack and break at some point get
the crisscross growth out all that
criss-crossing growth anything that's
touching any inward growth you want to
get rid of that inward growth if you
have to cut the top out of the main
leader the central leader of the tree be
sure you leave about that much about 3
buds on it so that in the springtime or
in the summertime it starts to grow
outward like that so that's it you want
to have a beautiful orchard make it your
own get out there and trim your trees
get out there and trim your bushes make
your place look beautiful do something
that'll make you proud I'm gonna get
busy I got about three hours worth of
trimming to do in about 20 minutes worth
of sunlight left time to get busy guys
thanks a lot I hope you learned a little
bit be sure you clean your tools in
between your trees click the like button
subscribe to the channel if you're not
already subscribed and if I see a coyote
I'm going to leave the camera rolling
and I'm gonna bust his butt cuz we got
coyote problems here on the farm
thanks a lot guys thanks be sure you
subscribe to the channel for not already
to subscribe click the little bell down
there and share this on social media it
will really help the channel out it'll
help me grow alright thanks for coming
to the Stoney Ridge whoa
during break
here at sweet that's way supposed to be
stone Tyrion
whoa