today we're repairing a Rain Bird inline
valve let's get started
[Music]
what about where's out you don't
necessarily have to cut out replace the
hole valve you can usually just replace
the top and internal parts unless the
valve bodies cracked or their particular
model of Bobby replacing is no longer
available the solenoid and diaphragm are
available for purchase separately for
most valves however it's often cheaper
and more effective to simply purchase a
whole new valve which will come with a
new diaphragms Illinois screws in spring
in fact replacing the valve top
including the diaphragm in Scylla noid
is the method we at sprinkler warehouse
recommend because the solenoid and
diaphragm tend to wear out at about the
same rate if you change just one or the
other you more than likely will be
working on this valve again in less than
a year
we'll start by pulling out the valve box
if your valve box is large enough you
may be able to work inside the box
without removing it however it's usually
easier to dig out the valve box and get
it out of your way here we're siphoning
water out of the hole with a hand pump
it's a good idea to wipe off the valve
to keep dirt and debris out of the
irrigation line before working on the
valve turn off the water your system at
the back flow or at the main valve
relieve the pressure by turning the
solenoid 1/2 turn cut the wires going to
the solenoid
[Music]
use a screwdriver to back out the screws
pay attention to which side of the valve
the solenoid is on remove the old
diaphragm this valve was pretty money so
we're cleaning it a little bit more now
we'll remove the top from the new donor
valve this ranbir valve has arrows
showing the direction of the water flow
pay attention to how this diaphragm is
oriented carefully remove the diaphragm
don't lose the spring
place the new diaphragm and spring on
the old valve making sure the diaphragm
is facing the correct direction now
carefully line up the new top on the old
valve making sure that the Silla node is
on the same side as it was on the top
that was removed tighten the screws
using a screwdriver don't completely
tighten them until all the screws are in
place work in a crisscross pattern be
careful to not strip the screws if that
happens you will have to replace the
entire valve strip the ends of your
wires connect one lead from the solenoid
to the hot wire
and connect the other lead to the common
wire or wires it does not matter which
lead from the solenoid connects to the
hot or common wires always use
waterproof wire connectors waterproof
wire connectors have silicon inside to
prevent water from getting to the wire
connections replace the valve box and
backfill the hole
remember sprinkler warehouse has
everything for your irrigation needs so
your trees lawn flowerbeds and gardens
are lush and beautiful and if you have
any questions about our products chat
with one of our amazing customer service
agents on sprinkler warehouse.com they
really know their stuff and they will
get you squared away subscribe to our
YouTube channel for helpful tips
tutorials and general sprinkler
instruction I'm Duane Smith for
sprinkler warehouse professional quality
rock bottom prices
[Music]