hi there and welcome to little garden on
the prairies
so i'm very excited because this is the
first outdoor video of 2022 that i'll be
sharing with you today and it is a
beautiful sunny day
so if you've seen on on my previous
videos i have a lot of indoor starts
going on in my basement and in the
garage and we are still a few weeks away
from that last frost date so none of
that can come outdoors yet but there are
a lot of things that can be planted
outdoors directly into the ground before
last frost date so in this video i'm
going to show you some of the seeds that
i'm going to be direct sowing into
containers so before we get to the
planting i just want to take you on a
quick tour of the garden
to show you the beautiful blue skies
we're having here today on the
saskatchewan prairies if you have a look
here at my garden it looks pretty
disastrous right now
i am in the process of converting my two
raised garden beds to containers
i have access to
many of these wonderful 30
gallon tubs they are mineral tubs that
we
get from our cattle once they've licked
them clean we wash them out and they are
food grade safe and they make such a
good container for growing
and it's just a lot easier than
crawling around on your hands and knees
i'm kind of getting to the point in my
life where i don't really want to be
doing that a whole lot i'll probably do
another video here next week kind of
giving you more details on how that's
all going to go
and how i'm going to fill up these
containers
the soil in these raised garden beds you
know is just several layers of wonderful
materials that i've added over the last
few years leaves
wood chips compost
and i didn't want to just throw it away
so i'm digging it all out
and going to use it to fill these tubs
so i'll go over some of the seeds that
i'm going to be directly sowing today
plus give you a list of other
seeds that you can plant early these are
all cool weather crops that require
soil temperature to be somewhere around
that 10 degrees
to 15 degrees celsius
and when i came out yesterday afternoon
and did a temperature check
the soil seems to be about you know 17
18 degrees on the surface and
down below it was you know around that
10 degrees mark
we had some super windy days this past
week where the wind was gusting to 70
kilometers an hour
those two days were just horrible you
didn't even want to be outside
and a system like this would never
hold up in any kind of wind like that
so i don't think it's worth
fighting with i'm just going to remove
all this i think the soil is nice and
warm so
we can get planting
so before i get planting my lettuces
here i'm just going to put in a
all-purpose fertilizer and add that into
the soil here so this is just a 444
general all-purpose type fertilizer that
i usually add into my containers
so i've taken some fresh soil from my
raised garden beds that
is
you know really nice
organic soil it's got lots of material
in it some broken down leaves and
compost that i've added and some
wood chips so i think it'll be a nice
soil for this lettuce
and i plan to do section planting with
my lettuces and kale and spinach
so i plan on just going to be
planting up
on the back half of these containers
so here the sun rises over there and it
comes across my garden so these will
have sun shining on them for probably
you know 16 hours a day
throughout the spring and early summer
for sure
so if i plant
this first round here in the back these
will grow up in about three weeks i'll
do another planting in the front here so
these won't you know be shading out the
new seedlings when they come through
so i just add a little handful of the
fertilizer here
try not to let it all blow away
work it into the soil
i'll work it into the whole container
i don't really follow any kind of
particular
measurement just a little sprinkle
so something that i try to follow is the
square foot gardening method when i'm
planting and it just helps kind of show
you
the proper spacing of your seeds
depending on what you're planting
it is a bit of a challenge to use this
square
space seed spacing thing in a round
container but i'll just kind of show you
how i do it so for lettuces and kale and
spinach
you
use this spacing
of the red circles so that kind of shows
you so you can just press down just to
kind of mark where you're going to be
pushing
where you're going to be planting the
seeds
and i believe these in a square foot
there is 16
spaces for lettuce or kales and then
from there i just kind of go outwards
following this
pattern a little bit
so that i can plant a few more
to each side
just kind of eyeballing it
and then from there you should have
all your holes marked where you want to
place your seeds
this is covering a little more than half
of my container but that's okay
so in this one i'm going to be planting
kale
so i try to just do one
per hole
you can you know just sprinkle it around
i've done that before you know you end
up with a very
thick crop that
needs to be thinned out
i'm going to try this and see
how it looks once it starts coming
we could even go a little bit closer to
the edge here and throw in a few more
but this way you kind of got a nice
general
spacing of your seeds
another reason why i'm moving to uh
container gardening is
my little doggie here that you see in
the background
is already been digging in the
garden burying some treasures so i'm
hoping if i switch to the containers
that
that won't be such a problem
then after getting the seeds in just
give it a good generous water and ready
to move on
to the next container
so the next thing i'm going to plant up
here today is some radishes and some
spring onions so i have two kinds of
onions that i'm going to try today and
one's kind of like a purple
and this guy is going to
really give me grief while i do this
okay so i just relocated these
containers uh so i can do some videoing
with hopefully without the dog
sticking his nose in things and
disrupting it
so for
onions uh these are like a spring green
onion
that i like to grow in containers and
something this size works perfectly
and it's good because you can move it
around the garden and make sure it's in
a sunny spot
and for radishes
pretty much any container goes as well
this isn't very big but because i can
you know plant about 16 in here today
and then find another little container
in a week and start some more you can
kind of just
grow radishes anywhere every couple
weeks so that you always have some
i find that if i grow too many at one
time they you know they grow so fast
that i can't keep up with them so
little containers like this work
great so i did the same i had just a
little
sprinkling of the all-purpose fertilizer
into the soil here worked it up a little
bit so it's nice and loose
and i'm going to do some french
breakfast today
and according to the square foot method
you should do kind of the same spacing
you do with lettuce where you have 16
per
square foot but i'm kind of just going
to eyeball it
not too worried about them being too
close together
it's easy to thin out later or just let
them grow sometimes they
will grow together and just push each
other aside and still you know you can
still
harvest them
and get a pretty good
crop that way
so i just push my seeds down with my
finger
wherever i see them
i think i can shove a few more in here
and then just
gently pat it down
so hopefully it's not going to be issue
with my dog this year
getting into these small containers so
we'll see how it goes
and again just give it a good watering
and then just find a nice sunny location
for it and leave it in your garden so
radishes are one of the fastest growing
garden vegetables these should be ready
to harvest within 25 to 30 days
and for these onions i'm just going to
run a line down the middle here and plot
both of them
into this container
again green onions are another
type that you can succession plant
throughout the summer
find a container find a corner
somewhere in your garden where you could
throw in some more of these
you can plant them
all summer long
i just pulled these out i did grow some
of these indoors hydroponically this
winter and i see that i hardly have any
seeds left so these are only going to
take up a quarter of this container
i just lightly cover them
work them in
don't bury them too deep
so i got lots of these ones these are
more of a purple type of a green onion
these are called the rosa lunga de
friends
another seed that you can direct sow
before the last frost are peas
so peas are cool weather crops that love
being planted in nice cool soil in early
spring
so i have got these four cloth grow bags
designated for my peas here
we have an old
remnants of a rabbit cage here that we
left one side up that's chicken wire so
we thought it'd make a good trellising
system for peas
so that's why i have them up against
here
they get lots of sunlight here as well
so i'm going to be planting two types of
peas today
this is a burpiana early so it's a
potted pea that you have to shell to eat
and these are a sugar pod
so they have the edible type pod and
these are called oregon sugar pod so i'm
gonna set up these two in these
containers
so i usually push my peas down about one
inch into the soil
spread them out about you know two
inches or so apart
using the square foot method
they say about six per square foot
so we'll kind of follow that
here
you see i just push it down so it goes
about you know a good inch into the
soil
so peas are have very a very shallow
root system
so that they're they're best to direct
so you can try starting peas indoors but
they don't transplant very well like i
said they have
a shallow root system and they don't
really like to be disturbed so
this is the best way to do it once your
soil is warm so i got about i think 14
in here
and i'm just gonna
cover them up
and these ones growing on this side will
hopefully attach to this chicken wire
and then i will also probably stick a
tomato
cage in here as well for them to grow up
as well in the front parts
[Music]
if you are enjoying this video and find
value in the information i share on my
channel you can help support me by
clicking on the thanks button below and
make a small contribution to the channel
so one final step after planting your
seeds uh you should always use some kind
of mulch on top of the surface just to
keep that moisture in
and protect it from the hot sun keep it
from drying out too fast i have a
an abundance of
old straw so that's what i'm going to be
using on my planters today you can also
use dried leaves you know kind of ground
up dried leaves makes a great mulch if
you have some wood chips
grass clippings
anything like that will make a good
mulch on top of your containers
so i hope you found this video helpful
and that you will start doing some
direct sewing outdoors if you're still
waiting for that final frost date to
pass there's a lot of things you can be
planting outdoors right now
so please leave comments below hit that
like button if you haven't already done
so hit subscribe so you don't miss out
on any more
videos coming to my channel
thanks for watching
[Music]