catch a whiff of that it's the alluring
scent of chives your next Garden
Superstar imagine a herb related to
onions garlic and leaks but with a more
subtle refined flavor picture long thin
leaves that mirror the Elegance of grass
and small hollow tubes filled with Aroma
and taste now here's the kicker chives
are not just a culinary delight they're
a gold mine with a maturation period of
just 45 days they're one of the most
profitable short season crops and the
Harvest every 25 days for 3 years
straight that's right a gift that keeps
on giving so why not turn your green
thumb into a green bank account with
chives you're not just gardening you're
investing and remember the best time to
plant a seed was 20 years ago the second
best time now subscribe for more H
cultural hacks