[Music]
the cattle industry has a significant
economic impact throughout the Northern
Territory the industry was one of the
first established Industries in the
territory and is made up of a mix of
long established family stations through
to large corporate organizations that
operate on several pastoral leas at a
time unlike any other industry the
cattle industry has a footprint covering
around 45% of the territory's total land
area it is an industry providing
significant employment opportunities for
regional and remote areas of the NT
nationally agriculture as a broad
Industry Group has been identified as a
priority industry due to the high
numbers and rates of injury and the
Hazardous nature of the work NT work
safe has commenced a campaign to assist
station owners to reduce the frequency
of injuries in the industry from the
stations visited so far the industry has
demonstrated awareness and commitment to
work health and safety this snapshot
provides an overview of two station
managers on the hazards facing the
industry in the territory and their
interaction with NT work
[Music]
safe I'm benen kle uh with tiporary
station manager at tiary uh been with
with AA company and been with them for
been here for 6 months and been with AA
for 5
years well I started out as a as a as
anyone as a station hand on a on a
bigger property um I've been through a
few different areas of the industry as I
said I've been into the part uh tanning
hides and that sort of thing in in that
sort of area building machinery in that
for the agricultural industry um and
moving through on onto the head Stockman
rooll overseer and the station man manag
the opportunity was given to me uh as a
as a station manager in central
Queensland on a smaller property um to
move to a big move to the bigger
property and really go forward in my
career and and take on a bigger role AA
has at least 12 properties in in the
Northern Territory um from brunette on
the Barkley right up to the DAR region
here and obviously the the abire just
out of D we are vertically integrated
from a cattle sort of supplyer um into
the beef industry we obviously have a
lot of station managers so we
collectively between us there would be
hundreds of years of experience between
all the station managers the general
managers that have been in the business
and right up to CEO turn off here so
live exporter was was probably the one
of the main ones last year um this year
we're just turning off wieners to
brunette so this year we'll probably
turn off about 8 10,000 wieners down to
brunette with our background on the
Lakes at brette so yeah so it is it is
very vital that our staff are trained
and and managed them cattle in a safe
manner I think going into the company
side of things you focus on safety we
want to create a safety culture and
that's from the ground up so our our
staff telling us what they think uh you
know what what is their what is the risk
what is the hazards and they have a and
they have the opportunity to voice that
to their manager or their next in line
manager and that comes through to the to
the station manager and onto the GMS and
onto the board um the board obviously
takes it very seriously and they are
implementing things um for us this
station managers and and we communicate
down but we also from a site perspective
we want the communication to come up
from the from the guys on the ground the
station hands to tell
us well right at the beginning doesn't
matter what aak property you're on you
do a onboarding program the moment they
sign up um so that will start a week
before they actually arrive at the
station uh we spend three or 4 days with
them we'll go right through all the safe
working procedures and everything that
we have and we'll actually take them to
the yards and we'll work a small M of
cattle uh we'll spend a day on the
horses uh we'll shoe and we'll do the
quad bike assessments and the motorbike
assessments and we'll have all that
ticked off and we'll have them assessed
in the first week and then we work
through the training and what we need to
go forward with we go through that first
initial assessment um we will set a
review date on that and that's done by
myself or the operations manager I made
a very apparent point of that we will
talk about safety and we'll have toolbox
talks weekly so that's the head Stockman
to his staff and that's on a issue that
I've risen or something that I've seen
as as the manager that I want dealt with
to something that one of the station
staff have actually brought to me and
said I need this communicated up toolbox
talks go up to a safety meeting that we
will generally have once a month and
then uh we have a bigger broader you
know with 27 staff we have a full safety
meeting every 3
months I think outside the box um I'm
only young and I and I look look for
things uh since since my management here
I've identified a few areas that I need
to work on um this year I'm offering a
safety incentive to the staff um so if
they come to me with near misses uh any
incidents and anything that they want to
bring forward there's a there's an
initiative there for them we understand
the policies and procedures coming from
NT work safe and we we identifying the
issues and um seeking you know ways to
limit them mainly and this is what we've
identified uh with AO is the you know
the cattle the horses and the and the
motorbikes and the mastering as our main
areas but we certainly don't forget
about the me mecs The Cook The Gardener
they're all involved the maintenance
manager they're all involved in what we
do here for safety we have the low
stress stock handling that all the
station staff here been through and that
is something that everyone is aware of
and does very well when you're talking
about the wieners we handle the wieners
with low stress and we keep them heers
they come back next year as as Joiner
heers so they've been handled properly
they come back the next year as a wet
care theyve been through the yards
properly low stress handling uh the
staff know how to handle them properly
cuz we we put them through the low
stress handling School schs but does it
actually you know does it actually stop
instance of when you're working with a
live animal um it'll be very hard to say
well you know just that alone and a set
of Standards alone would would work in
every every
case we have a cattle handling procedure
um we go through it with them how to
shut the gates properly how to yard up
properly and all that um that is
something we do and we tick off and and
all our staff aware of what risks and
Hazards are involved around the cattle
and around the cattle
yards back back back so this is where we
you know this is where we can go back to
those B we did need to get the training
and the horsemanship skills to a to a
better level here at tiary we felt we
had the expertise to do it instead of
getting someone external and paying for
that um we felt we had the expertise and
we'd share that with our staff so we
went from first round to you know young
Green rers from that is they been all
the staff of going from a from a level
to the next level I've initiated this
year that we've brought a new Quad baret
it's speed limited to 35 km hour they do
have rollover protection systems on them
uh I've made a conscious decision that
myself the operations manager and the
head Stockman are the only ones allowed
to Master on quad bikes other staff are
allowed to fence on them aao policies
that all Riders of quad bikes and and
two wheelers have to have a helmet on
they are commy assessed and they
reassessed every 6 months to get their
attitude right on a quad bike is what
I'm after um but part of it is slowing
the bikes down and the training and we
haven't had a quad bike incident this
year mastering out in a lot of like
fixed scrub country and in a remote area
um of implemented GPS units that
actually they use as two ways in GPS if
they get lost uh something happens they
fall off a horse they press a button on
the GPS and we know their exact
location definitely retention is one of
our biggest things that we we're
identifying and and we're working with
at AO you know obviously we keep someone
he understands the property and he
understands our policies and the
motorbikes the horses all that's at a at
a level that we want them to be at to
keep them here we are looking at
offering incentives and and getting that
retention rate cuz the cattle industry
and in general the egg industry is a
industry that can only keep people for
one year 2 years we have a budget and I
have to I have to report to uh general
managers on what my budget is and what I
put my money into but looking at the
safety side of things there's things
that you don't compromise you measure
what is it going to save me in Lost Time
staff incidents all that sort of stuff
but when you look outside this box it a
few things well you weigh up your
options and most of the time it'll tell
you that you're better off doing it no
matter what the cost is NT work safe
come out a month ago I found it very
interactive very positive so it wasn't
about uh what we were doing wrong it was
about just identifying things uh looking
at areas that we can we we can work on
the positive for me was it was just an
open discussion some of the issues that
were raised um just minor ones that we
just off off the cuff conversation um
I've gone and addressed them and I think
you know it's that outside Outsiders
perspective the second set of eyes um
that just show you look this is
something that you could work with the
regulations and that do I fully
understand all of them we have people
that do that for me as a manager for AO
I have someone that does that for me but
on the ground uh the helping and the
communication from NT work safe is is
what we need well we may not always be
able to get out there uh to assist the
guys on the ground and have a look in
that at at their at their location we
are still contactable by uh phone and
obviously we've got email website as
well a lot of information on the website
that can assist stations and that but by
all means they can give any work safer
call and be asked to speak to an
inspector and we will provide whatever
we can to assist business and better
understanding um Health work health and
safety uh my name's Cameron kroo I am
the manager at man BL station um you
I've been with CPC for about 13 years uh
growing my role through the rank
starting as a first year Jack
through to head Stockman and becoming an
overseer now station manager here at
mamboo previously to that 5 years before
I ran a stock Camp here as a head
Stockman for 2 and 1 half years I come
across here when I was 17 running away
from home and wanting to get into the
industry it's all I know all I want to
ever do consolidate pastoral company has
17 places across Australia through um
the territory uh the kimbery region in
wa and through Central Queensland and
the North Queensland it's operations
that cattle go to export to Indonesia
from Windham and Darwin um and and then
yeah domestic markets through
Queensland Man bl's part in CPC um
historically with CPC it's it's just
been a breeding facility but in the last
couple of years we're starting to
transition um so it's a value adding
Place cattle coming here um to grow
value add kilograms and then to move
them out over the wet season when as a
as a shortage of cattle to go go to
market on man and blue we have 11 to 13
staffs throughout the year starting with
myself as a manager below me we have a
head Stockman and a leading hand a
couple of second years and and a couple
of First Years to keep fresh blood
coming through all the time other staff
we have is a Borman the cook he provides
meals keeps everyone fed get everyone
towing a line in the kitchen keep them
on side my wife is she's the
administration person and as well as she
also takes a wider role on and accompany
as a training coordinator our um our
youngest people our new recruits each
year they they seem to be the ones
getting hurt the most and I it's wider
across the whole industry um I think you
know it's a little bit to do with ego
going straight out of school getting
away from your parents and getting full
of confidence you know showing off in
front of your mate so you know basically
that's why we we got to train our people
we got to we got to get them going and
get them thinking right get a get a
culture developed so they're they're
thinking about what they're doing and
they not just racing into things and
getting themselves hurt at the end of
the day that's that's where safety
really comes into its own it can be very
tough to handle you know I was young
like that once myself I know exactly
what I was like um but basically just I
think you just got to just got to work
through it your first couple of weeks
are your hardest you just got to work
through it and really you know get them
thinking um you know all the training we
doing constant reminders you know
toolbox to each each month um and and
having meetings just just just making
them aware you know we might we might
have been lucky and not got to had any
incidents but just making aware the
incidents that are
happening when we um our employees to
first start with a company we run them
through an induction process um it it
takes place out at the Charles D
University cther campus and some of it
on man blue itself here um at at um at
the rural College they they do their
first aid certificate chemical
certificates some maintenance training
they have qualified mechanics um so you
know they're experts in their field so
they they provide us with that service
then the horsemanship side of it um this
year we we had four groups rang from
beginners to the more experienced Riders
throughout them um and they came out
here to mamboo and U we basically um
just stepped them through some basic
horse riding we asked them to do a self
assessment of their Ro riding then we
had a couple of horses around that are
Fairly reliable horses you know they're
quiet and nothing's going to go wrong
with them got them catching them and um
you riding them and safely handling
basically getting getting them them take
their hips away so they're not horses
not kicking and just working with the
animal and then they do about 3 days of
that mind you they're not they're not
totally right to go for the job but
they've got to start and they know how
to keep themselves safe uh safe so yeah
they can improve from there um and with
the low stress stock handling they go
right down to basic stuff for opening
shutting Gates moving cattle making sure
cattle have water and moving cattle
around the yard safely so everything you
know can be as safe as
possible we're trying to um basically
develop a culture here of um just having
an understanding and an awareness for
safety but because we basically live all
live here together um you know it's our
home as well as our workplace I think
we're just trying to develop an
awareness and understanding and start to
take responsibility of where we are when
it when it comes to safety um yeah it's
a joint effort for all of us not just
just me barking down the shots to to my
staff our RS have being cattle horses
and motorbikes after the induction
training program of horses myself and my
head Stockman we assess assess our own
stuff here on Manalo again um and just
watch them ride and allocate horses to
the their level and then just step
through the training like that that's
ongoing the horsemanship training all
year it's it's a constant Improvement
like I still got Improvement we all do
so with motorbikes um we carry out we do
some training with Charles Darwin with
their motorbike experts and then then
basically they we come out here and I
only try to allocate one or two people
to ride the motorbike and then we step
them through make sure they're all right
they got you know they know how to ride
safely motorbike is a big risk because
you can be out in a padic riding around
on a MOBA cattle and there's a log lying
in Long Grass and that's all it takes
you might only be idling along and you
can fall off and and injure injure
yourself so just trying to get awareness
into them and um you know just
understand that um you know there could
be an issue and we're trying to trying
to avoid it I believe low stress stock
handling definitely uh takes away a lot
of the risk it'll never totally take it
away cuz we we're dealing with animals
at the end of the day and they can be
unpredictable I think it's a huge advant
manage our um our stock only come into
the yard some twice a year some only
once a year and a small percentage only
every couple of years so um using low
stress techniques as long as we we stick
to it all the time each year the ATT of
the cattle just improve they're used to
being handled in a good way you know
they become easy to put through the yard
become a pleasure to put through the
yard like I um I remember when I first
started um in the Northern Territory
chasing cattle in they used to see you
be in the stockyard and Gates would fly
back open cattle running back over the
top of you I've heard of incidents in
the last 5 6 years but I haven't
actually seen a cow run back and smash a
gate in the last 5
years we've been using quad bikes for as
long as I can remember there's been
quads around um but at current at
current stage cuz they're being
identified as such a danger I think they
will become phased out the sidebyside
ATV we got um yeah it'll probably
that'll that'll take over and um you
know replace a quad by it's being an
alternative use and seem to be a bit
safer you know seat belt and have a roof
on it for Roll by protection that so I
think I definitely feel that's a way
things will go all our staff have run
through chemical training at CDU they do
their uh chemer or the other equivalents
you know cuz chemicals are are a part of
it but yeah we've got a process where
everyone goes through that training and
when they come onto the station and they
have to undertake some Camel handling
we've got records there have to keep you
know they're recording what they're
doing where they're doing it and what
what they're doing it for in our our
chemical shed we have the MSDS sheets on
hand um for all our chemicals that we
use um they're provided there for the
staff if they an incident happens and
know how to treat it um how to use it
what PPE they need to use for it uh we
also have it on hand in the office so
there's a second copy
available work safe and um were out
earlier this year they basically just
did a had a visit and um yeah just ran
had to look at things and what what
we're doing to try and uh mitigate our
risk it was fairly daunting expecting
them to come cuz from what you know in
the industry have heard of other places
and in the past yeah they're coming to
kick your bum really um that's what
that's what the general feel was of it
but when they turned up it was really
good we just stepped through the paces
of it um doing we first we um just did a
bit of a basic induction with them and
then talked about our policies and
procedures and just worked walked around
and they just had a look at things and
yeah it was fairly smooth I think it was
good mainly peace of mind and knowing
maybe they're not so bad you know
they're they they're probably just
trying to help too and do their job
rather than um bullly into into things
yeah definitely having work safe um
coming on board this year and the role
of being you know there as an advisor
and it's being there to help us rather
than hammer us um it's definitely like
we got all the policies and procedures
in place and um you know them coming on
board and supporting what we're doing
you know it it gives you a lot lot of
confidence in knowing that uh what
you're doing is right and your people
you
know people are the key at the end of
the day we do make money out of cattle
but you know you can't do none of that
without your people um so at the end of
the day if they they're able to come
home safe um and our policies and that
are helping that happen you know I
definitely think it's it's it's better
rather than worse you know definitely
moving
forward I don't believe uh it's it's got
to be an expensive task I believe that
some of the systems uh that they can be
implemented on on site are rather simple
and can be maintained with minimum of
fuss it's it's um and I think uh by
doing so you're going to reduce the
number of uh incident rates on your uh
on your farm or your station and in
industrywide level if that uh if those
incident rates uh begin to fall over a
period of time that can only be good for
the industry both in a productivity
sense as well as their bottom
line uh I've been involved in uh
Insurance in underwriting and broking uh
for the last 40 odd years and uh of
those spent many years offering services
to the uh Cattleman's Association of the
Northern Territory when you do o health
and safety there's not immediate returns
it's a longterm plan program you you
need to implement it and then reap the
rewards as you go forward it's not
instantaneously because whilst you might
have had 5 years of bad claims and
implement the o health and safety
Service uh program you to to get a
better work safe situation the problem
is that you've still got 5 years of
really bad record so you've got to get
rid of that so you got to have one year
good one year maybe bit better or or not
as bad and then the insurance company
can and then work with you to see that
yes you're on the right track then the
benefits of the savings will come if
anybody's looking for Quick Fix it's not
going to happen that way it's going to
be a long-term
situation obviously given that the
Northern Territory does have a vast uh
land mass in that and some of these
stations are quite remote uh it's not
just restricted to us coming out there
and uh visiting them uh while we we
intend to try and do that as part of the
campaign uh if they uh require any um
advice or uh anything in relation to uh
work health and safety then obviously we
have the ability to through our website
and telephone and everything else the uh
the hotline to give us a call and say hi
and let us know what their um concerns
are or whether they require any further
information and we can provide them with
whatever we can just because they make
contact with us doesn't mean that they
they've caught our attention or anything
like that we encourage uh people if they
want to uh find out more about work
health and safety then by all means
contact us it doesn't mean that you're
going to have an inspect on your door
the next day or anything like that but
uh we we'll do whatever we can to um try
and help them with their uh with their
concern or provide them with what
information they require I think there
needs to be more of that I'd welcome
them back and and I would walk them
through any and say look you know where
can you help me here instead of saying
what am I doing wrong where can you help
me and then you know
authorized by the Northern Territory
government daan