[Music]
[Applause]
hey what's up everybody I'm Chef Mikey
welcome back to Chef's Harvest Farm I'm
sitting in my raised bed garden today
and today I'm going to be planting these
zucchini plants and marold plants over
in this raised bed I'm going to plant
these Direct through this mulch but the
cool thing about this mulch is that this
mulch was grown here and the roots are
still attached feeding the microbiology
in the soil while at the same time
mulching the soil to protect it from the
Sun and in this video I'm going to show
you how to grow your own mulch using
cover crops in your raised bed garden
let's go do it first
[Music]
just got my five gallon bucket of uh
peas and oats cover crop here and I'm
just going to broadcast it right on top
of the soil the oats are going to grow
straight up and then the peas climb up
the oats you know it's just going to be
like a four or 5 foot tall big mass of
cover crop it's been about 3 months
since I seated the raised garden beds
over here and so so today I'm going to
terminate them so this bed's peas and
oats right here which is what you
watched me do and then this bed got
planted to some mustard cover crops and
the peas and oats I'm going to crimp
them down so they'll stay like a mulch
on top of the raised bed and then I'm
just going to plant directly into the
terminated cover crop and to do that
with the peas and oats because I want it
as mulch on top I'm just going to like
crimp it using this it's like a tomato
stick I'm just going to step on it and
then I'm going to tarp the whole
area and leave it tarp for like 2 weeks
and then it's all going to be dead when
we come back
[Music]
okay so the next step I'm going to water
it in pretty good and then I'm just
going to pull the silage tarps over so
it's super important that if you're not
familiar with this process they're using
the right tarp it's not just like a tarp
from Home Depot they're UV treated tarp
so I'm not super concerned about um like
micr Plastics ending up in the soil or
anything because these tarps are made in
designed to be sitting out in the sun
but so yeah make sure you use the
correct tarp you could also use
greenhouse plastic and other than those
two materials I wouldn't use anything
else and so I'm going to water it in
first and then pull the tarps back cuz
the tarps are way more effective when
it's wet underneath so I'm going to tarp
this whole area including all this area
where the fence is kind of a problem
area where I have to mow and I have to
move it every time I'm just going to
tarp this try to kill this grass and
possibly just fill it all in with wood
[Music]
chip all right so it's been exactly two
weeks since we laid the tarp down over
the raised bed cover crop so I'm going
to pull it off and we'll see what it
looks like
all right y'all so you can kind of see
what it looks like when I move the tarp
over it's like completely dead and the
mulch is just right on top of the raised
bed garden so now I'm going to like
clean up the whole area I'm going to
take my little flame weer here it just
hooks up it's just a torch that hooks up
to a propane tank I'm just going to like
kill all the little weeds that are
around in the area I'm going to hit it
with my weed eater first and I'm going
to Flame weed it off and then I'm just
going to like fill in the whole area
with wood chips
[Music]
so what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to pull this mulch aside it's like
pretty thick and I'm just going to like
make myself a little hole and then I'm
just going to put a little handful of
compost in the hole just to make sure
that the plant has like all the
nutrition in there it needs and then I'm
going to take my zucchini
plant bury him in the
hole and then I just move the mulch kind
of back and that's it so this raised bed
was actually cover cro to mustard which
I use to like suppress soilborne
pathogens they suppress like pathogenic
nematodes soil born diseases and
pathogens like uh you know tomato bite
things like that so I'm just going to
plant these molds into this bed really
just like attract pollinators to my
garden and everything I don't really
need them to produce me any sort of
income it's mostly just for my wife and
I
[Music]