[Music]
hello everyone welcome to jadam in this
episode I'll talk about how to use and
store the jadam natural pesticide here I
have prepared jadam wedding agent Jam
sulfur and jam herbal solution with this
combination you're getting the perfect
natural pesticide for your garden and
for
farming and in this video I'll show you
how to mix all the solution in a proper
way this is Jam herbal solution which is
the extract of any herbs with
insecticide repellent effect herbs that
are often used are peppermint Rosemary
lavender Jerusalem Arch choke and broen
and recently we have been testing Cosmos
plant and it is showing significant
results with all this plant you can
control from AIT to might but above all
our most favorite plant is Ginko until
now because there is not a single path
that we won't be able to control with
this plant all the details and the ratio
are listed in my book Jam organic
farming and the new book Jam organic
pest and Disease Control briefly
speaking it is very straightforward to
make plant extracts all you need is to
boil the plant for five hours and more
detailed information is spoken in my
lecture so please click the link of to
see the lecture video the first thing I
would like to talk about is how to store
The herbal solution once you're done
with the boiling the herbs pour the
solution in the bottle to put it in a
sideway so that it can be vacuum sealed
in this way you can store The herbal
solution for a couple of
years but the problem is when you opened
it for use because when it contacts with
the air the properties of the solution
start to change gradually which causes
decrease in its insecticidal function an
easy way to identify that the solution
is usable or not is the air pressure of
the bottle due to the
fermentation but to make sure the best
way is to drop small portion of jam
wedding agent before any use in
different Beaker once you drop the jwa
if the color of the GH s doesn't change
that means it is still good for
use and another problem is how to store
an opened bottle properly even if you
put it into refrigerator the changes
cannot be stopped so the best way is to
get the help of ethanol there are
usually two types of ethanol sold in the
market one is with 84% Purity and the
other one is with 99% purity
when you are using 99% ethanol add
15% of ethanol from what is left over
and 84% with
25% with the help of ethanol you can
increase the shelf life of J herbal
solution even in atmospheric temperature
when none of the herbs are available
near you you can also use sodium
hydroxide as an alternative solution for
pest
control with sodi hydroxide you can
treat a problem of scale insects and
snails however I do not recommend
constant use of this substance because
of the concentration
damage jwa is recommended to use around
200 to 600 mL for 20 L and 5 to 15 L for
500 L JS is 40 ml to 60 ml for 20 L and
JHS is 200 mL to 600 mL for 20
L recently we have been receiving a lot
of questions from flower and gardeners
about our Jam solution so let me
elaborate on how to combine all three
solution for Pest and Disease Control
this this is the sprayer that I use for
testing the solution before the field
test this particular brand of spray is
my favorite due to its longl lasting
durability it cost little more but this
is a product worth a check out since we
are testing one liter of small amount
measuring the ratio also must be
calculated with the
shring before doing the mixing process
please do use soft water it is mandatory
to achieve its full capability and now
let me show you how the natural
disinfectant is made I I'll measure 800
ml of soft water first I will add 10 mL
of jam wedding
agent next
2 ml of jam
sulfur and now it is complete this
yellowish human urine like liquid is
natural disinfectant it can treat dowy
MW powdery MW and anthra no speaking of
anthros you can also control this just
by increasing
jwa as you can see Jam's natural Pest
Solutions are very easy to do with the
best effect on past and Disease Control
and by adding Jam herbal solution it
becomes allpurpose natural past and
disease
solution then I'll add a little more
water to make it one full
liter best thing about Jam natural Pesci
side unlike any commercially available
chemical pesticide Jam natural pesticide
is very safe to use there will be no big
problem even it is contacted on our skin
so you can also just wash the fruit to
eat right after spraying datam natural
Pest solution is all about combination
of
jwa JS and
JHS to increase insecticidal effect all
you need to do is the increase the
amount of jwa and JHS and for
disinfectant increase
JS but make sure to perform
concentration test in advance for JS
before spraying to the crops in this way
you can control almost all Pest and
disease you can add additional sodium
hydroxide and red clay powder for scale
insects and snails let me show you how
to add them just add the sodium
hydroxide in the beaker with water to
melt it
down this is very useful for scale
insects an additional red clay powder is
for increasing the penetration
effect first add the water and steer a
couple of times then let it sit for a
while until the layer is cleared out and
collect the surface of the red clay
powder to add it into the
bottle with this simple solution you
don't have to worry about Pest and
disease that occurs during farming but
make sure to use it all before 3
days however when you are adding sodium
hydroxide the solution can irritate your
skin when it makes
contact so please be aware of
that I've also listed all the detailed
videos on how to make all of this it is
also stated in my book so that you can
read one for
yourself thank you for watching and I'll
see you guys in the next video
[Music]