hey it's Matt from McGee farms and got
into the winter time now had a pretty
good first year with the garden here but
I think we're going to revamp a few
things we made a few mistakes that uh I
think I'm going to try to try to fix but
also uh in the winter time we're going
to try some uh cold weather vegetables
broccoli carrots lettuce uh some of that
and with doing that I've got some PVC
pipes that I'm going to cut down and I
have these brackets right here that uh
I'm going to use and I'm going to make
some hoops for these and with making the
Hoops we're going to put some uh clear
plastic over it too and just keep it a
little bit warmer because this is a
pretty you know colder colder climate
here in northeastern Missouri and uh
we'll see how the Winter Garden go so uh
first off I'm going to mount these on
the sides and and then I'm going to cut
these uh this/ in schedule 40 pipe down
and make some make some
hoops so I got the first one in and
mounted and this is uh 31 in
wide and I cut it at 6t and I think I
probably probably would have been okay
at 5T I think with the if I do the other
bed I'm going to go at 5T just because
the PVC is 10t and that way I can use uh
two sections for each pipe rather than
having to waste 4T of it but I've got
got that in it really wasn't too bad
bending and getting it in especially
being chilly out here I was afraid the
cold might make it a little hard to get
in so I'm going to get the rest of them
going to do
another I think I'm going to try three
on here see how that works I might have
to come back and do to four per 8T bed
and uh of course the lovely thing
putting these brackets in I just uh
cleaned out the horse stall and brought
the uh leftovers down here so uh now I'm
getting to work in that but you know it
is what it is it's a good free
fertilizer so I can't complain so I'm
going to start putting the rest of these
brackets in and get the rest of the
Hoops
done so I've got a couple of the hoop
Loops up right now it's an 8T section
I'm going to try with three see if
that's strong enough I may have to come
back and put a fourth one in as well uh
went ahead and I planted some winter
vegetables in here I've got some carrots
I've got some lettuce I've got some
broccoli green
onions uh I think that's all I got in
right now the winter vegetables that's
about the only ones we we really eat I
mean we don't eat kale we don't eat
cabbage so uh so figure we'll try it I
bought some
uh plastic at a Home
Depot I don't know if how it's going to
hold up or not it's a 3.5 mil just clear
uh plastic sheeting for like a painter's
drop cloth so I'm getting ready to put
it on I'm just going to staple it down
to the uh top boards see if that's going
to hold it
or if uh the wind's just going to rip
that off and I'm going to have to put
some little T some little boards on top
of it so we'll see I'm getting ready to
do that now and I'll show you the
finished product here in just a couple
of
minutes meanwhile enjoy some
goats all right so I've got it down in
there and what I uh kind of did I'm
going to work on a little more is on the
sides where I have the uh these
trellises that I made out of the cattle
panels I'm kind of working them in there
to kind of Hope help hold them down in
there and I took a staple gun I went
around on this side and just stapled it
down really good over
here I uh I kind of bunched it up and
tied it all
together uh probably going to have to
tie it down just a little bit
better but uh I got thinking I'm like
and I did stay pull it down in there but
when I got over here I got thinking I'm
going to have to get in there some way
to harvest them and then plant more so
what I did is I found a 1 by two that I
had that have been sitting in the barn
forever and I wrapped the plastic
sheeting up with the 1 by two and uh and
rolled it up till it got to about where
the edges and then I use the staple gun
to kind of staple it down as well and by
doing that that should hopefully hold it
it's going to sit on there and uh
hopefully that'll keep it from going up
and then whenever I want in
there I can I can get in there a little
bit I'm going to have to adjust it a
little bit but we're going to try this
out see how it goes I've got the uh
other one over there that I'm going to
do the same thing with and uh I've got
on the end down here we're going to
expand it out I've got some 10 put
2x4s uh we're going to go down a little
more put some more arches uh trellises
whatever you want to call them uh put a
few more of these and because it worked
really good we just didn't have enough
space and so I'm getting ready to start
in on that so it's Matt from mgee farms
hope you enjoy the uh gardening videos
as much as I do and the other stuff
around the farm that we
do if you like the videos give us thumbs
up subscribe to the channel share it
with your friends it helps the channel
grow and it's always appreciated till
next time have a great
day