so here I am with my wisteria vine I
love this fine because wisterias will
bloom if they get very little water very
little fertilizer but they do need sun
now the fragrance is intoxicating and a
lot of people ask about when to prune
wisteria pruning after blooming but I
want to introduce you to another vine
that will flower in part shade or even a
mostly shaded situation and it is called
a cobija so come with me we're going to
meet a key be divine okay so this is a
key via this one is called the chocolate
a cobija because it smells as sweet as
chocolate I love this vine it has very
intricate blooms and has a very very
long bloom time this fine starts
blooming Oh probably around April and
will bloom up until probably close to
June so here is a nice advantage of a
cobija vine you can take your pruning
clippers and when it's in most beautiful
bloom it smells the sweetest that's when
you go out and you remove some of the
dead foliage because a cobija vine in
the northwest is semi evergreen so you
can see the new foal just nice and green
and healthy but right up here these are
the leaves that are larger because
they've been on the plant all year and
they've got you a little bit of winter
damage and so it's nice just to be able
to come in break those off and because
this vine is already covering the
structure when I see these these
tendrils that are you know big and long
and shooting up straight up they're easy
to just break off as well and that's
form of pruning as well so this is a
vine that you can clean up and proved
right when it's in flour and then that
way it controls the size of the vine so
a key be mine a great flowering vine for
a semi shaded location