as cattle feeding has grown in North
Dakota we are seeing new investment in
feeding facilities and Renovations for
expansion and compliance open Lots with
runoff containment ponds predominate but
there has been some confinement hoop
barns put in use advantages are the
ability to locate an environmentally
sensitive or space limited farmsteads to
provide better wind protection snow
protection summer shade High animal
performance and greater ease in handling
cattle this relatively new barn is 300
ft long by 42 ft wide divided with a 12T
feeding pad and a fence line bunk
leaving a 30-ft resting area an eve
covers the bunk with the barn divided
Midway with a watering pad in fountains
resulting in two feeding pin with 150
head capacity each allowing 1 foot a
bunk and 42 s ft per
calf it's constructed with smant pony
walls ibeam supports trust pipe Rafters
and covered with a tarp with an open
Ridge and a rollup side curtain similar
structures are available with square
post and plank Construction in widths
from 36 to 50 ft and length up to 500 ft
manuring bedding management is critical
the feeding alley is scraped weakly or
as weather allows bedding is blown in
with a baale processor or unrolled in
pens frequently to keep dry the resting
area is typically clean between feeding
groups dependent on location preparation
construction materials design and labor
costs can vary from less than 400 animal
space to over double that reported
cattle performance and health has been
good often initial experience with a
first hoop Barn leads to expansion with
additional barns in the future