[Music]
hello everybody uh Dylan here and
uh with Nathan SCH sales reps here with
green cover talking a little bit about
uh when is the best time to start
planting our spring mixes I know
everybody's getting itchy to to get into
the ground whether that be moisture
whether that be it seems like Springs
here um so just kind of want to discuss
with you guys what our approach is um to
to going about that so Nathan what you
know when a customer asks you hey I'm
ready to plant you know when when's the
ideal time what do you kind of generally
recommend yeah so this is definitely a
really common question right now you
know the main thing is soil temperature
for germination and then air temperature
uh to avoid any winter kill so most of
your cool Sean species are going to
germinate around 40 degrees and so as
long as our our longterm average and our
current soil temperatures are at that 42
sorry that 40 degrees um and that's
probably that probably needs to be taken
at uh a 2in soil depth and early in the
morning um if if we're at that point and
then we we just need to be past any
concern of a hard freeze you know cool
season species can tolerate some Frost
it's when you get those hard freezes
down in the 20s that we're going to
start seeing some winter kill um of
course there are a lot of other factors
that go into uh you know when is the
time to plant so maybe you want to get
into the weeds a little bit more on
those yeah so I definitely agree with
with those parameters we cannot
physically be out there measuring the
soil temp you know so you know any any
kind of you know any kind of thermometer
works that has any kind of probe so even
just a you know just any kind of like a
food thermometer Works to to measure
those those temperatures um I I usually
refer to greencast um and with greencast
you can put your ZIP code in there you
can see roughly current soil
temperatures you can see five and 10
year average so I kind of combined the
two the three of those um you know to
get to that 40° temp and then I also
kind of incorporate the the 10day
forecast for the ambient temp to see
okay do we have any hard freezes you
know coming up or what do the what do
the 10day for what do the 10day forecast
look like um and you know that that
freezing temp you know really kind of
coincides with it I believe it has to be
around you know 4 hours at that
temperature you know kind of that's when
you start to get um that's when you
start to get those those killing frosts
for some of those cool season um species
so
uh you know keeping that in mind um
another another thing you can do if you
have if you're planting just something
simple like peas and oats planting it a
little bit deeper um it can you can get
it in the ground while you have moisture
get it sprouted and it's going to stay
in the ground a little bit longer so we
can maybe avoid if there are some of
those hard freezes here you know in the
next couple weeks um but that that at
least allows you to to get it in get it
up and and hopefully get a good good
Forge going with some more moisture but
those are really the parameters I try to
try to stick to and yeah it's the
biggest thing is going out there and
measuring it yourself too to get good
good hard data on on your area yeah
because there's G be a lot of factors
that affect that soil temp you know how
biologically active soils are what sort
what's our residue situation what's our
moisture situation so yeah tools like
that greencast website are great for
getting ideas um but the results are
going to vary on the farm so and I
definitely agree with that thought of
hey I have a really nice planting window
right now we plant now plant a little
deeper like those oats and peas those
cereals that can go a little deeper and
then we'll delay that emergence you know
by a couple weeks um it'll be a couple
weeks before those plants are up where
they're actually susceptible to being um
damaged and so that's how we can kind of
take advantage of early Springs like
what we seem to be having this year um
and and get our seeds in the ground so
you know it can be as simple as comp or
as complicated as we want it to be but
at the end of the day 40° soil temps and
past the hard freezes and and we should
be good to
go