[Music]
thought we do a little update
today on the chickens and how they're
doing and the new winter chicken coop
so it does smell a little bit in
here kind like a vinegary smell I guess
I would
say so what that's telling me is we need
more carbon I'm just going to take some
of this hay I
have and spread it out and let the
ladies go ahead and do their thing
[Music]
so now all you got to do is throw the
flakes of hay down and let the girls do
the rest of the work
[Music]
oh
they just go into town scratching
through it finding all the good stuff
out of it right now to
eat and they'll spread it around
and you kind of got to remember too that
these chickens been out on pasture their
whole life until they come into this
Coupe so all this hay and everything
they love it they're going to pick
through it and they're going to eat it
the best they can they're not just going
to use it for bed and they're going to
be eating this stuff they've been out
having fresh grass their whole life so
they really look forward to this free
range free choice oyster shells that
they can eat so if they need more
calcium in the diet they can go get it
whenever they
want they're making their own dust baths
[Music]
it's a little noisy in here right now
they're really enjoying the fresh hay I
put down for them
so we just got 15 chicken eggs so far
today there a duck egg over there and
another chicken egg over there so we got
16 17 eggs plus one duck egg this
morning we've gotten 18 eggs so far
today we've been averaging around 20 to
22 a day we only have 24 laying hens
been doing pretty darn good I think
you'd almost think it's springtime with
the amount of eggs you've been getting
they're really loving the greenhouse
they've been laying really good since
they've been in
here they love all the fresh hay they
get as you can see they scratching
through it and going to
[Applause]
town even the Ducks are loving
it now even just since I put this hay
down a few minutes ago the smell in here
has changed there is no more smell it's
kind of like a when you walked in you
just kind of felt it hit you in the face
it was a little bit of like a vinegary
smell you put the hay down down the
girls have come in they scratched it all
around and moved it and the smell's gone
away so the Deep bedding really works if
you start smelling a nasty smell or a
strong smell of anything all you need to
do is add some more carbon in this case
we're using hay the girls are loving
eating it it's a food source for them
they get more fresh greens and it's a
good carbon I've just been using the
lower nest boxes
here upper ones I keep locked up I don't
want the girls just hanging out in here
during the day and pooping up in here so
during the day I keep the lower nest
boxes open when I get home from work
usually around like 5:00 I'll come in
I'll collect my eggs I get my eggs out
and then when I'm all done collecting
the eggs I just shut it up and then that
way at night the girls can't go in there
and sleep and poop all over the place
that's usually when the nest boxes get
really
[Music]
dirty this right here this hay is the
same hay I put in the first time we set
up the CPE for
it's still clean there's no
poop the eggs we're getting out are nice
and
clean the Ducks love the water they're
just going to town they're the ones
making the biggest mess over there and
and I'm sure that's why we're going
through about 50 gallons of water a week
[Music]
[Applause]
we send our pigs off to the butcher shop
a couple of weeks ago we'll be getting
those back pretty soon I'm going to be
going over how much pork and meat we got
back from our pigs how much they weighed
and we're going to be doing like a
breakdown of what we're getting back to
feed all the noise the Ducks are going a
little crazy over there in the water
yes we're going to be getting all of our
meat back from the butcher shop on the
pig so I'm going to be going over to you
with the feet cost were with the butcher
cost were and how much money we have
into the food so if you want to check
that out don't forget to subscribe so
you don't miss it and we'll see you
right back here want to say thanks guys
for watching you have any questions on
the chicken coup or the chickens or
anything leave them down in the comments
below if you like the video give it a
thumbs up we're posting a photo a day
over on our Instagram account so go
check that out lumni Acres over on
Instagram we have a Facebook page we
love hearing from you guys so thanks for
watching and we'll see you right back
here next time at lumni Acres
[Music]