So much of Australia's story is to do
with water. There's often too much or
too
little. Drought is a constant
threat. Cattleman Randall Crosia
averages just three good years in 10.
Yeah. Well, it's uh 24,000 km or 6
million acres. Well, it's meant to be
the size of of Belgium, so to say, but
I've never been there, so I couldn't
tell you.
Randall manages Anna Creek Station. the
world's largest cattle property. It
survives on 8 in of rain a
year, if it comes at
all. We live in a desert, so it always
looks like it's dry, although uh most of
the stuff that grows here is very
nutritious. We don't need very much rain
to make it spring to life, you know, and
it um it's a very productive country if
if you get the water on it.
Across twothirds of Australia, no rivers
flow, just parched channels flooded
fleetingly by
rain, which hasn't come to Anna Creek in
[Music]
years. From when we get a decent
rainfall until the dams go dry, we've
got about probably 9 to 12 months
maximum.
[Music]
Well, that's the way this country is,
you know. She is she's got to learn to
live with it a bit and uh go along with
it. You can't go against it. You'll
never win.