I want to thank everybody we just hit
17,000 subscribers the other day
thanks modern standards good morning
modern standards we've got probably at
least inches of snow yesterday and last
night it's crazy it's cold out this
morning they're calling for today and
tomorrow to be negative 40 with the
windchill it's gonna be cold let's make
sure all the animals have extra hay well
we were getting a lot of questions about
how does our outdoor green house hold up
with all the snow and what do you need
to do this morning before I clean up the
winter chicken coop I thought I'd show
you how I do it what works well for us
[Applause]
they love the fresh hay this time of the
year especially go Peck through and eat
all the grain to help encourage that we
don't like to have electricity out
running to our coops so what we really
like using on these rubber water buckets
mat troughs whatever you want to call
them and they get frozen flip them over
step on them well nice and clean the
snow on the greenhouse it's pretty dark
in here too what I use to clean off the
greenhouse whatever I have in my hand
you have a push from that works good
you have your feed bucket that works
good
easy peasy just like that it lets so
much more light in but keep the snow off
of it and we don't have to worry about
the greenhouse collapsing off and the
chickens really like the extra light
one of the other really good benefits
about doing this is and piles up the
snow along the side of the winter
chicken coop slash greenhouse and it
helps keep out the drafts it seals it up
believe it or not snow is a very good
insulator believe for every inch of snow
you get one hour value so that's pretty
good so the heat can go up the top which
is fine
but if we can keep a lot of the drafts
out on the sides for the animals it's
great you don't want it airtight because
your animals need fresh air circulating
you couldn't have your animals in a barn
a heated barn that's not good for them
you want to have them out of the
elements the biggest things you want
keep my little wind and they want to
have a place room to go and get in from
the wind in the walk rain or water but
the elements the cold is still good for
them you just want to have an a draft
free area it's kind of weird like we
want to go inside in a warm house I'm
sure the animals would love to do it but
it's not healthy for them so we got to
remember that we're not animals don't
react to this weather the same way we do
the more they're out in it the better it
is formed especially the more natural it
is like our pigs are getting a huge
winter coat on them so that's keeping
them warm yesterday when I was out
feeding them in the afternoon it was
snow no good but all the snow was melted
off them they will wet sweating and then
they can go inside there too hey going
there they can dry off they can get warm
they can go back in and out this weather
doesn't bother them they're getting
acclimated to it they do it really good
speaking of that let's go check on the
pigs and see how they like and all the
snow
[Applause]
guess we gotta pack our trail down if it
ever warmed up we can do some
snowshoeing it's gonna be way too cold
this weekend to get under this tree
keeps getting narrower and narrower
we gotta keep ducking I think it's
between the snow buildup and the tree
get him weighted down from all the snow
they've been out and about good morning
what are you girls thinking of snow oh
you know what that means huh
I don't know if that noise will ever get
old they definitely are eating a lot
more which is a good thing I want to see
him eating that means they're staying
warm if we need to go through an extra
couple of bags of feed to keep them warm
it's worth it later on today I'll bring
them out a fresh bill of hay went to the
feed store the other day and I picked up
a few extra be able to hay because I
knew it was gonna be cold out this
coming week and weekend
it's banked up nice all around the sides
of the greenhouse what do you think of
all this snow okay the day off yesterday
in a two-hour delay today and this is
just the week back from winter break you
get a whole nother break I was hoping
today to start building our large soil
block maker that our medium-sized soil
blocks will fit into but with all this
cold coming and snow we got we're gonna
switch gears we have some Quonset tents
or tent sheds we got to clean those off
otherwise they're gonna collapse and we
need to get more firewood in the house
tomorrow today it's supposed to start
supposed to be like 40 below zero with
the windchill we're gonna be going
through some firewood so we've already
gone through quite a bit this week has
been so darn cold that pile is brought
up to the window we had another one in
front of it clean this up and get some
more wooden
ah
[Music]
the aprons dry in nicely my went a
little overboard I want to have like an
heirloom quality apron that I know will
handle my abuse that I can do anything
with it and I have to worry about it and
it just gets better and better with aids
like it gets more patina to it no last
that's what I like to do stuff that's
kind of my thought pattern now if we
built the house the use of all wood wood
floor wood walls with squid siding metal
roof like something's gonna happen to it
if we have used it or it gets beaten up
a little bit I want to look nicer with
age the outdoor kitchen all rough sawn
lumber it's just the older it gets the
more character it's gonna get the more
age is gonna have now with our new day
modern plastic world the older it gets
the crafty or it gets it throw it away
and get some new stuff what are they
saying vinyls final it's not wood is
final just don't paint it oil your oil
stuff it last like the outside of our
house we've oiled the siding and if we
have to redo it we don't have to scrape
it and paint it we can power wash it let
it dry and reel it easy-peasy and
they'll just keep adding to the richness
and the beauty over time and that's what
I'm hoping for
with the leather apron it's probably
half of it's probably completely dry so
I'm excited I can't wait to start using
it I'll be using it in the intensive
three-day pasture to plate class we're
going to be putting on here in April
with the pigs on us it's gonna be
exciting
all right enough staying warm by the
fire we got to get outside and get some
stuff done
judo doesn't look like she wants to come
out but I bet as soon as we get ready to
go out we asked should we write out the
door with us jumping around no
come back in July by the wood stove and
melt the snow off of her
you ready to go out
[Music]
let's grab snow shovels hay for the
animals snow broom this thing works
amazing for cleaning off your cars we're
not using it for that right now right
Pluto yes first of all I'm gonna get in
the hair
[Music]
all right that one's taken care of do
you covet Quan this way
[Music]
[Applause]
we're going to the tent Pluto you got it
whoo
snow is neat as snow is knee-deep over
here
Oh even deeper this quantit tent was
over that way quite a bit the tractor
was parked in it
we had a microburst that came through
last spring took the tent off threw it
up in the trees for the month later
laying it back down over here we haven't
used this with the boaters said well we
got to make sure we keep it cleaned off
otherwise it's got a cave-in
and it'll be jump
[Music]
well a snow hasn't been plowed it's
knee-deep right now it's just beginning
of January we're gonna get a lot of snow
this year I think Monday and Tuesday
they call for more snow glad I got that
roof beam off
I would've caved in with the next storm
I betcha
[Music]
lower down one floor down let's go hey
slow down
[Music]
you want to go and defrost you nice and
warm Figaro
[Music]
[Applause]
you're gonna have to finish up plowing
inside the cameras not liking the wind
chill out there this morning
we've already had a few camera errors
time ago get firewood
hi at least now tomorrow when it blowing
40 below zero all day long will be warm
[Applause]
[Music]
be happy too let's keep us warm for a
few days I hope there now I know I can
sleep good at night I'll have a nice
warm house we lose power we don't have
to worry about electricity heating our
house it's 40 below outside we got
plenty of wood in the house we don't get
to go outside and get it I'm ready to
stay inside this weekend thanks for
liking commenting and subscribing we'll
see you right back here tomorrow at
lawmakers a guide to modern home setting
self-sufficiency and freedom bye
[Music]