getting hit hurts
but coming into contact with a moving
part hurts a whole lot more
it can result in serious injury and even
death
every year of all work accidents contact
with moving parts of a machine cause an
average of 20 deaths 300 amputations and
more than a thousand fractures
construction professionals are
particularly at risk because of all the
equipment we use in our everyday work
as a construction professional you
should already know how to avoid and
control the risk of injury from contact
with a moving part
since there can be serious consequences
and there are several ways to prevent it
the risk of injury from contact with
moving Parts is considered zero
tolerance
on a construction site there's a lot of
machinery and powered equipment with
moving parts
that's why it's essential to prevent or
control access to moving parts
on some machinery and equipment the
moving Parts must be made 100
inaccessible even during operation
these machines must be equipped with
guards or safety devices that completely
prevent access to moving parts
on other machinery and equipment contact
with moving Parts can't be prevented
during operation in which case access
can only be controlled all such
Machinery must be equipped with guards
and or safety devices
[Music]
regularly check that all safety devices
are in place in good condition and
undamaged and working properly
if you notice any Vector malfunction due
to the necessary adjustments or repairs
never remove
[Music]
or block a safety device
and also never tamper with a guard or
safety device such as overriding the
limit switch on a mortar mixer
if you're a Machinery or equipment needs
maintenance such as a blade replacement
you should at minimum unplug it
or remove the battery in some cases a
lockout will be required
and on top of having compliant equipment
you have to use it properly too
one wrong move during operation can be
fatal
this is why it's so important to
properly train and inform your workers
so that they respect all the preventive
measures and safety rules in effect
being a professional is all about proper
planning because that's how you finish a
job safely
foreign
[Music]