[Music]
do
sharing i'm root rotten for the peas a
lot of history of that and we just
wanted to see
if we could get any inhibition of that
root rot
um
we chose the clear field technology so
we'd have the option like justin pointed
out of of using either raptor or beyond
we didn't put any fertilizer with this
and we ended up just using grass
herbicide only we didn't use the raptor
so on um 13th of
june we had a pretty nasty hail storm
this was the south end of the field
and it was 90 mile an hour winds and
tennis ball-sized hail and it really cut
things off
but being cool seasoned crops
the the growing point hadn't emerged
from the soil yet and so by the fourth
of july this is about what it looked
like it was
really coming back nicely the moisture
that we had gotten
with the hailstorm really
helped to advance the crop and
by late summer
we had really what i thought was a
pretty decent looking crop coming
what we were noticing was there were
more peas on the hilltops a little
lighter soil where the canola doesn't do
as well
and down in the lower ground uh wetter
and prone to saline we had more canola
taking over in those spots
um
so when harvest came we noticed that
this it was high lying yellows as was
our rp uh cultivar
and they were maturing
way ahead of this clearfield canola we
um we could see that was happening so we
did go out and we desiccated with a
quarter round up
took a while to get everything dried
down
and by the time we went out there you
can see the peas are pretty crispy
and in fact when you look behind the
header
you could see there was quite a number
of of peas out there we felt it was
probably seven or eight bushels an acre
so
um uh
you know it was overall we were we were
pleased with the bushels we got but we
felt we could have done better
that's what the the mix looked like um
in this instance uh by weight it was
two-thirds
peas and a third canola
and so we stuck it in the bin this way
we didn't have
our cleaning operations set up we had
plans to do it later on
we were concerned
that if the peas were 14 moisture and
the canola was 9 or 10 moisture
was at all going to turn into a
12 moisture where the canola was molding
but that didn't happen um we were we
were happy with the way it stored and in
fact uh we didn't get around to cleaning
it for about a year and a half
and it came out of the bin just as nice
as it went in so we were pleased with
that
so that year also we tried uh chickpeas
and flax seeded with the same drill so
they they went in one inch deep um
together
we had put on too much seed we ended up
doing 150 pounds and that was too heavy
on the chickpea seed
and we did about 12 pounds of flax and
that was too little so
we didn't use any fertilizer
and no fungicide
and
really that whole summer we we didn't
see
any ascochyta that we knew about this
was the same timing the field got hailed
on you can see the line between the two
fields
and this was fourth of july same way it
was coming back very nicely
and by late summer um the the flax had a
lot of bowls on it and a lot of pods on
the um
on the chickpeas
when harvest time came
we
we wanted to they were drying down
pretty well together
we decided to defecate them also with a
quarter roundup
and used a draper header to cut them it
cut similar to what soybeans would
the one thing we didn't like was the
residue distribution you can sort of see
it up in the upper right corner up there
when you put that much flax through your
combine it's just not going to chop and
spread as nicely
so we felt maybe in
subsequent years we would consider using
a stripper head instead
um that first year we really felt that
was our best fit comparing it to the
piola and we were pretty excited about
it
that's what our sample looked in the in
the hopper
i don't remember exactly i want to say
it was uh 60
by weight chickpeas and 40 flax
you can see there were a few unthresh
bowls in there but overall it it really
worked nicely together
so then moving forward to 2019
because of the shattering and the yellow
peas with the clearfield canola we
switched to
maple peas
and maple peas are a
longer vine
type of pea full season
they typically if you grow them by
themselves they'll get
maybe three and a half feet tall and
just about a week before you harvest
them they all go flat and you get to put
all of that through the combine so we
were kind of excited to see how that was
going to work out
we did try some different seating rates
we did three different trials we tried
120 pounds
and 110 pounds and 100 pounds of maple
peas all with two and a half pounds
of clearfield canola
we also tried uh some trials with 25
pounds of ams ammonium sulfate uh didn't
see any noticeable differences there
2019 was one of those years that was
a dry start to the spring and the um the
early summer were quite dry
but by the first of july it started
raining and that continued on in to
harvest
like a lot of you had
but it they really
you know they filled in nicely and uh
was kind of a jungle out there in places
and by harvest time um you can see we
had some weeds out there
but we also noticed that the um the
canola still didn't quite mature
as early as what the peas did
so
you know between rainstorms we felt we
better hurry up and get these off before
we lost them so we did desiccate with
reglone which is a lot like chromoxone
it's uh it's it's diquat versus paraquat
and um we got a pretty fast burn down on
that
and um
you know we had we had some struggles
with it you can see the that the stems
of the canola plants were pretty green
but um
overall we we got through it
um
we also tried some um
some yellow peas with canola actually i
should back up this was part of the um
population trial
the strip that you can see down the
middle that's lodged so bad
that was 120 pounds of maple peas
and as you go to the left of that that
was 110
and we came to the realization we really
didn't need that many maple peas in that
mixture it's a smaller seed
so um
we had also tried some yellow peas with
the canola and once again we had just
too much shatter on the yellows
but we also did try some yellow peas by
themselves
and once again this was a field that had
some history of root rot in it and we
had grown peas too many times over the
years
and
those peas by themselves were just
loaded with root rot and really were
quite poor
so that year also
we did
oh i just wanted to to say when we
harvested the
maple peas and canola we tried one round
with a stripper hat
but we felt we were shattering too much
of the canola so we did end up doing the
majority of it or the rest of it with a
draper head
so that year also we did um
try some more chickpea and flax that was
what we were most excited about and we
backed off that chickpea rate to about
120 pounds and we increased the flax up
to 15 pounds
we had some weeds and spots
but
it wasn't
too bad
but once again we had that prolonged wet
spell at harvest time
and
these two they're both indeterminate
type crops and with the cooler weather
and the
the the moisture that we got they just
wouldn't dry down
eventually the chickpeas started to
shatter and there was green mold moldy
seeds and black moldy seeds and
so it was getting to be
go time it was the first of october
and we just decided we'd go out with a
stripper head and just salvage what flax
that we could off of that
but what i was amazed we got a few
chickpeas in there but um it was
primarily flax but what amazed me was
that off of 15 pounds of of flaxseed we
ended up with about 13 bushelly acre
flax
and adjacent to that we had some flax by
itself seeded at a full rate of maybe 48
or 50 pounds
and that only yielded like 22. it was
one of those years that wasn't a great
one for the flax but i was i was
impressed with what 15 pounds of seed
could do for us
so in 2020 we switched it up again uh we
just wanted to get that maturity timing
figured out so we switched over to
yellow mustard and maple pea
and
we backed our seeding rate on the on the
maples off to 90 pounds and we
put in a half rate of of mustard five
pounds we felt that was a pretty nice
match
it's
they really
do a nice job of flowering at the same
time they attract a lot of
bees
into a mix like that
and they trellis together quite nicely
so
uh we're pretty happy with the way they
were looking
until uh an august second hail storm and
it wasn't uh i mean i've had worse hail
storms that have come through
but you can see there's a lot of mustard
on the ground there's some peas on the
ground
it didn't get all of them you can see
there were were certain clusters that
were greener so we still had some
production there so
seeing as how we had already lost some
to hail we decided to use the stripper
head and we were pretty happy with that
we you know it was tough to tell if we
were losing any more after the header
had gone by from what the hail storm had
done
but
at least we were able to
get the material through the combine
move a little faster and we were leaving
a foot or better maybe maybe even
16 18 inches of stubble out there to
catch snow
and uh help with erosion and those kinds
of things
i was amazed at how many uh
pheasants were out in the uh in that
field and this little guy jumped on and
rode for a couple rounds
um i finally had to get off onto the
platform and just pick him up and throw
him out
and he takes off flying
and he just he lands about 10 feet from
a hawk that was sitting out there and
i'm just going and you can't fix stupid
talk like me though
so um
we also tried with the mustard we tried
some yellow peas and that's a pretty
good fit also
the peas still
dried down a little bit ahead of the
mustard but we didn't dare to use the
stripper header on that use the draper
and
i think that's something that i'll
probably try again um most of the time
the maple peas carry uh
uh a higher
value than than the yellows but this
year it's gone the other way actually
the yellows are worth more than the
maples
so after the uh uh chickpea and flax
mess the year before
we we decided we'd try lentils of
plaques i had seen a neighbor a couple
of neighbors that have been trying this
and they've been pretty successful with
it
i thought i'd give that a try
we
we use 60 pounds of large lentils and 12
pounds of
flax
we had a lot of weeds in it
except for we had one done one strip of
fall valley we had actually intended to
plant soybeans on that
but
that's the strip off to the right
and that did a nice job on the weeds but
it thinned out the flax quite a bit so i
don't know if backing off from three
ounces to two ounces would be
a better idea or just increasing the
flax rate to um to
help some of that thinning
um
we still had disease
audrey's team had come out and scouted
that field
and let me know i i i believe it was a
fan of myself that we had in that field
and um
um
it was very poor we we ended up cutting
it with a stripper header just felt if
we can leave as much of that residue
upright again to catch snow and
keep from getting any erosion we were
we were ahead there was
you know the lentils we did get were
pretty beat up and and uh
we haven't gone back to that one since
so in 2021
we stayed with a maple pea and mustard
um
this went on an oats field the
the oats had been hit by that same hail
storm that got us on the on the maple
pea mustard
fields so we had a lot of volunteer oats
in it
we had to use uh two grass applications
this summer went on we just keep getting
new flushes and we still ended up with
some oats in it
at harvest time
we were fortunate this last summer we
had
one really good rain but we did have a
lot of a lot of hot weather with it
uh this was up along the north end of
the field along the road east of our
house um we had some flea beetle damage
and they probably worked their way out
maybe 60 feet or so into the field
but
what i like about
an inner crop is had this been just uh
mustard or canola on its own that kind
of flea beetle pressure would have been
huge
uh at least we had the peas to take over
it would have been bare ground and weeds
if it hadn't been for the the peas
taking over
in that area
um
so as summer went on they grew together
quite nicely again and
um when harvest time came we decided
again to try the stripper head and had
pretty good luck with it uh until we got
into some
some greener areas we switched and went
and cut some other crops for three days
and when we came back we've had some hot
windy days
and things were a little too crispy we
we tried the stripper head again and we
were just shattering too much of the
peas and the mustard so we ended up
finishing with a draper head
um
so we saw some
really strange differences uh this is
the field east of the house
we hit a line all of a sudden we went
from between 40 and 50 bushels down into
between 20 and 30 bushels
and we we didn't quite understand what
that was our seeding rate was the same
our
previous chemicals were the same uh it
had all been
hailed out oats the year before we were
at a loss i started looking back at
cropping history
and i
came to the realization in 2013 we had
seated peas on the south field till we
ran out
and on the north side of that
that had been flags
and
so we were still seeing
and again this was a field with a lot of
history of root rot so we were still
seeing some of that root rot taking hold
eight years later
so
the mustard helps to inhibit uh the root
rot but it it isn't the key role um
and i question if maybe the canola has a
stronger anti-fungal property than what
the the mustard does
but um
that was a little surprising to us on
the other quarter um
we knew we were going to have an issue
on the east we could see it all summer
that was actually the strip where we
started in 2018 so we didn't get give it
a long enough break so it isn't again
you still need to keep your rotations in
place but uh i think it it does help
having a brassica
in with your inner crop
this past year we didn't try a flax
inner crop with chickpeas or lentils or
anything
we went into the spring terribly dry
like the rest of you
there is no crop insurance on these
inner crops i was pretty comfortable
with the maple pea and mustard but uh
but less so with the flax
so i did a just a kind of a simple
comparison um
only using variable costs i didn't use
direct cost like
seeding or harvesting or land costs but
just uh a quick uh breakdown uh we had
about eight dollars 75 cents into
chemical
uh about 35 into seed
we used 40 pounds of map and 105 of urea
and
six dollars spreading charge uh for a
total of 77 of expense
um the income on that
uh this was a field that we had probably
two miles south of where we had the
maple pea mustard and um
it looked better all summer but i think
the heat affected it a lot worse than
what i realized
ended up 720 pounds we had a 37 cent
contract
for a gross of 266 and our net income
after variable was 189
now on the intercrop
again we had a little more chemical bill
there because we had to use two grass
treatments on
those fields
a little higher seed cost
[Music]
the inoculant we we have a cost there
but
our fertilizer and spreading
zero
and then we feel about a 17 acre
separation cost
for a total of 72 which is pretty
similar to what the mustard was but
by the time we we separated out 17
bushels of peas at 15
and 318 pounds of mustard at the 37
cents
it gave us a quite a bit higher gross
income and left us with uh 300
um net after variable costs
so
um
my neighbor morgan jacobs who's here
uh was kind enough to share with me his
breakdown and you know we saw
very similar results um
the the total costs he he put in his
combining and spraying and
seeding cost but um
you know it's still the the
the companion crop was the lower of the
three
and the gross income was the higher of
the three so
uh one thing he did that i really liked
was he had put together a uh yield that
it would take to equal what the inner
crop has done
in the case of the mustard
uh
he would have needed nearly 1500 pounds
compared to the 950 that he got to equal
the the bottom line of of the inner crop
and with the maple peas he was pretty
close he would only needed 37 versus the
35 that he got but um
you know there are a lot of advantages
to
not having to
scrape the ground to get the peas and
that was talked about earlier
so and of course there's going to be
advantages and disadvantages between the
two um i like the fact that it adds
diversity in the same field every year
it
has that potential for a higher combined
yield
we're reducing our fertilizer and
chemical bills
and i i truly believe that we are seeing
a disease reduction in in our in our
pees and and in the chickpeas in the
years that we've done that
and of course the disadvantages we don't
have
viable crop insurance we could be taking
hail insurance i didn't get a quote on
that decided it was too expensive
after three years
we might be able to get a written
agreement from rma so we'll see if that
comes out and see what value they give
us and and what the cost of that premium
is
of course the timing of maturities um
i've had to play with that a lot to get
things um to work out but
it is an issue
there's that need to separate it's
definitely an expense i do have a 5-2
quick clean also and i had planned on
running the maple peas and mustard
through that
this year we had a lot of dead
grasshoppers in the sample we had that
load of oats that was in there i just
felt it was just a little too dirty so
uh again i hired uh the neighbors who
have a bench sieve mill to run it
through
later on and then of course
we're pretty limited on our herbicide
options uh pre-plant is probably the
best way to go if you're after broadleaf
weeds fortunately the inner crops that
i've been using are
are grass tolerance so we we have that
in our in our tool belt at least
so i guess that's all i have um
did you want me to take a couple
questions or do you want to wait for the
panel
um well does anyone have any questions
that would be specific for drag because
we're going to have a panel
here next with um
maybe we'll just go right into the panel
i think sure yeah okay so we'll uh
oh audrey there was one question online
okay sure go ahead
um
sheldon asks which canola variety did
you use and is it a variety recommended
for straight cutting
um
it was pioneer
let's see
ends in a 76 h76 does that sound right
morgan
it really isn't a shatter tolerant um
uh canola variety uh not not like you're
invigors but um
again the reason we went with the
clearfield variety was thinking if we
needed to use the beyond a raptor on
as a as a broadleaf control
but
you know
i i think this could work really well
if we could find an early enough
seasoned
shatter tolerant canola to do this with
i
i'm still searching but
for the time being there's been some
nice contracts on yellow mustard and i
plan to do that again this year
you