here's a big old thistle anybody would
recognize it
I've been mob grazing if you will the
horses in this area so they've grazed
this right back the sheep were in here
before then the horses some people do
the horses first and then the sheep but
my sheep are my prophet not the horses
so in here you can see there and there
the horses have eaten the flowers of the
thistles so it cuts down on the seed
population I'll come in and I'll chop
this down as well so some of them
they've left the seed heads is there it
didn't quite get to the stage where they
were tasty for the horses but a lot of
the other ones you can see they chomped
through all the thistle heads right here
there's an old saying a chop in May you
double the display chop and June you've
cut too soon cut in July and you watch
them die basically the horses you can
see trimmed this thistle bloom and this
one here but you can see a second one
coming on so that's basically what
they're talking about is doubling the
display and there's more flower heads
coming up in there
despite the horse chop eating that one
so these are some more here thistles
that the horses ate blooms off of it was
hey I was getting from a particular
farmer was always full of thistle so
I've spent years fighting thistles and
when I came home these fields were
nothing but thistles and rye grass so
here you can see the horses haven't been
in this section you can see the grass is
higher and you can see the flower heads
of the thistles forming
and when the horses come in they will
eat those so you can see the height of
the grass there versus the height of the
grass where the horses haven't been so
the horses have been here and they're
going in there now it is eaten back by
the sheep but I'm getting instead of
mowing it or topping it I'm getting the
horses and you see they're fertilizing
it as well and so I do the field and
sections so that their manure is
relatively evenly spread I'll now come
in and Harrow these products that are
now free of fencing so here you can see
for manure piles but they're dispersed
around the place they're not all in one
location because I've done I think in
this small section here you can see the
horses up there so in this small section
here where you can see the electric
fence down that fence line here this
side of the row of trees the other side
of this dead oak tree and to there I
think I've done three six nine ten
twelve paddocks so they're now starting
on their thirteenth paddock which is up
here at the top and they have a line
that electric fence up there there's a
lane for them to go down to the water
trough which is right there so you can
see here is the product they're grazing
and here is the new product sorry this
is the paddock they're grazing now this
is the next paddock they're gonna go
into you can see there's electric fence
and that's a third paddock so I'm
dividing a strip into three and it
spreads the manure because horses always
have their favorite patch to go and
in a big field and their favorite patch
to eat
and this way they have to
everywhere and this is is what's really
good for the soil health and I'll come
in with the Harrow you can see they
there's no particular location now where
they it's everywhere which is great
and I'll also come in and chop down
those huge thistles now that I've
changed where I get my hey I'm no longer
I'm working on people who have diverse
wards of hay and feeding my sheep that
to resew more into my fields this field
here the Rams you can see are right
under that tree over there so they're
sharing their free-ranging in the field
but the horses are paddock grazing