I'm Mike MC from coltech energy uh our
company has been involved in developing
gasification projects since uh
2000 uh in 2003 we installed our first
system um and since then have gone
through a almost a continual upgrade of
Technologies uh probably the most in
most widely known system that we've
installed was in 2007 at fry poultry uh
if anyone has seen Dr Layman's video
aise of biochar or read his book that
unit is is shown in in both of those uh
both of those articles um what you see
on the screen is the latest of our of
our systems U this is kind of a
generation four the first three units or
the first three systems were were wood
based biochars I mean they were
developed gas fires they were developed
to process wood and we modified them to
to handle manur or more difficult fuels
um
after coming to the conclusion that that
biochar was a was an important piece of
the economics of of any project going
forward uh we set out and and designed a
system that was specifically designed to
handle manures and some of the more
difficult fuels and also produce a
consistent quality
biochar uh this unit pictured was
installed in late
2012 in Ohio it's on a farm that houses
approximately 4,500
cows and this unit can process
approximately 50 tons a day of
calor um at that facility they are
they're bringing manure and a
combination of manure and bedding uh
into a dedicated manure Barn between 35
and 50,000 tons a year uh we are taking
that material and drying it in a rotary
dryer to produce both animal bedding and
produce fuel for the gasifier and then
we are putting Cal or dried to 20 to 25%
moisture into the system producing the
energy to to operate the dryer and
producing a consistent quality
biochar now gasification is a thermal
process reacting carbon based fuels in
an oxygen starved
environment typically the sh gas
produced in the gasifier is then
combusted in a thermal
oxidizer um you know there are there are
systems out there that are taking S gas
and firing it directly in a
reciprocating engine but they're
operating with um processed wood they're
operating with a more consistent
fuel manure manure is not a consistent
fuel the composition varies and so the S
gas varies so it becomes very
problematic to try to to utilize the S
gas directly um we just add add enough
air and combust it in a thermal oxidizer
and then utilize the Heat
the product of gasification is is heat
and
biochar unlike paralysis paralysis they
also produce an oil and and we do not we
just we just produce a hot air product
and and a solid solid product form of
biochar our unit is a fixed bed
gasifier we do not have a fluidized bed
the material sits flat on the on the
floor of the
unit we inter ruce a controlled amount
of air in a
controlled Zone inside the gasifier to
provide the oxygen star
environment typically we are producing
mostly carbon monoxide inside the gas
fire and it's when we add air in the in
the thermal oxidizer then we're
converting carbon monoxide to carbon
dioxide and inside the gas viral our
temperatures in in the air inside the
gasar typically range between a th000
and 1500 degrees
F the the feed rates and the biochar
removal rates inside the gas fire are
controlled through variable frequency
drives so that allows us to control not
only the the input and so control the
throughput of the material but because
the the feed of the of the the feed rate
of the raw material is independent from
the feed of the bio Char coming out of
the machine so it gives us the ability
to control the retention time of the
biochar so we can impact the biochar
quality as well as in as control the
throughput and the energy
output we also have the our air fans are
on fre variable frequency drives so they
also can be modulated
to VAR the frut and energy
output and you know the one of the the
keys to being able to control the amount
of air in addition to uh starving it for
oxygen the minimal amount of air inside
the gas fire also allows us to control
particulate carryover so it it gives us
a cleaner emission
stream biochar is the carbon Rich
product obtained when biomass is heated
in in a closed container either oxygen
starred or oxygen free either
gasification or
paralysis gasification produces a
mineral that a material that contains
mineral ash from the feed stock as well
as the the fixed carbon and which will
be in the form of a carbon
Char and then this this carbon is
transformed into a very absorbent
material that has charged particles
which attracts nutrients and moisture
and the the ability of this
carbon changes dramatically with the
different minerals that are that are as
they part of the the biochar
itself um biomass materials contain
carbon two forms it's either in in the
form of fixed carbon or B of
matter and what we do is we react the
carbon in the volatile matter which
creates the energy and then try to leave
as much of the fixed carbon behind in a
biochar um typically volatiles start
acting at around 400° and fixed carbon
is usually closer to to 1,400 so it's a
i it's a very temperature driven
process due to the high temperatures and
retention
time biochar from Maneuvers are free
from pathogen ecoli growth hormones and
residues for medication so it it
provides an outlet for for a processed
product coming out of manur that that
otherwise Farmers don't have have the
outlet
for typically wood has between 2 to 5%
mineral asash and 20 to 25% fixed
carbon so when you're producing biochar
from wood uh you're going to have a very
high carbon
content if if you retain all the fixed
carbon you're going to be as high as 80
90% of carbon in the
biochar but wood has relatively few
Nutri
so you you have little nutrients in the
biochar it is predominantly just
Carbon on the other hand when we gasify
manures typically the manures will be
anywhere between 15 to 30% mineral Ash
and between six to 18% fixed
carbon so our biochar will be about a 20
to 25% carbon
product but the rest of that the the the
mineral Ash that's contained in that
biochar contains an array of of
beneficial nutrients it's nitrogen
phosphorus potassium calcium magnesium
and and a lot of trace minerals that are
that are beneficial both in soils and in
feeds the composition of of manure
biochar varies with the animal type and
diet and the levels of the various
nutrients change but their benefits do
not um for example poultry biochar will
have a high percentage of calcium
nitrogen phosphorus and potassium egg
layer biochar will be extremely high in
calcium due to the amount of calcium
they feed the birds to produce strong
eggshells calet or biochar will have a
higher level of of
magnesium and we're doing a lot of work
with um solid separation systems with
both swine and calor uh to try to retain
more of those nutrients in the solid
fraction so we're even increasing the
level of those nutrients when we're
producing biochar from those
products but but these nutrients all
provide different benefits uh whether
it's in the soil whether it's uh heavy
metal capture um the
different
nutrients all have different reactions
so there's they provide different
benefits so they provide different
applications for the biochar
and for biochars made from specific SE
seed stocks based on those nutrients um
was one of the slides that that Kurt had
earlier there was mentioned designer
biochar if you are
producing biocharge from different manur
or even manur and wood or agricultural
debris uh you will have different
qualities of biocharge just because of
the feed stocks and it allows you to be
able to to blend those biochars and and
create designer biochars for specific
needs the vast majority of biochars if
you read through Publications and
research are have been produced from
wood um quite frankly because Wood's a
very simple material to to gasify or
pize mans can can present problems so
most Technologies are designed for
wood um biochar made mother fuels such
as manur not only have a value as a
biochar but also provide an
environmental value as they provide a
method of disposing materials that are
creating issues um you know last year
city of Toledo had green water for four
days um you know the ches Bay has dead
zones the Gulf of Mexico has dead zones
and agriculture is not the only Factor
but it it's a contrib ruting factor
to to the algae blooms in all those
areas and finding a an outlet for those
manur other than land
application gives us an opportunity to
not only produce biochars which are
beneficial environmentally but but
eliminate some of the disposal issues
that are creating environmental
problems um you biochar has has
applications in a wide array of uses
whether it's so Amendment speed s
complements water
filtration soil
remediation odor moisture control I mean
it's it's amazing the the different
characteristics it has and the different
benefits it has in in in a variety of
uses and then when you on top of that if
you produce biochar from different feed
stocks and end up with a different array
of nutrients and different results then
you even increase the range of
opportunities and and effectiveness
in my opinion in order to make a
significant impact in the world biot
must be produced in large
volumes and and our relief
is producing it with feed stock such as
manur is a has a higher likelihood of
success um because those feed stocks
exist in large volumes and typically
they're concentrated in in in specific
regions um egg layers are in a certain
area
and daes are in certain areas and so
they they have a a very high
concentration of manures in those areas
and so disposal is is a bigger and
bigger issue every day
um but from a project developers point
of
view biochar provides an even different
value and that's
economics waste energy projects have
been developed for years and most of
them are in the field somewhere rusting
down uh they fail miserably or they have
subsidies to to allow them to
survive um because they are developed
for the energy component alone the key
to making these projects successful is
multiple revenue
streams just a very few and and we've
seen a few but a very few can survive on
single
stream um biochar can provide a
significant Revenue
stream um not always can it carry a
project by
itself but as a as one of a one of a
multiple of revenue streams it can make
the economic strong enough to make a
project
profitable from a technical
standpoint we don't believe developing
these projects is is extremely
difficult but raising the
is uh and education and biochar is
extremely critical because having a
having the established value for biochar
opens up a lot of funding
opportunities and and getting
sales getting sale prices uh is a is a
key component to to making these
projects
successful um typical
projects the unit that was pictured in
the first slide that is our standard
operating unit operating 247 it'll
process between 15 and 20,000 tons of
manure a year at an input moisture
somewhere between 20 and
30% poultry uh groer manure bro litter
turkey
litter coming out of the barns they are
in that moisture range so they can be
directly input into the gas
fire cow manure and Swine or require
some drying um either as we're doing in
Ohio just through a rotary dryer or the
the very high moisture contents require
some solid separation prior to
drying systems handling w calure we can
process 60 to 70,000 tons per year with
a single
gasifier so it gives you an idea of the
the size of of those systems and and
just rough numbers
that equates to about a 5,000 Cal
Dairy um biochar production with these
systems will be between three and 5,000
tons a year um and that depends on the
composition of the manure how how much
Ash is in it and and how fresh it is and
there's several variables but it will be
in that
range um and the use for the
energy can vary anywhere from using the
Heat to dry to heating buildings to
producing steam producing power
absorption chillers uh I mean we are
producing hot air and virtually every
energy
application that's
used starts off with a full of hot air
so I mean there are readily
available equipment that can be bed on
the back end for for the energy
application um you know in our
experience almost every project is
unique each customer has unique needs
and
conditions and but this system is very
flexible and and when we develop
projects they are tailored to the
individual needs of the customer whether
that's on the front end on their needs
of getting rid of material or or
processing material or on the back end
for what they can use the energy for or
or the biochar or additional byproducts
such as such as animal
betting um you know being able to
produce a solid product like a biochar
versus having a raw manure to handle or
or even a
digestate has huge environmental and
economic benefits