[Music]
hi guys welcome back to another episode
of mugs brew you here in my farm lab
we're gonna do this with a lot less
emphasis on the Edit and a lot more
emphasis on the information and today's
information is going to be about
irrigation not just any irrigation I'm
setting up a drip line system but I'm
not gonna be installing it today I do
have a little bit of something I am
gonna do in the lab today I'm gonna
replace one of the times of my broadfork
that I recently fabricated turns out I
can't to thin but first off if you
haven't already seen any of my content
welcome to my channel I am more glue I'm
gonna be dedicating the next few
episodes on this channel to our garden
that we busy developing and that is
where the stripline irrigation is gonna
be going I may put the link up there
it's not there yet means we haven't
installed it if it's there means we have
installed it however if it isn't there
it may just mean that I forgot to come
back from the future into the ponds to
put my tag up on the top of this and
talk to you guys these guys are terrible
things I put this little energy to them
properly so I always worry about you
know they're flying around my neck oh
yeah but we run into them at least once
a week in the in the banana fields in
the summer anyway that's that's
digressing from where I'm going I'm
trying to tell you guys about this
irrigation system that I'm setting up
and I got it down yet why are we setting
up an irrigation system well the primary
reason I suppose for me is time and
efficiency efficiency both in time
management and in water efficiency water
use efficiency farm work is considered
one of the lowest paid jobs so let's
just work at minimum minimum human cost
per hour is 20 rand and if you're gonna
water for an hour twice a day you're
gonna be using two hours of your time
strictly on watering
there's two hours equals 40 round a day
now this is probably like three bucks or
something in the states I don't know but
for you guys that's crazy cheap but
let's just roll with this calculation
for a second yeah you forty rounded day
ten days four hundred and thirty days
you're looking at thousand two hundred
grand every three months is 3,600 and
now this whole set up by the filter cost
me less than three thousand six hundred
Rand so what I'm trying to say is that
that time saved on watering pays itself
off in three months if you come and look
at my garden from the top and I will
zoom out here to the next section where
you can check it from the top we've got
a draw an image of our garden and I've
got this into four blocks and you can
see here could be four blocks block
block block block storage water both
five thousand liters of water
they're plumbed up in series of years so
they're both gonna come into it we're
gonna put off filter are difficult to in
line over here which is gonna run down
here into our garden and then it runs
along here this for Timo comes down into
the middle hostel our lemongrass and
Homer Inga's and then basically splits
the garden down here and we got two taps
on this but back to the photo so this
filter this is a basic dust filter what
the flow is in one way comes around here
and has to go through this disk system
before it comes out the other side of
the filter obeah and what I want to show
you is on this filter I don't know if
you're gonna get great focus but you can
see this ribbing so teeth on these
things when we tighten this up and if it
closes up all together what you end up
with is a hundred and thirty micron
filtration through this disk so that's
gonna hopefully stop any of our metals
from clogging up you know what it comes
down here we're gonna get to our first
forty mo 32 reducing
tea we're gonna come out of here and
that reducing tea into a 32 mo are 32
mullahs hanging around our sub main up
and down so that way and this way along
these beds on that sub main we're gonna
manage it through these ball valves so
the set up of six beds across this is
gonna be managed through the single ball
valve I said it would be easy you just
drill a little 8 mo hole and you stick
this little tip of key through one of
those holes in there and then you
tighten up this nut over here tighten up
the nut so that it comes up against ends
up against the plastic closing it off
problem with the system that I'm finding
is that you can't just push this little
paper key through one of these through
one of these holes over here because
I've never owned one of these things
[Music]
that's it looks like it's it it's in
anyways it looks like I needed a tin
mole bit on the end of my drill
give me so that's basically it put two
drop lines into each bed running the
length of the beds which are 10 meters
but now the strip line I haven't opened
it - hang on a second here let's pull
this guy yeah girl Susan brighten up
so that's what our drip lines are like
and you can see underneath is sort of
like a square underneath that hole a
Sackman oblak some who I liked so
there's really the square in a Neath
that hole and inside that you can see
that little molded inline emitter and
there's actually a molded in my little
filter inside there to help minimize any
other block because we might get thanks
I could cross you guys at legions for
supplying this so that's the basic setup
each blocks can be controlled by single
valve six bits per block and that's what
we're going to do there but I probably
fixed my broadfork
[Music]
[Applause]
as well I just want to give you guys a
any of you not as well this up they like
me a little took the secret to welding
to teaching the welding demons and the
most important thing is camouflaging
yourself so you can see I'm wearing
green to camouflage the metal and blue
to matte blend in with the UV are so
make sure that your shirt is the same
colors metal you're working on and
you're wearing a blue jacket
[Music]
so is the basic tech we've just got to
put it on both sides of the year so it
doesn't walk what I'm gonna do now is go
ahead and tack the other side a couple
of times and then run a deep world on to
this to close it up
[Music]
[Applause]
[Laughter]
[Music]
[Applause]
anyways guys that's started for me in
this so let's go outside have a look and
see and we're gonna put this drip
irrigation and then that's gonna be it
that's gonna wrap up for us and I'll
finish off in the garden here with a man
cave man cave garden let's go check this
and basically this is where we're gonna
be flipping out soon we're gonna be
changing out these onions turning these
onions drying them re composting these
systems this row cover here is over some
lettuce which is nearly done this side
over here we got our peppers which are
producing our cabbages which are coming
along nearly done we're gonna pull these
out and make some SAR crafts our spinach
we've just taken a massive you look fees
and on this side here we're gonna put in
these what sunflowers corns and beans
coming in our onions are just about done
the side too so they'll be coming out
soon and over here we've got some more
spinach and more cabbage planted up over
here umm yeah so this is the garden
these are our four plots and you're
gonna see us up here now
No
[Music]
okay guys and that's it that's gonna be
a wrap for us for today this is how we
have been watering we use two of these
10 meter watering caps for each of our
10 meter beds um it's just been a
tedious job you know coming out here
twice a day putting all that water arcs
we finally made the investment and we've
gone ahead and bought this drip line
we're gonna install it in the coming
weeks and like I said we're gonna start
flipping out these beds around me here
we'll show you we'll bring you along for
the installation process the harvest of
this garden and that's gonna start up
the season it's gonna be our next season
our summer season and our next season
here on YouTube so I'm quite excited for
this new season for this new chapter in
the garden with the drip line irrigation
and yeah that's about it but today guys
then thanks see you guys next week
Friday for another proof
[Music]
you