foreign
[Music]
hey what's up everybody I'm Chef Mikey
welcome back to Chef's Harvest Farm I am
a former executive chef turned Urban
Farmer and today I'm going to show you
how I built the ultimate no-till Garden
I'll go over the strategies of how I
built this I I started just growing food
for myself and my wife basically we
wanted to eat organic vegetables and uh
I started shopping at the farmers market
and then I learned that there's this
whole other level of food that you can't
buy in a grocery store so I wanted to
grow my own high quality food when I
started growing food I just started with
a little raised bed box garden that I
filled with soil that I bought from Home
Depot
and then that grew into a
a lot of them I had like 25 of these
little boxes that I built kind of back
here at one point those are all gone now
it's not an efficient way to grow food
trying to weed eat in between them and
mow around them it just doesn't work
well the reason I got into this style of
Agriculture and growing food and the way
I learned about it and why I grow
no-till is because I knew nothing about
growing food my mom was selling tea at a
farmer's market in Scarborough Maine
which is the town where I'm from and I
grew up there
and she said well there's this new
farmer in town and you should follow him
on Instagram and his name's Daniel Mays
and he runs frith farm so I followed him
on Instagram and he was promoting
these no-till methods of growing food so
basically they don't use a tractor or
anything or I don't use a tractor I
don't own a tiller or a tractor but I
might own a tractor soon just to use to
make compost and move it basically I
don't want it for working in the field
um
so anyways this guy was promoting these
no-till methods of growing food
where he was using big giant tarps to
tarp the ground and that's how I killed
the pasture here or the backyard the
grass I just tarped it the first time I
put a tarp down it was in October
and then it it gets cold so the heat is
what really kills it but even doing it
that time of year I just left the tarp
there all winter I'm in Knoxville
Tennessee Zone Seven we have relatively
mild Winters typically but it can get
really cold so when I pulled the tarp
back in the middle of the winter the
grass was mostly Dead with some like uh
weeds growing out so I dug those little
weeds growing out up with a fork it was
mostly onion grass and I don't know the
other kind what it's called I'll show
you it's this stuff this is like the
worst weed that I have I think it's
called Bermuda grass maybe or something
I could be completely wrong I don't know
but it's like that rhizomis stuff that
sucks so the silage tarps don't kill
that I mean I had it tarped for like a
year so the whole garden whenever I find
that I go in with a fork and I dug it
out so then I'd build the beds I'd get
like a pickup truckload full of compost
and I measure out 30 inch beds and 14
inch walk ways and tie it up with a
string from one end to the other while I
measure it out
and build the beds like that and then I
covered them still with a silage tarp to
just kill any more weeds that are going
to grow up
so then that spring I peeled back the
silage tarp and I moved it over to the
next part of the yard and I started
killing that part
and all this while I had a full-time job
so I'm doing this on the weekends
basically
and then the next part of the garden
just stays tarped for about a year
well then I built those beds in the same
method but then I just cover crop the
whole thing immediately to Winter rye
grass in like October of that year so
then the following spring the rye grass
is about six feet tall
I crimped it using a pallet I just like
threw a pallet on top of it that matted
it down I dragged the silage tarp back
over it for about two weeks because now
it's like April May starting to get hot
in Tennessee so it cooks that up pretty
quickly and just leaves a flat grass mat
and then this next plot that I have the
footage of that's this year after I
built this Market Garden and I had a ton
going on I'm super busy I'm like well I
still have all this yard so I just
pulled the tarp over there and I just
let the tarp sit there for a year then
the grass is just completely dead then
it was mid-october I was already
planning to do this obviously I planned
this whole thing two years planning you
can't just wake up one morning and say
hey I'm gonna use this method on this
YouTube video that I saw today like
you need to plan ahead
so I plan two years in advance had the
tarp sitting there for a year
I pulled that tarp back
and it's just red clay basically
and it starts pouring rain out and I got
a five gallon bucket filled with rye
grass seed and I just go out there in a
rainstorm and I just start shaking and
rye grass seed I put 40 pounds of rye
grass seed right on top of the soil I
just broadcasted it well sure enough
the rye grass sprouted
and
the rye grass grew up this tall
and I crimped it and I built beds right
on top of it and the wood chips so it's
just like a flat
sheet of mulch but the roots are still
in the ground feeding the microorganisms
they have a symbiotic relationship with
the plants that I've planted now into
that Garden then I layered the compost
in 30 inch beds about six to eight
inches deep right on top of that
and then I built walkways out of wood
chips right on top of that
Okay so uh it's been pouring rain out
for the last two days I don't really
know if that's good or bad to do this
um but my thought of doing it while it's
soaking wet is because I'm gonna crimp
this down and then pull the silage tarps
over it to kill it
um and then it's gonna be like a mulch
grown in place the roots are still going
to be attached
um and when I peel that tarp back it's
just going to be like
um straw everywhere basically like a big
amount of straw and then I'm gonna plant
right into that so I'm gonna go like
around the edges and crimp the edges in
first and then I'm gonna go and crimp it
all and all facing One Direction so I
can just pull the tarp over it so I'm
going to go down to one end and back and
then down and back and I'll speed that
up while I do it
this is my tool basically right these
things by string and I'm just going to
go up and crimp it down
and just keep going like that to crimp
it all the way to the ground and that's
the first step
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
so I couldn't be happier about how this
method turned out I hope you get
something from it and I hope you enjoy
learning how I built My ultimate
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
thank you
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
okay