[Music]
foreign
stewardship program is based on an
agreement on sustainable agricultural
practices on the one side of the
agreement the Farms commit to adopting a
series of agricultural practices that
benefit the environment on the other
side in recognition of this commitment
that benefits society as a whole
government Orca helps these Farms
through different ways one way is taking
action on farms by providing services
and materials ultimately what is sought
is to help and accompany the farmer in
their Journey towards sustainable
agriculture production it is a way of
giving a final push to make the changes
they want but for one reason or another
they are unable to be due to economic
reasons or lack of time
we take action in many areas in relation
to the farm but we could group them into
five main blocks
the first block is improving soil
fertility soil fertility is the basis of
soil productivity and has huge
repercussions in relation to the Farm's
economic viability in this area we
provide soil analysis soil management
recommendations and we also accompany
the farmers in implementing new directed
grazing practices and the materials
needed for this
the second block is improving water
management practices
in this case we aim to reduce as much as
possible the extraction of fresh water
from the aquifer because it is over
exploited
we also want to help maintain humidity
in the soil to improve soil fertility
what we do essentially is to restore
rainwater harvesting systems that are no
longer working or are abandoned for
example traditional Canal systems or
traditional systems called all jobs and
then we innovate them with solar power
pumps
also we ate soil water retention through
keyline Landscaping techniques rainwater
canals and swales or installing covers
to protect from the Sun and Heat
we have a third book of action which is
focused on biodiversity conservation so
as an environmental organization we have
an intrinsic interest in conservation
but there's also numerous benefits of
farmers too such as increased crop
resilience and biological Pest Control
[Music]
in this case we carry out annual
bio-indicator monitoring of certain
species and this is done through citizen
science project and it's carried out by
volunteers
we also create water sources for
wildlife and install nesting boxes to
encourage natural predators and these
control pests and diseases on the farm
the fourth block of action is linked to
Habitat conservation for example we
carry out a natural value inventory of
each farm and this helps us detect areas
to acts upon and it better helps us
better understand the land that we're
protecting
then what we do is collaborate in
habitat maintenance and restoration
actions so especially for forested areas
these are of Interest so that cattle can
Refuge from the Heat and also wild
pasture lands because these offer
quality food for livestock at a near
zero cost while they're also cataloged
as priority habitats at a European level
and we generally carry out this work
through volunteering sessions that are
run one Sunday a month
finally the fifth block consists of
restoring Landscapes so the Mosaic
landscape is characteristic of monoka
and it includes a patchwork of dry stone
walls fields and forested areas and this
landscape also includes ethnological
elements that are important parts of the
Island's identity and at the end of the
day this is what we all see in our
surrounding and we think this is really
important so we offer waste removal
services for Farms we install
traditional Wild Olive Tree Gates
we also help restore structures that are
made from traditional dry stone walls
that help protect fruit trees within
pasture lands
this would be a summary of ways in which
we take action and invest in the Farms
that are part of custody agraria but we
also carry out other activities such as
Product Promotion training and
Consulting and working with the general
public through volunteering and
Environmental Education and we will
explain these in the other videos
[Music]
thank you