[Music]
slim did you make a friend
you tried to let him go and what
happened
you held out your hand and he jumped
right in it didn't he
and then he jumped up your leg
liam said him down and said you're free
to go in the wild
and he jumped right into his hand
he says i'll hang out with you for a
little bit longer my jumping friend he
says i saw you jumping and you're a pro
[Laughter]
good jumpers
you're gonna trip
you're gonna trip over the walnuts
i already picked up
all the walnuts in this area
and there's
just as many fallen again
[Music]
all right put them in
put them in the wagon
pick them up
they're not going to help me are you
you watching those cows eat
they're so cute
who wouldn't want to watch cows eat
they're so cool
look who's coming
look behind you
look who's look who's coming it's baby
bowser
are you coming to see us
no
i turned around
you want to see the chaos
you love your girls they're sweet
bowser you are so fat
mama you are looking good
too i think we're feeding them maybe a
little too much
i'd rather have them a little bit hefty
going into winter though
oh
pink
snacks
got a bunch of starting to rot pumpkins
that we got to go ahead and hurry up and
feed them all before they get too gross
how's the wheat going
is that just the right spot to itch
[Music]
got some pumpkins and some walnuts we're
gonna see if they like
you think you're liking peaches
what are you doing you wanna give some
to the pigs wanna give some to the pigs
so i've had a lot of people tell me
that
pigs love black walnuts
i've been a little afraid to give them
to them because i know that too much
black walnut can be toxic
mama
[Applause]
see
will she eat them
i noticed that the boys had some black
walnuts above them that were falling
into their pan and they weren't eating
them so
yeah not sure about this my pigs are not
black walnut
fans it appears
oh maybe they are no
no
i already know the boys aren't eating
them
strange
what i know she does like
hey some
there she goes
chop chop chomp
these little mini pumpkins are not the
tastiest but they're still
this is still food
[Music]
[Applause]
me
[Music]
interesting side note
the chickens are interested in the
walnuts and i think that's because of
the whole maggots
or whole worms is a nicer way to call it
there's little bugs that parasitize the
outer hell of the black walnut
the chickens were probably interested in
that attracted by that
chickens are great to clean up after
other animals aren't they
[Music]
i don't know if his jaw is strong enough
to bite through the shell
come on cows
lashes friendship come on
i need you out of here now gotta get it
set up for the
piggies come on
come on cows
here i'll watch the gate you
gotta watch the gate because bill's
gonna try to sneak out we want to keep
him in there if possible
even though we know we can catch him
again
[Music]
come on
on come on lashes
there they go come on cows
good girls
[Applause]
they're like oh yeah
that grass had a chance to grow up for
us
that was a good nice little short rest
for this pasture
now that the season is slowing down on
the growth rate
alright so now we're going to take down
this fence around the coonies
we're going to move it up into here
give them a section right here
to rotationally graze ryan's taking it
down
we pretty much trust
that bowser
and peaches will stay with us
so we're not worried about them going
anywhere while we move the fence
should be pretty easy to get them where
we want them to go
[Music]
peaches is like not even aware that
there's no more fence she's just
chilling
uh she's like this is my area
i'm gonna lay down
she's such a chill little pig big pig
[Music]
all right we've got the electric net
fence set up
we're going to use this solar charger
all by itself on one fence so that it's
strong enough
they've got the tarped area for shelter
from the rain
we'll build another pallet shelter for
them up here for the winter once it
starts to get cold they'll have that
we've got the fence down right here
our water is going to go right here and
wallow will be in this corner
but we're going to bring peaches in
bowser in this way
pretty cool
we spent all that time putting up the
fence
over here
he just hasn't moved she has no idea
that there is not
a fence around her you have no clue do
you
right mama
[Music]
oh
come on peaches
you were supposed to follow him
[Applause]
use bread to catch fish
use bread to make sandwiches
now
using bread to
lure pigs
sacrificing our kids lunch
what's wrong why are you afraid
come on girl
it's so close
come on
critical turning point come
on where's that gate closed daddy push
that get close push that gate close two
seconds
now bonus points
all right we got her in the paddock if i
can get her
into the electric net fence without her
getting spooked by walking over a fence
that'd be great
slightly bigger pieces
oh i know
over here
out of the bread crumbs
there you go here we go here we go
a whole bunch right here and then i'm
going to come over the top of her
if i can get her
[Applause]
[Music]
and we still have half a loaf of bread
left for us to eat wow that was a full
loaf when we started oh my goodness pigs
pigs
and peaches
and bowser
united
reunited and it feels so good
you're so good you're so good
now i just gotta hook up the electricity
and now the dog house goes back
to its original use
move titus over here
so that the cows can use the original
use of that shelter which was for cows
so the cows have a shelter
the dog has a shelter
and
we will be building a
pallet wall and ceiling for these guys
shortly they're fighting over a pumpkin
bill is running around with a little
mini pumpkin in his mouth
you like those pumpkins
they're yummy huh
so
we have lashes back in the buckpin
she's just
in there in the buck shelter eating some
of his hay
and she's in here again because she got
out again she found a new spot
and she broke through a new area so
man i just wish we could just fence the
entire back side of the property with
regular fence instead of barbed wire but
it's just not in the budget or the time
limits that we have right now
so
she is in timeout pen
meanwhile the koonies are
loving their area they're doing a good
job
and staying in
they have a couple of ducks in there
visiting them right now
mama friendship
is out there she doesn't go far when her
baby's in here she doesn't go in the
woods
she stays nice and close
but the kuni kuni rotational fence is
up and functioning
so that was a good thing for us to be
able to accomplish this weekend
right bill
[Music]
um