let's do something special turn on the
light 2.5 billion people can't do that
because they only have access to wood
and charcoal for lighting heating and
cooking
even though charcoal is necessary for
their existence the production methods
used wastes most of the wood and lead to
deforestation famine and pollution while
wind and solar energy will be wonderful
replacements for charcoal by the time
they can be implemented all that will be
left is literal ash that's where the
clean and efficient charcoal kiln comes
in by recycling the pollutants as fuel
and improving the overall efficiency of
the production methods the amount of
wood or plant matter needed to make
charcoal and the pollution Jerr aid will
be significantly reduced thanks to its
simple continuous process design this
kiln will be easy to build easy to
maintain simple to operate and
inexpensive to manufacture by
implementing this method we will reduce
pollution and deforestation while
improving the lives of the impoverished