so
my name is david forster and this talk
is
introduction to soil minerals and um
to just to warn anyone who was here last
year i'm basically doing the exact same
talk i did last year
on the exact same subject uh there seems
to be enough confusion
around it that it's good to hear it a
few times um
i'm not an exception that took me a long
time comparing the same thing over and
over to learn it so
to warn you though if you thought you
got everything out of it last year
you may want to try a different one um i
have a little more time this year
so i'll cover things in a little more
depth that i did last year
basically my goal with this is to give
you a foundation for understanding
uh the soil system and what we at the
bfa talk about
and what really is it the the
one way of looking at what is at the
root of what
basically every one of the other
speakers here is talking about what's
going on in the soil
and i look at the soil minerals because
it's very concrete
it's something i can start with i'm
going to leave a lot of space at the
end of this talk a lot of time for
questions q a
um some of the other speakers here at
the conference i think have
brought up some issues that uh may make
me think that
i'm perhaps crazy to focus on this and i
want to
leave time to have those discussions
because i think that there are nuances
to all this
they are very important soil minerals
are very important
um but they are not the most important
thing
but they're a good place for people who
are just starting to start looking at
so with that introduction
i'll get started so like i said i'm
david forster
i'm the bfa agronomist staff agronomist
i also have my own consulting company i
consult with
private clients doing soil and farm
consulting and what i always focus on
is looking at the soil and i look at
what are the
limiting factors to soil health and so
that's where i
start every conversation and everything
when i'm talking to pharmacists
what are the limiting factors to get the
results that you want
so that's another key point here is that
it depends on what you're trying to
accomplish
uh and that sets sort of the framework
for how to think about this stuff
um the other goal with this
talk is to demystify the entire
thought process around this if you go
out and start reading books on this
you will likely get overwhelmed i mean
raise your hand if you've been
overwhelmed if you've been reading about
this stuff
it's very really very well and one of
the main reasons is because
we're dealing with living systems
they're complex
and there is more
in those books that you've read more of
it
is dedicated to the sort of nuances the
what-ifs the things that
you're frankly most people aren't ever
going to deal with the actual
fundamental
baseline of this is is not that
complicated it only gets complicated
when you start adding on all the
well what if you have this what if you
have too much magnesium what do you have
all these little things that in reality
if you're farming a piece of ground you
probably only have to deal with a couple
of your personal what-ifs
so i'm going to try to point out how to
think about it so that you can get
quickly to what you need to worry about
and stop worrying about all the other
stuff that you only need to worry about
if you
want to do what i do
so
so the other thing i want to do here is
before i
forget to do this before i lose track of
time
talk about some of the resources you
have available when we leave here so
financing.org the website we have a lot
of
information there in the growers section
especially uh we're reorganizing and
trying to do a better job of
presenting it these prep my presentation
and all the presentations here at the
conference with
maybe one or two exceptions uh will be
made available to everyone on the
website
um that's a really gonna be a really
good resource we also have our
conference recording from past years we
have
uh you can download the audio from every
one of them i believe
uh and there will be video for the ones
that we successfully have managed a
video this year
as well so that's a good place to go
i do free agronomy consulting calls once
a month
virtually and um if you go to this
website tiny
dot cc slash soil health that's the
media trans version of the link
and you can learn about how to get
connected with that
there and that is free as in like action
prayers and
free and you know free beer
don't if you remember the bfa you can
tell your friends tell
anyone who might be interested in
learning how to create better food or
you know grow better anything really um
so that's a great one if you're the only
one who calls in it's an hour of
one-on-one free consulting time so
i encourage people to call in the uh
next one is december 12th uh tuesday
december 12th
so it's coming up soon um i also do
through the bfa discounted one-on-one in
group consulting
um for anyone who wants that
the one-on-one is generally to help
people interpret their soil test results
get them started
and then group is something i would love
to do more of and that would be
if you have a local horticulture group
or a local vfa chapter
something like that i could come and
give a talk
and then we also have local chapters
throughout the country they keep
popping up uh more and more if you
anyone here wants to start one get in
touch with us
we have a mineral depot system we buy in
bulk
many of the minerals that you might need
and
and the biology and some of the other
products that are hard to find
and we make them available to chapters
um as best we can and that's a really
good way to get things that are hard to
find
so
uh all right i start with this picture
if you were here
last year you've seen this picture uh
this is
in minnesota and it's one of the first
places on earth
there's i think two inches of elevation
change in five miles
it's the bottom of an ancient seabed
and places in this valley are
extremely salty as in sodium salt
and things grow really well when you
have everything
working well but um i'll talk about this
a little more later but i
just wanted to mention now that when
the group that i was working with
started in this field about
20 to 25 percent of this field had
nothing going on so
it looked like these areas here totally
back up
20 to 25 percent around the perimeter of
all these fields looked like that
not even weeds wouldn't even correct
something they were spraying ground up
there
just weeds would not grow and not only
did weeds not grow
but the soil wasn't this sort of darkish
gray color
it was white it looked like it had just
snowed in the middle of summer
and that's because of all the salt the
sodium that was in that field
and this picture was taken just about
i think it was three years uh
after that after that point here it was
20 assault
and all but just this little part around
the outside edge was
planted uh it no longer looks white and
they were
actually growing really really healthy
sunflowers there i mean it's still a
modern crop
cultivation system but uh they were
actually building organic matter in the
soil
and it wasn't organic but practically
might as well have been they were
not certified almost entirely organic
practices there
and so in a very short period of time
they took soil that
literally wouldn't grow anything and
they turned it around to grow healthy
plants
and they did that with a combination of
minerals and biology
people around there tried it with just
biology people around there try to
adjust minerals and it doesn't work
or it takes a lot longer so when you
work together and figure out what the
limiting
factors are in your system you can have
some tremendous results
so i'll come back to exactly how this
was done when we're talking about soil
test results and working with your soil
system
so i want to start sort of letting this
foundation
with a discussion of what is soil
fertility
and soil fertility is the harmonious
interaction of a number of components of
soil so their
air water the physical chemical so it's
minerals it's biology
they all have to work together to create
healthy
living soils if you're missing any one
piece of that
then you don't really have healthy
living soils you have
dirt basically or or something that's
not working at its maximum potential
and so if you don't have these things
you don't have clay
silk sand water air minerals biology
you cannot build soil you cannot
grow healthy plants you may be able to
grow plants that look healthy but
they're going to be limited or they're
going to be
expensive in the sense that you have to
continuously dump something on there to
keep them alive and growing and happy
in this picture here it's just a sort of
standard
chart of the physical composition of
soil
in terms of clay uh silt sand
and various compositions of type various
categories of
loam in the middle
and so the key thing about fertile
healthy living soils is they are
compounded
when you have healthy soil pretty much
by definition you're
creating more of it the
the great plains uh had in places many
dozens of feet of soil
that were built over many millions of
years and that was done
through the healthy symbiotic
relationships between the various
components of soil biology the minerals
the air the water
the plants etc and as they grow they
actually produce more soil they produce
topsoil
and they do that by breaking down the
rock breaking down the parent material
incorporating organic matter and that
that process creates what we think of as
top soil
and that topsoil is able to support life
and grow abundance and
continue to create more of it and this
is something that
our industrial agricultural system
has been mining this soil for a number
of years
and until we can get away from that and
start building soil
uh we aren't really it's not a
sustainable model uh it is just like
mining
in any other sense and so what i'm
really talking here is
called pedogenesis this is the building
of soil and creation of soil
and there's an equation made up by a
russian geologist
that defines how you create soil and
creative soil is a function of these
things that are down here at the bottom
it's a function of climate prepared
material
biological process and time and
there's only certain multiples that i
can control i cannot control time
it can be kind of cool i can control
somewhat climate like in terms of i can
make sure that my plants have enough
water
i can make sure i can do mean
differences make sure that they have
so i have hair uh that there's stuff
happening around them
you know the gases they need etc i can
do that to some degree
i can impact biological processes for
sure i can bring in inoculants i can
feed microbes
i can um i can bring in the things that
are missing
and try to balance and keep them alive
and then i can also do this this
apparent material so
we think of soil as this sort of
stamped stable thing it's been there for
a long time
we go out there we just look at soil and
assume that that
dirt out there it's always been there
but in many cases around here
one of the ways it got there is through
glaciation it's been through
geological processes these things take
millions and millions of years and so
the way i think about building soil is
that what i'm trying to do is make this
equation
as efficient as time or as efficient as
possible
and the thing i can't control is this
one so i worry about these
so i always tell people if you can't
maintain hydration
you can't keep your plants moist none of
these things matter
violet's going to die the minerals are
going to sit there doesn't matter don't
waste your money
if you can't do that so um
and the same thing applies to any other
ones if you have biology
but you don't have uh the hydration if
you don't have
the minerals necessary to have as much
diversity as you can in biological
processes
as much vibrancy there then you are to
some degree
wasting some of that investment of time
or money
and so i like to look at all of them
together find where my weaknesses are
and focus on those i'm a lean sigma
black belt by training as an industrial
engineering
uh methodology and so what i learned was
always
find your um your weakest link link in
the system
and that's where you want to focus
because until you fix that one
everything else you're doing is a waste
of your time and in farming it's
very similar if you're spending all your
time um
making really awesome compost tea but
you're not making sure your plants
maintain hydration or that you've got a
little bit of boron there
then you might actually just be wasting
your time
so try not to get stuck on in a dogmatic
approach
to your farming your growing practices
i think that's one of the things that
where a lot of people get tripped up
they hear a great idea and it's a great
idea and they think it's a great idea
for them
and then they wonder why it doesn't work
and it doesn't work probably because
they've never thought of this so
um and why is pedogenesis important
pedogenesis
is important because basically if you
aren't growing soil
you are likely destroying it
soil is rather easy to destroy and so if
you're not
making your decisions in a way that
you're really consciously thinking about
how can i grow
more soil make it healthier and heavier
you're likely destroyed um
you're likely not sitting on the knife
edge of in between
perfectly balanced between um just
barely
not destroying it or not building it so
if you're not
seeing new soil being created you're not
seeing improvements in your soil over
time
then you're probably engaged in mining
so keep that in mind um so what i like
to do when i look at
accelerated heterogenesis and that's
what i want to do to make this equation
as efficient as possible
and what i like to do when i do that i
don't just you know go out and try to
throw chemical fertilizer or anything
like that what i do is mimic
natural processes so i try to eliminate
the inefficiencies
in them what i see in my system and
mimic natural processes
if i didn't care about making money
i didn't care about feeding my family i
could wait for the next glacier
but i have a short life span and i'd
like to
be a shepherd to the land that i take
care of i like to teach my
farmers and science staff as well and so
that to me is really important so
if you have enough time to wait you
don't have to really worry about this
but most of us don't have those types of
time scales available to us
and i would propose that what we need to
be doing is helping nature out a little
bit
what we're doing is not necessarily
counter to what nature
intends we're just trying to work within
those systems accelerate them for our
own purposes
so these are the things i i look at i
look at creating more perfect climate
um ensuring that we have adequate and
balanced
minerals so that's the parent materials
and also
eliminating stress on biology so that
might mean
you may not have biology that's a thing
that happens
uh so you may have to bring it in and
then you may have to feed it and take
care of it
um people here that's not a big
shock to when i talk to conventional
growers generally when they hear
soil biology um if they've really
thought about it all they've
usually thought about it in terms of um
something trying to kill their plants
that they have to spray
and so it's this is a big leap for some
people
um but at the same time it doesn't take
much to
get this the one thing many
a lot of the soil the pathogens and soil
they actually have protective
properties for other pathogens and when
they're balanced
uh they actually help plants uh grow
better so um i'm gonna
blank on the example i had in mind then
that's great but
we'll get back to that so
delving into the sort of nitrate
of what how of soil and how some of the
minerals
place a role in healthy soils
um starting i'll start with this so for
this picture
so this is how you can think of
how minerals stick into soil so this box
represents
the clay portion of soil and these
minerals
are some of the cation elements that are
in those soils
so cations cats generally think of as
positive unless you're allergic
anions are like ants and you know
they're you know positive unless they're
in your kitchen so we
you know that let's call it negative so
ants are negative cancer positive
and so these are cations which means
that they can stick to soil
uh soil colloid the clay particles and
soil
because they have an electrostatic
charge where they're attracted to each
other
so what what soil is made up of what the
clay component of soil we're going to
talk a lot about clay and i'll tell you
why in a second but
clay soil particles stick minerals to
them
and the amount of play you have can vary
tremendously
and also how many sites can be on the
play so this is
a box it's a certain size box and the
same size box
in different types of clay can have a
different number of these elements stuck
to it
and that's based on the age the
weathering the type of clay it is
some clays just naturally hold more
minerals
and some clays are very weathered so in
the south
southeast united states for instance a
lot of the clays are very old
geologically and weathered and the soil
may be
pure clay practically but they hold very
little nutrients
some people have heard of this um and
we'll talk about how you address that in
just a moment uh but
what i want to point out here too is
that
clay isn't in a box shape like this clay
is is comes in sheets so there's layers
of clay
and on the outside edges of those clay
you'll have a lot of these elements
and sometimes you'll have some of those
stuck between the layers of clay
and the size of these elements actually
will influence
how closely those clay layers are stick
to each other
and so one thing i'll talk about a
little later in more detail
is that certain things like calcium make
those clay layers
get further apart things like magnesium
tend to have them stuck closer together
and when they're close together they can
trap things inside of them and it can
change the physical properties of how
the clay reacts in soil
and this is the piece where
where it's important to realize that
when you're adding soil minerals you're
not just adding soil minerals because
you think
that there's not enough in the soil it's
also about changing the physical
and uh the physical properties of that
soil and how biology
works within it and to create a more
efficient system
so we're going to talk about that more
in a minute um
changing gears slightly here um
there's this concept that there is an
ideal cation balance
um dr william albright came up with this
concept
he did a lot of research around the
world studying
places where animals uh and
people but mostly animals uh nutrition
and health was higher than in other
places
and he found that there was this
correlation between the health of the
animals
and the soil in which their food was
grown
and the and basically what he found was
that
anywhere in the world and almost and
then he started looking on the cross
anybody wrote any props
if they if it approximated this ideal
cation balance everything seemed to work
better
and so he spent basically the rest of
his career studying this
and so that ideal cation
balance is approximately 68 calcium
12 percent magnesium four percent
potassium
one percent sodium and the trace
elements the trace electron
now one important thing here is that um
going back to this the amount of
minerals that can be held onto
the tight portion of the soil remember
these are cations there's a name for
that
and that's called the total exchange
capacity so it's the total
capacity of your soil of your
mostly it's clay because it plays tiny
it has
a huge surface area which is why so many
things can stick to it
uh very many orders of magnitude less
things stick to silt
and many orders of magnitude less things
stick to sand
so the clay is really where most stuff
sticks in terms of cations
and so the amount of this stuff that can
stick to this size box of clay
or soil is the total exchange capacity
that's an important thing to keep in
mind because
that is what relates the percent of
these elements
to the actual amount of pounds you need
to have in your soil to have a balanced
soil that
works well and um
when you have this in your soil
it leads to a ph of 6.4
every time
when you are higher or lower in some of
the cations it changes your ph
and this is also why
ph is a core metric for soil health
and mineral balance it's because
basically
all of these things in all of these
things
impact ph but
we don't know which ones and so for
instance this
calcium actually impacts ph less than
magnesium which is less than catalyst
potassium which is less than sodium
so you may have and actually this goes
back to the minnesota picture
um the ph in that soil was i think 8.4
so it's very basic uh if you're from new
england
we'll see of you can't imagine at 8.4 ph
uh you're usually 5.4 maybe six if
you're you know been working on for a
while
um but out there was 8.4 it was because
they had super high
sodium and magnesium which has a big
influence on ph
and the solution to their many of their
issues which we'll get to a minute was
adding calcium they literally added
basically limestone
and their ph went down
this is totally count counter to the
sort of accepted
uh truth about lyme and ph normally
you have low ph you add mind with ph
goes up
well that's only if uh
you need the um if you're deficient
in in these in these catalysts if you're
excessive
in anything but calcium you can actually
see the ph go
down when you enlarge them so there's a
lot of nuances here about things
that are like half truths that get just
sort of repeated because it's simple
and i'm going to try to explain them in
enough detail that you understand it
without current confusion so
uh anyway so then
one last caveat to this is that this
ideal balance
this ideal count imbalance is subject
to change a little bit based on your
exchange capacity
you have low exchange capacity you have
to modify these numbers a little bit if
you have super high
uh you have to modify them a little bit
but by and large that's
that's a good target
all right and so um
these are what these are our recommended
values
for the elements of soil tests and this
is a logan lab soil test
and i want you to be very clear if
you're taking notes
that this is based on a logan labs base
saturation
test any other lab any other type of
soil test
you cannot use these numbers
very clear here if you apply these
numbers to other people's tests
you likely will screw things up because
they don't
all test the same way um it is not that
they test something that it's uh it's
not wrong it's not bad
it's that this cannot apply in the same
way
the best thing to do is ask your lab
what they recommend
um mandy lab will be happy to do so
my only issue is that many labs do not
even look at half of these things
and that's a problem for me um
but that being said people after using
labs that do different methods they get
good results
uh i'm not saying my way is the only way
or even remotely the best way
but it does work and i don't work so
this is this is on the website this uh
here's the
link to it tiny dot cc slash mineral
targets
if you don't want to scribble it down it
is also on your handout
again menu doesn't have a handout um
grab one we're gonna get to that
on the far left side of the handout is
a quick dirty version of this
all right
all right all right so
we're going to jump into the soil the
soil tests
um on the sheet on the handout you've
got three different sort of tests
representing some variation
that i was able to pull together to show
some uh interesting things
to should be aware of and make some
points
and every time i look at soil tests um
the first thing you always want to look
at is your tc numbers
so at the toward the top about the third
line down you've got tc
for the vegetable garden sample it's
10.29
and if you remember i was mentioning
that that's a really important number
that's important because it is what
tells you how much nutrients your soil
can hold
which then also tells you if you have to
modify that
that ideal cation balance that we were
talking about
and so when you have a tc above about an
eight it means you can hold
theoretically
enough nutrients in an extractable form
for an entire year growing season for an
annual crop
generally speaking if you're below a tc
of eight
it will mean that organic matter becomes
more important for you
because you are able to hold fewer
minerals on your
clay colloid
and so that's something to keep in mind
so
organic matter is always great you
always want to work on that the best way
to get good organic matter
is to grow healthy crops we'll talk
about that
later in terms of the chicken and the
egg problem of
growing healthy crops when you don't
already have healthy soil but um
for now what you need to know is that if
you're above eight
you're pretty good if you're above 10
you're definitely pretty solid in terms
of being able to hold your nutrients
and that gets important when you start
talking about the back we're
going to skip down here a little bit the
most important thing after tc
is looking at the base saturation
percent numbers which is in the middle
gray area of your soil test
and there you can see numbers on that
first one 59
and 32 and this is where you want to pay
attention to
the recommended base saturation percent
numbers
so basically for base saturation
of calcium you're looking for 60 to 68
percent
magnesium is 12 to 20 potassium's three
to six
sodium is point five to three and so if
you look at that first one you've got
59 calcium 32 magnesium 3
potassium 1 a little bit more of sodium
so right away this is
basically how i assess soil
testing services laboratories uh if they
claim to do this type of soil test
where they're actually interested in
base
base saturation cation balancing and
they don't
they either don't give you this
percentage or the percentages don't make
sense when you actually look at the
field and you know something's up
but in this particular case you've got
low calcium and high magnesium
and what that does in soils is it makes
the
clay particles stick together more
closely it
makes your soil
slimy and kind of smear
and this this is a 10.29 this particular
was not high in clay necessarily but
they described it as heavy placed oil
this is one of those little triggers
every time someone describes your soil
as have you played soil
i say what's your base saturation
magnesium and
nine plus times out of ten it is higher
than it's supposed to be
usually by a lot and this is one example
of that
being true so the magnesium acts to
actually
stick the soil together more tightly and
what that does is it makes act like clay
uh or what we think of this cloud it
reduces the porous
pore spaces where there's oxygen where
there's air it reduces the
rate of influx of water
basically it causes an awful lot of it
causes compaction or it causes
recompaction very quickly and it causes
it actually traps minerals so when you
have high magnesium
you can actually get potassium gets
trapped in the layers of clay
and even though it may show up on your
soil test
when your plants really need it it may
not be available to them
in the amount that you think you might
have so in this particular case
this garden was exhibiting uh it had uh
prone to root diseases it had poor uh
soil soil flocculation so like it wasn't
really crumbly like you've ever seen
really nice crumbly soil
um that's a well flocculated soil you
can get that a lot easier if you have a
good calcium magnesium balance they
didn't have that here
they had potassium deficiency symptoms
far excess of one of three
might indicate normally on a soil test
uh and that was because the magnesium
was blocking uptake of potassium
and if you read i didn't mention it
before but there are several really good
books i recommend on this
one is um the ideal soil by michael
astaire that's probably the easiest one
to digest as a beginner and then there's
sort of the
bible for this which would be in my mind
neil kinsey's
neil kinsey's book hands-on agronomy and
in that book he goes through a whole
slew of examples of many examples
of of all the different interactions
between these elements so what
i just mentioned one high magnesium ties
up potassium
that's one example uh another one behind
nitrogen ties up potassium
uh high phosphorus times up zinc
hydrogen phosphorus
these are things that are in um hands-on
agronomy that
really are really valuable when you're
trying to understand your soil system
and so when you have when you're looking
at soils that's the first thing you want
to look for is you go down through
you highlight anything that's deficient
and he's below your target
highlight preferably a different color
anything that's excessive so above your
target
and that's where you really want to
focus your effort and try to
tease out what the things are that you
need to work on
and so cation base saturation
percents that's the that's the first
place you look if you have a big
imbalance between magnesium
calcium potassium and sodium that's has
a huge impact
the nice thing is it's one of the
easiest things to fix so say you're
low in calcium you need usually a high
calcium limestone
or gypsum if you're excessive in
something like
magnesium gypsum is often best because
gypsum helps to
break up that the bond between the
magnesium and the
soil colloids split that magnesium off
uh and replace it with the calcium so
gypsum is good when you have excess
of something other than calcium um
and so those are the first places to
look there the other thing
um at the far right side is this test
called salem
and this is something that most people
in new england i don't think
have seen where you have excessive
calcium i've seen it sometimes when
people are
adding compost that they add a lot of
egg shells to a lot of limestone too
and in that particular case you can also
have the same kind of problem you have
uh you decrease potassium availability
so
you need to try to get it within the
targets you try to um
try to address the
deficiencies by adding things and then
with the excesses that's a little bit
trickier and i'll talk about that in
just a few minutes i want to get to the
back to the
the top of the sheet i'm just going to
run through how i do it
uh when i'm looking at these so you've
identified your
your deficiencies you looked at your
excesses so
looking at sulfur this is one that is
almost always
deficient unless you've been adding lots
of sulfur for many years or you live
in some place uh that has sulfur vines
which is
as far as i don't know where east of the
mississippi river um so this one's 14
parts per million
sulfur the target is 75 parts per
million
sulfur and so here we go to some math
and i forgot to warn people there would
be a little bit of math
um so you take 75
you or in well let me back up
when you're really low you don't want to
do everything at once
that's an important thing that i haven't
mentioned um
often times so a lot of the arguments
against using minerals
is that they kill soil life but they can
actually negatively impact the biology
and to some degree that's definitely
true everything you do every step you
take in a field
every element you add does kill soil but
it also creates conditions where other
life can live
and potentially increase the diversity
and how healthy that life is
so in the case of sulfur if you're like
a 14 in this case or
20 i like to target 50 parts per million
that's the beginning of good
75 would be considered sort of excellent
so if you're targeting 50 you take
the 14 parts per million you subtract
your take 50 subtract 14. so you need 36
parts per million sulfur and
to get to from part per million to
pounds per acre you multiply by two
so you have 36 you multiply that by two
you have 72
and then you have to divide that by the
amount of sulfur in the material you're
at
and here's another point where people
get very confused
i think that's 50 minus 14
i've been here so the fifth sorry yes
the 50
yes that's because i wrote 75 and i
didn't write 50.
50 is the minimum target 75
is the ideal target it is not on there
because
i screwed up
is the minimum target like for good and
75 is ideal
um and so then once you get once you
figure out you're taking your
your target you subtract what you have
so
15 minus 14. you get 36
you multiply it by 2 to get pounds per
acre
so you get 72 and then you divide that
by in 0.9 or whatever the
composition of the material you have is
so if you're using elemental sulfur
which is my preferred method of adding
sulfur and i'll tell you why in a minute
it's 90 sulfur so 90 0.9
so you take the 72 that you got before
and you divide it by
0.9 and you get
let me write this down somewhere in the
neighborhood of 80-ish
pounds of elemental sulfur so you need
to add 80 pounds
elemental sulfur to get you from 14 to
50.
and that's in a perfect world we do not
live in one of those so you'll add that
and you will not get to 50 you will get
to something else
usually with sulfur there is such a need
for it in the systems
that you will put 50 down or you'll put
you know 80 pounds down
should be enough to get to 50 but you
won't get there you'll come up somewhere
short
um don't fret about that the sulfur
didn't just go away what it probably did
is went to fixing some other aspect of
your soil system so
when you have an excess light in excess
of magnesium like in the soil
um some of that sulfur is going to go to
fixing the excess
so when you add when you have an excess
of a cation
sulfur helps to get rid of that excess
it helps to strip
that element off the soil colloid and
make it
and flush it out of the system making
space for other things
so a lot of that sulfur is going to go
to that and so
i would always i would round up to about
100 pounds of sulfur on this
instead of the 80 and that will give you
a little bit more but
honestly this soil will take probably
three years of adding that to get enough
sulfur
the sulfur doesn't go where you think
it's going to yeah
yeah so there's basically a big
sulphur sink in your soil it's going
into the it's going
to attach itself to the magnesium that's
excessive
to help remove it from the system
because in reality
the idea of soil balance isn't just
ideal because we think it works
the best it actually the soil almost
seems to want to
approach that balance on its own so when
we actually have a sulfur
the soil system it's not necessarily
intelligent but it uh
certainly acts that way it'll the sulfur
will attach to the most excessive
cation and it will remove it from the
soil the clay
which will make the space you need for
the things that are deficient
so it'll make the space you need for the
calcium or the potassium or whatever
and the magnesium will flush out to the
soil and
um and you'll lose it that way
basically it'll still be there available
to plants as a fertilizer element and
sulfur is extremely
vital to plant health and human health
but you won't show up on the soil test
until
you've addressed until it has basically
worked on all of those excesses
so it um it's one of those things that
triggers i get a lot so many calls about
sulfur it's
crazy the other piece about sulfur
is people don't don't understand this
but
um sulfate is not the same as sulfur
sulfate is an oxidized sulfur and
when it is in sulfate form it is a
water-soluble form of sulfur
and it does not act the same it will
quickly leach out of your system
it doesn't really build sulfur on your
soil test it will help
feed a crop sulfur and but it will not
stick around sulfur to
be transferred from sulfur to a plant
available water soluble form takes
something like 56
biological sort of steps and processes
biochemical steps
and so each one of those there's things
in the soil that will grab a hold of it
there's bacteria that will chelate it
which means bind it up into organic
compounds and it will
help to keep it around a lot longer so a
lot of people like i don't want to use
elements of sulfur it's super acidic it
kills microbes sure yeah it does
every microbe within maybe a quarter
inch of each little pellet is probably
going to be dead
but when you actually spread 100 pounds
of sulfur over an
acre of ground i do everything by the
acre that's how my
mind works but when you do that you put
100 pounds per acre
the pellets are about maybe this far
apart and
they're only going to impact the biology
in that little quarter inch
around it you've got six inches or more
of soil below it so you're killing yes
you're killing microbes but you're
killing microbes on a tiny fraction of
your total soil
and you're adding the things that are
holding back your system and functioning
better
the things that are holding your system
back from more efficiently building soil
uh in a lot of cases sulfur is one of
the top ones
and until you can address it you're not
working as efficiently as you can
so can i ask you another question sure
certainly uh all right so this first
quick one is the 72 times 0.9 you're
saying
why is it
and um is there a
chart that shows kind of like a standard
uh
let's say like elemental sulfur it's 90
percent
they are online i can quickly i could
also i can give a list
maybe remind me at the end and if we
still have time i'll give you a list
verbally and
they are available even google them is a
good way to
search online also keep in mind that
every material you might buy
may be a different number so always
check the bag
or the source of what you're using you
can get a lot of trouble doing that with
trace elements especially if you're
assuming it's
five percent but it's actually 39 that's
a molybdenum example
for instance um you always check the bag
of music
is there one more another question back
there yeah can you explain the why
as far as these targets go but it only
works in the local lab versus
yes thanks for bringing that up and um
so loganlab does this very specific test
basically what they're looking at when
they give you a base center
is that they're looking for extractable
minerals
they're not looking for water soluble
and they're not looking at total
elemental
so our total elements will be like
everything that's in your soil like a
geological assessment every element
um and water soluble is what it sounds
like it's the water soluble nutrients in
solution
um that you can get out of your soil
their test is an
extractable so it assumes that you have
some biology it assumes you have
a system that's working together they
use different
acids basically to break some things
apart so
the number will be higher and water
soluble but less than the total
elemental
and every lab does that test a little
differently and
the reason we can't apply the same
numbers is because
many labs over the years have to cut
costs and save time etc
have changed how they do that
many of the labs don't necessarily know
how to use these numbers the way that
i'm trying to teach
people to use them and so that they have
made
they've changed how they do it and the
numbers don't work out
the same anymore and that's why i also
say it's not that this is the right way
this is the way i know how to make it
work
and um
and i guarantee you the numbers that you
get on a load and lab test
are wrong in the sense that your plant
doesn't necessarily see
exactly these numbers but that's not
really the point because the point is
that
when you when these numbers are
approximately where they're supposed to
be
the whole system actually does work
better and it works better because
of the how calcium magnesium work
together to change the structure the
physical structure
the amount of air and water in your soil
the relative amounts of some of these
things are really important to
which species of microbes are living or
not in your soil
and so that's why there's these general
recommendations they're not hard to fast
rules i don't want anyone to
leave here thinking that they need to
like farm to a
soil test it's a good way to throw money
away
um but they are a good place to start
and so if you have major imbalances like
what some of these are on the soil test
those major imbalances are going to
point you in a direction it's going to
be helpful for you to make decisions
um sometimes
you'll see something that's out of whack
in your soil tests but you
won't actually do anything about it you
know i have high phosphorus here
all right so the biggest thing you want
to look for when you have high
phosphorus
is where's my zinc because those are
that's a really tightly correlated
um nutrient system there so when you
high phosphorus
it ties up zinc and when your eyes dig
it ties up phosphorus so when you apply
phosphorus you want to make sure you
also have um
towards the higher end of sink so if you
look at
look down there zinc the recommendation
is eight plus
and it's eight plus because when
phosphorus is much higher than it's
supposed to be as it is in this case
you actually need to double or maybe
even a little more
in your level of zinc to make sure that
you can maintain zinc availability
um so that's like that's how this works
and why
when you cut your corners and you make
it a little cheaper you make or you just
change it because you think it's a
better way of doing it so
it no longer the ratios no longer work
the relationships no longer work
so that's a key point there
[Applause]
are you familiar with working with any
other lab reports like csi
so not particularly i've seen many of
them
um i've worked with some of them i've
talked to some of the people there
i mean there are good
consultants and around us getting
results with a lot of different sort of
claps
and so i'm just teaching you what you
can do on your this so one reason we
like logan is it's not there
not very expensive and you don't have to
work with a consultant to use it so you
can
take serial tests yourself send them
there and get your results and then we
try to teach you
how to interpret them yourself many
other labs you have to actually work
with a consultant in order to even
access the lab
so we're trying to we're trying to
basically give you the tools to do it
yourself
and so that's a big reason why we've
done that
i have an issue when i'm doing
calculations
because i'm working with a lot of very
small spaces they're not any cars
right they're um you know hundreds of
square feet right
and i get really prolifed up in terms of
where the decimal place
is going when yeah so
so i'll just tell so when i look at it i
think in terms of
in acres um
a lot of them i like to start with acres
even if i'm
doing a thousand square feet i start i
can make all the recommendations
in terms of acres and i divide by 43
and that gets you thousands per thousand
square feet and if you need to go
smaller than that it's pretty easy to
just
lock off a decimal point or and uh to
get a hundred square feet so that's how
i
do it do it in acres divide by forty
three
thousand square feet and that is usually
where people like to
like to end up and then when you start
really dividing it you're starting to
talk about tiny amounts and
we can talk about that later if we have
time about how you actually apply
a half an ounce of something yeah yeah
yeah
um how do you go about correcting this
um phosphorus
yeah yeah so um the first thing i want
to point out on phosphorus is that you
may
notice that the numbers are different
between these two
recommendations um and this is really
another important point that i
kind of left it confusing like this for
a reason is to draw your attention to it
remind you of this
these are in parts per million
if you look at this sheet you'll see
that it's in pounds per acre
it's my one biggest pet peeve with logan
labs
is that sometimes you get your results
and parts familiar and sometimes you get
a passport
and if you don't notice that you can
kind of screw up your map a little bit
so just i want to point that out
it's a good opportunity to do that this
particular one your phosphorus on here
is in pounds per acre so that's why
there's the discrepancy
um what that means in reality is that
while it says you have 2427 on here
thousand it's actually and thirteen or
fourteen
um based on parts per minute but it's
still high
obviously yeah um so there's a couple
things
um phosphorus is often high it's often
low
because there's a huge range in
available phosphorus
um i constantly see people who've added
a ton of compost over the years
who have astronomically high phosphorus
levels
and there's not anything like specific
you can do
to address that not necessarily even a
problem
if you can bring everything else up to
an ideal level
if you've got good phosphorus that's
actually an expensive thing to fix when
you're deficient
so count yourself it's somewhat of a
blessing but you do have to
keep it in mind and work extra hard to
bring everything else up because
um because if you have high phosphorus
and you're deficient other things
that makes the high phosphorus worse
it doesn't does if that makes sense the
other thing is sometimes
um the phosphor is a good example you
can have
other things that will tie it up so
phosphorus and calcium
uh tend to get along so well that they
don't like to
ever split apart again and so when you
apply phosphorus adding
adding calcium sometimes you'll add a
lot of calcium you think you're going to
get your calcium where it needs to be
and it just won't show up but slowly
your phosphorus will come down
and that's because phosphorus and
calcium like to tie up in the mineral
called
it's a appetite apatite rock it it
basically turns back into a hard rock
and both of them become unavailable
so one approach if you've got super high
phosphorus is to add
um keep your calcium high keep your
calcium
available and it will slowly tie up some
of that phosphorus
so that's one way to do that but again
really just
making sure when you have an excess in
in phosphorus
and many other ones bring everything
else up to
the target that's the first thing to
focus on um
so hopefully that helps to answer that
question
find your you have 150 prosperous
up there you have 75
right and that's the whole that's what i
was talking about with that's in parts
per million
and this one is in pounds per acre so
the 150 right here over in that column
right that's pounds per acre
so that's the important consideration
that first of all the math to go from
one to the other is you multiply your
parts per million times two
and that gets two pounds per acre that's
because they assume that an
acre of soil the top six inches of an
acre soil weighs two million pounds
so if you want to like your math to make
sure that these numbers make sense
that's where it comes from
um so yeah um and the phosphorus
in the loading lab is about just p205
exactly yes i'm glad you mentioned that
so um
when when agronomists farmers
fertilizer sales people talk about
phosphorus they're usually
basically always actually talking about
phosphate
phosphate is what um they're actually
measuring what they're actually
concerned about
so it's not actually elemental
phosphorus that they're looking at but
it's phosphate
um and it's you'll see that also when
you start talking to people about
potassium they often say
potash potash would be um
it's not actually potassium itself so
that that's something to keep in mind
the definitions in terms of an
agriculture versus actual chemistry if
there's chemists in the room
or if there's chemicals who become
farmers they're constantly frustrated by
the fact that agriculture doesn't use
the real the right words
in quite a few examples so that's one of
them phosphorus
um all right but the so that
75 ppm is for
phosphate it's for phosphate and even
though many labs were reported as
phosphorus
i don't know if any of that are
measuring it as anything other than
phosphate
um all right so
let's see where do i want to go next um
all right so there's so many nuances so
this is another thing i want
i want to mention um
there's a lot of a lot of times when
what people get messed up and why they
really can't understand soil test
results why they get frustrated that
it doesn't make any sense is when they
do something and then it doesn't
behave like they expect it to and often
that's because
there's the interrelationships between
these elements is what screws them up
so in the case of this is a good example
a lot of people have this problem they
have low potassium
and maybe they have high magnesium like
this first example their ph is above
seven
and when your ph is above seven things
don't exactly work
the same as if they're lower than seven
so
one of the things that happens is that
the soil when it has
when the pitch is above seven there's
not much room
on that on that box on the soil box we
look here
it's full in fact not only is it full
but it's kind of got extra stuff
floating around it's not really attached
but it's sort of attached
and so there's no room there so if you
want to add something like calcium
the calcium is just going to like come
in here and be like well there's no
place for me to go
and that's why what i was mentioning
before sulfur is important the sulfur
helps to
like say this in our example on the
sheet helps to cut this bond with
magnesium
making room for calcium and the same
thing happens with potassium so if you
in this soil your ph is above seven
there's no room
to add potassium to this and so until
you can get
calcium and sulfur and to start
splitting off your excesses
you're wasting money if you add any more
potassium basically than what your
plants need that year so in this
particular example
you um there's a deficit if you look at
the exchangeable cations potassium
growth guesses are 75 pounds per acre of
potassium
and that's how much you need to bring
your soil test result to four percent
but there's no room for 75 pounds of
potassium on here
and so what you would want to do is
actually
trickle feed your crop to make sure the
crop has enough potassium
until you can fix your imbalances here
get rid of the excess magnesium make
space here
for the potassium otherwise you're
literally just throwing money away
because the potassium is going to go
it's going to float up here so my god
it's full i'm gonna go over here
and it's gonna go down the stream into
rivers it's going to
um not not stick to your solar power
um furthermore and this is where we're
gonna start to talk about what lane you
who i think told a lot of you
is that it's ridiculous to add minerals
because there's tons already there
and potassium is a great example there's
40 000 pounds
of potassium on average in every
acre of topsoil and that's just actually
the top six inches of topsoil forty
thousand minutes
and so it's a little bit ludicrous that
we ever think to add potassium
ever because there's tons there um
but having it there and having to build
plants of incredibly different things
and it is true that biology will make
things available if you have excellent
excellent biology
but the fact of that is it's really hard
to good biology if you don't have good
plants because then
what's feeding the biology and it's
really hard of good plants if you don't
have any potassium
so that's why when i say on an example
like this where you have borderline
deficient potassium your magnesium is
really high
so it's going to block the availability
of some of that potassium
if you're not adding some potassium that
you're going to have a really hard time
to keep plants healthy enough to be
putting carbon into the soil and feeding
the microbes
that are then going to unlock more
potassium for you so by adding a little
bit
you can potentially unlock a lot and so
that's a key
part of all of this to keep in mind
like i said earlier we're not trying to
get a perfect soil test
we're trying to build soil and one of
the ways to do that is to make the metal
test
a little better try to tweak it as best
we can so that we can unlock the
conditions for the biology to do the
rest of the work for us
um so that's gonna make that point um
now i wanna talk a little bit about
trace elements before
i open up your questions um trace
elements are something that
people get stuck on they can be very
difficult to
understand like how to get the materials
out there um
we're dealing with tiny amounts uh in
general
and um but
a couple there's a couple things that
are pretty universal
unless you're from the rocky mountains
or points
west you are unlikely to have enough
boron in your soil
it's just a fact of geology
if you have really really really good
biology you're going to find maybe be
able to
get enough for healthy plant growth but
to add the maximum yearly application of
boron costs seven dollars an acre
boron is extremely important for moving
elements up and down in plants and when
plants can't move elements up and down
it means that they run out of things
when they're growing quickly
which is invites disease which limits
photosynthetic efficiency
and limits the amount of carbon they're
able to put in the soil to feed the
microbes in the soil
and so if you don't address these things
when you have a deficiency in boron
and you're just going to assume it's in
your sword and hope for the best
you're not going to get the best you're
never going to get the best
um and so while you may not have to get
more and all the way to two or three
parts per million in the target i would
argue that
your mid
you're not well served to not add any
and um
and anyway so yeah i just wanna
you should add some boron if you're
deficient in warm like
hands down i'll make that categorical
statement um
you may not need to add all of it but
it's yeah it's cheap
um so to understand how much more you
can add
every one of these things has a maximum
yearly application rate
every element borons is low so you only
have two pounds of actual form per acre
and if you're using a 10 boron that
would come through
20 pounds of product if you're using a
20 boron it's 10 pounds of product per
acre
so giant small amounts those small
amounts make a tremendous impact
which is also crazy when you think about
it because 10 pounds spread over an acre
is not very much stuff
um but that's how you look at that
um i don't we'll see if we get time to
go over the elements of where you get
these things but
um that's what you need to do for the
whole question
right so whether you need to or whether
you're just going to blend it into
something that
isn't going to be isn't going to hurt
you or it might be beneficial for other
reasons so compost is a great one
and after compost you can add it to um
leaf mulch there's lots of ways if
you're doing it
diluted water you can dissolve it you
can spray it on
um i generally my recommendations are to
use granular whenever possible
by my my way of working it's a lot
easier
you can mix it with other granules you
can spread them out easily
the granular stuff generally is a slower
release so you're less risk of burning
plants when you use water-soluble things
you you really need to cut the rate of
application so i said two pounds of bond
per acre
per year but if you're using soluble and
you put all two pounds at once
you're liable to burn things like borax
right
yeah borax is one of those things that's
not as soluble as soluble
but it's soluble enough right and um if
you applied it all at once so if you
applied all 15 pounds or so borax at
once
then you could burn things um
and so what you'd want to do is divide
it into multiple smaller applications
maybe divided at least by three or four
and apply those as your liquids
but it's not hard to add it to compost
in fact i like to when i'm making my
compost piles and things
add these minerals to it so if i take a
soil test i'm building compost the
compost is eventually going to add up on
that soil
i add the elements to the compost that
my soil needs
and it helps to digest them gets them
chelated in with organic compounds
and that's really important because many
of these things are
can be harsh on soil life um and so the
more
carbon that you can put out when you put
them out it'll buffers that effect
so you kill less microbes and it doesn't
have the harsh effects that
people worry about so um but
basically so i've talked a little bit
about how to do the sulfur math
uh in terms of you take your target you
take how much you
want uh to take your target take where
you are now
and then do the math in terms of parts
and millions of pounds per acre
and then you figure it out if you
actually do that math on most of the
trace elements so
you have 80 to 90 part parts per million
target say on manganese you have 31
you get 60 let's say um parts per
million deficient
multiplied by two to get pounds you get
120 pounds of manganese
if you did all that at once you would
burn everything and give everything
manganese toxicity so and all the trace
elements especially have to
take into consideration maximum yield
application rates
those are on the resource on the
resource page earlier
i pointed to a um
um here it is so at these minerals on
this page
i need signing fcc literal targets has
the maximum yearly application rates
very important for the trace elements so
when you're doing your math
have that sheet from you to make sure
that you don't do anything you're not
supposed to yeah
yeah so the question is about
time of year when you should have
different minerals
the general rule is you should add them
yesterday if you need them
but there are some things that are
better to do in the spring than some
better in the fall if it's a
water-soluble element you need to feed a
crop so
in this example that i used before you
have a potassium
potential potassium deficiency issue
that you might come up on that first one
if you're trying to grow tomatoes or
something there especially
if you do in the fall you're going to
lose some bleaching over winter
essentially so you might want to do that
one in the spring or
during the growing season if you're
adding limestone
uh you want to have that the winter time
helps to break it down
so anytime you're adding rock dust rock
powder type of
material uh fall is a really good time
to use that winter
rest period um when it helps to unlock
those the compounds from those materials
um and then anything that's
leachable water soluble is best in the
spring when you have
a lot of biological activity that can
chelate it or bind it up into organic
molecules so it doesn't
run away uh and leave your leave your
farm
so that would be like boron phosphates
sulfates would be a springtime thing
sulfur
limestone azomite some of the rock
powers would be
fall everything else is sort of in the
gray area you can do either one
but those are the general rules
is that information um
no but i'll simplify so i'll simplify
i'll say it again um
rock dust that dump that are not
water soluble plant foods some limestone
sulfur that requires biological process
to break down
things like that are best in the fall
but you can do it in the spring but
they're best to say in the fall and
anything is water soluble so those would
be the things that are commonly thought
of as fertilizers
so potassium sulfate kmag or sulfur mag
any of the phosphate the the sulfate
fertilizer any of them really
they're going to leach more readily so
you want to apply them in the spring
when you have a lot of biological
activity
to tie them up to make sure they don't
run away
yeah can you like say for salt for
sulphur can you just throw it on your
soil or is it
so uh you do not have to incorporate
uh i certain if you're like if you're
chilling just to incorporate minerals
um i highly recommend you not do that uh
if you are going to till
anyway then it's nice to put the
minerals down first because it is better
to
incorporate them but if you have healthy
soil life they'll bring your they'll
bring those minerals where they need to
go
quite quickly so yeah it's not necessary
for sure
how about if you have like a lot of
organic matter yeah so if you have
organic matter you can put it right on
top if your organic matter
is something like um if it's something
like leaves
that where it might sort of concentrate
some of those things so if you
it hits the leaf and then it rolls and
it all goes to one place where you're
gonna
overdo the soil on a certain mineral
then sometimes
that's less than ideal um but most
things you can put right on top without
wearing so
just kind of look at how it if you're
spreading it by hand or whatever
look at an area see how much it's
concentrating in your particular
type of mulch and see if you think it's
going to be a problem and if it is you
can always just put half as much down
and then do the other half in the spring
or at a later time
um to make sure you don't overdo it at
one time
would you say azerite in the fall i
would but i
like his i mean if i'm going to use i
might use a little bit involved a little
bit again in the spring i actually
really like to do that when i can if
it's not adding a lot of extra work
i do want to also mention that all of
the recommendations on the website
they are in terms of granular materials
i really want to stress this
if you're using water soluble you want
to reduce your application rate
it's an important piece
all right so i didn't get through nearly
as much as i wanted to
um there's so much to this
it is it is overwhelming um but i do
want to just
mention again the the thing you want to
focus on is you look
for the weakest link in your particular
soil so that's where you want to focus
don't get super into getting the soil
test perfect
um soil tests have a tendency of
humbling you quite quickly
you think you're doing everything
perfect you take your next soil test
and it's it's like what the heck just
happened
um it happens all the time generally
there is an explanation for it
uh but it can be frustrating um when you
don't understand that explanation
but generally speaking if it doesn't
look like what you expected it to
just do the whole exercise again what is
now the weakest link and focus on that
um some things that get people tripped
up as they put line down the next year
they test
and they don't see anything improved and
because they don't realize life takes
three years to break down so if it takes
three years and you're testing more
frequently than that
it's quite likely you're gonna see um
nothing
or a very reduced influence of that and
so
um keep in mind what you've applied in
the past
and if you use your intuition to
somebody make sure you're thinking about
that and don't overdo it so if you're
testing every year and you're adding and
you needed limestone and you had
limestone last year don't
add the same amount of lime again
because you're probably gonna
likely be overdoing a lot when all that
becomes available in three years
you will have a new problem you've
created so um
take a slow and steady approach to it
remember that we're not actually trying
to get a perfect soil test we're just
trying to
influence the soil structure and the
biology in the system as a whole
and and here's where i mean so
the biology trumps all this stuff every
time
i mean if you had perfect soil biology
like you could shred this and never look
at it doesn't matter it doesn't matter
at all
um the key though is that i've not ever
seen an example of
really healthy um and i mean like
perfectly efficient like super massively
efficient systems where biology is
working really well
where the underlying soil chemistry was
really screwed up i've never seen it
maybe other people have but i would
argue that even in that system you think
it's
functioning really well in biology alone
add the minerals and see if it does even
better
because everything i've ever seen when
you
work with the whole system holistically
look to try to figure out exactly all
the places you can
influence it it always works better than
just looking at one thing at a time so
that's
that's a key thing i want to stress
yeah so i'd like to open up the question
because i don't have time to go to the
next
section of material um there's a lot of
material in these slides at the end
i talk about what i have in here every
element
what it does for plants how it works in
soil just a really quick little slide on
each one
because then that that helps so if you
understand what it's doing
then it can help you can help to figure
out what your plants might be
lacking what your soil might prove um so
take a look at the slides
from the website well they'd be on the
website they will be on the website
yes and hopefully soon and
there's more slides in here this uh
mentioned something real quick
so when you have uh imbalances you often
will see
them show up in different ways and so
sometimes you'll see
um you can find potassium deficiencies
by looking at the leaves you can see
calcium efficiency looking at the plants
and so you can actually figure out a lot
of what you might need
based on just looking at your field of
getting good at observing
differences in changes in your plants um
and sometimes you'll have plenty of say
potassium control tests but
you've got plants that look an act just
like potassium deficient plants
you see it actually all the time
generally it'll it should
tell you there's something else going on
maybe your irrigation system is not
working right
there's not enough water or there's some
other issue that
what happens all the time and just real
quick does anyone know
um does anyone know what causes this
calcium calcium there you go so if you
have
calcium getting your plant attitude
amounts you will never see this
ever um what is what is that what caused
this one
does anyone know is that what your
tomatoes look like
um that is potassium efficiency it's a
pretty classic potassium
deficiency if you don't have enough
potassium getting your plants you don't
get uh even ripening and you may not
even have examples where you can get no
ripening at all and it's really bad
uh and what about this one does anyone
recognize this first so this one's
commonly uh uh this is commonly called
early blight
some people may have had it on their
plants in the past
and this and this are caused by the
exact same thing
if you have adequate potassium in your
plants you will not get early blood
your plants will die from frost at the
end of the year
with green leaves always from the ground
all the way to the top so
um these things you know so if you're
seeing these things you have a
sign of so underlying problems
uh i would argue that there are a number
of ways of addressing them
uh the psa likes to talk about the soil
the minerals the biology
one thing that i have found extremely
helpful is
liquids foliar sprays inoculants
these things are by my way thinking like
cheating if you go out when you spray
really good foliar amendments uh plant
shore from agridynamics foley 8k
uh people out there talking we have them
in the mineral depot
you spray those once a week tiny amounts
like tiny tiny amounts
off in the grand steaming land they can
keep you from having any of these
problems they keep your plants healthier
and then what i have seen is one of the
best ways to build biology in your soil
is you use the foliar sprays you
inoculate
and what happens is your plants stay at
you know one percent more efficient or
so at
say photosynthesizing um than the sun
that one percent
say they're they need this much and they
sprung synthesize and they're
photosynthesizing this much so they're
putting this much into the soil
and you're able to increase it one
percent more of that one percent
increase is going to go into the soil um
so little tiny influences on
photosynthetic efficiency
can quickly double triple et cetera the
amount of
carbon that your plant can put into the
soil because it's creating now
excess energy and that is what feeds
soil life that's what builds biology
builds
uh healthy biologically active soils
and so anything you can do in my book
anything you can do to keep plants a
little bit healthier whether that's soil
minerals whether that's foliars or
anything else it's going to
um improve the biological function in
that system so
that's the last thing i wanted to stress
i think
and so i will stay as long as people
want to stay and ask
can you questions about aluminum a
little bit aluminum yeah it's always on
this oil it's always not sort of this
yeah
so aluminum is always on uh at least
logan left soil tests and many others
uh the recommendations for aluminum i
don't know where they come from
they i have to see 200 250 parts per
million
i almost never maximum with 250.
i almost never see one in range so i
basically disregard the recommended
range because
as with literally all of these elements
the
target amounts are basically just our
best guess
and aluminum is one of those things that
um our best guess just
isn't that good so i don't worry too
much
basically aluminum is a problem where
you get toxic aluminum toxicity
the main issue there um aluminum is
everywhere
it's the foundation of clay uh play is
aluminum silica so it's in every like
clay molecule
and so it's everywhere and the only
issue is when it becomes
toxic the only way it becomes toxic is
if you're
massively deficient in in your soil and
other
areas so that the plant is trying so
desperately to get the nutrients it
needs
that it's making extremely harsh acids
dissolving
aluminum and sucking a little bit of the
plant and causing a little toxicity
so if you have balanced soil if you are
if you're even anywhere close on your
soil test
i've never seen aluminum toxicity the
only place i've seen it is where you
have
people going blueberries where they've
been told the only way to grow good
blueberries is to lower your ph
which by the way is not painful to
blueberries or anyone wants to know
um and then they push it so low they
make it so imbalanced that aluminum
toxicity
so um i don't really worry about it
unless i'm working with a blueberry
farmer
is there a visible sign or something
there is
i don't know off the top of my head i
would google that there's a lot of
resources
online um i mentioned in one of these
slides this one i believe for
looking at nutrient impacts on
plants so how you scout for nutrient
deficiency or excess
is that related to arsenic
yeah i mean it's just a similar thing
applies
so people are really worried about heavy
metals metal toxicity in the soil
lead uptake by plants my understanding
is most like
heavy metal issues with produce is
from physically splashing lead
contaminated soil on your
feet and very little is picked up by the
plants
but everything i've read suggests that
if you're if your soil
balance the more balance your soil the
less of those heavy metals are actually
brought up into your plant tissue
and also the more biology you have the
more of that gets chelated in such a way
that
that's not a problem yeah
um
[Music]
yeah so um well first of all i recommend
testing soil about every two years
every other year testing or even every
three depending
so that's the first thing uh and then
uh so where what other that was
[Music]
right
it's a different focus perhaps yes but
i'd say they're complementary they're
not
mutually exclusive um i think that
i don't i try not to get very dogmatic
about this and it kind of bothers me
when others do
um because uh we don't
it's not helpful to be dogmatic about
this so
no but no but plenty of people do and
i just want to uh it's
yeah basically um
if you're thinking about it holistically
you're trying to make improvements
um
did you approach that field also
improving the microbial
yeah okay yes absolutely so if you look
at
no no so this is what i've been saying
so just doing the middle approach does
is not the best way to do it if you're
if you need biology and minerals
you do both um so this field we could
not have gotten this in three years with
minerals alone
and i would argue i don't know anyone to
do with biology alone either now if
someone can please talk to me
um but people were trying to fix these
fields with biology alone and people
were trying to fix it with
minerals alone and no one had as much
successes when they put it together so
this field got
the minerals it needed so it got
um so this field in particular it had it
was like a tc
exchange capacity like 80 plus so it's
like pure clay if people know that uh
the sodium
percent was 30. the magnesium was 30
and the calcium was 25 and so like
look here they have to totally screw up
soil and that's why nothing literally
nothing would grow
and we probably could have added biology
alone to that but you add biology along
with that with something where you can't
even get weeds to grow
the body just dies there's nothing to
feed it
so what we did was we we broke every
rule of the book
we applied like 2 000 pounds of
elemental sulfur
we applied 10 tons per acre of gypsum
by the way do not do this unless you
have
this soil don't do that
um but it's exactly what this soil
needed to jump start the system like you
couldn't have jump started
a functional system here unless you did
something that radical
most of the time you're not dealing with
things that need radical change you're
dealing with things that need like
tweaking
um but it works on when you have big
problems
it works and it works because you're
addressing the your big
challenges which then allows the whole
system to work better
so what we did is uh lots of
gypsums what luckily jupiter was cheap
in this area we used lots of sulfur to
help get rid of that extra sodium and
the
magnesium we tried we grew whatever the
heck we could
uh we added a whole bunch of humates and
carbon sources
and microbes are not going to have
microbes and then
this so yeah if it works together it
works
really well yes uh yeah that kind of
soil is
somewhat similar it's over seven percent
uh
7ph sorry okay and um i'm curious so
they recommended
some of the micronutrients in sulfate of
copper sulfate because as the ph is
going up some of those micronutrients
i'm curious if they were recommending
smaller amounts just because that was
you can only add so much per year and
how much of an impact will that
potentially have on my ph
smaller quantities not much what's
your exchange capacity that's so that's
partially what determines how much
material it takes to increase
protein so i mean i haven't seen the
result your testosterone of course but i
would say
if you're not adding elemental sulfur
you're not going to see your ph change
dramatically
um if you're adding just a little bit of
sulfate fertilizers
then it'll might change it marginally
when you are adding those small amounts
of those elements
your in many cases they recommend them
to to feed the crop model to get your
crop healthy enough
uh you can also use foliars in that case
so if you're if your soil is really high
ph
a low sediment is not really high but if
it is really high you can use foliars
because if you add it to the soil it's
not going to be available to plants so
there's a lot of strategies that you can
utilize
in that example but if you're i mean i
don't know what
low numbers you were given like what
whether it was 30 pounds
it might have been like about 15 15. um
if you're 15 pounds is basically nothing
it's on a per acre basis for l slower so
i mean if you were
already basically at 50 million or
already at your target or 75 even better
15 is probably a good maintenance
application to keep it there
um the sulfate oil is critically
important ones and one thing that i'll
mention is that
um sulfur we used to barbecue get a lot
of sulfur in
their fertilizer when they used
conventional
phosphate fertilizers there was a there
was gypsum mixed in so they got calcium
sulfur and phosphorus all together
and then they they started moving to
triple super phosphate because it was
more efficient
because they had always stripped out all
the calcium sulfur is just phosphorus
great great idea um and then the other
thing that happened
in the last couple decades is the clean
air act
uh has dramatically reduced the amount
of sulfur in the atmosphere coming out
of coal-fired power plants
and farmers we're actually getting a
reasonable
dose of sulfur sulfur fertilizer
everywhere from acid rain and now we're
not getting it
and i would argue there's a lot of soil
systems that kind of got used to it and
they were hooked on it and
now they're struggling because they're
deficient and the sulfur
was being rained on for so long
was also stripping out some of those
other elements like calcium
so i think just thinking that we can
just let nature take its course
we've already screwed the pooch on that
one so um you gotta do something a
little better than that
uh yeah please speak to uh the use
of sea salt yeah um
so sea salt is great uh basically
anything from the ocean it's gonna have
a lot of
trace elements a lot of like micro trace
elements so we only looked at a couple
of elements here on the soil
before but there's plenty of evidence to
suggest at least 42 maybe 46
elements are necessary for enzyme
pathogens that have been identified
there are 92 naturally occurring
elements and there is probably an enzyme
pathway that needs every single one
uranium included um just haven't
discovered it i've
seriously spent money on that um and
what that means is if you can get
those in there in tiny trace amounts you
might be actually
um increasing your your the efficiency
of your system
um salt water is going to have most if
not all of those naturally occurring
elements in it so you're going to get
those tiny trace amounts which is really
all you need
if you don't have them um if you have
too much sodium you
definitely want to avoid the sodium uh
the sea salts that don't have the sodium
removed there are some processes you can
use to actually
remove most of the sodium from seawater
and still keep the
trace elements um but yeah it's
it's great i like that uh azomite it has
a lot of trace elements
um that's why we have to recommend like
the salt rock dust or any rock dust
really
because there's a lot of those trace
elements um well that don't think i
mentioned was that
we're talking about biological diversity
but one thing that
spurs biological diversity is diversity
of
things in the soil parent materials so a
diverse
diversity of minerals in your soil will
actually spur a diversity of biology
because
different types of biology are are
better or worse at
digesting different things in your soil
so um
i mean there's microbes that eat you
know sulfur
sulfur sulfur vents under the ocean
there's like the microbes that literally
live off of that
and so it's um when we add sulfur we're
probably
keeping entire new species of life
alive in our soil and giving them
conditions to thrive so anytime you can
add
diverse sources of things i like to do
it yeah
just back to your question about test
frequency once every two years
um i wanted to steer away from doing
mineral testing chemicals because of the
very
inherent variability in the sampling
yeah yeah and
then so i love your comments on that
plus seasonality impacts
the window or do you or or does it
somehow wash out the little
matter excuse me so the way i recommend
the question about the variability in
the testing itself and procedures
what i like to say is basically
when you test try to do the same way
because you're really going to compare
you want to compare yourself over time
to your same you have to start somewhere
but then you want to
kind of do an applesauce comparison do
the same time of year
do it in the same way you always want to
make sure you take
your samples from multiple places in the
field so you want to try to get a
representative sample
the best way is to figure out this i
want to test this area so
basically try to do random tests don't
like
let your biases influence where you go
or you might find that you
go to the places that are the best if
you're like
i just ate a really good carrot from
here or the worst where you're because
you're thinking like
man this is not a good field so you're
gonna go to the worst and then you're
gonna
you know it'll but you can buy us your
soil sample with how you take
your test and so try to do randomly try
to do at least
seven to 12 ish that's a good branch for
the number
of cores that go into a bag the other
thing you want to do
is many people take it put into a bucket
mix it up take a sample put in a bag and
chip it
not the best way to do it because soil
is not homogeneous it does not break up
the same way
so when you mix it you're not actually
mixing and making homogeneous
usually unless you're really and
diligent about it
and so what that's why soil probes are
really nice they don't have to cost a
lot
um you get them i think for as little as
fifteen twenty dollars or you can pay
um but basically anything that takes a
core sample
push the whole sample right into the bag
don't mix it the lab will mix it when
they get it they got the equipment to do
it
and homogenize it that's the best way
you also avoid
a potential route for contamination
which would be your bucket
i've seen soil tests come back where i'm
like that doesn't make any sense
i'm like where'd you put your sample and
then i put it in the bucket i said what
did you use the bucket for last fall and
they're like
well used i planted some bulbs and so uh
oh
bone meal and limestone okay there you
go just a little bit that's left over is
enough to contaminate a sample
so um if you can eliminate those sources
of contamination and think about that
when you're doing it
so um does that answer the question
so best time to test take soil tests uh
was yesterday um if yesterday isn't an
option
then tomorrow and uh fall i like
if you want to know um the worst your
worst case scenario
spring is best if you want to know your
best case scenario assuming you
live in a place that has winters and
that's because
soil rests over the winter time and
things become more available generally
speaking so your numbers and spring will
generally be higher your numbers and
fall and so
whenever you're taking soil tests kind
of think about what what are the
questions you're trying to answer the
results you're trying to get
because um that will help you to figure
out
should i do it now with the original
sprint and it might change depending on
whether it's an existing
field or a new field or there's lots of
lots of new ones there's no simple
answer unfortunately
all right uh yeah i'll stay as long as
you want to stay but it is um
the closing remarks happened in three
minutes yeah
you need water