be
[Music]
be five little animals dancing on the
farm how would a horse dance like this
Gall Gallop
Gallop Gallop Gallop gallop
taada let's try the animal dance
together huh
yeah five little animals dancing on the
farm one stepped up and showed off his
dance Stomp and stomp and stomp and
stomp and stomp and stomp and stomp and
stomp and stomp and
STP a great time and daddy said more
little animals dancing on the farm
I want to try the duck
dance four little animals dancing on the
farm one Ste up and showed off his dance
clapping clapping clapping Clapp and CLA
and clapping Clapp and clap and clap and
clap they all had a great time and said
more little animals dancing on the
farm I will do the Sheep
dance three little animals dancing on
the farm one stepped up and showed off
her hands jump and jump and jump and
jump and jump and jump and jump and jump
and jump and jump they all had a great
time and Mommy s more little animals
dancing on the
farm time for a pig
dance two little animals dancing on the
farm one step up and sh off her dance
shake and shake and shake and shake and
shake and Shake they all had a great
time
and more little animals dancing on the
farm I want to try the rabbit
dance one little animal dancing on the F
he up and showed off his dance hop and
hop and hop and hop and hop and hop and
hop and hop and hop and hop they all had
a great time and head let's all dance
[Music]
together five little animals dancing all
together they alled up and showed their
Dan STP and stump and stump clap and
clap and clap jump and jump and jump
shake and shake and Shake hop and hop
and hop and HP they all had a great time
and said let's do the cat dance
together dance and dance dance dance and
dance and dance and dance and dance and
dance and
[Music]
dance hit the Subscribe button