[Music]
ah thank you for coming
so yeah drought we're going to talk a
lot about that um
amongst other things so we're going to
focus on financials primarily i've got a
couple of confessions to make and i will
make those in a minute but first a quiz
just so i can get to learn the audience
better so i'm assuming this is the strip
hill conference you're all strip tillers
right
any no-tillers
no tillers
all right
cover crop users
how many people have used cover crops
tried them and quit
how many are thinking about it
so a few
be proud when you say we're thinking
about it so you are my audience today
so the people that are using cover crops
you think you've got a benefit you can
see from the combine cab to the line
where you plan to cover and where you
didn't have it i've got data for you
but really my audience both
my target audience both here and
in my other presentations is for people
that are thinking about cover cropping
but they're worried about the economics
whether it's yield reduction or added
expense of the cover crop or
implications related to we control
that's really the heart of my research
and outreach program now and i'll talk
about that again but that's uh what
we're going to talk about and so mostly
it's uh
it's financial in nature
anyone hear from ser
so let me put the plug in for sarah this
is labeled as and i want to thank sarah
and lesson here for inviting me here
so this is really a sarah farmer forum
so
i'm on a speaker bureau a lot of my
funding comes from sare
and so we speak at various conferences
around the country talking about this
air program
and um
and uh the good work that they're doing
i am an independent research agronomist
this is my third growing season as an
independent my past affiliations are
two stents as a county-based extension
educator
in southeast wisconsin
and also two stents with michael fields
institute which is a non-profit
that works in the area of sustainable
agriculture in east troy
wisconsin southeast wisconsin
i was initially a research agronomist
there did a lot of work in cover crops
and
more recently
and the position i left to become an
independent
was the
research director
i currently in kind of a combined role
professionally and also as a farmer i'm
a member of my local producer-led
watershed protection group so really
there are several of these groups
there's like 40 of them in the state of
wisconsin and really it's a bunch of
like-minded farmers who are really
interested in conservation and soil
health and so this movement wisconsin
got started several years ago and it's a
place where we get together informally
and
share information
and then i'm also just a fun fact a
member of the soil health subcommittee
of the wisconsin
nrcs technical committee so i work with
a lot of agency folks
on issues related to uh
to soil health
so i've been at this a long time if you
include graduate school i've been
working in a cover crop arena since 1989
and i'll tell you
with all
that experience i have more questions
than i do answers
every time that we start researching a
topic and
farmers come to us with issues or maybe
they're leading with technologies it
always um
raises more questions and so that keeps
keeps us employed as uh researchers and
it keeps things interesting
so my past research uh past work
when i started there was little known
about cover cropping in the state of
wisconsin so i did a lot of work on
species screening what works here that
led us more into uh management and my
particular focus of interest is in
nitrogen management so i worked in
nitrogen crediting and also in nutrient
management implications especially when
we started seeing a lot of
winter i used on on
dairy farms i have subsequently well let
me back up so this information is all
out there if you're having trouble
sleeping at night you can look at the
research literature and you'll see that
i've published there but my emphasis in
publication is in
formats that we'll get into farmer hands
so um
and again no one here from sare but i'd
like to plug this book here managing
cover crops profitably this is a
national publication i worked on
initially as a
contributor but also contribute data to
it
under its uh revisions and it's
currently being revised so it's going
into the fourth revision i've got
several university of wisconsin
extension publications but most of my
work is incorporated in
wisconsin university of wisconsin
extension fertility recommendations and
that gets to
phosphorus and potassium removal as well
as nitrogen credit for the cover crops
my current topics like i said i am now
solely focused on
economics and this relates to
wheat suppression but primarily to the
yield response of cover crops because
all of the social science
data that's out there says that of cover
crop non-users
it's the finances that prevent people
from using them so
that's why i'm working on
that arena now i'm in that arena now i'm
working on yield effects and the related
economics and we're working on weed
suppression but then also on a
conservation component so from all my
on-farm research i collect conservation
performance information
that feeds into
the software programmers and the
modelers for
the different models that estimate the
cover crops role
in reduction of
nutrient and
sediment loss
where does that build into
into the phosphorus trade so finance
ultimately it's financial so if you can
cut or if you can trade for phosphorus
because you've done the right thing and
you've cut your phosphorus losses then
that's financial so i'm very active in
that and i mentioned uh sierra support
i've gotten support
throughout my career from various
different programs
because this is a sarah farmer focus or
forum i feel the need to talk a little
bit about my farm but this is also
important because about 50 of the
research that i've done in the past has
been done on my farm a lesser extent now
because my on-farm research program
has grown but i'm in walworth county in
southeast wisconsin 30 miles roughly
southeast of southwest of milwaukee i'll
show you my location on a map
in a minute so i'm on the family farm
it's a typical dairy farm for southeast
wisconsin we skipped a generation so
when my
my grandparents retired from dairy
farming the farm was rented out on a
cash lease basis
30 years 25 30 years roughly of
going from a dairy rotation soil
conserving rotation to a corn soybean
rotation with a lot of tillage
so when i started farming there in
94 i inherited a soil health nightmare
and so for the past almost 30 years i've
been working to to build that up we'll
talk about that journey a little bit
as we go
so the soil type is very common to the
area it's a lighter glacial soil it's a
fox silt loam on my farm i've got a
slopes absolutely flat ground
but most of it's rolling four to six
percent slope um i've got some highly
erodible land and this picture here
shows you uh pretty much typical um
uh scene from my farm with a red clover
cover crop
the thing to know about my farm is that
i've got 18 inches to 24
inches of topsoil and subsoil and that's
perched over gravel
so i don't have available
moisture holding capacity my moisture
holding capacity is very limited so that
definitely plays into everything i think
about
as far as farm management my cover crop
history i started out with cover crops
right off the bat
three crop rotation corn soybeans wheat
i interceded red clover in the wheat
because i was interested in the nitrogen
question
i
for financial reasons quick growing
wheat in 2012 so i switched to corn and
beans
and i set out for of the cover crop
world for a couple years but back into
rye planted into corn stalks before
soybeans to me that is the no-brainer
there's no yield penalty in the
in the soybeans and let's be frank we're
going to talk about dryness you have dry
years you're not taking up all the
applied nitrogen you want to keep it on
your farm and in a form it'll become
available to subsequent crops instead of
losing it to uh
to leaching
2002 the current growing season based on
some data i'm going to show you next
slide
i planted the entire farm except for
areas i'm saving for research trials
into winter rye and that's specifically
to deal with
the crazy weather that we're
experiencing experiencing
recently uh my tillage
journey i started out conventional
farmer tilt hilltill i phased in no-till
i've been on 100 no-till since 2003 so
this is the 20th growing season
as a no-till farmer i forgot to tell you
give you my confession
i have strip tilled
20 acres that doesn't make me a
strip-till farmer uh all the data i'm
going to show you is coming from
from no-till i will tell you i've got a
couple in my big project i've got a
couple of strip tillers in there and
i'll talk about how they're
incorporating uh cover crops into their
strip till system but all the data that
i'm showing you is
is from no-till the other confession is
that um
because this is air farmer forum they
want us to talk about current projects
so i've got one completed project i'm
going to talk about with actual data the
other two are
projects that are in process so i can
show you what we've got so far but no
firm recommendations
all right my motivation for cover crops
on my farm right now it's strictly
tactical and it's adapted management how
do we deal with extremes and
precipitation
so the graph there is the growing season
of precipitation almost 30 years of data
from my farm on the top it's the season
total for the growing season so that's
april 1st through october 31st
and then on the bottom it's the three
tenderloin months of the growing season
june july and august
so these graphs show a couple of things
so here's the mean
so the average that's the black line
there and then the annual variation
the mean the average do we do we farm
for average do we strive for average
from a risk management standpoint maybe
but no we want to be above average
here's the other thing i'll say about
average and you've all heard this a
statistician can drown in an average
water depth of three inches right
it's not the average we're interested in
we're interested in the spread so the
high and the low and it's going to come
up in all my data
discussion
let's look at the last four years and
this is what's really driving me
the wettest and the second wettest year
on my farm
as well as the driest year so this is
the benchmark year you all think about
the dry year the drought of 2012 right
to me that was um the benchmark
2021 almost two inches less
precipitation than we had in uh in the
drought here here's the other thing uh
20 20 right here we ended up a little
bit below average the actual
precipitation in that year
happened in garbage time when the crop
couldn't use it anymore
so a football analogy would be okay so
we got rainfall in the fourth quarter
the football analogy is okay we're down
56 to nothing we score 14 points against
the third string defense who cares
statistically it shows that hey maybe
that year wasn't bad but i would argue
from a
moisture standpoint it was just as bad
as last year's uh drought which was
an official drought here's the other
thing let's look at the tenderloin
months
june july and august so these are the
monthly totals and you can see we got
some variation of the data and you would
expect that you get a wet june you get a
dry june
look at this
2007 it's like you flipped a switch
suddenly
the amplitude the variability has
increased it's almost doubled and we've
got months where we're getting 10 inches
of rain
followed by months where we're getting
almost nothing
embedded in this data is three hundred
year storms
what's a hundred year storm a storm of
sufficient intensity and rainfall amount
that it only happens once every hundred
years that's the probability
i've got three of them in a span of 15
years that really influences
crop production
and also as i think about my crops how
i'm gonna manage them that's why
everything on my farm this year going
into the growing season was planted with
a cover crop to help me manage
this variability and the moisture
so we use what we call adaptive
management with the cover crops if it's
dry what do you do you terminate early
so this picture is from
2011 or 2021 last year a declared
drought in our area this comes from a
cooperating farmer of mine
who's also a crop consultant his name is
tom novak
so this is part of a long-term trial
that he's had on his farm to prove the
value of the
of the cover crops to his clients and
it's a real simple trial with and
without cover he collects the
yield data and he shares it with his
clients
if it's a wet year we terminate later we
let that cover crop use the moisture
dry the soil out this is my farm this
year
and it worked
it worked all around me i live in
no-till nor nirvana everyone around me
no-tills but i'm the one that uses the
cover crops i let it go i was in the
field planting a full two days sooner
than my neighbors which is important
when you have five inches of rain in
april
and you haven't gotten anything done in
the field everything's all compressed
the sooner you get out there the better
off you are
remember this picture we're going to
circle back and look at it um
in just a minute
so you got to have the rye
in place to do adaptive management even
if you terminate early there is a
benefit to it and i want to show you
data that shows that there's weed
suppression but also there's a yield
benefit even from something that has
such little amount of biomass
here's tom's data core yield
no rye and rye averaged across two
different trials which are basically
nitrogen rate trials a four and a half
bushel yield advantage to the cover crop
he also saw some yield suppression he
also had or not yield suppression um
weed suppression he also has the same
thing in soybeans and his soybean yield
he had a bump of four
4.3 percent so
he got a yield advantage but had it
turned out wet he could have
terminated later and uh used it to
manage soil moisture
we also and he's a cooperator on this
trial i'm going to talk about this this
is one of my weed management trials so
we had three different treatments
at three different locations
in southeast wisconsin where we had a
control no rye we had rye terminated
let's call it burn down and where we
planted green and terminated later in
the season
in the case of the no rye versus rye
very little yield difference and the
thing that's really intriguing to me we
talked about the spread and the data not
the mean statistically the means are the
same in fact we got a slight yield bump
but look at the spread and the data with
the rye
it was a lot tighter and again this is
averaged over three locations
three different farms
compared to
the uh the no rye
so that's telling us there's something
there with the rye
that's either enhancing
weed suppression or yield let's go back
to the uh the original drought and this
is where i became convinced that cover
crops have great value
to deal with drought so up until this um
this past year 2012 was by far the
driest year that we had had on my farm
at the time i had a uh i was in the
fourth year of a nitrogen response trial
looking at the nitrogen response of corn
to
supplemental nitrogen after a red clover
cover crop and this is what the system
looked like so this is going into the
season this is that time of planting and
then this is an in season
what i had was basically a mat that
helped with infiltration but also a cut
evaporation losses
so it helped me capture water and store
it
this is what the crop looked like in
season i unfortunately did not have a no
cover control in this trial
but i had data to compare it to and that
was the pre
pre the three previous years which turns
out in southeast wisconsin were really
good cropping years so at harvest time i
looked back at the yield
from the pre
three previous years and guess what
eighty percent of
what i had in good years so that was
kind of compelling but i thought well
let's look at the rest of the county so
i took nas data from walworth county
this is all the corneal data
non-irrigated
but it includes all practices so based
on my knowledge of the neighborhood i'll
tell you this is all conventionally
tilled there's a little bit of no-till
in there a little bit of cover crops
mostly this is conventional
they're yield in 2012 compared to
the three previous really good years
so i'm like 20 percent better with my
cover crop and i attribute that all to
managing the moisture that i got
all right my motivation right now is
tactical but my primary reasons and the
reasons that i grow cover crops
uh they remain basically the same i'm
looking for the ecosystem uh services
both general but some very specific ones
soil health that's a gimme i drunk the
soil health kool-aid long ago i don't
worry about testing for it i know it's
there how do i know i have soil health i
can see the earthworm castings on the
soil surface i know i can close my slots
i know my soil breaks apart freely i
know i don't have ponding that i get
really good infiltration and i know that
leads me to
yield enhancement i'm also interested
because of my soil nature and increased
surface residue both for infiltration
but also to cut evaporation early in the
season i'm also interested in in season
biomass production four weeds
suppression so i can cut
herbicide application not rates but
number of applications and i'll show you
some data um what happened this year in
a little bit and i'm also interested in
nutrient retention
not only
nitrogen
but also increasingly in phosphorus so
in wisconsin there's a group that's
affiliated with the university it's
called discovery farms and they've done
a lot of on-farm monitoring of runoff
from different farming scenarios
what they're monitoring shows is that in
no-till we're not losing sediment but
our achilles heel as far as surface
water quality is concerned is soluble
phosphorus so now i'm thinking about
ways i can use cover crops to cut the
soluble phosphorus on my home farm
it's not really a big deal because i
number one drain internally about 70
percent of my farm drains internally
the runoff water that leaves the farm
goes to the marsh and it has to travel
through several thousand feet of marsh
which is going to capture that
phosphorus before it gets to the rain
channel to the the main channel
my problem is on rental ground and
that's this picture right here
so i've got one field it's a small field
but i like it because it's relatively
uniform and i do a lot of research on
this field
it's got a swale that runs right through
the middle it runs to the edge of the
field it crosses six inches of mold lawn
and then right into a gully which
plunges over the course of only a couple
hundred feet 60 feet down into the marsh
it goes through like 50 feet of marsh
goes into a pond that has a channel that
gets it into the main channel which
means it gets into the mukwonago river
why am i so concerned about the
mukwonago river
it has
a designation by wisconsin dnr as an
exceptional to outstanding water
resource not only because of water
quality but also because it's home to
several endangered species so the dnr
has a lot of interest in it a lot of the
conservation groups have huge interest
in my watershed which means as a farmer
i am under the microscope as far as what
happens on my farm and what could
potentially end up in the uh
in the river
the other thing to say like all of you
my overarching reason for using
conservation is for the next generation
so i can pass the farm on to the next
generation
in better shape than i found it
all right
economics my primary justification i
mean i talk to farmers all the time so i
know economics are the
the bottom line of the decision not to
implement cover cropping
my justification for
grant purposes is this so the folks at
sayre
along with the conservation
tillage information center have
conducted a periodic
survey for the last 10 years to look at
farmers use of cover crops or non-use
they want to look at the motivation but
primarily what are the barriers
and so every two years they publish the
survey it's the same results of the
non-survey of the non-users every time
there is no
demonstrated economic benefit
to me i interpret that as we don't have
good data we don't have numbers from
acceptable side by side comparison
there's a lot of anecdotal evidence out
there there's a lot of testimonial
farmer jim will say yeah i got a five
percent yield response to it people want
to see the data so that's why i am data
driven they are
in my research program
fear of yield reduction added cost and
time commitment
complicates management especially weeds
and increased risk
all those are valid concerns and reasons
not to do it what's really interesting
in this survey is among the cover crop
users they say the exact opposite hey
we're seeing a yield increase corn uh
especially in a drought year corn up to
almost 10 soybean up almost at 12
those higher numbers those all came from
the first year of the survey the drought
response here of 2012.
the users say we get improved we control
we can cut our input costs including
herbicide
planting green boy this is the greatest
thing it allows earlier planting in wet
years like on my farm this past year
like i talked about
and it may prevent us from having
prevented plant acres because it dries
it out enough that we can plant
so that's the data and then just to add
a little bit of
richness to the data this little sidebar
here i looked at evaluations from a
winter workshop my uh producer group put
on this winner and got actual comments
from farmers who would listen to gabe
brown talk for six hours
about regenerative practices and here's
what they had to say you know the
practices are great but how do i
actually implement these practices and
remain profitability
remain profitable so there it is
profitability the next one how do i
implement regenerative practices
without losing money initially to me
that gets at the fact that people have a
perception that maybe there's a
transition period
which ties into the third one
what about rental ground so most ground
at least in the state of wisconsin at
least on three-year leases so if there's
a perception there's a transition period
and you're going to have a yield loss
initially why would you do it also why
would you want to improve
the soil on rental ground when you know
you could be albin you could lose the
lease so one of the things i'm keenly
interested in is first year effects
showing we can have a yield impact
the first year
all right so let's put a number on it so
these are the three sarah projects that
i have
that are related to economics the first
one do cover crops pay this one is
complete but this is the rationale
for the second one the second and the
third one can cover crops pay and
do ken planting green suppress our
troublesome glyphosate tolerant or
resistant weeds and no-till soybean as i
said this is a work in progress
i will show you completed data i will
show you the data that we've gotten from
the trial so far but
no recommendations it is what it is
you can look for updates at the sare
site and lesser tears gonna publish it i
put down no-till farmer i didn't know
about strip till farmer or cover crop
what's the other one cover crop
your third publication cover crop
cover crop strategies it'll be in there
somewhere right
all right
do cover crops pay this was a really fun
project so the um this was funded by the
producer grant program our partnership
program
it's a two-year funding cycle i was able
to get federal funding from another
source so i stretched it into
into three
years again conducted in southeast
wisconsin three different counties it's
a replicated strip till trial it's got a
formal experimental design and a real
simple treatment design
with cover
without cover
here's the fun thing about it i had a
protocol as far as me collecting data
and how i was going to do it
as far as the cover crop management
that was up to the farmers and there's a
lot of wisdom in doing that because
farmers know how to manage cover crops
we'll talk about the universities later
later on in the session anyway they know
what they're doing let them do it here's
the ball google play kids
we're going to collect some data we did
a financial analysis we use partial
budget analysis so we're just looking at
additional costs and returns there's no
assumptions in it it's just the two
practices
side by side and i use the co-operators
input costs as well as their
output prices the differences between
the systems are primarily in the cover
crop costs so there's additional costs
of the seed the establishment management
if necessary like clipping
and then termination costs one thing
that's kind of unique to this research
and this economic research was we also
looked at interest charges so you think
about it most the cover
trials use winter rye you plant rye in
november of one year you don't have
access to the grain income till november
of the next year
you've got one year of carry on that
money so it's important
to carry that
we also looked at
the yield increase and the cost of that
if you have a yield bump that's free
money right
the answer is no
you still got to haul it you got to dry
it you got to shrink it and you have to
account for p and k removal so we did
all of that to come up with our break
even
numbers and
some other things which are on this
slide
so at the end of the day we ended up
with 14 sight years of data so that's
like having 14 little farms scattered
across
three different growing seasons
we saw positive yield response 75
percent of the time
and that's important because it matches
what tom novak has been doing in that
trial i showed a couple slides ago
that he's been conducting for the last
10 years he in corn and beans are seeing
a positive yield response about 75
percent of the time
so here's the raw data this is the corn
and this is the soybean
on average
our corn meal response 2.1 percent
soybeans a little better 2.3 percent
so the average is up represented by the
x on the graph
average is great what i'm really
interested in is the variability soybean
much less variable than the corn and if
i look at corn data i'm seeing a lot of
upside potential
so in a lot of academic studies they
won't talk about the variability they'll
just talk about the average
we're going to talk about the
variability the upside potential as well
as the downside potential
sir
so in this trial it was very good
questions and the question is what were
the cover crops most of it was rye
combination of after corn or after
soybean so whatever the farmer pretty
much typically does
a couple of the sites
also and this was
two site years on my farm after um
after a red clover and then another
location had after red clover but
primarily was corn bean rotation with
winter rye after one
or the other
so we run the numbers based on our yield
responses and based on current market
conditions at the time
we weren't close to um to break in we
needed a yield response of 5.7 in corn
5.3 in soybeans to break even that means
we need to figure out under then market
conditions
what's driving the responses here and
here
so that led to the next generation trial
but before we do that i just want to
look at a couple of the really
interesting little cases from this trial
all right
it takes forever to get a yield response
right
no you can see it first year here's
proof positive so this is on a kid or
silt loan this is the first year of the
trial
winner after soybeans
it's a no-till situation the pictures
are taken here close up in a field shot
taking the day of termination when i was
there to do the sampling to characterize
the conservation
performance
not a lot of biomass there 400 pounds we
did in soil sampling realized we were
able to scavenge
some leftover nitrogen now this is going
into corn so maybe that wasn't a good
thing
but even that little bit of growth rye
growth we were able to scavenge 30
pounds of nitrogen to me from a
conservation standpoint that's huge
cooperator nick here never grew a cover
crop in his life
at the end of the day
9.9 bushel yield increase
5.3 percent
he grows cover crops now based on that
one experience this is not the most
spectacular one but i think this one is
more representative the most
spectacular i'll get to you in a second
sir most spectacular 18 bushel that was
corn following red clover he too had
grown it on his farm but he quit doing
it
guess what he went back to putting red
clover in his winter wheat even though
it's kind of hard to manage and that's
an expensive system he is doing it now
question or comment here
okay so most of these are after harvest
in this tryout they were all drilled
after harvest so we're looking at
november
i mean in the case of soybeans yeah you
can do it in october but realistically
it's in in november
so i told you i'm gonna run out of time
yeah 10 25 here most of them are in that
window these guys know that you got to
get it in the ground but things get in
the way like harvest so
yes and no
how about you folks do you have aerial
application so drones
okay
so we're getting more and more of that
uh the drone phenomenon we're starting
to see more and more of that in
wisconsin i got rumors of two startups
in southeast wisconsin that will be
doing it
that works
there's a timing issue there i don't
have time to get into the technicality
but i'll talk about that in the after
session how about that or at the beer
and thingy tonight
i gotta keep rolling
so this one here this one is really
intriguing this shows adaptive
management wet spring this is 2019.
the site has a long-term cover crop
history two covers every three years so
a summer cover after week followed by um
rye after after corn stubble he had
planned to burn down couldn't do it
because it rained i did sample in the
rain three weeks later he uh he planted
green and then he terminated
what did he get 3.7 yield response 3.7
percent yield response was that because
of planting green was it because the
non-cover was in withdrawal i don't know
what's really intriguing about this site
was i came back in the middle of the
season in no cover control treatments
there was water hemp in the cover
treatments there was no water happening
can we use this planting green to
suppress
our troublesome glyphosate resistant
weeds we will get to that at the end
that led us that experience led us to my
current project so can cover crops pay
very much it's like the other one except
it's much larger in scale
we're documenting the yield impacts but
we're really drilling in on first year
impacts but we're also looking at the
cumulative effects we're still trying to
identify the best management practices
to maximize yield and on the flip side
to look at practices
to avoid so you don't reduce yield we're
putting a number on it with a partial
partial budget analysis we're going to
generate a lot of
data analysis
this one i am punting to campus so we
have a extension a economist who will do
the economic analysis
and we're also collecting the
conservation
estimates in an effort to improve
the numbers for water quality trade so
the farmers that do this do get
compensated for it
at the farm level in effect what we've
got annually is 30 little on-farm trials
where we're answering a specific
question that a farmer may have
what about my seating rate
or what about if i'm planting corn green
what about nitrogen management should i
increase my starter fertilizer nitrogen
because the rye is presumably going to
take some of it up so for the farmer
those are the questions that we're
asking we take all that data in
aggregate we do a meta analysis we can
tease out
what causes the yield impact is it this
practice on this soil type in this
environment so our goal is to get 90
site years of data over three response
years
that's pretty close to big data
let me back up
this trial is a little more involved we
have the no cover control trial we also
to look at the management factors we
have two different cover treatments the
farmer's base treatment
and then some variation on that the best
example is seeding rate so if i see dry
at 40 what happens if i see it at 80.
actually it's the other way around so
nrcs says you've got to have in the
state of wisconsin says you need to have
higher seating rates than
probably what you really need so i'm
doing 80 can i get away with 40.
especially since rye seed prices have
basically doubled in the last couple of
years so that's the nature of the
treatment design
so fun facts we had a goal of 30 trials
to put out
this past year we got out 29 we lost one
of them because of poor rye
establishment and that was in the
soybean stubble planted in uh first week
in december
27 of the 28 are cereal rye we do have
one winter wheat you always have to have
a contrarian out there he got some
really cheap seed he's got a really good
stay in the cover crop
more power to them most of trials are
looking at response in soybean but we do
have seven that are
corn following soybean and then
interestingly we've got three that's
second year corn
and one of those is in a trial that i'm
doing with my watershed group
the comparisons what are farmers really
interested in its rate and i think this
is driven
since this is mostly rye by the fact
that rye
supplies have gotten really tight and
the seed costs have gone up dramatically
we've got some interest in
termination timing whether it's the burn
down or the pre-plant
and then nitrogen management and corn
and this is a picture from one of my
sites this is dodge coney um he's
looking at seating rate but he's also
this is a double trial
so he's also looking at
skip roll planting so this is going to
in row versus between row
so when i say row crop row so this is
going to yield some really interesting
results
and here's a map just showing where the
trials are located i put this up to show
the magnitude we're in six or sorry five
different counties i told you this is my
farm right here i've got a bunch of it
because it's easy to do research on your
own farm you don't have to travel unlike
up here into dodge county
so basically we're in a triangle what
this gives us is two different things
growing season environment and we have
definitely segregated uh environments
keeps raining up here in dodge county
uh we're in drought down here and we're
seeing in kenosha county extremely dry
here
in rock county we're somewhere in
between we have the best soil types in
the state of wisconsin plano salt loam
we also have kitters
sandy loam
that's on the well-drained soil class we
also have some very poorly drained
soils here in dodge county uh pella
and then some elliots and tile during
other tile drained
type soil types in
in
racine county
all right last topic
and this again is based on that first
one the observation that hey there's no
water hemp where we planted the rye
green can we suppress glyphosate
resistant weeds in no-till soybean these
are the weeds that we're concerned with
in southeast wisconsin
giant rag
this is a field picture and a close-up
of a resistant
individual this is on my farm this
population was just confirmed by
uw-madison
two weeks ago
it also has multiple uh other
resistances which i don't understand
because i haven't used those modes of
action on my farm and on my farm as far
as glyphosate stewardship i have done
everything right i have never used the
roundup ready trait in corn
my presumption is
that this is pollen the blue end from
somewhere else
the other one meers tail this one is all
over uh confirmed resistance for about
the last 10 years
now in southeast wisconsin these two
pictures are from tom novak's from his
clients and they show in the field this
one with the marestail
you can see the susceptible versus the
resistant individuals and then a
close-up of
the resistant individuals and then water
hemp these plants are taken from the
same field
obvious case of resistance
we don't have palmer amaranth yet i just
submitted a seed sample
from some camelina seed i used as a
cover crop with my rye on my farm last
year
i just got a call two days ago from
foundation seed i sent it in for
analysis
purity and germination
we have amaranth seed in there
will you pay for dna testing for four
seeds that's a hundred bucks absolutely
palmer amaranth it's on the
horizon we've got it in illinois just
across the illinois border you folks
dealing with it yet
let's hope it
you did
southern iowa
that's another thing just to watch and
be careful of because that one
the experience in the southern united
states is something we don't want to
deal with but it's on its way
produced on farm
by one of my cooperators i cleaned it
but the seeds smaller than the
camelina seed and i don't have
official cleaning equipment i did a
window screen
so it's there
did he have it on his farm i don't know
i haven't talked to him yet about it
i wait till i get the positive or
negative results before i
spook him
all right so the last trial um we're
looking at wheat suppression and
basically this is the same group of
cooperators as in the first one so this
is funded by the sare partnership
program
two-year we have four locations and then
four replicates so we're going to
generate a lot of data we have three
basic treatment sets the first one is
the control treatment this is no rye and
we are using best management practices
for
management of the uh
the resistant weed so we start clean
that means complete burn down glyphosate
plus some kind of growth regulator
herbicide
to control the ones that are resistant
so we used lv6 last year
this year because of our tightened up
planting window and i didn't want to
have
planting restrictions we used um in list
all these trials are using the endless
trade
and then we use residual so um the
generic version of authority for same
thing as uh sonic i can't pronounce the
uh
common names with all of you looking at
me in fact i wrote them down i can't
read my own writing so you all know what
i'm talking about right
all right the next set is the first
cover crop treatments these that were
burning down but on our data it's
labeled as pre-emergents why i call it
that some people burn down beforehand
some people plant it then terminated
right away here we have two rye
treatments 40 and 80 pounds to get at
the seating rate
difference
and we use the same herbicide so the
glyphosate that's in the burn down mix
also terminates the rye
the planting grain treatments same rye
treatments 40 and 80. we're using the
broadleaf burned down so they enlist the
growth regulator herbicide to control
the broadleaf weeds that are there and
the residual and we come back with the
glyphosate to terminate the rye the rye
we're terminating
at pollination so in effect in our data
set we have the two polar extremes we
have the minimum amount of rye growth
pre-plant that we burn down or at
anthesis and there's some implications
that i'm going to talk about in a minute
our questions of course can ry do it
what about the termination timing is
that important and what about the
seating rate does it matter especially
since seed has gotten to be so expensive
so here's our one year results so far
and again 2021 this was a drought year
suppression yes both in mayor's
and giant ragweed
waterhemp did not show up to the party
last year it showed up this year but we
don't have data from it from last year
going from nori
to
the uh
the plant green and terminate late
treatment
in mare's tale and this is measured 45
days after planting marestail 98
suppression
in the giant rag 99
so yes it does work
what about the uh the burn down yes
we're seeing suppression there also in
the case of mare's tail 64 percent
suppression
and in the case of the giant rag
50 percent um
suppression the other thing
question
[Music]
so you peeked ahead at my next slide
so
let me say i should have said this up
front
okay so the honest answer is and this is
counterintuitive
seeding rate had no impact on any of our
response variables other than
biomass production
so that makes sense you got more plants
you're going to produce more biomass
what is counterintuitive is we assume
it's that biomass that's giving us the
weed suppression
either through competition
or as a residue mat to keep the weeds
down from germinating or physically
to
to inhibit them and then there's the
issue of allelopathy so what the
research literature says that the
chemicals that are in the biomass they
reach their peak concentration right at
pollination you got more biomass a
higher concentration that natural
herbicide is there it makes sense if you
got more biomass you'd have better weed
suppression planting rate doesn't matter
recently published uh studies by um penn
state university there's two of them
they looked at the same thing basically
the same seating rates they found the
same effect biomass yes any crop
response variable
no
so you can cut your seeding rate
but i shouldn't say that because it's
only one year of data
but going back to the other on-farm data
they're all doing 40 pounds
so nrcs in wisconsin requires for cost
share programs 55 pounds
iowa illinois are you in the
i heard 40.
46.
yeah of course
okay
yeah right then you gotta you gotta
boost it that that makes sense so we're
all in the same ballpark but the point
is that it didn't
okay so we saw
a 98 reduction by planting green
i can't show you the data you've already
seen it in that soybean yield we're also
by planting green and terminating late
able to suppress soybean yield by
in a drought here
that's unacceptable
so i told you we got the two polar
extremes
of biomass production
there's a sweet spot in there somewhere
in between and that's my next generation
work so people are looking at my data
and they heckle me at field days all the
time you're killing it too late
well no this is a formal trial we're
trying to see what the degree of
suppression is somewhere between the two
is the sweet spot where we're not
impacting yield
but we're getting the weed suppression
that's what i'm looking for and my
questions are
how do we stage it do we stage it based
on rye growth stage do we base it on
height
because people are saying when it gets
knee high you terminate it do we base it
on the soybean growth stage so i got to
figure out funding
you say folks i'm coming back to you
this fall and figure out how to do it
this is a really involved trial i can't
do it on farmers this is going to have
to be done on my farm because you're
going to be terminating like every five
to seven days a different treatment
so anyway and here
that's where we're going with this data
so here's the seating rate thing matches
work by penn state
what our data doesn't show you is that
plain and green
delayed the flush
the mid-season
flush of weeds it delayed it
the implication here is that if you're
suppressing
maybe
you can get away with one in-season
post-emergence application versus two
i've got guys in my neighborhood that
are on three i'm sure they're up against
the limit on their enlist as far as
total active ingredient per year
on my farm i showed you that picture
i got away
in most of the field with one
application
but this is actually a really
interesting story
so this is the field that i got all my
soybean research in i went to terminate
a couple weeks after planting
it was turning dry i started getting
concerned i opened the field up it got
dark
so i thought okay i'm going to start
spraying the next day
was too windy too windy to spray for
eight days the rye grew like this i
couldn't see my rows i don't have
guidance equipment i'm too small
where i grew like this i couldn't see
the rose but i could see the green
streaks where the rye had taken up the
sulfur and the starter that i applied to
the soybeans
where i had sprayed it the first time
i had to go back
with enlist and glyphosate because i had
a flush of weeds coming on the other
where i
did it really late i just recently like
within the last couple of weeks made my
one and only application so i saved an
application
where this is important other than
saving money from one application if we
have fewer individuals from that
suppression
plus fewer applications
that means that we have fewer
individuals
that are going to be exposed to this new
active ingredient
which reduces our chances of developing
resistance so this is a resistance
management tool
and it behooves all of us
to practice resistance management
because we've got nothing new coming
down
the pipeline as far as new products to
deal with it so we've lost
we've lost glyphosate and a lot of weeds
and that's really unfortunate in these
other chemistries we could lose them too
if we don't manage it
anything we can do it's important
the reason i'm harping on this other
than i have the resistant population a
giant rag on my farm
look at this picture here this is giant
rag this is five days after a full rate
and list dual application
look at its colleagues they're all
yellow they're twisted up
brings a smile to my face seeing them
all twisted up like that not this giant
ragweed here
look at the the leaf margins they're all
fused you see this with apple or with
exposure to certain modes of action
i've never seen it like this it's also
green and growing it's got a little
crook to it which shows the
the 2 4 d exposure
to me this plant is doing something with
that active ingredient it's figuring out
how to metabolize it metabolize it it
goes on to reproduce that's just
resistance developing in my field
right now
i pulled that weed before i even put the
camera away i don't want any part of
resistance this motor action on my farm
all right like i said this work is
ongoing we're going to get a bunch of
results uh this year the yield response
is going to be a couple years out but we
have ample evidence that i am confident
in saying
that if you use adaptive management that
means manage the cover crops
appropriately don't let them get too big
don't let them compete against your crop
don't let them use soil moisture
we can see first-year responses and with
the pre-plant termination if you're
using the rye
or the cover crop just to manage soil
moisture
it may seem like a waste if you're
terminating it but there's still some
kind of yield benefit there and also
there is um
there also is uh weed suppression i
forgot to talk about 20 22 because this
is about when i killed the screen
so our 2022 data
um pretty much mirrors what we saw in
but this is universal across all four
farms we are seeing foxtail suppression
even in the
burn down
treatment that's lasting long beyond the
residual
products that we put down that to me is
really intriguing and these guys tend to
go back they're all in 30 inch rows so
they tend to go back with
some kind of grass herbicide both
post-emergents but they also put
metallic lore on because they're worried
about season long control
so that um observation is really
intriguing
and really positive
next thing is to make these things work
use the low cost cover crop systems
wherever possible so that's the result
of that first one do cover crops pay
that was the major take-home
message in effect we had the yield
response it wasn't enough to break even
but it reduced our cover crop costs by
60 percent
reducing the rye rate
looking at ways to
terminate it with your routine
program your routine herbicide program
so you don't have additional costs
and then planting green we are seeing
demonstrated weed suppression
so we have to find again that sweet spot
that's somewhere between yield reduction
but we get the suppression and i'm going
to be working on that hard
in the future
so that we can have our cake and eat it
too
with that i finished on
two minutes over
i am done i'm ready for the grilling any
questions or comments in the back
the question if you use the cover crop
for something else is it still a cover
crop so the cover crop purifies tell you
no that is a crop you are harvesting
what is a cover crop it provides soil
cover during vulnerable i mean this gets
back to the original definition during
vulnerable periods in your rotation
as such uri is doing that my inner
farmer says you're finding a way to
market this and make more money so i
talked about my initial work looking at
the nutrient implications of rye
rye is a luxury consumer of both p and k
the higher
your soil test results are the higher
the tissue concentration
it's like open bar at a wedding versus
cash bar
rye is definitely at the open bar it'll
suck up everything that it can so that
would be a concern the allelopathy just
in corn and beans i wouldn't worry about
it i'd be more worried about that
with the grass seed
for the mat that you're producing right
so and i talked about the concentration
of the little chemicals so we have
identified them they're benzoic acids
that's the same thing as
bentazon so it's like commercial
herbicides that are out there
so traditional wisdom says it's a small
seeded species that are more susceptible
than larger that's what we can get away
with it with corn and beans
but not alfalfa so think about that
grass seed that's really tiny
so maybe you ought to do a little pilot
on the side to see if it works with
germination with your your intended crop
yeah so the question is allelopathy is
it with the
is it in the above ground portion or
below ground it's in everything what
causes the soil effect we don't know my
presumption is it's not a leoparty from
the above ground biomass if it's
standing if it falls down and that stuff
can leach out then yes
but below ground and the roots they're
exuding it all the time chem plants are
always
conducting chemical warfare against one
another so this allelopathy is to keep
other things from germinating so the
point is that if things are still
germinating and it's leaching out from
the above ground you'll probably get
some suppression but if it's already
leached out and
gone then no
sounds like another research trial
[Music]
you