[Music]
a few foresters Amy here and today we
are going to harvest our Virginia jumbo
peanuts that we got from ehsan's family
gardener or aka the sapper gardener
sorry if I messed up Rob yes so we
planted peanuts through this whole
raised bed here now unbeknownst to us
some of our yellow Mexican sunflower
seeds happen to get spread in here and
so these will will transplant these
somewhere else but I'm not gonna worry
about bringing them pulling them up
right now but for the peanuts that takes
about 90 to 110 days and what you want
to do is when the leaves start to start
turning yellow here that's when you want
to harvest them so I've got my basket
and we're gonna go ahead and pull a
couple out and then also to when we get
done picking the peanuts off
left over
all right when we get done picking the
peanuts off of the roots what we're
gonna do is we're gonna take these tops
and we're going to go ahead and give
them to our animals as a treat so let's
get started okay so as you can tell
these are very tall because this bed is
a little low but I'm going to buy one
here oh wow
here we go
I don't know if you can see this there's
some peanuts just pop one open and see
if it's well let me pull I just broke it
off the root you should be we should be
using a fork I'll have to get one a
little large tool but look well let's
see if the being inside is if the peanut
is fully formed crunchy crunchy is good
yep yeah it looks like it's filled up
that's good yeah it's good hold on let
me get my gloves off so I can peel these
I want to see and sure one of course I
know it's gonna be all natural it's
probably chocolate tastes like a roasted
peanut we have a little bit of green
I'll have a little dirt with it dirt
don't hurt alright so there's the peanut
out of the shell all right here goes
definitely has the peanut taste it's
like um
it does it's not really an earthy taste
though but it's good it's different it's
more like a um like an unsalted peanut
basically not boiled not cooked not
roasted we're gonna boil these up and
probably freeze some eat some and
probably freeze them but let me try that
one you want to try that one here let me
get your reaction
that's about eating a green peanut Bo
but not bad
no not bad at all it's up salt tastes
like a big raw harder green bean or
something yeah not bad not bad at all
all right so let's uh pull out some more
here you know what um in our little tool
shed here I think down at the bottom is
one of those fork things and a shovel
you want to go grab it
that's jalapeno but this one is got the
peanuts in it
yeah peanuts in it
I mean they are come it is coming up
really good loosely off the dirt didn't
think no no in the food oh you get so
excited you dumping dirt everywhere
everywhere
alright let me pick so this basket ain't
gonna be big enough we might have to
pick them out of here yeah nikka balls
let me um hold on cuz there was some
that fell off so
I just wanna make sure cuz it went older
that nice big warm
all right guys we're gonna start picking
them yeah I'll just start separating
them and putting them in here but we may
need a smaller basket cuz this baskets
got a lot of holes in it so we may have
to grab something else okay all right
we'll see it a little bit
what you doing a me pick a pea nuts
[Laughter]
so now just so you know it's July
today's supposed to get up to 104 with
the heat and the humidity so sweating
and breathing heavy not a good
combination
if he's not outside alright so as you
could tell this is our pile so far this
is what we're gonna be giving a duck's
and in the turkeys and the chickens some
nice little treats Donald's been pulling
this up in sections we got one small
section left but as you could tell now
you can cure these by hanging them to
dry but we're going to be roasting them
right away and also we're going to be
boiling them so we're not going to
bother with curing them we're gonna go
right to cooking them now just for you
guys to know what we're gonna do is
we're gonna let this bed rest for a week
we're gonna add some nice topsoil to it
once I'm able to get the rest of this
stuff cleaned out because you can tell
we got dollar weed in here and I went
crazy and then we are going to go ahead
and plant another crop of these jumbo
peanuts we still have some left over and
then that way come near the fall we'll
have another harvest of the peanuts
that's one good thing about Florida we
have a very long growing season
long and hot so we should so we're
attempting to get a second season out of
the you ain't guarantee and we can but
it's a good experiment to see if we can
and they did so well in this bed we just
got to replenish it and I think what I
may do is I may take one of these
Mexican sunflowers do the chop and drop
that's gonna add in that nitrogen back
into the soil
I don't know we want to do with all
these seed pods on these I'd rather chop
and drop them someplace else I don't
want more I don't want to end up with
the same thing with Mexican Sun well to
be honest this is the first year we've
been able to grow them I've planted
these all over the place before and just
got a little itty spindly I mean they're
everywhere and look oh look at all the
butterflies yeah
butterflies love them yeah look at the
butterfly you see they don't
all right sorry I don't take camera
directions very well no you don't take
directions period very well do I you try
that's why I always here yes dear see
even the turkeys are laughing action oh
here's a flower what's left of one the
flower just a yellow leaf no it's a
petal of a flower
ah all right and all I do is I just
double check before I lay it down just
make sure we got all the good ones cuz
Donald likes these little itty bitty was
they have a little tiny shells on them I
eat them whole I don't even husk him
when I boil those I'll just eat those
shell and all okay yep one more small
row I'll show you how he does it
you just come right out yeah you just
pull gently these little runners that's
what these are these will have them yep
- well that's how they that's how the
flowers fall yeah because the stem of
the flower that's got a lot yeah I just
double-check in the soil yeah sure miss
any and that one didn't have a bunch
that's okay
somethings better than nothing
one more plant
and we oh yeah the weeds hold the plants
in pretty good just double-check that
make sure there's no throw that in the
ditch peanut more
what's these dollar weeds get into a bed
yeah it's almost impossible to get them
out
all right
all right smooth that out and then uh
you want to smooth that's that corner
over there out that hole over there yes
you can see downer weeds are pretty easy
to pull out it's almost like they're
what they're just roots and literally
you pull on one and almost the whole
thing comes out so throw that over the
fence all right guys so we're going to
go ahead and finish harvesting this and
then we're gonna take it inside hey guys
if you liked that video hit that like
button
remember that Belle and subscribe and if
you want see any of the other videos
check out everything over here
[Music]