oh that's crooked whoops okay okay I
think we're good to go
well hey guys Natalie here and welcome
back to hey it's a good life and welcome
to my kitchen table where we are going
to be spending a lot of time together
listen here as we launch this new series
than all about featuring people in the
community or doing good today's video
features Steven Cornett of nature isn't
always right steven is a regenerative
small-scale farmer who's had a really
successful market garden over the last
three years he's sold that local farmers
market
and has his own YouTube channel as well
where he shares his knowledge with you
he's on a mission to equip as many
people as possible to get started with
their farm even if it's in their
backyard steven is a wealth of knowledge
and we covered so many topics please
consider this video a 30,000 foot
overview of small-scale regenerative
farming and how you can get started
growing big in a small space I will of
course provide as many info cars right
here as I possibly can linking topics
covered it in this video to videos on
Stevens Channel where he goes more in
depth so in this video we'll get to know
Steven a little bit about how he got
into farming his beliefs about farming
why his name is nature's always right
how he set his farm on a small scale to
be really successful and what he and his
wife are up to next so without further
ado let's get into the video
[Music]
so what did seven-year-old Stephen do
nothing man oh so no seven years old uh
probably a video game designer something
like that I think my first job was
working at a golf course in all 15 and I
had to do weed whacking and mowing lawn
and I needed it and like I promised
myself I'm never working outside ever
I'm gonna go to college and then get a
desk job you know that's what I thought
my head and then I got older and I got
some more wisdom and I learned more
about reality and the world and all the
stuff and and I realized today I'm with
my friend Steven Cornett everybody
nature's always right and we're here at
his property before he leaves to
Tennessee and we're doing some cleanup
today and I thought I would come out and
share with you guys about how you can
get started in a small space with
regenerative farming so Lauren lemon
grove San Diego as you can see we're in
a backyard so I do all of this in my
backyard plus over time I got other
plots so my next-door neighbor's yard
had moved into his yard and then I've
rented or leased another plot down the
road and tell us what your lease terms
are you pay them in I pay them in
vegetables so I found people that wanted
their yards to be improved or turned
into gardens and in exchange
given the vegetables like it's the best
lease ever yeah that's so really nicely
if I like those terms how much space did
you have when you first started carving
yeah okay so well when I first started
farming this is like eight years ago
another part of San Diego and my best
friend Jarrett Smith started a farm
called Jared's real food that started
just with like 24 8 by 4 foot raised
beds now fast forward to here three
years ago or a little over three years
ago when I started this the first part
of the plot was this square right here
and initially that's all the landlord's
allowed me to do they didn't but over
time as they saw be more successful and
they liked it more and things like that
they allowed me to build a few more beds
over here for like a home gardener or I
guess someone in their apartment got a
bunch of really nice soil these grow
bags and the system which is awesome
it's a cool system if you want to have
another area I can move these to which
is kind of neat at different times of
the year you're gonna get better Sun in
different areas so you can move it there
that's something I like about the girl
bags and now what I'm doing because I'm
leaving I'm just I'm selling these so
I'm gonna get a bunch of my money and
like the investment money I'll get it
back when I sell it I paid off my
investment in one season and made like
twice what I put into it so it was very
effective for a short little season kind
of one of the things I wanted to prove
was possible in a backyard what's the
show you could create all your own
nutrients on-site or at least most of
the nutrients that you needed for your
farm on-site and I wanted you to show
that you could start farming in a
backyard on a really small scale be
successful at that and then go to the
next level at a larger scale so that's
kind of the whole reason behind this
backyard and this YouTube channel that I
make all about doing this stuff as well
the chicken coop is a big deal for me
that's how I make all of my compost 20
chickens in there dropping a lot of
manure I can make really good compost
I'm betting and everything compost
number one so the chicken coop is a deep
litter system which means I'm putting in
layers of carbon in here vegetative
material like straw leaves cardboard
things like that floor is like al is
alive it's always making compost so what
I do is I rake it all out of here and I
take it out here and then I mix it with
a bed of vegetables that's done for more
greens to make the ratio correct and
cool so this is what you describe as the
engine of your farm yes definitely this
works I was able to run my Market Garden
for three years basically just off this
this compost and not much else but from
a business standpoint it's cheaper to
buy in the compost that to use my labor
if you wanna do this as a business and I
recommend buying it but it's still great
to have a system like this to process
all of your leftover waste they're
making compost for me for free with no
work what would you tell Stephen eight
years ago Stephen okay I got to go work
smarter and not harder a lot of things
like that were hard on my back
I'm just bending over and lifting things
like that or you know so now that I'm
older I do a lot more things
ergonomically and or I'm gonna do a task
I try to think well what's the least
physical effort I could do to get it
done I guess I tell my younger self to
think about your future body and take
care of it this is the disaster this so
this is my worm system it's essentially
designed on the three toe system I like
I got your top taupe here is where your
fresh is adding will be most of your
worms will be also a tote underneath
this is typically where your castings
will be any juice or like the leachate
that comes out fall into the third toe
and on my system this whole bottom shelf
here is the third tone I did this to
save money cuz I would have had to buy a
third tote for each one of these it's
modular I can have more totes to it if
you take this out and carry it to where
I want to fertilize so it's been a
really great system for me why nature is
always right sure came from the idea
that this is a nature's are already a
perfect design as perfect as it could be
on this imperfect planet it's the idea
that nature itself is gonna provide the
best solutions for growing food for
health or whatever issues that we really
have on this book on this planet it's
already the solutions are already here
for us to to take and use but
unfortunately especially in Western
society we've gone down this road of
thinking that our God and that we are
more than God we can create on top of
God so we've done things like GMO crops
and other scimplet you know
synthetically derived pharmaceuticals
you know all of this is just mimicry
fentanyl or oxycontin this is a
synthetic derivative of opium which
comes from a plant so nothing is new the
airplane we mimic the bird like we
didn't come up with any of this stuff we
we saw it we saw it in creation we
mimicked it and then we use it or we
improve it but we haven't really created
any so I guess it just goes back to the
idea that nature and natural systems
will always be the best way to grow food
so trying to find kind of strike the
balance between because agriculture
isn't a natural
process right so trying to make
agriculture as natural as as we possibly
can
what kind of health struggle did you
encounter that led you into farming my
big one the big health problem that I
had was self-inflicted
mm-hmm because of listening to medical
advice and I was desperate for a cure so
I had really bad acne when I was in high
school some cystic acne and you know the
real nasty bad guy so yeah under my my
back and so that's with a lot of
teenagers it's a horrible experience and
you hate it you hate how you look and so
I wanted to fix it like now that I was
on an antibiotic for like four or five
months because the theory is that you're
killing all the germs that live inside
the pores so they can't get inflamed and
then the pus develops and all that but
if you guys know it's obliterates your
gut bacteria on your whole body
massively damaging to the digestive
system then later I did
accutane which limits vitamin A
production in your body and the
lubrication of your body anyways what
resulted from this was like digestive
problems oh yeah I eventually had to go
see a doctor even and to figure out what
the heck's going on and but ultimately I
adopter didn't help me I solved it
myself I had to fix it myself because
then I finally figured out what was
going on and and while I was having the
problems I was having and then change my
diet
boom fixed never had a problem again
back behind here you're seeing 18
different grow beds here they're all
about 40 foot long they're 30 inches
wide and this is the standard Market
Garden like small scale farm size and a
lot of people like it just because you
can stand over it you can step over the
road really easy they're easy to work in
stuff now my very small pathways though
as you can see because I've got to fit
as much grow room in here as possible
because like I said I'm on in a backyard
I'm this back square right here is about
five thousand square feet it's like an
eighth of an acre back here so it's not
very big and I focus on lots of crops
that are the most profitable so things
that grow quickly turn over within 60
days typically or I can harvest them for
a very long window of time like chard or
kale or tomatoes cucumbers salad salad
mixes like my my go-to thing I'm
make the most money on salad mix heads
of lettuce and microgreens I really
focus on those and I have a whole method
for growing salad mixes and washing and
packing them and it's kind of a whole
thing because there's a lot of labor
involved but we cut out some of that
labor by some of these awesome DIY
inventions that that the small farmers
have come up with like the salad spinner
made from a washing machine or a greens
bubbler made from just pipe at a Jacuzzi
pump so this is kind of half taken apart
right now but this is my post-harvest
station it's most of its set up to clean
salad greens and microgreens
but this used to be was a greens bubbler
it basically blows air did this jacuzzi
pump it blows it through these tubes and
creates a ton of bubbles basically just
mixing all the the greens pulling the
dirt and bugs off and from there it goes
to the spinner
electricity's off otherwise I would show
you but it just spins this basket now
I'm just like yourself spinner at your
house it gets off most of the water and
then it comes through the drying table
it's got fans on it to flow air over the
top yeah and then after this I would bag
the greens Curtis Stone for sure Curtis
Stone the urban farmer on YouTube and
he's also got a fantastic farming book I
recommend for everybody called the urban
farmer so he's the one who really kind
of dialed in these super small-scale
techniques his stuff was all in urban
Lots and that's what was different about
it so he's one who helped me to really
conceptualize how to think of the
profitability of a crop how to analyze a
crops performance and then and then
decide well maybe I should select
something else that would make a little
bit more money because on a small scale
like this every little bit counts all
the efficiencies really matter too so he
helped me like really put all these
ideas together with what I already knew
about how to raise plants regenerative
lee so how would you describe your style
of farming zai know you take from a lot
of different methodologies yeah I'm so
for me it's I guess to call myself a
natural farmer holistic farmer
regenerative farmer I don't know what
the right term would be I guess but I
just like I use any method that is
natural it's made from nature I either
sell by making compost compost teas
do worm castings things that are made
within nature like even using plants
such as cover crops using the plants
themselves to put nutrients down into
the soil
no-till so we're never or very rarely
tilling the ground or you know turning
the subsoils and mixing those subsoils
together it also chops up microbes
fungal strands the communication network
all the different billions and billions
of organisms that exist some of the soil
they're being disturbed their homes
being messed up and those microbes are
responsible for the breakdown of
nutrients in the soil which then gets
transmitted to the plants through
communication the plants actually ask
for specific nutrients and they give out
carbohydrates to the microbes so the
microbes get food and the plants get
food and there's this constant exchange
going on the Korean natural farming now
making your own nutrients kind of to the
extreme where you can you can create
every input that you would ever need for
your farm so I'm kind of constantly
experimenting with all these different
methods from around the world to see
what works on this context as a growing
for money or also for growing just for
your home scale what makes sense for
everybody and I just want to really
awake in people's minds to God's design
of nature and plants and all of this how
they communicate with the soil give them
a deeper understanding that will allow
them to garden without any chemicals
with nothing just using the design of
nature
how has farming grown you as a person oh
I can't even begin to yeah to tell you I
want you to help me grow it helped me
realize everything the truth about this
world this reality that God is actually
real it helped me understand that there
is a design and a designer to all of
this
I studied like biology slow biology and
plants the more you dive down deeper
deeper deeper it just gets more complex
and I just had to admit that how is this
not a design it's obviously a design the
way it all works together to you the way
the soil the plants the birds the
animals the everything it's an obvious
system and systems are designed I guess
that was a big way that it changed me
and just the amount of lessons that are
out in the garden or the farm it like
the whole lesson of life is out there
for you to go find if you're paying
attention enough but ultimately I think
it spiritually just strengthens my
belief in God and that it's it is real I
can't deny that creation we have no
reason to deny God because you can't
deny that this is a creation in just
finding out the truth that Wow the food
that you grow in your backyard that is
your medicine that is the key to your
health diet and what you put into your
body and just knowing that that is the
the truth because I've experienced it
now for eight years I've experienced the
change in my health my families have my
mental health so you guys are on a big
adventure and something we didn't talk
about earlier is why are we cleaning up
your farm well because we're shutting it
down because we're moving so it's really
excited actually we're gonna be going to
Tennessee to buy our dream land and
homestead and all that so that's kind of
the next part of the journey is how do I
take a backyard farm take it out to the
country and you know build a much bigger
really cool property so I'm excited to
show everybody what's next so tell us
like what do you envision what's your
ideal situation on so we're looking for
like five to ten acres you know
somewhere about like 30 to 50 minutes
outside of a major city now for the land
I want a little bit of flat a little bit
of everything like a little bit flat a
little bit of hills a little bit of
forest in the back maybe a stream or a
pond would be incredible don't have one
maybe I'll build a pond but yes
Tennessee is cool cuz it you know we get
50 inches of rain out there so it's like
you
the irrigate and a lot of fun things but
it'll be more difficult growing yeah a
lot of bugs the weather's more difficult
so different obstacles but this is one
that you guys have waited for for a long
time yeah very long time something
you've looked forward to for over a
decade okay yeah most of that probably
yeah I've been dreaming of having my own
land and they're getting to develop
whatever I want and doing you know a
crazy big very diverse complex system so
I'm excited to combine trees and
perennials and annuals all together
there's something awesome so if you guys
know of any cool places out there in
Tennessee I've got a lot of snow
[Music]
you guys thank you so much for joining
me tonight it has been so good to be
with you I know that I'm sitting at my
computer is so happy to be with you guys
really excited for 2020 I'm on this
mission to help as many people say yes
to their dreams say no to the limiting
beliefs and get started growing big in
their small space if you guys enjoyed
this video and it added value to your
life and you know other people who might
be interested in watching content like
this then I would ask that you join me
in this mission and helping as many
people as possible and share this video
share it with your friends with your
family post it on Facebook send it to a
friend and a text message because when
you share my videos YouTube goes oh oh
people like this content great
we shall push it along to more people
and so thank you in advance for sharing
some of these videos as I know you guys
do thanks for joining with me in this
mission to help as many people get
growing big in their small space and I'm
really looking forward to this year I'm
super excited for 2020 I'm really
excited for this video series and
bringing you guys as much content that
is inspirational encouraging and
empowering you to get started growing
big in your small space I feel like I've
said that 20 times but that's literally
the vision for 2020 is like how many
people can I help inspire empower and
equip to do this thing already like
everybody everybody can garden everybody
can garden I think we just get caught up
and we tell ourselves these lies like we
can't or you know my got my dreams of a
garden or my dreams on the farm don't
matter and I'm here to tell you
absolutely not like your dream of a
garden or a farm or whatever it may be i
100% believe that it's there for a
reason and I have seen amazing things
happen in my life from saying yes to my
dreams I have gotten to travel the
country I've met so many other
like-minded people and I'm just I'm 100%
convinced that we all have dreams in our
hearts for it reason and so I want to
help other people come alive to those
dreams and so thank you in advance for
partnering with
in that and I really hope that this
video blessed you if you want to
continue the party join me over on the
livestream where I'll be hanging out
with you guys for a little bit to say hi
cuz I missed you guys
and if you're catching this on the
replay I'm sorry you missed the live
stream but you can catch my videos every
Friday and I might pop in on Tuesdays
for like a two minute Tuesday we'll see
we shall see but for sure every Friday
so thanks again for joining me today you
guys I hope to see you live on the
livestream and if not I'll catch you in
the next one bye hi oh my god did you
get Congrats
[Music]