you hear the term regenerative practices
a lot and I'll I'll say that's something
that like I'm not sure exists um to me
like regenerative agriculture and
regeneration in general it's based on
principles and so a regenerative
practice doesn't necessarily exist
because there aren't practices that are
re regenerative right regeneration is an
outcome that we're trying to achieve and
so how do we achieve that outcome and
there's lots of different ways to do
that but it's kind of in the way that
you apply whatever practice it is
because any given practice can achieve a
regenerative outcome or it could
degenerate the same practice on
different operations in different uh
climates in different states different
rainfall areas and so you know I try to
keep that in mind that it's it's it's a
lot I say it's simpler it's more complex
than just practices it's it's how do you
apply principles