hello this is um
an additional presentation um to
understand how to make
and reproduce imo or indigenous
microorganisms
so what are indigenous microorganisms
they are microorganisms that have been
adapting and evolving in the native soil
for a very long time before we even came
here
so it's all about it's the diversity and
the life
that lives in the soil and connects the
trees under the soil
for them to share nutrients and
communicate
so there are mainly while there's many
and probably many that we don't even
know about
but there are fungi bacteria and yeasts
within these ones they kind of some of
them look like this in the piece of bark
that i'm showing
and the the important thing here is that
the more beneficial biodiversity we have
in the soil
the less chance for non-beneficial
microbes to reproduce
they also will add a big um
web like an extension on the roots of
trees so that they can be more drought
tolerant
and and we can boost their immune
systems and and resilience to
this ecosystem that we are if we harvest
them here
um so that our our crops and plants can
grow
a lot better
so where to harvest indigenous
microorganisms
so the best shot would be in nearby
forests that you can go into a
functional ecosystem
close by hopefully that you have access
to that
the closest the better so that um
you can go and find them there so
it's gonna be an expedition for sure
it's gonna be a nice way to connect
in the nature so you want to find
something that looks like a mycorrhizal
something like looks
something like the picture i showed you
in the bark they
they normally appear in leaves
like this white webs barks
um pieces of wood of course it has to be
a healthy soil full of
mulch that if you remove a little bit of
the leaves there you'll find
kind of like a white dish presence there
in the soil
that's the fungi that's the that's the
mycelium that you're looking for
a quick recommendation is that you
shouldn't harvest in a rainy season
you should at least wait for two days
with no rain
so that you can harvest the imo
so the benefits of
imo indigenous microorganisms is that
their drought tolerance they have
adapted to this place so they will
benefit
your plants to be more drought tolerant
this is a picture of how they look like
this is a picture of when we already
have reproduced them but that you can
understand how is it that they look like
this kind of white web in the soil
they also boost the immune system as we
said so these filaments they add to
plant roots
and they increase the ability to get
more nutrients in water
so the imo there's many steps on how to
make imo
so to start with the imo one
the first process is that um you cook
some rice i normally make one kilo of
rice but you can make as much as you
want
[Music]
and that will depend on the size of your
natural container
i'll show a picture of that but you want
a natural container like like a wooden
box
um that is not plastic however if you're
reusing plastic i guess it's okay as
long as
it can breathe that you can have um
some holes underneath that on the sides
for the biology to grow
so um it can be a canasta also
something that breeds that is made from
palm leaves or natural material is
most convenient so what you're gonna do
is
the cooked rice you're gonna put it in
your container
and then you're gonna cover it with a
paper cloth on top
so um you're gonna take this container
full of rice and you're gonna
full of cooked rice you're gonna go and
bury it
where you have found that fungi and
those branches
so um if you can you can dig a small
hole
and you place your container there and i
would recommend put some of the branches
full of the
fungi on top of the paper cloth never in
there never in the rice
so what what's going to happen is that
the biology
that lives in the soil is going to
travel through the paper cloth and
through the holes of the box
and it's going to go and reproduce in
the carbohydrate in this case it's the
rice
so you're going to leave it for five
days without getting wet that's very
important
um make sure that it's in a dry spot and
in case that it rains
or it's a rainy uh area maybe you want
to cover it a little bit
so that there's no rain on it so what's
going to happen is that
the biology is going to it's going to
reproduce in that carbohydrate
and it's going to heat up and then
you're going to have a big big colony
in that rice so that would be imo 1
to harvest them and after five days it's
gonna look something like this
where this webby stuff is reproducing
it is important not to add organic
matter in the rice
that was my first mistake and then it
was very difficult to get rid of that
you just want the pure rice with the
ecology with the biology
so avoid doing that adding the leaves
and stuff
in the rice the biology will spread in
in any ways in the carbohydrate so
it should smell nice and fresh if
there's a
smelly odor i would dispose it i would
throw it in your compost
but it should smell very nice very fresh
like the forest
and then once you have your rice full of
the biology
i would say that you live just one hour
until you start doing imo too so
you want to to harvest it when it's full
of life and you don't want to take too
long
because it can heat up way too much and
you can lose part of the biology
so with ny hour one hour we moved to imo
2.
and basically imo 2 is mix the equal
amount
of that rice full of fungi with brown
sugar
that's the only thing you have to do so
the sugar will absorb
the available water that is still in the
rice
and it's gonna make it not available
anymore so
they that the the biology go into a
dormant state and they release some
spores
and this way you can store imo from the
forest for a very long period of time
as you can see i have many samples that
i have taken in different
forests that i have found and it was not
necessarily a forest but it was a
very abundant natural sight that i found
one of them so to have the most
diversity possible
so you just grab that rice that you have
with the same weight the amount of black
of brown sugar and then you mix it in
one boil
in one bowl you don't really want to um
to press that hard on the rice once
you're mixing it
you just kind of want to gently and
evenly mix it
so um you don't want it to be too liquid
in case it's looking very liquid
i would add some of the brown rice on
top
of that imo so that you avoid that
that there's a lot more water because if
there's a lot of water then it's going
to react
and the bacteria is going to start
eating all that sugar
and it's not really going to store very
well so um
i wouldn't use that as a primary imo in
case that happens
just make sure that it's not too liquid
that is consistent and it's
uh and it's more solid
so always i i use a sugar a brown sugar
cap on once i'm finished uh mixing the
rice with the sugar
just add a little bit of brown sugar on
top
to make sure that there's not going to
be excessive moisture
and this you can store with a breedable
lid
you can store um in a place without
direct sunlight
and it can be good for for a long period
of time
and you should have many of these and
this is the way that you're already
relating with the natural biology
and implementing it in your soil is the
best fertilizer
so once you decide you already want to
take your biology out of the dormant
state
it's called imo 3 step number 3
and i'll briefly go through how to
activate and reproduce
10 gallons of imo
so of course you're going to use your
imo 2 and you're going to have several
inputs
that are going to help that reproduction
so
fpj is the first one or fermented plant
juice
and you use 0.3 ounces for them
you use brown rice vinegar same amount
sea water so
if in case you don't have sea water it
would be great to go on a little trip to
the ocean
and otherwise i guess you could order it
online
a little bit of um of seawater or
you know just the best way that you can
get sea water
be okay 5.3.3 ounces
humic acid in liquid form is best
um so the imo 2
now i just use one finger and then
water 1. 24 gallons
so what you want to do here is that you
want to make a kind of
of a tea so in the water you're going to
add all your inputs and you're going to
mix it gently
so that the sea water and a humic acid
is gonna
is gonna enhance the fungi fungal
activity is gonna give them enough
nutrients to reproduce
so um
i'm gonna briefly say how to make plant
fermented plant juice
so in this case i used moringa because
it's produced
here locally organic so i got a lot of
it
fresh so what you want is to harvest
your plant
and it it can be a local weed
if you want a wheat that you know that
has a lot of potassium and magnesium a
lot of
nutrients one that you see that is
thriving
in the environment that you live in so
what we want is to extract those
nutrients so we can give them back to
our plants
to our biology
so i used moringa and i used brown sugar
and so
um i cut them and i mix them i i cut
them
very small so that the juices can come
out and i added the sugar i just mix it
in
in a bucket with my hands and once you
do that already there's some moisture
coming out
and then what you want is to let it sit
for two weeks
maybe a week is is enough but just
make sure that that it remains liquid
that is going to stay liquid
so that the fermentation can start
and um when when i did this i had to
extract it didn't look very liquid
although it had some liquid i had to
take out the moringa
and just really really press it with my
hand so i could get all the liquid out
and then that's how i stored it with a
breathable lid
so this is briefly how you make fpj or
fermented plant use
juice you can use um
a plant that you see that is thriving
and with the sugar you're going to be
able to get its nutrients
and ferment it so you can give it back
to
our biology
so along with the inputs of the imo 3
you need 5 gallons of
carbs and 5 gallons of carbon
maybe you can check what is available
locally for you
what i use uh in this case is five
gallons of wheat bran
that is very easy to find here and five
gallons of cacao shells
it's a very good smell i mix them even
mix them evenly
because the wheat is going to cause um
it's a carb and it's going to make
the biology heat up a lot so i try to
stabilize it with the cacao shells that
is not only the wheat bran because
if your temperature goes above 120
fahrenheit
then most of the beneficial
biology will die because of the heat
so when it's dry you mix your your
calves and your carbs and your carbon
you mix them well
and then you add your liquids
including the imo 2. so once you add the
liquids you really
try to mix it thoroughly um
and you want to use a natural box for
that because if you use plastic
then um the the part
of the imo 3 that is against the plastic
can become an aerobic and this is
something that happened to me as well
so you really want a breathable box
whether it's wood or cardboard
something like that so this is
when i already mixed my inputs with the
carbs and the carbon
and it's it looks like this this one
smells like chocolate cake
so it has to always have a good smell
and so after five days
you have to turn it every day so that it
doesn't heat up that it never goes past
120 fahrenheit
so mix it every day i do it with my
hands you can use a shovel
you just really want to move it you know
not
for it not to become an aerobic and you
know that that
you can keep that aeration stabilization
this is this happened one and on the
second day
this photo and it looks so beautiful
just to see that much ecology uh biology
just thriving right there
but yeah it will look something like
this
if you're in a very dry climate you may
need to regulate
the moisture it happened to me that i
use cardboard because cardboard absorbs
a lot of water
it dried up in three days you really
want it
you want it to be at least five days
that it's reproducing so it can really
colonize
all the all the grains so uh
you may add a little bit of water not
too much just to keep that
going for in case it's drying up and you
feel that
the moisture is not correct the moisture
should be um
you can press it with your hands but it
doesn't really stay like a ball it just
has like a little bit of
compression but it falls apart that's
that's what you're looking for
in cold climates it may take a longer
time than five days just stay vigilant
and be open to
to make mistakes and do it again just
always keep an eye on them
they look something like this they're
very very beautiful
so in the end after the five days it
should look something like this
so you get this um these chunks
of they will colonize these chunks
and if you open them up you you
shouldn't open all of them but
if you open them up they should look
something like this very webby in there
it looks um it looks very good it smells
great
and those are good biology for our soil
the native biology
and you can store that in a natural uh
in a wooden box in a closed wooden box
you can store that
for some weeks and from this you can
make
you can make certain things you can make
liquid imo
or you can just mix the imo 3
the finished product with your native
with your native soil and the same
inputs so that you can
build soil that's how we really build um
native soil again you mix your native
soil with the with the biology
and then you have that soil full of that
um
or microorganisms you know that are
going to
stabilize are going to help with the
restoration of our soils
and to make liquid imo which is very
easy to add
you just need this amounts of um fpj
same brown rice vinegar seawater humic
acid
imo 2 or imo 3 is ok to use
when making liquid imo and your water
important that when you're making liquid
imo since we mainly have fungi
you need a narrator something looking
like this
i got something like this with at least
two
tubes giving oxygen you can use um
your stones you can add the end of the
tube to a stone you can make that
oxygen rock and it goes in the bottom so
that you can always have this
stimulation for 36 hours
and then you have your liquid indigenous
microorganisms that you can add to your
soil and to your plants
so i hope that was helpful on how to
make
in written reproduce indigenous
microorganisms
that is uh has been very helpful for us
it is super fun
to do and that way you make sure that
you're working with the available
native biology which is most important
thank you