welcome to this series on mastitis in
dairy cows brought to you by the
University of Edinburgh this video is
the hygiene in the shed
let the cows tell you a scoring system
mastitis is the infection of the milk
producing glands the other bacteria
invade the teat end via the teat canal
and cause an infection mastitis is a
fight between bacteria invading the
other and the cow fighting the infection
hygiene in the sheds let the cows tell
you there are many different housing
systems depending on the number of cows
and the space that they have clean cows
mean the system is working
daddy cows means it needs attention
clean cows will have less mastitis
hygiene scouring this lets the cows tell
you if you have a problem each cow is
called in three areas on a scale of 0 to
2 the areas are the flank including the
tail the lower hind leg and the other
houses caught in this areas as follows
clean cows with only splashes of manure
score a zero if there's more than a
palm-sized amount of dirtiness it's
called a 1 if there's more than a four
I'm length of dirtiness then score a two
any score of two suggests is a problem
of shed hygiene if only the lower hind
legs are dirty then the problem is
likely to be cleaning of passageways or
drainage where the cows are working if
the other and the lower part of the cows
are dirty then it is a problem with
where the cows are lying if it is around
the tail on the flank where the tail
swishes is it a problem of diarrhea is
there a problem with the diet if the
dirtiness is all over is there perhaps a
problem with overcrowding or manure
removal
you