hi guys it's Matt the stoned ape farmer
coming to you from farmer all and I just
wanted to talk to you a bit about
gardening without irrigation and if you
can see all this lovely corn behind me
but it's been grown without any
irrigation other than rainfall and I
want to talk to you a bit about some of
the techniques I used here and
throughout the garden to reduce or
eliminate my need to irrigate let's go
check it out
[Music]
so here's a close-up of my corn it's
part of my three sisters bed and the
corns finally tall enough that I just
planted my beans the other day and I
haven't popped up yet
one of the things you might notice is a
little interesting is that this corn is
planted in a little depression and in
fact all of the corn plant in little
depressions and in the in-between
depressions it's filled with woodchips
and you can see you little squash
popping up right there what these
depressions do is capture any rainwater
that falls and forces them forces that
rain water towards the plants you see
water follows the basic rules of physics
if you put it on a high mound it's going
to roll off but if you capture it in a
basin it'll stay there and slowly sink
in and because our summers are typically
3 to 4 months of drought during the
rainy season I want as much water as
possible to penetrate the ground right
here where I'm growing the corn now the
reason I have wood chips in between all
these little pockets of corn is because
those are placeholders where I'm going
to be planting my winter squash and the
wood chips do a couple of things first
of all they provide weed suppression
since there's nothing growing right
there now to block out weeds to shade
them out so what chips do that for me I
have a few little weeds yeah this guy
right here
couple of these guys right here
poro quick but for the most part I
haven't really had weeds coming up in
this does it read it we did really well
before I planted the corn and I put the
woodchips in to prevent weeds coming up
in between the corn but the other thing
that the woodchips do is they stop
evaporation if I come down here and open
this up what that is mind you this isn't
good soil this is this is mostly clay so
the woodchips are also gonna break down
and help make the soil a little bit
nicer than it is right now
now mulch and weed suppression are both
great because on the one hand you're
preventing evaporation and on the other
hand you're preventing transpiration
transpiration is actually according to
Steve Solomon who has done the most work
in dry farming at least in contemporary
times corn Steve Solomon most of the
water lost is actually through
transpiration and that's the water
evaporating off of the leaves of the
plants so wherever you can eliminate
weeds you're going to conserve a lot of
your water one of the other things
that's important for gardening without
irrigation is plant spacing now most
people are under the impression that the
wide spacing between rows that's
recommended on packets of seeds has to
do with farm equipment and being able to
get machinery between rows of plants
it's actually the other way around
before there was plumbing and pumped
water people didn't irrigate their crops
and the machinery was designed to work
with those spacings in mind
you see if you leave more spacing
between the plants that can put out
larger root systems without having to
compete with each other and then they
can mind their own nutrients and water
without having to have them provided
non-stop as you might be able to see
here if the corn isn't shading my
measuring tape my core plants are about
18 inches apart and that's up from the 8
to 12 inches that's usually recommended
generally you want about 50% more
spacing than the packets recommend in
order to go without irrigating your
crops and this is with pretty minimal
rainfall like I said we get three to
four months of drought throughout our
main growing season here and these corn
plants will not need to be irrigated at
all even with all of the drought you may
have noticed all of this rotting
firewood in the background this was all
from my landlady we had a bunch of
rotten firewood because of a leak in her
shed and she was just going to toss it
down a bank well I went and recovered
all of it saved her the work of moving
it and this will be another part of my
water saving strategy let's go check
that out know if you'll take a look at
this hot mess on the other side of my
kale plants you see that my kale plants
are doing fine without irrigation
they've gotten regular temperatures into
the 90s although it's been a weird year
and we've been fluctuating between cool
temps and hot temps either doing fine
because I've kept the wide spacing so
that they don't have to compete for
water
but the idea here is that I'll dig out
all these paths and I'll fill them with
that rotted wood that you saw basically
I'm creating Hugo paths and many of you
are probably familiar with the idea of
Hugo culture at this point the idea that
you dig a trench or just lay wood on the
soil cover it with more soil and that
becomes your garden bed now as the wood
breaks down it acts like a sponge and
soaks up any excess rainwater and during
periods a drought it will release it
into your bed one of the things the Hugo
culture is intended to do is to because
it's a mound it'll shed excess water
like if it's way too much it'll shed
that water to keep your bed from
becoming waterlogged well I don't want
that because that is designed for areas
where the rain is pretty constant
throughout the year that is not the case
here we get three to four months of
drought during the main growing season
when I really need a lot of water so the
idea is I'll take out all of the paths
between the rows and the main kitchen
garden and I'll fill them with that
rotted wood and I'll cover it back over
with the soil you see there that I've
dug out but I'll leave a very slight
depression over the path and that's
where the water will settle during the
rainy season well that'll seep in soak
into the wood and then when we get
around to our drought II season it can
kind of release back into the beds on
either side of course I'll cover the
pass with with woodchips so they don't
become muddy mess but then what I'm
doing is I'm actually storing all of
that water that would just run off with
traditional Hugo culture and I'm saving
it up for our dry season you can see
that might kill plants are a good two
feet apart in the row and about three
feet apart between the rows and I'm
hoping that once these Hugo paths are
good and established that what will
happen is I'll be able to plant things
much closer together and cram more stuff
in the same amount of space I still want
to maintain wide spacing it's easier to
weed it's easier to harvest and it still
gives you that protection from drought
but by adding this extra redundancy into
my water saving I will be able to get a
little bit more production out while
still maintaining a complete lack of
irrigation now I've already talked about
mulch at least wood mulch but a lot of
people get hung up on what mulch they're
using it really isn't important what you
use as long as you're keeping the soil
covered so here's this beautiful cabbage
starting to get some size on it finally
and you'll notice that here I don't use
wood chips I could it wouldn't be my
first choice and I can't get enough of
them to use in my garden beds but I
don't need them
I have laws of space here that just
growing grass and weeds and I can go
through and clear it out and get this
nice straw that I can put down and if I
pull it back you can see that the soil
is nice and moist here again this isn't
good soil this is this is terrible clay
there's there's a little bit of organic
matter on it but it's it's mostly just
garbage these plants don't care as long
as they've got a little bit of mulch a
little bit of organic matter so that the
microbes in the soil can start doing
their thing and as long as they're
getting the moisture which they are
because you know that mulch is keeping
the soil covered and protected I don't
care use whatever weeds grass clippings
woodchips heck I've seen some people use
rocks I'd really hate to have rocks in
my garden but there's a perennial
planting then sure maybe of course the
one downside with something like rock is
that you're not getting the organic
matter which is why I would go for
really anything oh there's a random
stick here anything that's growing and
gets cut back can go in the garden or
put it on top don't mix it in because
that'll tie up nitrogen but if you leave
it on top worms and microbes and
everything will slowly break it down and
add nutrients to your soil well holding
in the moisture so like I said you can
use literally anything as a mulch and
one of the problems I'm having right now
is that the weed eaters broke and I
don't have access to all of that fresh
straw hay from chopping down all the
grass and weeds growing around the
property but you can use anything one of
the other things that
Steve Solomon teaches is to use Dutch
best mulch he's actually very opposed to
using deep mulch in the gardens which I
don't agree with but one of the great
things that he teaches if you don't have
enough organic matter to most a garden
with is to use a dust mulch it still
protects the soil even if it doesn't add
in organic matter and helps hold in
moisture so here's another row scores an
era and I'm surprised this many came up
because it was old seed but what you
might notice in between the rows is that
there is no mulch now you probably see
all this cracking right around the
plants that's what clay soil does when
it rains really hard and then it dries
out the surface dries out faster than
the lower soil and it cracks as it loses
the moisture and contracts so because I
haven't been able to get enough mulch to
mulch this what I do is after a hard
rain I come through with a hoe and I
just break up this top layer and
although it doesn't add organic matter
into the soil it does act like a mulch
in the sense that it prevents
evaporation if I dig down here a little
bit get in to this terrible clay
and see that it's still nice and wet
garbage play but it's nice and wet
because it's protected under this dust
mulch and that's one of the things that
Steve Solomon teaches about dry
gardening just that well he's the posed
to mulch in general except for the
Deaf's mulch but a just mulch is just as
good if you can't get actual organic
matter to mulch your gardens with yeah
well add nutrients in like organic
matter well when it breaks down it won't
feed the soil working the soil organisms
like mulch will when it breaks down but
from a water conservation standpoint
it's just as good as organic matter now
one other thing that I don't really want
to show because plants haven't popped up
yet but this is one of the ways the
Native Americans taught settlers to
garden when they first got here the
garden in Hills now a hill doesn't
necessarily mean that you have a pile of
soil that's raised up above ground level
it just refers to planting in clumps
with space in between them rather than
in rows so the idea here is that even on
completely virgin ground overgrown with
weeds as I've been worked at all you can
still start a garden bare out of space
it's about 18 inches plant your seeds
there go over four feet do another one
four feet do another one four feet do
another one four feet do another one
what you accomplish with this is that
you have your plants and in this case
yeah just like with the corn I made a
little depression so that it would
capture water plant seed in the middle
and because I'm leaving four feet of
spacing between they won't have to
compete with each other for water I
still need to go through and clear some
weeds out but they're pretty sparse to
begin with and I'll be able to drop all
these weeds down in between the plants
and any others that come up and there'll
be my mulch in between the plants this
is really the way to go if you need to
get a lot of plants in the ground and
you don't have a clear spot to put them
you don't need these nice nice and neat
little rows you don't need you know to
rototill you don't need to come clear a
bunch of weeds and stuff literally get a
hoe I like this big grub hoe here clear
little spot put your seeds in the ground
move to the next spot put them in which
is exactly why these ended up here this
was not my plan at the beginning of the
season but I had issues with my cucumber
seeds not germinating when I put them in
the ground I think this year was a weird
year and it's been way wetter than it
usually is and a lot of my seeds just
ended up rotting in the ground because
it was cold and wet so I pre germinated
some on paper towel and ended up with
way more than I need well I didn't want
them to go to waste so I ended up making
these little Hills at the edge of the
garden to put them in and they might end
up just being sacrificial plants for the
deer and that'll be okay if it keeps
them out of the main garden
now one more thing that I didn't mention
or mentioned only briefly with the
cucumbers in the Hills is that if I'm
not expecting rain for a while and I
need to plant something I soaked or pre
germinate my seeds now that's what I did
with my beans I need to plant them in
around my corn and the three sisters bed
but we aren't expecting rain for a while
so I went ahead and sucked my beans
overnight
I didn't chit them or pre germinate them
like I did with the cucumbers but I did
soak them ahead of time so that they
would have plenty of moisture to
germinate that's one of the things you
can do if you're not expecting any rain
for a while to get things to germinate
outside of the rainy season I'll go
ahead and show you some okra seeds that
I have started to show you what it looks
like if you take them all the way to the
pre germination stage since I haven't
gotten those in the ground yet no okra
doesn't grow here quite famously because
our nights are too cold and it just
doesn't like that but I got this variety
from a local seed supplier and it's
supposed to tolerate our cool weather
and start producing relatively fast food
so I thought I would give it a try you
can see that what I've done here is go
ahead and roll them up in a wet paper
towel and leave them in an open ziplock
bag overnight it's actually been a
couple of nights now but they started
sprouting last night and I just left
that bag in a sunny window check on them
every once awhile to see when these
little roots are starting to form and
that's when they're ready to go in the
ground I actually could have done it
last night because they already go then
and the roots wouldn't have been so long
and fragile but it was hot last night
and I didn't want to go out now this is
one way
that you can eliminate watering when
you're trying to get things to germinate
just wrap them up in a moist paper towel
or even soak them overnight and let them
absorb all the water they need to
germinate before you ever even put them
in the ground that way you don't have to
irrigate while they're out there they
don't have the soil constantly being
cooled down because you're watering it
and they'll take off a lot better all
right guys that's it for this video hope
some of these tips help you out with
your gardening so that you don't have to
irrigate as much or you can go without
your getting at all again use
depressions when you can to help capture
extra rainfall plant your things further
apart about 50% more than the package
recommends use mulch wherever you can if
you can't get enough of mulch then use a
dust mulch just after heavy rain come
through with a hoe and just kind of
scratch the top inch or so of the soil I
mean I don't like doing that but given
my lack of mulch this year that's the
best way to do it incorporate organic
matter I already talked about that with
the mulch but compost is another great
way to do that it'll hold in extra
moisture and you know if you can do a
little bit of Hugo culture to really a
soak up some of that water then go ahead
and give that a try there are some other
tips that I have that I'll share you
know as I get around to it as I get good
examples of them going but those are the
big things for now and I hope it's
helpful and you guys have a good one
[Music]
you