once again thanks for thanks for
inviting me it's it's fun to be here I
did spend i am at Oregon State
University now and but I spent 18 years
at Montana State University so I kind of
know the the the Northern Plains and had
a lot of exposure to some of the animal
agriculture out there so my my talk is
adopting policies and priorities that
might help encourage some of these these
activities that we'd like to see and I
guess one other observation that I had
is you know just walking outside in the
in the lobby in the 10 years that I've
been or 12 years or more than I've been
seriously doing climate change there's
been a sea change in terms of what's
happening in terms of people not yet not
embracing as much as but seeing the
economic opportunities associated with
some of these changes and that's a
really good thing it's going to you know
15 20 years ago I was doing climate
change research in Montana and a group
of growers gave us a t-shirt and the
t-shirt said Montanans for climate
change and it showed people shivering
and things like that and so it was a it
was a very different environment that it
will question why we do in climate
change and I think that has been a
really kind of a theme going on here is
that you know there's winners and losers
there's some people that will benefit
from this and I think what we need to do
as a whole is to is to try to design
policies that are also climate smart
policies and that will speak to the
benefits of doing both of those ok so
the themes I want to talk about once
again I will probably not spend a lot of
time on this but just what do we mean by
this climate smart agriculture concept
some of the policies and goals and how
do we get there and once again
integrating economics as we've heard in
many of the presentations this morning
is really critical it's got to be
economically viable economically
sustainable or you know then it's just
an exercise if not and so we really need
to pay attention
to that background of course science has
always led to better policy we'd like to
see it lead to better policy faster but
I think that's been the history of this
integrated research but the details are
important as I said we need to know how
do we integrate across the sciences and
there's been like I said a lot of work
in the economics area that I'm involved
in on efficiency as well as other values
that we that we care about poverty
vulnerability natural capital ecosystems
and so we can just move a little bit
from that okay so climate smart
agriculture is kind of a very recent
term it's been defined by FAO in 2010
and it's composed of basically three
pillars there one is to increase
sustainability sustainably increased
production productivity and incomes
adopt and build resilience and then deal
with the greenhouse gas emissions
wherever possible and I think this was a
form of yours too we're looking for that
sweet spot that we can and hopefully
it's a little bit bigger than the red
one that you showed I'd like to see that
being expanded so why is it needed we
heard this from the earlier
presentations as well is that we're
going to have to feed a larger
population we've got climate change
happening and that can lead to
reductions in many cases and lower
incomes in very vulnerable areas and so
a lot of the CSA climate smart
agriculture was very concerned not just
with the US but with what's happening in
developing countries and people that are
pretty much living on the margin and
once again in 2005 agriculture did
account for about 13 and a half percent
of the GHG emissions so the approach
then for the climate smart agriculture
is basically coordinated efforts toward
these resilient pathways but we got to
do that in the following way we've got
to build this evidence which i think is
what Megan it was just great to see your
study and see some of the other studies
that have been out here in terms of
building evidence
identifying viable options and tools
that will assess these different
technologies and then also as we all
know you've got to increase the local
institutional effectiveness we've got a
force to some kind of coherence between
climate energy and AG policies and then
we've got a link on climate and
agricultural financing this is
incredibly important at the end it's not
a new approach it's been around under
different names there's a short history
there like I said it really has been in
the last five years that it's been kind
of recast as this climate smart egg as
opposed to just dealing with the
changing climate or wood sustainability
and resilience it's this is kind of a
nice schematic here it shows that it
builds on what was first referred to as
sustainable development poverty
reduction environmental risk and then
it's also come under the little more
encompassing name of a green economy
where we're looking at carbon emission
reductions resource use efficiency
enhancements and now today's version is
more of a climate smart agriculture and
I think that's because of two concerns
one is not just dealing with the
environmental concerns and sustainable
development concerns but also this issue
with food security and agricultural
production improvement so looking at a
little bit broader and putting all of
all the pieces together here so there's
been this kind of a schematic that's not
mine I borrowed it from John beddington
in the this schematic really talks about
these goals of climate smart agriculture
in terms of a safe operating space and
the safe operating space really is from
a very you know high level view is we
want to sort of increase that sweet spot
or that safe operating space in there
such that the bigger it is the more
resilient we as a planet we as a society
will be in terms of being able to adopt
to
more changes going on and things like
that so if if that sweet space and that
safe space is really the space that's
sustainable is very small then we're
kind of pretty fragile in terms of some
of the some of the things we have so
those three lines there the orange lines
are basically represent some
relationship between food production and
climate change so the climate change due
to the food system means that as we get
more climate change happening oh I'm
sorry as we get more food production
occurring under the existing
technologies we're going to see more
climate change or more greenhouse gas
emissions occurring the the global food
needs one is a graph that just
represents our food needs in a temporal
sense as population increases and then
finally the maximum food production is
just is trade-off between food
production and climate change so we can
play around with those graphs and so
what we can look at here is that if we
want to look at the global food needs
under a changing climate what we can
oops what's happening here okay right so
what we're looking at is policies that
might try to shift that curve down such
that we are increasing the safe space by
looking at new global food needs and
what would some of those be kind of
eliminating the waste in the food chain
being able to make better use of the
food that we have okay so for any given
climate at any given climate or whether
point in time we can actually the food
needs from the primary production would
be reduced because we're having less
waste going on if we're looking at how
to improve maximum food production we'd
be shifting this other graph that's a
little slow on the uptake here and so
improving maximum food production would
be looking at policies that would be
shifting that curve out and those
policies would be things
drought management adaptive grazing
methods perhaps for agriculture
livestock and maybe matching livestock
intensities to the environment and then
finally the third graph is how to
mitigate climate change from agriculture
and in this case we'd want to increase
that safe space by actually trying to
think of it as shifting the the climate
change due to the food system graph back
and that would be things like mitigation
policies and stuff increase on-site
greenhouse gas decrease the on-site
greenhouse gas emissions capture co2 etc
so that's kind of how this this graph
has been used so what is the u.s. doing
to enhance climate smart agriculture
well as as be said and we've got these
climate hubs there's a lot of activities
going on that really are in the that
fall under this umbrella of the climate
hubs we've got global research alliances
feed the future climate clean air and
then the u.s. global climate change
initiative these are all pieces really
important pieces of what's happening in
the policy avena to promote a more
sustainable climate smart agriculture so
this alliance has been the most recent
of these lists of global efforts and
it's a number of countries at a number
of organizations the problem is it
doesn't have a lot of teeth to it
there's nothing mandatory about this
it's all voluntary and I'll talk a
little bit about that in a few minutes
so the key characteristics once again
it's voluntary however it's trying to
develop these enabling environments that
would encourage the adoption of some of
these approaches and it's also engaging
with business foundations and civils on
society etc so
joining to a little more policies in the
US so the question that we ask in a lot
of the research I do is so what about
the farm bill what's happening with the
policies that we currently have in the
farm bill do they incentivize resilience
to climate stresses that are consistent
with climate smart agriculture what
types of tools policy tools might be
available to promote a more climate
smart agriculture and most importantly
what do we need to know and what do we
know and how is that gap being being
filled so the farm bill everybody here
knows it's basically the primary AG
policy tool there's different titles in
the farm bill 12 of them the ones I
circled are primarily the ones that work
to deal with some of the climate smart
agriculture the three orange ones deal
with commodity programs conservation and
crop insurance and then we have a
research title in the farm bill which
indirectly is probably the strongest
piece of legislation that we have to
continue to fund some of the research
that's needed meg and I think you know
yours are the great example of this type
of policy and then the distributions so
I looked a little bit at some of these
different titles and in the farm bill
and the + next to it means that i think
it is moving us in the direction of
climate smart agriculture so
conservation compliance basically limits
conservation requirements to crop
insurance premiums etc the farms that
have highly available lands or wetlands
have to follow this conservation program
to receive the government payments and
so the question is what happens with the
conservation compliance it's a shift
toward working lands there's an equip
program and so in terms of my safe space
diagram i think that the conservation
can result in an outward shift of the
food system curve which is going to
increase that safes that um that safe
space and helps to stabilize food
production
so manure management to curb greenhouse
gas emissions I'm trying to do a little
bit with respect to the the animal
agriculture costly but but effective for
greenhouse gas emissions is these
innovators there's a Douglas great study
at WSU that was done around 2010
currently the economic viability hinges
on how to finance and the potential
revenue so the operating costs versus
the capital costs the revenues from
somebody operating a digester come from
electricity and renewable fuel the fiber
products in the nutrients that are
by-products carbon credits if they were
to exist and then payments for ecosystem
enhancements and once again another case
of shifting and making that safe space
bigger commodity programs I'm just not
going to spend a lot of time on these
because I think most people are familiar
with them but the commodity programs
covered commodities include wheat oats
barley etc they can cause this safe
space to increase perhaps by improving
the maximum food production but as we
all know there is some downsides with
some of the commodity programs and so
they s why I have a plus and a minus up
there they may increase their income
make them more resilient but it doesn't
necessarily encourage adaptation to
other programs that we may want in to
deal with climate change drought
management basically the drought
management policies could encourage
flexibility and increase resilience the
earlier paper that Justin did is a great
example of what can happen if we were to
get proper drought management policies
in place or better drought management
policies in place and so once again here
I think I've got the drought management
could also basically increase the safe
space by sort of shifting the the
maximum food production curve out
adaptive management a.m.p grazing
management this is another
policy short intensive braising followed
by long recovery so once again looking
at how do we grade so vain how do we
graze those lands the claim in some of
the studies is that cattle grazing using
this amt may increase productivity and
store more co2 so that's one of the
claims the adaptive it's adaptive touch
it is an adaptive type of carbon capture
and storage the question is it really
hasn't been quantified and in order to
quantify those claims we would have to
be we would have to be able to go out
there and measure the increase or the
decrease of the change in soil carbon as
a result of this a.m p versus the
current system that might be in place
and then we need to know the economic
dimensions what's happening to the
weight of those animals what's happening
to some of the products going on and
once again this would be a case of
increasing that safe space for climate
smart agriculture so designing policies
just a few more minutes and then take
some questions designing policies
fundamentals is that incentives matter
economists are always coming back to
this we need to understand those
trade-offs and the opportunity costs I
can skip over this okay so some of the
tools that we have that we're developing
for better informing our policies are
both at the landscape level as well as
at the farm level so once again ah
premise is that farmers and ranchers are
the ones that are making the
on-the-ground decisions and so I think
it's really important that we develop
tools for them to use and so that the
landscape level these are the ones these
big models the swap model the epic model
and then we have one at Montana State I
mean at Oregon State called the
trade-off analysis model it started at
Montana State at the farm level these
are the ones that we were that have been
we've been looking at AG tools or AG biz
logic which is the one that
be talked about is comes under these
farm level decision tools and basically
they're designed to help Boaz or van
choose make operational choices the AG
the AG tools on the on the right-hand
side there is basically our software
which can which is being developed now
web-based and it has a number of sub
programs in there AG profit a Gleason AG
finance and then AG environment this is
once again the same the same flavor and
theme that Justin was talking about in
terms of what he was looking at so the
farm level decision tool this AKA we
nicknamed TurboTax platform for two
reasons one is that it's going to take
information from the growers tax returns
and populate it into this program but
it's also one that allows the growers to
be able to fine tune it for their
situation so what has been what are
their list of imports what has been
their their experience in terms of
yields or outputs and so the decision
tool has these kind of components to it
the first is we want to use this
platform to ask questions for the grower
to ask questions you know should I
change my crop rotation or my raising
rates and invest in new equipment or
invest in other kinds of inputs based on
expected changes in climate and crop
yields that may come along with some of
the climate changes that was seeing the
other thing is it has to it's going to
gather this data on their inputs and
other spatially relevant data on their
yields it's going to take all of that
information and run it through the
scenario the scenario that we have these
sub sub routines that we have using
different scenarios to look at basic
outcomes and how the economic and
environmental outcomes will change as
the scenarios change so we've done this
with the wheat and this
is what he was referring to we ran
through this egg tools with them without
climate change and we show that yes in
order to deal with and adjust to climate
change this farmer this farmer would be
better off switching his annual propping
rotation to something that includes seed
oil and canola so once again just
comparing those those two bottom circles
there so the application so I was
thinking a little bit about the
application of AG tools to livestock and
clocks eved is doing this and I think
one of the big pluses of a tool like
this is it's going to allow the growers
to make sense of all of the data that
they have that there and make sense of
it on something that means something to
their operation and not just here is a
typical ranch and so I think trying to
drill down and get it to be as relevant
as possible so what what we're doing in
clocks eva is actually doing this in
oregon for some of the livestock
operations is setting up these baseline
budgets and information making them
site-specific talking with growers and
with ranchers to decide what are the
scenarios that we need to be addressing
and then to explore what those under
those scenarios are their current
operations economically viable
incorporate precip forecasts download
downscaled climate data and information
and then i think step four is really
important when I use TurboTax I tend to
do a lot of different scenarios on how
should I what should I be doing with my
income should I be investing it here and
here and being able to compare those
well AG tools is going to allow a
venture or a grower to do the same kind
of thing is to be able to say how much
better or for worse off would I be if I
were to switch how I manage my operation
when we see changes in climate coming or
changes in play
is or changes in technology so it's
going to be used in a relative sense as
opposed to an absolute sense and being
able to allow the grower or the venture
to be able to explore those and
understand those trade-offs and you know
what I can stop here because this is
this is kind of repetitive of what other
people have I think come up with what is
quite far as presented what does climate
change mean for agriculture some of the
direct and the indirect impacts and so
this gives me a flavor of what are the
kind of things we need to be modeling
and capturing in a tool like AG tools
yeah I can just stop there great thanks
and I know we have the governor coming
on in about five minutes so late okay
great one question for me
in Western Hemisphere we don't have that
much problem with production of
agricultural I think the problem is
mainly the distribution of it version of
the distribution lies in comparison with
safe space yeah I don't think it is
actually captured that well because
that's a much high level issue you know
I think you're exactly right you know we
talk about food security we probably
have plenty of food on aggregate it's
just not in the right places at the
right time and so I think that that is
an area that hasn't been captured at
least in that diagram it has been people
are paying a lot of attention to it you
know or again we're pretty wealthy in
terms of you know the outside world
looking in but we've got a lot of hunger
and a lot of issues and it's you know so
it's not just the aggregate that's
important it's the distribution and it's
looking at the winners and the losers
and usually the losers are oftentimes
low-income and so paying attention to
some of those those concerns as well and
not just always feeding more I think the
other thing on a little bit on that food
demand is you know that there's a lot of
effort going on on trying to minimize
the waste if you look at some of the
statistics on how much food is wasted
and thrown away and not consumed or used
you know if we can minimize that then
the amount of land we need to bring into
production or the types of may be much
less than we think if we can get some of
those numbers down so yeah sure
the one I didn't talk about the Toa the
landscape level tool will do some of
that at a bigger higher landscape and in
that one what we actually have is
trade-offs between some of the
environmental outcomes and then we've
modeled the agricultural outcomes as
they grow up may produce a commodity as
well as produce ecosystem services for
example a carbon offsets or that
commodity he could make choices or she
could make choices between producing
some of the grain crops for actual
grains versus energy and so there could
be those those kinds of things but in
but at the landscape level one at the
farm level one now but that's a that's a
great example one of USDA's new calls
for purple not USDA I guess it's USDA is
it that the one that has the food food
systems energy and water Nexus yeah that
one is I think really really important
it's hard to yeah we need to capture
those complexities on you know what
gives there sure
Zoomers by encouraging climates
labeling and
yeah I don't know for sure it's not my
area there probably is I guess it's
probably something where people are
looking at the consumer demand how much
more people willing to pay could this be
the more interesting part of what you
have is you know can this be somehow
marketed that this was I guess it gets
into the area of sustainable or you know
not organic but produced sustainably so
I think the climate smart agriculture
like I said that whole movement grew out
of fao in a lot of concern with
developing countries and looking at you
know what are the what are the options
and what are some of the ways that we
can keep that safe space from shrinking
down more and more because if we just do
business as usual the projections are
those those you know curves are going to
start condensing in and then that safe
space for producing food and sustaining
our climate will be shrinking and so the
idea is how do we keep it from shrinking
down or it's all get to expand yeah all
right thanks