hi i'm albert bates what i'm going to do
today is walk you through the process
that we use
uh here in my community at the farm and
at the ecovillage training center to
make biochar and we object the
objectives of how we do it are to make
it very simple and easy and very
accessible and low cost
it's not perfect in fact it's going to
lose some carbon dioxide back to the
atmosphere that could be saved if we did
it a slightly different way
but in the process that we use
you don't need very many tools
and
you can do this
yourself
at home
in
a very small area
we like to use bamboo because we have a
lot of it
and because it grows very quickly
and so we're going to be using bamboo to
make biochar we'll make about
two wheelbarrow loads in 45 minutes
and i have a lot of bamboo at the moment
because it grows fast
fastest growing plant
on the terrestrial surface of the earth
and this is my feedstock for making
biochar for cutting bamboo i'm using two
simple tools loppers and a saber saw
battery powered
and i have a lot of bamboo coming into
my garden it's been creeping past the
fence
so now i'm going in and i'm cutting it
back i'm going to take it and trim it
down and make it suitable for
the biochar kiln that i'm going to build
and right now i'm just taking it all
down and
stacking it letting it dry in the sun so
it's good and dry before we burn it
just those two simple tools loppers and
the saber saw
now we're cutting the bamboo's uh
branches off using the machete that's
another tool
and after we've done that we can cut the
trim it down to size
uh using a table saw that we've moved
out into the forest there
this makes it very easy to trim the
bamboo combs down to the right size for
to fit our kiln
and after we've done that we're going to
start the fire we always start
from the top down that eliminates smoke
so we want to not have smoke coming off
and to do that we start a small fire
using some paper and kindling and
cardboard at the top and then let that
work down as we add more bamboo
and we're going to be adding bamboo
that we've got stacked up here dry and
ready to burn
until
we've completely filled the pit that
we've dug and we've dug a pit that's
about
1 meter deep and about two meters two
and a half meters across
and i'm watching the temperature here
i'm gonna mark it
i want it above 450 degrees and i want
it uh somewhere in the 450 to 550 degree
range
now that we've completely filled the pit
and
it's starting to turn white i don't want
it to go to ash
i want it to stay black that's the
biochar so it i can't let it go to the
final stage where it oxidizes and turns
to ash
so i've stuck the hose down in the
bottom of the fire so that the water
rises from the bottom of the pit
and comes and steam cleans all the pores
after that we move over to the chipper
shredder stage i've got a little
electric shredder here for compost
shredding and we're using that to bring
the size of the of the particles down to
the size an earthworm could digest
now we've built a second pit this one is
up by the driveway where i've got still
more bamboo to cut back i want to cut it
away from the power lines and so we
built another pit
and we started the same process over
again
we're letting it go to
the point where the pit is full
and we're keeping the ash from forming
we're anytime we see it
turning a little bit white we we spray
down with water or add more material and
then eventually it gets to the point
where we put the hose in the bottom let
it steam clean the pores again until
we've quenched the fire completely it's
come up over the top of the biochar and
there's nothing there
on the but a pool of wet char
if you want to eliminate the electric
chipper shredder this is a way to
micronize the particles
the final stage of
microbialization and mineralization
uh involve turning the biochar into
something suitable for soil and we do
that i bought a 30 pickup truck load of
composted cow manure and we moved that
down to the garden using the tractor
where we make a compost pile with the
biochar
biochar straight out of the kiln is
hydrophobic it repels water so we have
to moisten it and then we need to add in
the microbes the microbial community
before we add the biochar to the garden
otherwise it will steal it from the
garden
any kind of substrate can make good
biochar if it's a photosynthetic origin
when it goes through the kiln it forms
new forms of biochar new forms of carbon
because carbon bonds to itself at 450 or
500 degrees and it forms ring structures
and chain structures and that's why it
endures in the soil for hundreds to
thousands of years
the pyrolysis process itself has many
potential yields because it produces
heat it's exothermic it loses about half
of the carbon back to the atmosphere but
it produces all the things you can
produce with heat
and it saves biochar in the soil carbon
in the soil and that goes into the
carbon cycle of the soil
rather than returning to the atmosphere
in oceans
so photosynthesis is our key ingredient
here that's what takes the carbon out of
the atmosphere out of the ocean and now
we want to change it into a form that's
going to stay in land for thousands of
years
there are many good designs for using
the heat from the process to cook with
or to
apply to make electricity
lots of good designs there for stoves
and other implements that make biochar
of course if you're doing this a lot or
with larger volumes you might want to
invest in a little more permanent pit
this is the
method of the contiki kiln easy online
available public domain design
and it can make prodigious amounts of
biochar as shown here
biochar absolutely has to scale if we're
going to get out of this century and
alive and many companies are already
jumping into this space
thanks for listening and i hope you will
try making biochar yourself it's going
to be fun and you'll have a good time
and it's simple scalable and shovel
ready
you