[Music]
you
morning guys Tammy Trier Trier
wilderness calm I hope you guys are
doing good this morning
I will wait a little bit here I've got
some fun stuff to share I'm not sure my
connection seems a little funny so I
will wait and see if we can get some
other people on here I thought we'd
share some homesteading and off-grid and
life tips with everybody this morning so
I'm just gonna wait a little bit here
well gorgeous weather we are having I am
like so excited that's why my cheeks are
all flushed I just did a treatment out
on my back porch in the Sun and it just
felt so good to be sitting there soaking
up the vitamin D which I need also so it
was just it's just wonderful but our
weather's been low 70s and it has just
been gorgeous with a nice breeze and
just very refreshing I could handle
these temperatures all year long this is
just awesome and it just smells so good
outside so many things are blooming and
it just it's it's wonderful so it's not
looking like anybody's jumping on right
yet so I am going to dive in here share
my thoughts and if we get people on
that's great if not you guys can watch a
replay and you guys on YouTube can
follow along up hello Brenda thanks for
joining where are you from Brenda we had
an absolutely amazing weekend this past
weekend we actually got a chance to get
away the mountain boy wasn't interested
in going so he stayed home here and held
down the fort with the dogs and the
mountain man and I got to get out with
some friends of ours and go camping and
we actually camped in our hammocks both
in Montana and in Idaho we did like a
big loop and it was just such an amazing
escape sometimes we just need to do that
and escape and get out there but I'm
gonna try to do something here while I
have you guys on here see if my live
shows up on here I want to share some
photos in the feed
hey good morning glad to have you guys
joining me getting out and being able to
be here we go let's see if I can do this
I don't know if I can share I want to
share some photos there we go
nothing like listening to yourself give
me a second here I want to try to share
these photos how have you guys been what
have you been up to and are you getting
things in your garden are you getting
out and enjoying joining the wonderful
weather we have had an absolutely
amazing weather darn it I can't I don't
think I can add to the comments right
now let me just try another way
oh maybe here ha here we go
okay I'm going to share some pictures
and hopefully you guys can see them in
the comments below and let me just find
the other ones there we go it's just fun
to be able to share I got to get a
little bit more techie here and be able
to share things a little differently
with you but right now I'm going to
share it this way in the comments below
you should be able to see three photos
my mountain man is a tremendous cook
when it comes to well no matter where we
are he is really good on an open fire as
far as cooking our meals he used to do a
lot of pack trips back in the
backcountry in Wyoming and he did a lot
of hunting trips as well so he was camp
cook and also guide but in the one
picture you can see him making fry bread
and in the other picture you can see
that he's got elk steaks on a skewer
over the fire we've got coffee going on
and potatoes in a big frying pan and
then he also made eggs so we might hike
but we we eat well out there it's good
that we do hike we come back a lot
heavier I think but he's an amazing cook
and it's just there's nothing better
than cooking on an open fire so right
now we are taking advantage of the
opportunity good morning Sean good
morning Debbie we are taking advantage
of being out there and being able
to take opportunities with the open fire
because it gets so dry here that later
on this season we won't be able to have
an open fire and cook on it so it really
sucks sometimes because there's nothing
better I love sitting by my campfire and
just taking it all in
and in the other picture you can see my
feet on my hammock we were hanging on
the side of the mountain on the first
night in Montana and it was awesome now
we did have a big tarp over top of us
because it was a little sketchy looking
but we were he enabled that by using
mule tape which is some heavy cordage
and we strung that zigzagged across the
trees above us and we're able to put a
tarp up so we stayed dry but I have to
share this this was really wild a storm
blew in and of course it was an
electrical storm and we're hanging there
in the trees and our friend and his kids
and the dogs were an attempt below us
and the storm started coming in but all
of a sudden simultaneously the lightning
and the Thunder hit and it was so close
that it made your hair stand up and you
could just feel it go through your
entire body it was really freaky it was
that close and I was ready to dive and
hit the truck just because the truck has
the rubber and it's safer place to be
than hanging in a tree good morning Chad
and waited it out a little bit and that
it just started to dissipate then but
man it was you know our eyes were closed
and it was like somebody just shined the
brightest light possible in our eyes it
was really crazy but it was also really
neat to experience and we had not camped
the whole weekend then and had really
got to see some nice scenery some
different parts of Idaho that we haven't
seen before so it was really nice but I
encourage you guys to get out get out
practice your skills sleep in the wild
if you haven't you're missing out some
of you may not like it but I'm a dirt
girl I like being out in the dirt I like
you know I'm not keen on spiders because
I react poorly to their bites but
they're easy to flick and fling and get
rid of and just hanging in the trees
like that there's just nothing better a
wise old woodsman once told me a good
campfire will cure anything that ails
you
amen Shawn amen is that not true it's
just amazing the food tastes better it's
aroma therapy going on it's just is
awesome
and I did good I was really concerned
because I went I wasn't sure with my
body and my my illness as to whether
being out there amongst all the molds
because everything said wet right now
how I would do but I had a little bit of
head pain I think more from our height
and the barometric pressure but I like
like Shawn said I think the fire cured
all that was ailing me so it's
absolutely amazing so guys don't miss
out on getting out and don't forget to
take your kids such great learning and
opportunities to be out there and teach
them things I also wanted to share with
you my goodies there's my spearmint
jelly that is finished and my dandelion
jelly you can see that's a little bit
lighter and then here is the lilac now
you can I don't know if you can see that
but it actually does have like a purple
tinge to it and I also have my
strawberry and there's nothing better
than fresh jellies especially when
you're making them from what most people
consider weeds and the lilacs I was
blessed by my friend Vicki who shared
some of her lilac blooms but
everything's out there guys it's all at
your fingertips just like it is mine
it's just a matter of taking the time
and and and getting out there and doing
it yes get the kids out there absolutely
Chad Chad's another one who's constantly
out there with his littles and it's just
it's a great being out there with your
kids there's nothing better than
teaching the kids how to do these things
they get so empowered our friends kids
are what's the age-wise well I'm gonna
go buy grade ones going into third grade
next year should be finishing second
grade this right now and the other is
finishing kindergarten going to first so
six and nine eight nine Navy great kids
and they just love being out there and
they had the opportunity to each build
their fire ring while Glenn was making
the meal
and they practice starting their fires
and gathering their materials and
keeping the fire going so you know that
skill although some people would be
fearful that that's teaching them you
know how to do something dangerous yeah
but it's also teaching them how to do
something that could save their life if
they're ever stuck somewhere even if
they don't use it as as a child but they
use it as an adult because they learned
it when they were out in the woods with
their dad plus it's such a great time to
bond with your kids honestly and I told
the mountain boy today on our walk I
said next time we're going out he's got
to go with because he missed out on so
much fun he was just afraid he was gonna
be too cold
last time we were camping it was pretty
cold so anyway I want to share something
else with you
you guys hear a lot about modern
homesteading you hear a lot about off
gridding you hear a lot about you know
primitive skills and things and a lot of
average people feel that that doesn't
apply to them but honestly I feel all of
those skills traditional primitive
homesteading off-grid all those skills
are things that the average man should
know because they are for us a lifestyle
of preparedness they are things that we
think about all the time good morning
Blake glad to have you joining me Sean
says practice and understanding doesn't
mean it's dangerous it teaches respect
and discipline absolutely absolutely and
and that's that's what it's about plus
it also empowers encourages and gives
them confidence and and also pride that
they're being included in in the
opportunity to participate that just
giving them a pack these kids each have
their own little pocket knife starter
pocket knife and they're whittling all
the time while we're out there they get
their hot dog sticks ready and you know
and they've cut themselves while we're
out we've had a patch them up but you
know what it's it's part of experience
and and it'll teach them just like you
said it's gonna teach them the respect
for the for the the equipment so great
great thoughts and thanks for sharing
that Sean but the skills that we share
and when I
sharing the modern homesteading things
and the and the gardening things you
know if you live in town and you're
living vicariously it doesn't mean you
can't do these things it doesn't mean
that just because where you are is is
limiting you and and knowing these
things and practicing these things you
know even if you live in an apartment
there's nothing stopping you from
getting out into the woods and getting
some dirt time and also experiencing it
so don't limit yourself and don't feel
limited when somebody says modern
homesteading things and you're not a
homesteader so you don't participate
please don't limit yourself knowledge is
power and it doesn't matter where you
are or what you're doing in your life
today you can still learn these skills
and these skills are what are going to
carry you through if anything were to
ever happen in any way to our country to
your your family you know we've gone
through situations had we not lived a
life of preparedness with our food
storage in 2016 when we went six and a
half months without an income we would
have been eating unless we were foraging
and harvesting and we know how to do
that but it would have been adding more
stress to the fire when we were already
very stressed so eating like kings and
queens because we planned ahead and
prepared it's key and and that's what
these things are for so the reason I'm
mentioning that today is because in
addition to getting the tray at
Wilderness Academy live and running
I was also videoing a segment for the
modern homesteading summit that my great
friend Melissa Norris is running and I
love her dearly and I'm so proud of her
she put together a really nice summit
and it will be starting on June 10th and
you are able to get your free seats a
while it is all online so you can watch
it at your convenience I did a course on
things to think about before going off
grid and there are 26 other homesteaders
and off-gridders that have shared their
knowledge and insight and I encourage
you to go check it out you can go there
by simply going to try our wilderness
comm slash homesteading summit all one
word and the links are down below good
morning Richard so guys don't miss out
on these free things they
put three or four presentations in a day
and I believe it starts at 7:00 a.m. and
then and then it switches off at
midnight and then the next day's will
start again so you have 20 I believe you
have 24 hours to watch the presentation
so it's seven to seven so it's you've
got 24 hours to watch the presentation
so depending on your work schedule what
you've got going on you can squeeze it
into your day they often have encore
days and then you are also able to
purchase the event but it is free to
everybody a good deal thanks Sean have a
great day and thanks for being a part of
this so don't miss out on that the other
thing that's going on is I had mentioned
last week grow your own food workshop
was going on and they are having their
encore days today and tomorrow so you
can get in and pick up and watch the
ones that pertain to you the ones that
you would like and that's something else
you can do is see what presentations are
most important to you and most valuable
to you if you can't watch them all pick
the ones that you can so they grow your
own food you can find by going to try a
wilderness calm slash grow your own food
and again the links are all below and
there's a lot of links below check them
out they're all things that pertain to
what we're talking about and some
inspiration now this is one of the this
is what I wanted to share with you today
right here you see that it's frozen
water you can see it's starting to melt
a little bit I just pulled it out in my
freezer I have this in my freezer this
was shared with me this is not my own
idea but it's ingenious and I'm going to
share it I don't know who the original
person was but my dear friend Mona
shared it with me there is if I can get
it out of here there's a quarter in here
there we go there's a quarter on the top
of my frozen ice so say you're out and
your freezer goes out and the electric
goes out so your freezers your freezers
off while you're at work and for us we
have a propane freezer but our lines
could get clogged or our tank could run
out and and it would shut it off till we
switch the tanks
so it could happen to us too by having
that quarter on top of ice if your power
goes out and your freezer starts to thaw
if that quarter ends up at the bottom
you know very well that your meats
probably spoiled because it's been off
for a long time and at which point you
have no idea how long it's been off but
if that quarter only ends up Midway that
means that your food did not get spoiled
and and that you can still save what's
in your freezer that it probably may
have thought a little bit but it reefer
it's gonna refreeze or it's part way but
by having that in there it gives you a
gauge on how long the freezers been off
so I encourage everybody to do that
because I know many people who have
thrown away a whole freezer full of meat
and things because they weren't sure how
long it was off and sometimes it's
pretty evident especially if you've been
gone for a while you'll smell it first
but this is a great little gauge to be
able to determine how long your freezers
been off the other thing to keep in mind
is I use glass good morning Holly you
don't want to fill it the whole way up
or this jars gonna crack good morning
Kerry so fill it like three quarters of
the way and put your quarter in the top
and that way you will have a gauge to
know how long your freezers been out
when the power goes off if you're out of
the house and you can also if the power
does go out and you're there and you
don't have a generator if you keep your
freezers closed they will stay cold for
a long time so there's a good chance
that you will be able to you know save
things if it's only goes out for a
couple of hours that's awesome I know
what I'm doing well I know isn't that
one when Mona told me I was like you
know aha
you know duh but that's that's such a
great such a great way engaged to be
able to double-check you know what's
going on in your freezer and and with
all the game meat we have and the work
that is required that's required to get
it in our freezer
I would absolutely be sick if we
and I'm sure you guys would too
especially if you're purchasing things
as well because then you've got money
tied up in it we have time and sweat and
sometimes blood tied up into getting our
meats in the freezer not so much the
money but nobody wants to throw good
food away now good deal good deal Tammy
yeah that's a great it's a great idea
you don't have to use glass you can use
a plastic container but I figured that
was easiest it enables me to see through
it real well
hello truly so guys it's really
important to be able to educate
ourselves and learn how to do these
things and not be fearful and not be
afraid hi Becca to not be afraid of
making mistakes guys mistakes happen all
the time and without a mistake you're
not going to learn so you know I I look
at mistakes and and mishaps as
stepping-stones
it all depends how you look at it you
know that my cup is over always
overflowing and I'm more thankful that I
have a cup than how full it is so it's
my positive perspective but if you use
your mistakes as stepping stones you'll
constantly be moving forward not
backward right so those of you that just
jumped on I was mentioning that with
them you know all the modern
homesteading and off-grid things that
are being shared and and different
skills that are being shared you know
sometimes people feel that that doesn't
pertain to them because they're not
actually homesteaders or offgridders but
this knowledge is open to all of us so
check out below directly under the word
resources are the two links that I was
sharing for the modern homesteading
summit that's coming up on June 10th
that you can get involved in now and if
you're interested in being able to watch
them later they've got a great price on
it right now
and then the grow your own food summit
is doing their encore days sorry had a
brain fart for a moment so check that
out and for those of you that just
jumped in I shared some pictures of our
weekend in the comments below so that
you can check those out it's always
important to get out and step away from
our chaos we all have chaos
and last week I shared about endurance
and I want to just share something with
you I was doing my devotions outside
this morning and I was going through
Hebrews and read this and I just thought
it pertains so much I almost wish I
would have found it last week but
there's purpose in it this week -
because perseverance is important every
day every week we're gonna run into
struggles we're gonna run into things
and you know I'm a positive person I
don't mention that because life sucks
it's not that it's that there's just
there's we're not promised anything
perfect we're not promised you know
clicking our heels are going to occur
every day it's what we make it though
and being able to persevere through our
struggles and anything and in learning
persevere through making jelly when it
doesn't turn out right the first time
you know some my first batches of jelly
ended up being syrup not jelly and that
was with elderberries so you know it's
gonna happen to all of us you know I'm
no different than you are we make
mistakes too or things don't always go
the way we want them to go you know we
might be skinning an animal and want to
use the hide and accidentally slip and
put a hole on it I mean we're no
different than you guys stuff happens
and you know I was a little bit
disappointed when I pulled my jelly up
the morning after because I'm holding it
too high sorry it didn't look like it's
set right but it actually set wonderful
Pomona's pectin is awesome but you got a
try and you got a persevere through the
hiccups used on the stepping stones and
keep going but in Hebrews 10 34 through
36 it says you suffered along with those
who were thrown into jail and when you
when all you owned was taken from you
you accepted it with joy you knew there
were better things waiting for you that
will last forever so do not throw away
this confident trust in the Lord
remember the great reward it brings you
patient endurance is what you need now
so that you will continue to do God's
will then you will receive all that he
has promised and guys you know I hold
true to this stuff and I lean on this
and this is my my life
it's my strength and I just thought it
was kind of interesting that I read that
this morning after sharing with you what
I did last week and her the week before
I guess it was and uh it's just one of
those things you know we're walking
through a valley we could very well lose
everything but it's on material things
and it's how you view life
I am so rich in the relationships that I
have in the life that I live that the
material things around me really are
meaningless they help me through my day
but they're not what I hold on to for
for anything it's just material things
so that's just a really excessive view
of perseverance but it's all how you
view it it's all how you view life and I
know many of you get afraid to try the
new things and you see us showing you
how to do it in and and you know we've
we've perfected it we've done it and it
may intimidate you but I don't want you
to be intimidated I want you to also
realize that we're human and make
mistakes too and there's no reason why
you can't do this as well so don't miss
out on the free trainings that are
available to you sometimes it can be
hard to cram things into our already
tight schedule so I do get that because
I sometimes would like to participate in
the summits and watch them and I don't
have the time but there are options to
buy them if that's something that you
are able to do but don't miss out on
what you can like I said if you only
have a limited time figure out what the
courses are that will best benefit you
at this time Tami says our gelée didn't
set became pancake syrup yep you just
you roll with it it's still usable and
you know what if it doesn't become
pancake syrup it ends up in my meats
jellies and preserves jams the sweet
stuff is so amazing in in fried up meats
I you tools and onions a lot of times
I'll just slice up an apple and put it
in with my meats and and different
fruits pears go really good too I've
used my pear jellies and meats too but
um
the next thing I'll be making is hot
pepper jelly I absolutely love that on a
bagel with really good organic cream
cheese I will have to be making bagels
out of coconut and almond flour but I'm
sure it'll work well I have made bagels
already and they're really good so I
just haven't made him in a while but
don't miss out guys don't miss out
because you feel you don't fit the mold
you know last when I was talking about
the perseverance I was talking about
comparing yourself and and I think a lot
of people compare themselves to others
and question their abilities don't
question your abilities and don't
compare yourself because it'll hold you
back yep my strawberry jam syrup is
natural waffles or pound cake topping
cheesecake topping - there you go
you'd make lively bring that over to my
house along with your cheesecake but
this stuff is usable it's not like it's
trashed it's not like it's not used you
know yes it's useless now you gotta even
even when you make a dish sometimes I'll
make something good morning Tiffany and
it may not turn out the way I want it to
but the next night I'll use it in
leftovers and it's absolutely amazing
you know it's just I never waste
anything nothing gets thrown away and
even our scraps go to the chickens some
of the scraps go to the dogs but you
know perfect well set a date but don't
waste anything and don't don't be upset
with your mistakes because in my opinion
that's not a mistake you just you just
flipped it and used it a little
differently than you initially intended
right now I just want to encourage you
guys to also you know take advantage of
what's around you like I said earlier
with my dandelion jelly you know that's
something that most people consider is a
weed and I'll tell you what the
dandelion jelly tastes like honey so it
is our number two honey in the house and
honestly I can't believe I haven't been
making it all these years I have been
actually utilizing the dandelion to dry
for my teas and the roots for my teas
and sometimes for coffee
I just wasn't making the jelly and what
a mistake I've been making so anyway I'm
gonna wrap this up by just saying a
prayer for you guys I do this every week
it may not be your thing but it's my
gift to you
so dear lord I just thank you for these
folks taking the time out of their busy
schedules to join me for sharing their
input and their tips and tricks and and
Lord just be with them strengthen them
give them perseverance and endurance
through their week and just help those
that are in need that may be struggling
or ill and Lord just bless them show
your presence to them and just continue
to guide them on their journey just as
you are on ours
lord I just ask this in Jesus precious
name Amen so guys again I appreciate you
taking the time to join me
join me next Wednesday 10:30 on Facebook
live and don't miss out on the
homesteading summit it starts on June
10th but you can sign up now that way
you'll get their emails and know what's
going on there's bonuses involved also
which are really great resources to add
to your archives and don't miss out so
guys have a fantastic day thank you
again for joining me today and god bless
[Music]
you