my name is dawn Nicholson along with my
wife Trista and three boys Aiden Gavin
and Ian we farm and ranch in Frederick
South Dakota and one things we're trying
to do is incorporate our livestock more
into our crop ground where we live in
Frederick here the climate and the
rainfall is very east and west they
cross 281 that just starts drying up
more so we have kind of farming in two
different areas where the stuff east of
281 we have generally more rainfall as
we go further west it starts falling off
and it lends itself more to the
livestock side of the operation
initially I started in a no-till after
college I came back to the farm it was
just me and my stepfather at farming so
labor was and it seemed like an easier
Avenue to go you know less tillage less
work so it started out as a labor saving
and then I started seeing you know
benefits to the to the soil and doing
less work and still keeping up yield
wise with neighbors you know we've
always had livestock and we've always
had crap ground focusing on the cattle
in the fields longer start seeing the
benefits of the soil health the crops we
grow here are corn soybeans
triticale alfalfa and starting to do a
little bit more in the cover crops the
alfalfa I think has been key for me to
start identifying areas of the field
that are not as productive and allows me
different time of the season to be able
to get into those areas if it's fixing
saline area spots in our area it's also
there are a lot of potholes so with
excessive water ponding and ditch effect
saline areas start popping up and
expanding you know if they aren't cared
for or treated differently than the rest
of you your crops might use a lot of
precision stuff in my cash crops so I
started using that to identify the poor
producing areas and then zeroing in on
what those spots need and how to do it
the best way to do that and my operation
is through the cattle and Bale grazing
some of the effects that I've seen in
the areas of where I have been Bale
grazing after doing it the first year
you know you get the cover which I
believe the cover helps eliminate some
of that evaporation it keeps the soil
moisture rather than drying out and
bring in all those salts to the top and
then wicking moisture from other areas
and pulling up more salts it's part of
the healing process it might not look
the prettiest at times but it's a rut in
the ground it's something that's growing
also on our pastures I have been
rotational grazing for quite some time
golfers say play the course don't let
the course play you we got a
look at how the ground is and what kind
of grasses are there and what you can do
with it each area is managed differently
just like in my crop ground each zone is
is managed differently so there's
challenges every year and every year is
a different challenge and what I have
found in my soils you know building the
organic matter having better soil health
allows me to weather through whichever
weather storm I faced with I wasn't born
into farming but from a very early age
since I was probably nine ten years old
I was been exposed to to farming and
then got a great opportunity and a lot
of freedom to try different things
my stepfather gave me a lot of a lot of
freedom that way and and that's helped
me going forward I remember him always
telling me you know do what you think's
best and you know that's what I hope to
pass along to my my son's you know
whatever they're doing is and do what
they thinks best
[Music]
you