[Music]
In a small community in the Pacific
Northwest, a dynamic company is growing.
This company has served the equipment
dealer market for 30 years. They did it
by following their principles, by being
the best, and by being honest to their
customers.
Dis
technologydriven, people focused.
[Music]
Well, dollars per employee.
Um, numbers might sound good, but when
you're working with a team
concept, be it you start in the service
department, move up through parts,
everything else. If your parts and
service is doing a good job on it, your
sales come as salesmen, we we get credit
for it. But as SA the other areas bring
it up. So we don't look at anything
individually because uh we have to look
at it from the standpoint
of profitability for the whole
dealership and and giving the customer a
fair price for a fair product. And
that's what we look at. And when we was
nominated for this, it we that wasn't
even I didn't even know what it was per
employee. And so we got into the fact
that we don't look at it that way
because we're doing a lot of double
tasking around here.
Um we have one one mechanic. He does our
uh warranty work and things like that.
We full-time service rider. We we kind
of duplex on that a little bit. I run
the shop and yeah, I do the sailing. So,
we're trying to uh take the revenue and
uh make the dealership a very solid
foundation and then we can expand after
[Music]
that. In a small community in the
Pacific Northwest, a dynamic company is
growing. This company has served the
equipment dealer market for 30 years.
They did it by following their
principles, by being the best and by
being honest to their
customers.
Dis
technologydriven, people focused.
[Music]