cilantro is a fantastic addition to your
garden but it can be a real challenge to
grow I find Cilantro is a bit of a
contradiction it's a shortlived annual
herb that prefers colder temperatures
but it really is best in the kitchen in
the summer when it goes so well with all
the hot season crops it can be hard to
get plants established it's a bit
finicky and when the tomatoes are
finally ripe enough to make salsa the
cilantro is often all bolted and bitter
it's also best used fresh and it's hard
to preserve a surface plus if you
planted too much although I do have some
ideas for processing at the end of this
video so I'm going to talk about how we
plan ahead to have fresh plantable
cilantro all year round including in the
winter and if you want to see more of
what we're doing in the restaurant
culinary Garden hit subscribe so first
things first the seed the cilantro seed
is actually coriander seed which you
would recognize from your kitchen both
cilantro and coriander are used in
Cuisines from all over the world but
they both have really different taste
profiles and flavors so we're just
talking about growing cilantro for the
leaves in this video so there's a lot of
different varieties of cilantro that you
might see when you're buying seed uh a
lot of them have to do with their bolt
tolerance so how slow bolting you'll see
listed on some of the labels um some of
it might have to do with the height or
the growth habit or The Taste uh but
really there's a few types I often have
planted Calypso which is slow to bolt
I've also just planted cilantro seeds
from the Shelf in my kitchen
it had pretty low germination rates but
it did work cilantro is definitely best
grown by direct seating it has a tap
rout so it really doesn't like being
transplanted and it'll undergo
transplant shock so that means when you
put it into the ground it will just
basically stop growing or grow very very
very slowly last year I grew some in
soil blocks uh early on in the spring uh
this is the cilantro here so two rows of
cilantro and every second Bunch this
Bunch was when I trans planted and then
this is what I seeded so at the same
time as I did this I also seeded little
clumps of cilantro and it's interesting
because this has hardly done anything
here's a transplanted Bunch here's a
seated Bunch here's a transplanted Bunch
so I would say uh transplanting them out
in early April which is like almost two
months ago now really made no difference
and waiting for them to come up from
seed probably would have been a better
bet so it wasn't really worth the extra
effort of growing the transplants and
then putting them in the garden it would
have been better off just direct seeding
so that's what I'm going to do this year
you can plant cilantro in rows or in
clumps the seeds can be about 1 cmet
apart and they need to be lightly
covered because they need dark to
germinate but just lightly covered uh
you want to keep it well watered until
it germinates in a week or more and the
ideal germination temp is around 18 to
21° C so 65 to 70 fhe so you want to
start seating them around your last
frost State when the soil temps have
warmed up if you want to get a head
start you could warm up the soil in a
bed by putting a piece of plastic over
it or some row cover even though
cilantro plants are cold hearty to get
the seeds to germinate it really wants a
fairly warm temperature soil that's
light well drained not wet pretty
standard for any herb or vegetable plant
uh and now the hard part is don't plant
too many seeds at once this is a mistake
I've made year after year if if you're
planting a rows maybe just think about
planting a quarter or a half of the row
space now and then plant another section
later so the reason you don't want to
plant all your cilantro at once is
because it's considered a short-lived
plant so it's going to bolt it's going
to produce flowers and then seeds and
then it's going to die when the days
start to get long in the summer and when
the temperatures are warm in the summer
this is programmed into the plant and
once it starts to bolt there isn't
really anything you can do to change it
the leaves really start to change
texture they go from sort of a thick
typical cilantro looking Leaf to sort of
thin and fern like and they often become
bitter and there's not as much of it to
harvest either so if we look at a chart
to make sure that there's cilantro all
year so I'm going to start with the
seeding dates and then I'm going to
harvest around 6 weeks after planting
and then I'm going to expect to harvest
from these plants for about a month
before it bolts and I pull it out so you
can see if I decide to plant on May 1st
I'm going to harvest June 15th 6 weeks
away and then I'm going to pull it out
July
15th but then I've got my second
sucession coming so I've got some that I
planted June 1st I'm going to harvest
that July 15th which is when I'm pulling
the previous cilantro bed and then I've
got that till August 15th and then you
can see if I do it July 1st August 1st
I've got cilantro going right until the
frost and that's sort of an estimation
but it gives you an idea of the kind of
thing you can do uh I'm probably going
to plant cilantro actually every two
weeks instead of every month like is
demonstrated here but it gives you an
idea of um what kind of timing you want
and where you want to put it in your
garden and you can put this in the same
bed you can actually plant seeds among
the plants that are already there that
you know you're going to pull out or you
can plant them in a different spot in
your garden what are other ways we can
keep cilantro plants happy and healthy
in the summer so one is pick where you
plant them using the sunny beds in
Spring and then Shady in the summer so
early on I'm going to plant in the first
places that warm up where my heat leming
crops aren't ready to go yet cilantro is
great in the under story of taller
summer crops like beans or tomatoes or
cucumbers that you might have growing up
vertical support so then you have some
bare soil underneath and you can put
clumps of cilantro we also seated this
cilantro it came up and it was growing
uh and I actually pulled out all the
spinach around it and left it here and
planted the tomatoes among it because it
doesn't take up too much space Also
keeping the cilantro plants well watered
and mulch can keep the soil temperature
down and really the soil temperature is
as important as the air temperature so
if you can cool your soil then then that
helps keep it from
bolting and cilantro will go right until
the end of the season it's Frost hearty
to below zero so I've had cilantro
plants that are frozen in the garden um
come back to life when the sun comes out
and light frosts um Can are fine for it
especially if it's covered with row
cover and another thing you can do about
bolting is can just leave some plants to
bolt uh it's a beautiful flower that
attracts all kinds of beneficial insects
you can let the seeds go until they're
ready to harvest which will take
probably another month and then I
harvest the plant when about half the
seeds are dry pull it out of the garden
uh put it in a paper bag let it dry
completely I find it's hard to save
cilantro seeds because as you're letting
it dry on the plant they're dropping it
all over the garden and so you end up
with self-seed cilantro as well in the
the past we've had a lot of cilantro
self-seeding and it's always a good
indication of when it's ready to uh
germinate when the soil is warm enough
when it's at its Optimum temperature so
you can let these volunteer seedlings
come up they might not come up in the
right place but they'll come up at the
right time so maybe that's a signal for
you to plant cilantro seeds or maybe
it's just uh a couple of cilantro plants
somewhere on the margins that you can
just let go and harvest from I find it's
not worth it to try and move Cilantros
that that are self-seeded in the garden
they don't like being transplanted like
I said so at that stage um either let
them grow where they are or just pull
them up like weeds so when you're
harvesting you can cut the leaves you
can either just chop the whole plant
right to the ground uh and then let it
regrow it takes about two weeks to do
that you can also just selectively pick
leaves off of the plants if you have a
big clump of them that works really well
and and cilantro is best when it's a
little bit bigger than this um and you
can harvest the leaves really easily and
often I'll just pull it straight out of
the ground and then keep that in the
fridge so that's an easier way than
cutting it I find it lasts longer
because it has this nice Tap Root on it
if you put that on like a piece of
moistened paper towel it'll actually um
stay perky and stay uh straight for a
couple days it'll maintain some of that
water or and when using in cooking you
can also use the stems they have the
same flavor and they're pretty tender
and juicy so uh just chop the whole
thing up and to preserve it it's a tough
one drying does not preserve the flavor
and I don't really find that freezing
does that well either um the best bet
that we found is to blend it into salsa
verde or other sauces that can be Jarred
or Frozen uh flavors are integrated into
the sauces when they're made and then
it's in a form where it can stay tasty
and delicious for many months so we make
uh salsa ver that we put in the freezer
we make salsa that we put in jars that
does take more processing time up front
and and it doesn't fill the Gap in the
one beautiful cilantro sprig that's
placed on a dish for garnish but that's
what micro greens are for so the other
thing that we do is we grow micr greine
cilantro over the winter so I'm using a
1020 tray here a shallow one for micro
greens filling it with just a promix
potting soil uh and then I'm putting in
this case it was 30 gram of cilantro
seed into a container soaked for 24
hours so then I spread those out on the
promix and I cover it with a container
just another one just to exclude the
light until it's germinated so I'm going
to check on this every day or so then
once that done I'm going to pull it off
and I'm going to put it under the lights
and you want to put it right up close to
the lights that you have um maybe
propped up with another uh Bin and then
let it grow I find it's not the fastest
growing micr green compared to radishes
or peas shs but uh it is delicious it
has all of the cilantro flavor and all
of that beautiful cilantro look that is
um just really like iconic and really
nice on a chili or a noodle bowl that we
have on the menu so so thanks for
watching give this video a like And
subscribe if you want to see more like
it of The Culinary Garden this summer