[Music]
[Applause]
Across the globe, water is fast becoming
a precious commodity as more and more
people use water for the household,
industry, and agriculture.
Rice uses up the most amount of water in
agriculture with almost half of the
world's population depending on rice as
their staple food. By
2025, 15 to 20 million hectares of
irrigated rice fields may suffer from
water scarcity.
To address this problem, scientists have
developed a technique called alternate
wetting and drying or AWD, which uses
less water to grow rice. AWD is a
water-saving technology that lowland
rice farmers can apply to reduce water
use in irrigated
fields. In AWD, the rice field is
allowed to dry for a number of days
before being flooded again. Hence, the
field is alternately flooded and left
dry. The number of days that the field
can be left dry depends on the soil type
and other field
conditions. A practical way of applying
AWD is by observing the depth of water
in the field using a field water
tube. After irrigation, water level will
gradually decrease.
When the water level has dropped to 15
cm below the soil surface, the field
should be reflooded to a depth of 5
cm. Allowing the water in the field to
drop to 15 cm below the soil surface
before irrigating again is called safe
AWD.
The 15 cm limit will not cause any yield
decline since the roots of the rice
plants will be able to take up water
from the saturated soil and the perched
water level in the surface. The field
water tube helps farmers see the hidden
source of water.
Safe AWD irrigation can be started a few
days after transplanting or when the
directseed rice crop is already 10 cm
tall until first heading. When many
weeds are present in the early stages of
crop growth, safe AWD can be postponed
for 2 to 3 weeks until the weeds have
been suppressed by the ponded water.
Local fertilizer recommendations for
flooded rice can be used. Apply nitrogen
fertilizer preferably on the dry soil
just before
irrigation. A week before to a week
after the peak of flowering. Water
should be kept at a 5 cm depth to avoid
water stress which could result in
potentially severe yield
loss. After flowering and during grain
filling, apply safe AWD
again. In safe AWD, water savings may be
relatively small about 15 to 25% but
there is no yield penalty.
Once farmers are confident that safe AWD
does not reduce yield, they can
experiment by lowering the threshold
level to 20, 25, 30 cm depth or even
deeper before
[Music]
irrigation. The field water tube can be
made of a plastic pipe or bamboo or
other indigenous materials that will
help farmers see water below the soil.
Cut these materials to a 40 cm length
with a diameter of 15 cm or more to
easily see the water level inside the
tube. The bottom 20 cm length of the
tube should be drilled with holes on all
sides. Holes should have a diameter of
about 0.5 cm each and spaced about 2 cm
away from one another.
[Music]
The tube can be placed on the side of
the field close to the bond, but not
less than a meter away for easier
monitoring. Bury the tube vertically
into the soil so that 20 cm or half of
its length protrudes above the soil
surface. Take care not to penetrate
through the bottom of the plow pan or
hard pan, which is a dense layer of soil
that is largely resistant to water.
Remove the soil inside the tube so that
the bottom of the tube is
visible. Check that the water level
inside the tube is the same as that
outside the tube.
Alternate wetting and drying or AWD is
already a mature technology that can be
readily used by farmers. The field water
tube is a very simple tool that guides
farmers to effectively and efficiently
manage their limited irrigation water
for their rice crop.
However, farmers can only truly
appreciate the benefits and water
savings from AWD if adoption of this
promising technology is done at the
community or system level.
[Music]