hello my name is dana jokola and i'm a
graduate student working with dr aj nair
in the sustainable vegetable production
lab
at iowa state university today is august
13th and we are here at the horticulture
research station
in ames iowa and i wanted to give you a
brief update on the research that i'm
doing on
reduced tillage systems for organic
vegetable production
i'd like to acknowledge the series trust
and north central ser who have both
provided funding for this project
so thanks to those organizations so
while no-till has become relatively
common in
field crop production in some parts of
this country it has remained relatively
absent from
organic production mostly because
organic farmers rely on
tillage and mechanical cultivation for
weed control however tillage has a
number of adverse effects on soil health
and so we're working on systems that
will allow us to minimize
the tillage in this study we're going to
look at two such systems
no-till and strip till in the production
of organic broccoli
and peppers so these systems are based
on the use of cover crops
for weed control the idea is to grow an
in-situ mulch
through which you can eventually
transplant your crop or plant your seeds
so in this study we seeded rye and vetch
last fall
on september 12th at a rate of 90 pounds
per acre for the rye and 25 pounds per
acre for the vetch
you'll notice that the planting date is
a little on the earlier end of the
spectrum
and the seeding rate was a little on the
higher end of the spectrum and those are
both intentional
they're both required in order to
generate sufficient biomass with the
cover crop
in order to suppress weeds for the
subsequent growing season
so the cover crops grew throughout the
fall and the spring and then
in late may they start to flower so now
when
rye reaches anthesis which is pollen
shed and the vetch reaches
early pod stage they can both be fairly
well
terminated by mechanically rolling them
with a tool called a roller crimper
in this study we have three whole plot
treatments no-till
strip till and then conventional till
the conventional till is the system
used most commonly by organic vegetable
growers in the midwest
each of those plots were subdividing
into two subplots to test out two
different nitrogen fertilization
strategies
in the first we apply the full rate of
nitrogen 150 pounds for broccoli 80
pounds for pepper
using a granular dehydrated chicken
manure product which we banned just
before planting
in the second subplot we're applying
just two-thirds rate
of that granular fertilizer pre-plant
and then we apply the remainder
using fertigation of a liquid fish
product
in four events starting three weeks
after planting
and then repeating every 10 days for
four events
so we've only just begun harvest in the
last few days so it's too early to tell
how the yields are going to compare
between treatments but our
hypothesis is that we're going to be
able to achieve equal yields between the
no-till and strip till
and the conventional till we have
however been collecting data on nitrate
leaching
in all the plots using lysometers which
are installed in the plots
and pretty consistently across the first
four collections we've seen that
the conventional till plots are leaching
at a rate
four times greater than the no-till and
the strip till
which is important because we're seeing
widespread nitrate contamination of
groundwater issues and
iowa has introduced a reduction strategy
to try to reduce
the amount of nitrates going into the
groundwater
so it turns out that no-till and strip
till using these surface mulches
might be a good way to achieve that i'm
here in a conventional till plot
as you can see there is no cover crop on
the soil surface
the cover crop was incorporated with a
rototiller prior to planting and has
mostly broken down
at this point and we have had to come
through with a rototiller twice to till
in between the rows to control weeds
okay here we are in a strip till plot
and as you can see we have about a 12
inch wide tilled band where the crop is
planted
and this provides some of the benefits
of conventional tillage
in the row where the crop is planted
while we have done a little bit of
weeding between the plants
we've done no weeding in between the
rows where as you can see we still have
a nice mulch suppressing weeds
so we're here in a no-till plot and as
you can see there is a mulch covering
the majority of the soil surface
in these plots and the peppers are
looking healthy
and you can see that we have a nice
still pretty thick mulch here that's
suppressing weeds in between the rows
okay this is the roller crimper this is
an eight
foot inj model it was designed by the
rodale institute who did some of the
earliest research on organic no-till
systems
and so it's a barrel that has blades
welded on it in a chevron pattern
and the blades crimp the stems of rye
along the length of it and allow the
cover crop to
dry down and kill more reliably
you can also fill the barrel with water
which adds additional weight
resulting in a more effective kill as
well
this is a hindker 6000 strip tiller
which we used in this project to create
the strips
it has several components up front it
has row cleaners
which move the rye mulch out of the way
next there is a coulter which cuts
through any remaining rye stems
which would get in the way of the rest
of the strip tiller
following that is a subsoil shank with a
rolling disc
on either side these discs are designed
to float
however we found that in order to
successfully till in the rye
we had to put a u-bolt and fix it to the
frame of the strip tiller
the shank also allows us to deliver
fertilizer in the row
with this side dressing unit that's
mounted above
then lastly there's a rolling basket
which breaks up any remaining clods
that would be in the planting area we
used the strip tiller at two points
during the growing season
once in the fall about six weeks after
seeding the cover crop in order to kill
the rye in the rows
and then again just before planting
which allowed us to
kill weeds that had grown during the
spring fluff up the soil
to make a seed bed and then deliver the
fertilizer to the crop that we planted
days after
you