did you know that homegrown peas can be
up to 10 times sweeter than store-bought
varieties in fact studies show that
fresh peas lose their sweetness within
hours of being
harvested if you want to enjoy the
freshest most flavorful peas right from
your garden stick around in this video
I'll share essential tips and tricks to
help you grow a bountiful pea crop
ensuring you never have to settle for
Bland store bought peas again welcome
back to my Channel today we're diving
into the wonderful world of pea
cultivation whether you're a seasoned
Gardener or just starting out growing
peas can be a rewarding
experience let's get started first off
why should you consider growing peas
they're not only delicious and versatile
in the kitchen but they're also packed
with
nutrients plus they're a great crop for
improving soil Health let's talk about
the types of peas you can grow first off
why should you consider growing peas
let's explore some compelling
reasons one nutritional benefits peas
are a Powerhouse of
nutrition they are rich in vitamins a c
and k as well as essential minerals like
iron and
magnesium plus they're a great source of
plant-based protein and fiber making
them an excellent addition to a healthy
diet two versatility in cooking peas are
incredibly versatile you can enjoy them
fresh frozen or dried they they can be
added to salads soups stir fries and
pasta dishes or even blended into
smoothies for a nutrient boost their
sweet flavor and vibrant color can
enhance any meal three soil Health
Improvement peas are legumes which means
they have a unique ability to fix
nitrogen in the soil this process
enriches the soil making it more fertile
for future crops by growing peas you're
not just benefiting yourself you're also
improving the health of your garden for
years to come four easy to grow peas are
one of the easiest crops to grow making
them perfect for
beginners they germinate quickly and can
thrive in cooler temperatures which
means you can plant them early in the
spring or even in the fall plus they
don't require a lot of space making them
ideal for small gardens or
containers five pest resistance peas are
relatively past resistant compared to
other crops their growth habit and the
fact that they're often planted early in
the season help them avoid many common
Garden
pests this means less time worrying
about pests and more time enjoying your
garden six sustainable gardening growing
your own peas contributes to sustainable
gardening
practices by cultivating your own food
you reduce your carbon footprint and
Reliance on store-bought produce which
often comes with packaging and
transportation
emissions seven Family Fun finally
growing peace can be a fun family
activity kids love to help plant seeds
watch them grow and of course enjoy the
delicious
Harvest it's a great way to teach them
about gardening nutrition and the
importance of eating fresh homegrown
food now that we've covered why you
should grow peas let's dive into the
different types of peas you can
cultivate each type has its unique
characteristics and uses so let's
explore them in detail one snap peas
description snap peas are a delightful
hybrid between snow peas and garden peas
they have a sweet flavor and a crisp
texture making them perfect for
snacking harvesting you can eat both the
pods and the peas inside and they're
best harvested when the pods are plump
but still tender uses enjoy them raw in
salads stir fried or steamed as a side
dish they're also great for adding a
crunchy element to various
recipes two snow peas description snow
peas are flat and have a tender pod that
is edible they are harvested before the
peas inside fully develop giving them a
unique sweet flavor harvesting pick them
when the pods are still flat and bright
green usually about 2 to 3 in Long uses
snow peas are commonly used in Asian
Cuisine especially in stir fries and
salads their crisp texture adds a
refreshing crunch to dishes
three Garden peas or shelling
peas description Garden peas are the
classic variety that most people think
of when they hear peas they are round
and sweet but the pods are not
edible harvesting these peas are best
harvested when the pods are full and
round but before they become tough
you'll need to Shell them to enjoy the
sweet peas inside uses Garden peas are
perfect for Soups stews and
casseroles they can also be M
description dried peas are harvested
when fully mature and then dried for
storage they come in varieties like
green and yellow peas harvesting allow
the pods to dry on the plant before
harvesting once dried the peas can be
stored for long
periods now that we've discussed the
types of peas let's get into the
nitty-gritty of planting them proper
planting is crucial for a successful pea
Harvest so here's what you need to know
one
timing peas thrive in cooler weather so
the best time to plant them is in early
spring about 4 to 6 weeks before the
last expected Frost in some regions you
can even plant them in late summer for a
fall Harvest check your local Frost
dates to determine the best planting
time two soil
preparation peas prefer well draining
lomy soil with a pH between 6.0 and
7.0 before planting a mention your soil
with compost or well- rotted manure to
improve fertility and
drainage this will provide the nutrients
your peas need to grow strong three
planting depth and spacing plant PE
seeds about 1 to 2 in deep and space
them 2 to 4 in apart in rows that are 18
to 24 in apart if you're planting in a
container ensure it's at least 12 in
deep to accommodate the root system four
watering after planting water the seeds
gently but thoroughly to help them
germinate keep the soil consistently
moist but not water logged once the
plants are established they can tolerate
some drought but regular watering will
promote better growth and
yield five support
structures depending on the variety some
peas may need support as they grow peas
and climbing varieties benefit from
trellises Stakes or netting install
these supports at the time of planting
to avoid disturbing The Roots later six
mulching applying a layer of mulch
around your pea plants can help retain
moisture suppress weeds and regulate
soil
temperature organic mulches Like Straw
or shredded leaves work well and will
break down over time adding nutrients
back into the soil seven companion
planting consider planting peas
alongside compatible crops like carrots
radishes or cucumbers
these companions can help deter pests
and improve overall Garden Health just
be sure to avoid planting peas near them
eight
fertilization peas are nitrogen fixing
plants meaning they can take nitrogen
from the air and convert it into a form
that plants can use because of this they
generally don't require heavy
fertilization however a light
application of a balanced fertilizer at
planting can help boost initial growth
especially if your soil is is low in
nutrients nine Pest and disease
management keep an eye out for common
pests like aphids PE Weevil and spider
mites you can manage these pasts by
introducing beneficial insects like
ladybugs or using insecticidal soap if
necessary additionally ensure good air
circulation around your plants to
prevent diseases like powdery mildew 10
thinning once your pea plants have grown
a few inches tall thin the if they are
too crowded this will allow for better
air circulation and reduce competition
for
nutrients aim for the recommended
spacing of 2 to 4 in between plants 11
harvesting as your peas grow keep an eye
on them for harvesting snap still tender
while Garden peas should be harvested
when the pods are full but before they
start to turn yellow regular harvesting
encourages the plants to produce more
pods planting peas is a rewarding
experience that can yield delicious
results with the right timing soil
preparation and Care you'll be on your
way to enjoying fresh peas straight from
your garden now that your peas are
planted let's talk about how to care for
them to ensure a healthy and productive
crop proper maintenance is key to
maximizing your yield and keeping your
plants
thriving one
watering consistent moisture is
essential for pea plants especially
during their flowering and pots setting
stages aim to provide about 1 in of
water per week either through rainfall
or supplemental
watering water deeply to encourage
strong root development but avoid
overhead watering to minimize the risk
of fungal
diseases two
mulching as mentioned earlier applying a
layer of mulch around your pea plants
can help retain soil moisture and
suppress weeds organic mulches like
straw grass clippings or shredded leaves
not only provide these benefits but also
break down over time enriching the soil
three wheed control weeds can compete
with your pea plants for nutrients and
water regularly check your garden for
weeds and remove them by hand or with a
hoe be careful not to disturb the roots
of your pea plants while weeding four
fertilization while peas are nitrogen
fixing and generally don't require heavy
fertilization you can apply a light dose
of a balanced fertilizer or compost tea
if you notice slow growth or yellowing
leaves avoid High nitrogen fertilizers
as they can promote Leaf growth at the
expense of pot
production five Pest
Management keep an eye out for pest
regularly inspect the undersides of
leaves for signs of pests and take
action promptly to prevent
infestations six disease prevention to
prevent diseases such as powdery mildew
ensure good air circulation around your
plants by space them properly and
avoiding
overcrowding if you notice any diseased
plants remove them immediately to
prevent the spread of
infection seven supporting your plants
as your pea plants grow they may need
additional support if you haven't
already set up trellises or Stakes do so
carefully to avoid disturbing The Roots
peas naturally climb so providing them
with a sturdy support use trellises
netting or even simple staks to help
your plants climb this not only keeps
the plants upright but also improves air
circulation and makes harvesting easier
be sure to check the support regularly
and adjust as needed to accommodate the
growing plants eight pruning while peas
generally don't require much pruning you
can remove any yellowing or damaged
leaves to promote better air flow and
reduce the risk of
disease this also helps the plant Focus
its energy on producing healthy pods
nine monitoring
growth regularly check your plants for
signs of stress such as wilting
discoloration or stunted growth keeping
a close eye on your plants will help you
catch any issues early and take
corrective action 10
harvesting as your peas mature be sure
to harvest them
regularly for snap and snow peas pick
them when they are plump but still
tender for garden peas wait until the
pods are full but before they start to
yellow regular harvesting encourages the
plants to produce more pods extending
your harvest season 11 as well snow peas
are best enjoyed when they are still
tender and sweet for garden peas wait
until the pods are full and round but
before they start to turn yellow this
usually occurs about 60 to 70 days after
planting depending on the variety the
peas inside should be sweet and firm two
how to harvest use your fingers to
gently pinch the stem just above the Pod
to avoid damaging the plant if the pods
are particularly tough you can use
scissors or garden shears to cut them
off be careful not to pull too hard as
this can disturb the roots of the plant
harvest in the morning when the
temperatures are cooler as this helps
preserve the sweetness and crispness of
the peas three storing your Harvest
freshly harvested peas are best enjoyed
right away but if you need to store them
them keep them in a breathable container
in the
refrigerator avoid washing them until
you're ready to use them as moisture can
lead to
spoilage for longer storage consider
blanching your peas in boiling water for
a couple of minutes then plunging them
into ice water to stop the cooking
process after they cool drain and freeze
them in airtight
bags this method preserves their flavor
and
nutrients four encouraging continued
production ra regular harvesting is key
to encouraging your pea plants to
produce more pods the more you pick the
more the plants will focus their energy
on to wrap up our guide on growing peas
let's go over some essential tips for
Success that will help you maximize your
yield and enjoy a thriving pea Garden
one as well snow peas are best enjoyed
when they are still tender and sweet for
garden peas wait until the pods are full
and round but before they start to turn
yellow this usually occurs about 60 to
70 days after planting depending on the
variety the peas inside should be sweet
and firm two how to harvest use your
fingers to gently pinch the stem just
above the Pod to avoid damaging the
plant if the pods are particularly tough
you can use scissors or garden shears to
cut them off be careful not to pull too
hard as this can disturb the roots of
the plant harvest in the morning when
the temperatures are cooler as this
helps preserve the sweetness and
crispness of the peas three storing your
Harvest freshly harvested peas are best
enjoyed right away but if you need to
store them keep them in a breathable
container in the
refrigerator avoid washing them until
you're ready to use them as moisture can
lead to
spoilage for longer storage consider
blanching your peas and boiling water
for a couple of minutes then plunging
them into ice water to stop the cooking
process after after they cool drain and
freeze them in airtight
bags this method preserves their flavor
and
nutrients four encouraging continued
production regular harvesting is key to
encouraging your pea plants to produce
more pods the more you pick the more the
plants will focus their energy on to
wrap up our guide on growing peas let's
go over some essential tips for Success
that will help you maximize your yield
and enjoy a thriving pea Garden one
choose the right variety selecting the
right PE variety for your climate and
growing conditions is crucial some
varieties are better suited for cooler
climates While others thrive in warmer
temperatures research and choose
varieties that are known to perform well
in your area two soil
preparation peas prefer well draining
lomy soil rich in organic matter before
planting amend your soil with compost or
well- rotted manure to improve fertility
and and drainage a soil pH of 6.0 to 7.0
is ideal for optimal growth three
planting depth and spacing plant your PE
seeds about 1 to 2 in deep and space
them 2 to 4 in apart this allows for
good air circulation and reduces
competition for
nutrients if you're planting in rows
space the rows about 18 to 24 in apart
to make it easier to access the plants
for maintenance and harvesting
four watering
wisely consistent moisture is key
especially during germination and
flowering water your peas deeply but
infrequently to encourage deep root
growth avoid overhead watering to reduce
the risk of fungal diseases instead
water at the base of the
plants five
mulching applying a layer of organic
mulch around your pea plants can help
retain soil moisture suppress weeds and
regulate soil temperature
straw grass clippings or shredded leaves
work well as mulch
materials six companion
planting consider planting peas
alongside compatible crops like carrots
radishes or
turnips these plants can benefit from
the nitrogen fixed by the pea plants
while also helping to deter
pests seven Pest and disease
management keep an eye out for common
pests like aphids and pea weevils
introduce beneficial insects like
ladybugs to help control pest
populations
naturally additionally practice crop
rotation each year to minimize the risk
of soil born
diseases eight fertilization continued
while peas are nitrogen fixing plants
and generally require less fertilizer a
light application of a balanced
fertilizer at planting can help boost
initial growth avoid High nitrogen
fertilizers as they can lead to
excessive foliage growth at the expense
of pot production nine support
structures if you're growing climbing
varieties of peas provide adequate
support with trellises Stakes or netting
this not only helps the plants grow
upright making harvesting easier but
also improves air circulation and
reduces the risk of disease 10 regular
monitoring keep a close eye on your
plants for any signs of stress pests or
diseases early detection is key to
managing issues before they become
serious problems regular Le the leaves
and stems for any unusual spots or
discoloration 11 harvesting at the right
time as mentioned earlier timing your
Harvest is crucial for flavor and
texture regularly check your plants and
harvest peas as soon as they reach the
desired size this encourages the plants
to produce more pods 12 enjoying your
Harvest fresh peas are best enjoyed
right after harvesting
consider incorporating them into salads
stir fries or simply steaming them as a
side dish the sweet crisp flavor of
freshly picked peas is
unmatched 13 learn and adapt every
gardening season is a learning
experience take notes on what worked
well and what didn't and adjust your
practices for the next
planting engaging with local gardening
communities or online forums can also
provide valuable insights and tips
by following these tips you'll be well
on your way to a successful pea
Harvest remember gardening is as much
about patience and observation as it is
about
technique happy gardening and there you
have it with these tips you'll be well
on your way to a bountiful pea
Harvest if you enjoyed this video don't
forget to like subscribe and hit that
notification Bell for more gardening
tips what are you planning to grow next
let me know in the comments comments
below happy gardening and see you next
time