should I walk run really fast like they
do in the old time yes yes we planted
this in 2013 it's a Gravenstein apples
and it desperately needs pruning let's
see what you can do in one minute
[Music]
I think that may have been the 45-second
foe but it's okay can you tell us I can
tell you why I did what I did okay
because I only had 60 seconds that's why
I did what I did okay so just for the
quick and dirty you know we hadn't this
Scot was getting what you called leggy
it was getting too long the branches the
fruit can break the branch right so what
essentially what did you do what I guess
I took out all the branches that were
really low that may be when you mow and
drive a tractor and I took all the
branches going straight up and the ones
that are going way out too far because
this branch is way too long for its
thickness okay so what I did is I found
a side branch here that and I left the
tip you always live to terminal bud oh
and I left the tip there and that will
become where the new branch goes out but
it's not near as long it was so long
that it was going to bend down like this
when the fruit came on yeah and bent out
of shape and then it would stop
producing as well and for the top what I
did it was about six feet taller yeah
and so what I did is I took I found a
branch that we could Bend like this so
there's still one more thing needs to be
done here okay I'm gonna put a stake up
here Oh like you're gonna put a stake
here yeah and you're gonna take this
branch and you're gonna tie it with a
piece of bamboo like this and this is
the new top oh so it has a top and
because the top still has a terminal bud
that I didn't cut back yeah it would
gives a message to all the other bud
other branches to grow out and produce
fruit if I would have cut that off yeah
whenever you cut a terminal bud off a
branch it puts out a bunch of side
branches below that and we didn't want
more branches so I made sure I didn't
just cut it off like here I cut it off
to a branch that we could tie up with a
terminal bud and that's gonna be your
new top and you've got to remember to
put a little bamboo stake right up there
and now your trees about five foot
shorter and it has the branches going
where they want okay is that something
that we would never trim off later then
that will always stay there no what's
going to happen is this is going to grow
way
yeah and eventually it's gonna get way
taller than you want and you're gonna do
the same thing so imagine now instead of
standing on the ground I've climbed up a
ladder and this it's like 10 years from
now and I'm like about safe five six
feet off the ground
and I'm up at the top of the tree it
it's really tall like that I'm gonna
look for a new branch like this one
right here and I'm gonna cut everything
off above there and this thing new one's
going to become the top but I'm not
going to tip it back I'm gonna let it
stay and it'll become the new top and
that's what you always keep doing it on
your trees you make them shorter but you
always keep a top by finding a less
vigorous branch that's going upwards and
that's well usually like in the winter
and stuff we could probably could have
found a branch that was going up enough
we wouldn't a need even to stay give it
okay it's kind of kind of a rule of
thumb and you're thinning your fruit and
it's a good time to do it what you want
to do is put your hand out and wherever
your thumb is and your your little
finger that's about how far the fruit
should be apart so you can do that now
in just a second the other door so take
these two off well you can leave one
about here what about here is fine
that's enough
usually they're in a cluster of like
five you picked the just one of them to
keep out of the cluster so you go
through your orchard and about this time
of year when the fruit is roughly the
size of a Super Bowl yeah and you start
pulling that off mm-hmm and you can you
can pull it or you can use a little
pruners and turn it off but here is it
so pretty much you got a figure about 35
leaves can support one fruit in general
give you an idea but if you don't want
to count leaves you could use the rule
of thumb I really enjoyed editing this
video and kind of just kind of was a
reminder of what a wonderful time we had
with with Sam and James from rain tree
nursery that came out and helped us with
us orchard
or with our orchard I think this video
is really important because it it really
distills them I think it really
simplifies for the you know for the
common person kind of some basic things
to help take care of our fruit trees
that I have never really known how to do
to be honest with you I've always been
somewhat intimidated about cutting that
I was afraid I was gonna do something
wrong and I have never really known why
we weren't getting a lot of fruit and
just by adopting this rule of thumb and
thinning the fruit out if you know in
June or early summer and and the the
simple tricks or instructions for
pruning I feel confident to be able to
go out and do this so I hope you enjoyed
the video and again another very
heartful thank you to to the folks at
Raintree for coming out and putting this
on and sharing this this vast knowledge
with the rest of us also we have a
coupon code
Raintree nursery ships all over the
country so we would like to support them
and you want to get on the list now
pre-order so you have will guarantee
your shipments for your fruit next year
and the coupon codes regular start so
just go to regular star and tell them we
said hello and we really appreciate
appreciate everyone's support so thanks
for watching don't forget to click the
thumbs up and we'll see you guys on the
next video