[Music]
I'm Jeremy Smith and Trish Jenkins so we
have a little farm mixed vegetable farm
here in Spearfish Valley and we're kind
of halfway through our sixth season here
the Spearfish Valley is in western South
Dakota twelve miles from Wyoming we're
the northern Black Hills when we started
the farm we were marketing through the
farmers market in town and then three
years ago now we moved one of the old
farm stands from down the road to the
front of our place and started selling
just direct from the farm we have a
pretty good crop rotation that we're
happy with some of its on a four-year
rotation where it's peas and beans corn
or garlic potatoes and then winter
squash so that's one of our four year
rotations and then the rest of the
vegetable beds are on an eight year
rotation between families a big part of
our land management practices is we're
doing a mixed vegetable production on
using no-till methods
and that's requiring a lot of mulching
and cover cropping we're trying to have
the soil covered pretty much all the
time if we have gaps in the in the
vegetable rows we're trying to get cover
crops in there and get living roots
feeding the soils of pulling carbon
dioxide out of the air through
photosynthesis and feeding soil
microbiology increasing our soil organic
matter because that's one of the reasons
why we're trying to build the organic
matter in the soil and keep things
covered and we're on sort of a not too
temperamental but a little bit
temperamental watering system and if
it's dry and the waters shut down if
there's like it up the line breaks or
something you don't have to stress too
much about not having water back there
because the soil has that resiliency to
manage some dryness there seems to be a
push of matching that like the no-till
and soil health principles from bigger
agriculture down to the small scale that
I think a lot of new farmers or people
like ourselves that didn't grow up in
agriculture but that are coming to it
are coming to it and seeing like the
benefits of soil health practices and so
they're trying to apply these things
that have been figured out on big scales
shrinking them down to like how do I
have like arugula crops here and still
not disturb the soil even though I've
got tiny little seeds that I'm trying to
plant we're growing organically beyond
that we're trying to minimize our off
arm input so as much compost and
nutrients that we can generate on farm
we're trying to do that and the crop
rotation has helped us with nutrient
cycling on the farm and making sure that
we can
kind of feed everybody appropriately
yeah and that we're not like pulling all
of a certain nutrient out by having the
same crop in the place over and over
trying to get people on the farm and
engaged with the local food system I
think is a an important part of what we
do in addition to the farm stand we also
take some produce to a couple of local
restaurants in town I guess we'd say
that the like awareness of local food
and support from the community has grown
over the last six years awareness of
local foods in kind of it some of the
benefits are just just kind of starting
to like snowball here so it's really
exciting to kind of be here at the
beginning of that and kind of watch as
the local food system develops so once
in a while we get asked why we're
farming or why we're we're doing this or
why in Spearfish or part of its that we
both really like like massive challenges
that are like multifaceted and we have a
friend that farms in new hampshire that
has a beautiful like quote that farming
is not rocket science it's a lot harder
than that
which we love so that kind of like
challenge of farming but also the the
idea that like we can do really good
work that is beneficial in as many ways
as possible so like the carbon
sequestering the feeding the community
the like education component like that
the farm every aspect of it can be a
positive and feel rewarding I think is a
lot of why we want to do it
you
[Music]