[Music]
[Applause]
going on a road trip going to get a big
one what are we going to go
get bow a
bowl are you excited yeah good I too
pretty
excited in January Ryan
was in a car accident and he injured his
ribs pretty bad and could not work we
went a couple of weeks without a
paycheck and we went over a month
without going grocery shopping and one
of the good things that came out of it
is we realized that we had enough meat
and
vegetables in our storage because we had
raised enough from our farm and we were
okay there the only thing that I had to
have Ryan stop and get at the grocery
store during that month was milk butter
cheese and sour cream all dairy products
and all I could think was we have got to
make getting these cow's bread the top
priority so after 2 years of trying to
find a bowl locally to breed our Piney
Woods and now our mini Jersey we have
fin finally found what we hope is the
perfect bow he is very young so we have
a little bit of time to raise him before
he's going to be ready for the job but
it should be pretty minimal amount of
time considering we've already waited 2
years so one of the challenges that we
have faced with having our own cows is
finding the proper B to breed them with
originally we thought we were going to
have access to a Pineywoods bowl that
didn't work work out and we started
searching for a bowl for our piny Woods
2 years ago well a lot of people don't
realize is Piney Woods are actually a
very short breed of cow they're usually
under 45 in into the mini range and so
what I was looking for was a mini bowl
or a bowl 45 in or shorter like a Dexter
um mini Highland mini jersey and because
we have a small farm with small kids we
really didn't want the bulll as a
full-time Adventure we wanted to borrow
a bull breed our cows and be done with
it that did not work
out at one point we had a texture lined
up but he ended up getting sold before
we had a chance to use him so the
journey continued on searching for the
right Bowl one that was small enough to
breed our cows safely but also you know
make Mak sure that they were disease
test disease free tested good you know
quality all of that became a very
difficult Journey we looked into Ai and
from everything in our research AI would
be a very expensive way to maybe get our
cows sprad looking into AI turned out to
be something that I didn't think we
could financially handle there were a
lot of different reasons why I also was
faced with AI technicians that said that
they could not get the straws for the
smaller bowls and nobody guarantees it
it's not a guarantee even if I pay
almost $1,000 to have my cow
AI I have no guarantee that it would
work and they don't come back and do it
again for free so it didn't feel like
the right fit for us in our situation we
don't have a cattle shoot we don't have
the infrastructure that would have made
made it easy to do AI so we went back to
looking at Bulls again we basically sat
back prayed on it said you know all
right let's see what the universe is
going to bring us we we know that the
right decision is ahead of us we know
that we're going to get our cows bread
we just don't know how yet and then I
came across an ad for some beautiful
miniature Jersey gold
cabs
[Music]
[Applause]
oh
I tell you what this is nothing like a
baby goat or sheep bottle this thing's
huge baby calves are
huge morning
chap how are you doing
buddy good
morning are you ready for your
Bubba
yeah oh you know what time it
is yes you
do just about the cutest time ever on
the
homestead so this is
trap he is our new Mini Jersey bull calf
and he will be breeding in a few
months when he's
ready to our mini Jersey Daisy and our
Piney Woods
so we are very excited to have this
opportunity for milk on our Homestead at
a much higher volume than goats or sheep
could ever
provide he keeps running for the door
even though it's closed it's like he
almost knows it's not locked I'm trying
not to get attached or overly
affectionate with him because he is a
bull and Bulls can be dangerous when
they're older
which is super hard cuz he is so so
sweet he wants more milk I'm trying to
break his bottles up into two feedings
for my sanity cuz his bottle only holds
half a
gallon so yeah he thinks he's supposed
to have more milk right
now but we're going to break it up into
two feedings a day instead of
one oh no put it his head don't pit his
head I have to keep telling myself that
my cows love to have their head
scratched so I'm trying not to do that
cuz he's a bull and I don't want to
encourage any off
behaviors but he likes his neck
scratched and he likes his body
scratched so I'll do
that it's hard not to love on him all
day long but I also want to make sure
that
he doesn't get to be a mean Jersey so
he's staying in the trailer today we got
home late last night and it was dark so
we said okay you just go to bed we'll
we'll set you up with a cool little spot
in the
morning so when Ryan gets home in a
little bit we're going to do just that
aren't we but buddy I keep calling him
buddy cuz he's like a buddy but
his his other friend that we didn't
purchase was named buddy so I'm like I'm
hope I'm not confusing him but yeah he's
doing good I shouldn't be letting him
look on me probably huh that's what some
of you probably going to be saying in
the comments I'm going to take all
advice that um is kindly
delivered and I'm going to do even more
research because I was actually thinking
we were going to end up getting buddy
who is already off of the bottle he was
a month older and then when I met them
it was obvious see how he just did that
headbutt thing that's
a I want my mama milk movement I don't
want them to think I'm mama so I got to
be a little more assertive with him
using my knee to push him back when he's
a little too pushy and I don't want to
stop him from licking me I oh my gosh
how am I supposed to not let him do that
oh I can't let him do that it's bad I
can't do this oh my goodness I'm going
to get so much Flack for
this God she's so
sweet how do you people with bowls on a
bottle handle
this I don't know how to handle it but
I'm going to do my best and it's going
to be it's it's going to be good
enough he's only going to be here long
enough for his
breeding and then we will offer him to a
new
home
[Music]
Daisy do you have pollen in your
nose huh you got Pine poen all in your
nostrils hi
baby so Daisy is ready for breeding but
we've had a hard time finding a bowl
locally that is small enough for her so
we had to take steps to get our very
own
all right come
on I turned it on to show how good he
was walking with me and he stopped okay
come on he's such a good boy come on
baby bringing him to his new
shelter I decided to let him off the
leash here in the quiet
guine in the buck pan so he could
stretch his legs get some
exercise
this is his new shelter over here until
he's big enough to go in with the big
girls good work
daddy those cows are like what is
that
feeding time on the
homestead everybody gets a little bit of
grain even if they don't quite need
it spoiled
babies good job
Daddy good job
Liam
yeah good job
trap I'm going to go make you a bottle
okay
will you be will you be happy if I make
you a bottle you got your nice
bed you got lots of hay and water and
food oops and you're super curious
you're so sweet I'm not supposed to pet
the head is that right I don't know he
seems so young still like he needs a
little bit more affection cuz he's so
little I'm so little all right I'm going
to go get you a bottle you're acting
like you need a bottle
you're doing that bottle thing that
babies
do who's a good boy huh who's a good boy
trap what are you doing
Liam I'm feeding the cat that's fun huh
yeah
a he loves oops careful like I said
watch when he bumps that you don't bump
your knuckles on the
fence he is very excited to have his
bottle you know there is one thing that
I can say is that cows are a much
different investment than
goats you are going to spend four times
as much on a single
animal the inputs of milk are going to
be four times as much the inputs of time
are four times as much everything is
just quadruples
but it's so going to be worth it I just
know it I can't wait till I'm just
making cheese and butter and enjoying
all of the fresh raw milk for our family
one thing I know is that with three
growing boys the goat milk was just not
high enough volume and high enough cream
to make all of the other sub products so
this was the best decision our family
could make and I do not regret it not
one bit I don't regret the time or the
money invested into this it is already
filled my heart with pride and love and
I am so glad oh that we could do this hi
Daisy I heard you she wasn't there when
I started recording she just showed up
she loves her
mama don't you Daisy girl don't you love
mama she what
girl this my Daisy Daisy is where my
dream really began to come true never
thought I would be able to get a mini
Jersey
[Laughter]
heer but with the generosity of somebody
gifting this one to us made it
possible never could have done it
otherwise