hey guys it's from a bread and I'm going
to take you along for my morning chores
it's gonna grab some breakfast my go-to
breakfast cereal is many processed foods
it's the best of both worlds
you got your sweet side and you got your
regular side
[Music]
okay so first up guy
the pair of the meat birds a bag of food
[Applause]
on the farm here let's measure feed out
by this new gallon bucket most common
what a Mexican water bucket I hate the
gallon version that works well we're
measuring out the feed I usually tell
myself is this a one bucket or two
bucket operation and go ahead and move
this chicken tractor
[Applause]
now unto the other chicken tractor
now right behind me is the main flaw now
they are taking care of is they have the
automatic chicken water bucket right
there and then they have a lot of feed
in the inside that I only have to fill
it up like maybe every two weeks then
over here I have some juveniles that are
growing up and they're taken care of
with the automatic chicken water then up
in here either feeder
and then I just gotta finish put in the
other water and that front chicken
tractor and I almost forgot to show you
the baby chicks so last Friday we
received a hundred and sixty-one baby
chicks and now we're down to a hundred
and fifty a hundred and fifty-six
[Music]
[Applause]
thanks for coming along to my morning
chores hope you enjoyed the video and
hope you have an excellent day bye