uh first of all I want to just say that
I am not a PhD I am a PhD candidate so
hopefully I'll have that done uh here
within the next year year and a half so
uh one of the things that um I'd like to
uh talk about is um how we can mimic
mother nature and I'm having a little
bit of difficulty doesn't seem like I
can move so I'm going to let you guys
move it let's go to the next slide so we
want to mimic Mother Nature with the
application of manure and when I talked
to Regulators I'd like to remind them
that you know in the early 1800s we had
over 60 million buffalo in the United
States and and the question I like to
often ask is did they stop eating or
pooping in the winter time and of of
course they didn't and and did we have a
water quality problem so um as far as we
know we had pretty good water quality
back then I think there's a few lessons
we can learn from uh the Buffalo first
you need to apply the manure to a live
crop second if we apply low rates and
we've already heard many of our speakers
talk about that and then really third is
proper uh management of that grass uh uh
those those Buffalo rotational gray so
if we go to the next slide and if you
look at uh This Grass uh you can see
that uh in in one case we have a lot of
roots and in another case so we have
very few so I'm reminded uh several
years ago uh there there was a report
that came out that said 45% of the osor
is coming off of graze land and that
confused me until I saw this slide in a
lot of cases where we have uh very
little top growth we'll get about 50%
top growth 50% uh below ground growth
and if you have the grass is over Grace
you're not going to have very many roots
there uh we we need to think about how
we manage not only the cover crops but
all all of our plants so the more Roots
we have you have to remember live Roots
absorb soluble nitrogen soluble
phosphorus next slide
so if we look at uh some Concepts on
eco-farming where we're using notil and
cover crops we hear a lot about notel
how the macropores move that water
through the soil very quickly so I like
to think of them as super highways but
if we can move that water from a
macropore to a micropore to a biopore uh
we can actually use the roots there
where we have the cover crops and they
can actually absorb a lot of this
nitrogen and they can slow down uh the
the the water so that we have time for
that minerology the soil Act is a a very
good filter of these nutrients so
between the minerology and live plants
we can absorb a lot of soluble nutrients
especially nitrogen and phosphorus next
next slide so as we look at um uh what
we've done when we do intensive tillage
we tend to get these hard pans or a plow
pan there uh here we're going down uh 20
cm or about 8 in and uh that gives us
less soil volume to work with where we
have continuous noil and of course my
goal is to have uh continuous living
cover out there we have this network of
biopores uh that uh will slow that water
down and give it time that we can
actually absorb uh some of that nitrogen
and phosphorus so it's it's a retention
time the longer we can retain that water
in uh in the soil the the better U we
can uh absorb some of that nitrogen
phosphorus next slide so uh as we look
at some of the data soil organic matter
is extremely important on average we'
lost about 50 to 60% of our soil organic
matter uh from our soils uh if you look
at a sandy soil um it may have anywhere
from 1 to 2 and a half um uh store 1 to
2 and A2 Ines of water but it really
depends on the amount of soil organic
matter so the higher the soil organic
matter what this slide shows is that so
organic matter and available water
holding capacity per inch uh inches of
water per one foot of soil so a sand
will go from 1 to 2 and2 a silt Loom can
go from uh almost 2 to four uh and a
silly clay LOM can go from 1.4 to three
again as you increase that so organic
matter you can uh really store more
water and have more chance to treat it
next slide it's also related though to
how fast the water is moving So the
faster the water is moving it's actually
exponential so it goes up 2 to the six t
uh Power so uh if I double the speed of
water I can actually uh uh carry 64
times more nutrients so going from 1 to
2 mph is 64 times more nutrients uh that
uh uh that water can hold some of our
streams are actually moving now at 16 to
to close to 30 m hour we see a lot of
flashiness there and so that's over a
thousand times more nutrients the good
thing about the cover crops and the
plants as they slow that water down and
then they'll drop their load next slide
if we look at where nutrients are
extracted majority of them are extracted
in that top couple of inches so that's
where we want to put the manure as much
as possible uh and uh the deeper we get
that manure in the soil if we inject it
too deep uh the closer we are to some of
our subsurface drain so again over 40%
generally at least on corn 40% of it's
be taken up within that top 6 in so we
want to think about root structure and
where that manure needs to be applied
next next slide so what what cover crops
to use uh there's a there's a number of
different ones we have grasses versus
brassas versus legumes the nice thing
about the grasses they tie up uh
nitrogen and phosphorus they have very
fibrous root systems um most of them
live year round one of the best cover
crops we have to tie up uh manure is
oats but the problem with oats are they
they generally die uh in the winter
brascas uh also take up uh a lot of
manure they they can take up a very high
concentration of nitrogen uh but again
some of those brascas especially the r
radishes will die when it gets to be
about 15° fah legumes already make their
own nitrogen but they will readily
absorb uh uh free nitrogen if it's out
there so in in many cases we may decide
to put out a uh a mixture but if we are
going to put out a mixture we would
really heavily lean towards some of the
grasses cuz they they tend to do maybe
just a little bit better job Force so
again as we look at some of the
different types of cover crops next
slide um we're looking at the grasses
some of the ones that that uh we like to
use Are cereal Rye TR annual Ry grass
barley uh wheat uh again oats is
probably one of the best ones but it
depends on what time of the year if
you're going into the winter uh the oats
can die off the Sorghum both the Sorghum
and most of the millets are summer
annuals so they will die with the first
frost on brasas radishes are commonly
used however those radishes get a very
big root and they uh can cause almost
like preferential flow they're going to
move that uh nutrients when they Decay
uh could move those nutrients lose them
very quickly so you have turn-ups uh
some of the ones that will survive the
winter are kale and rape and then the
legumes there's a number of different
legumes uh again we probably want those
to be a fairly small amount of the
mixture because they do make their own
nitrogen uh and they do tend to have tap
roots that will will move that manure uh
down uh quite deep next slide uh you can
see some of the nitrogen uptake uh this
was a study we did at Ohio State Annual
Ride grass had uh anywhere from 5 to
5.3% nitrogen in the tissue we had four
4550 lbs of of nitrogen being recycled
serial Rye had 4 to 42% nitrogen the
tissue or about 350 to 400 lounds of
nitrogen and of course the daycon radish
they had the highest uptake but again
they also had the fastest release
because uh they can uh uh they will
decompose once it gets cold next slide
shows uh uh probably what we'd like to
say is an award-winning uh uh radish
this is Dave brand uh who who raises a
lot of radish again the problem with the
radishes uh they take up a tremendous
amount of nutrients uh very efficient
but uh since they don't survive the
winter uh in most cases uh they they can
release it so on the next slide we're
looking at the amount of fall soil
nitrate after manure application uh this
was an average of 24 test over seven
field sites you can see where we had no
cover we had
21.3 parts for million nitrogen compared
to where we had the oil seed radish uh
we had 6.5 in in the in the soil so
those radishes take up a lot of of
nutrients however again they can be an
issue uh going into the winter if if
when they die what are the best cover
crops next slide for manure
uptake uh again oats and radish are
probably the best ones if you're
applying in the uh in the summer uh
early fall but if you're going to if you
want those nutrients toh tie over into
uh the winter and through the spring
months you can see the ones that we have
starred that means that they generally
survive the winter seral Rye annual Ry
grass are uh have some of the the best
root structures and take up a lot of of
nutrients uh wheat and barley can also
take up nutrients but they're not don't
have near the root structure that Cal
Rye or anual Ry grass for the brasas we
have kale and rape uh you can see the
turnips and the radish they generally
will die out and then all the uh the
legumes we have winter peeas crimson
clover red clover sweet clover hay vetch
uh cow peas is one that is a an annual
summer annual and that will die out next
crop uh as you can see here uh this is a
slide where we had annual Ry grass and
we can get tremendous growth uh these
grasses take up a uh a lot of nor her
where we plied 6,000 gallons of swine
manure and we got some tremendous growth
just within 45 days so again the grasses
have more of a fibrous root system and
are very efficient at taking up manure
nutrients next next slide cover crops
for winter application of manure what do
we want in a good cover crop we want a
live plant to absorb both nitrogen and
phosphorus I prefer to see fibrous root
systems versus a Tap Root not that we
can't do some mixtures but you want to
make sure that you have some that are
going to survive that winter uh and uh
have some of the fibers more fibrous
root systems we want something that will
hold up the equipment in wet weather uh
in a lot of cases uh especially on
livestock Farms there's the forage
possibilities of getting something out
of that cover crop it needs to be easy
to kill and then we don't want to have
too many carryover problems for the next
crop either with insects weeds or uh
tying up those nutrients too long so if
we let those grasses grow too long in
the spring sometimes we can get some
apathic effects uh or uh they'll uh tie
up that nitrogen and won't make it
available to the next crop if they get
too high of a carbon and nitrogen ratio
next C next slide cover crops again for
manure winter manure application uh
these are probably the the five best
ones kind of in order seral Ry annual Ry
grass sometimes with Annual Ride grass
can be a little tough to kill uh and it
can become a weed problem the tral The
Barley the wheat uh if you're looking at
mixtures uh don't want to put out too
many of the radish probably no more than
a pound per acre at the most oats can be
part of that mixture and then uh
obviously we can put a few of the
legumes in but we don't want them to
make up too much last issue is uh uh
some things that we might want to be a
little bit concerned about is on very
short pastures because we don't have the
the root growth there uh we can get uh a
lot of uh uh either running off the
surface or even through preferential
flow we can get cracks in those those
pastures it's all about root growth and
then where we have alphalpha hay because
it has such a long tap route uh and
especially on a mature alphaalpha hay
field uh they tend to be very leaky and
sometimes those can uh get into uh uh
the tile line so you have to be a little
bit concerned you have to pick your
cover crops uh in order to avoid some of
these issues so I think cover crops can
really help us uh uh by adding that
extra organic matter and tying up some
of these soluble nutrients