I was sick and tired of having all of my
tractor tools stored in the weeds grass
growing up through them you couldn't mow
around it they're just buried in a pain
to get to I put 300 linear foot of
parking pad storage for all my tractor
attachments 10 foot wide it took three
rolls of fabric 100 foot rolls of uh
like the under driveway geotextile
fabric 40 yards of 21 double A I've got
2 000 bucks into it about a dollar and a
half foot I'm sure there's a lot of
other ways to do it but this way worked
for me keeps the weeds at Bay nice high
and dry above everything else so that
kind of pool up in water I'd love to
have covered storage for them all but
this is a big Improvement what do you
think