[Music]
while farming anyway as a way of life
it's not a job it's a way of life you're
gonna be a bottom entity that's how you
have to look at it and organics
definitely is you have to open from my
personal point of view is you have to
work with nature of course within
organic farming is a whole spectrum
you're getting some organic farmers who
just see that not using chemicals as
they is the answer but they're still
using the industrial model of inputs and
outputs in their in their head and then
you get fertility that you have to start
seeing the farm as a whole and has to be
a balance there and that is one of the
main principles of a biodynamic farm
that behind this concept you have that
it it has to be not bringing in inputs
from outside that you see that the whole
farm is a kind of whole which has to be
in balance but you have to be able to be
use all the feed for your animals of
that farm that they in turn will if you
have the right balance of animals will
produce enough manure so different sorts
to maintain and increase the fertility
on the farm the important for in
biodynamic is to have the farmers in
organism so the farm is able to produce
all its own manure and it put a label to
produce its own fertility what people do
here which is much more efficient of
course is then to use the clover to feed
it to your ruminants to your cattle to
your sheep you know to your cows and
they in return give you when you are
it's very important that we all try and
go as organic as possible
for the health of everyone and I think
to try and reduce the amount of
chemicals that we're using because
firstly if the food is not organic
you're eating a lot of chemicals anyway
and then there's lots of chemicals used
to grow that food so if you can go
organic then it would reduce the damage
to the environment and then on top of
that in biodynamic farming there is the
concept of the preparations which are I
think enhancing the manure to a way that
the manure is able to really support the
plant life for it to support the animals
and the people that live on the farm and
feed of the farm so again in creating
this cycle of health and sustainability
by having the cows eating grass that is
suitable for them that is healthy and
then this money also goes into the
vegetable garden this money also goes
into producing grain in cereals which
then is fed the people through through
the farm shop with organic food
it's a very whole environment that you
grow up in so everything is affecting
that food and I think that makes you
very aware of your environment and what
you're bringing in and what you're
putting out so I think to learn to grow
organically is vital for how you treat
the tree and I think if you experience
the goodness that the organics brings in
to your food into your environment then
you start to see what else needs to be
done around you
cows biodynamically which means that all
of their food comes from our own farm
and it's all grown organically and we
use biodynamic preparations the cows
have their horns which we feel is very
important for the digestive systems
which is also reflected in the milk and
the milk is more nutritious and they get
to be outside all through year of the
year and in the summer months spring
summer autumn that they're out on grass
eating grass which is most natural way
for a cow and you can really taste in
the milk that it is sort of fresher more
nutritious and a lot of milk which is
you know blended for many different
farms in which is an organic I think the
future is definitely for people to see
not just organic or production but a
small-scale small-scale production which
is much more manageable for people and
is able to employ more people and
empower more people as to where their
food come from and to have healthy food
and have a stronger connection with
their food because with industrial
farming we have lost connection with the
source of our food and the quality of
our food one person can go to sue and
buy pepper doesn't matter what time of
the year we are able to import fruit and
vegetables from all over the world and
we don't think about where food comes
from and how much effort goes into it
but in this farm
it's a small farm 200 acre farm the
people who are fed from this farm that
people are in touch with this farm it's
much more in touch with the food I eat
mainly vegetarian some fish and I tend
to buy from local farmers markets only I
hardly ever enter a supermarket anymore
and eat mainly organic food mainly
vegetarian I was vegetarian completely
for it was only two years but I will eat
the meat from this farm or from our
sister farm table house because it's
biodynamic I know the people looking
after the animals and I know what food
they're eating and they're their
environment that they've grown up in so
as long as I know that I'm happy to eat
the meat I became vegetarian when I was
six so I haven't eaten meat in a long
time and I think probably if I wasn't
already vegetarian then I would probably
eat organic and biodynamic meat but I
don't really have any need for meat now
so I stay vegetarian I was vegetarian as
a child the whole family was vegetarian
but I own eat organic meat really oh by
dynamically vegetarian methods which are
available which can show that we're not
just talking about minerals and pure
substance but there are forces in our
food and working in nature and one of
those methods was developed by Pfeiffer
when he developed the chromatography and
I'm dr. Callisto as well with the
crystallization method and by using that
method you can see other than just the
chemical constituents of something but
it actually shows completely different
picture depending on how alive or dead
it is if there are forces in that or not
and and these pictures are quite
objective and it's absolutely clear you
can take a dead soil and take a sample
from that
and one which has been enlivened of that
same soil with compost and by dynamic
methods and it creates a completely
different picture each farm is a small
community of friend colleagues for being
interested in organic agriculture and
what the farm does here is to do with
the fact that you can involve the
community in it and also when you work
with biodynamic agriculture organic
agriculture they're actually producing
food that people can trust so after I
became more interested in organic food
and growing my own food and cooking my
own food
I got also interested in what isn't
organic or the conventional and and the
use of GMOs and me personally I'm
completely against using GMOs when
you're cooking or or eating or anywhere
because they unfortunately are
everywhere plant is genetically modified
it's missing a vital part of the life of
the plant and when you consume that
you're also missing that vital part of
life yeah I personally don't believe or
believe in GMOs because of the health
benefits of wealth for people and for
the for the planet as a whole I don't
think there that's gene-splicing is an
advantage I haven't seen proof of it
getting better yields the only potential
downsides I think and which is why I
avoid it is that it'll have an effect on
us do you know food I think is a
limiting food source
and limit your diet it limits the
variety you can eat and it makes you
very dependent on the seed companies
that produce this GMO seed you can't
save the seed you can't grow next year
from the same seed so for me that raises
questions about how good it is for you
if it yes it's not fertile enough to
produce its own seed that is viable then
to eat foods like that I don't know how
good that is for your body the
Terminator gene in it which means that
the plant is not able to produce seeds
for the next generation how does that
affect also honor on a material level on
a nutrient level maybe there is nothing
there it's the same as organic or
biodynamic soya but for me from a
quality point of view ask the question
how does it affect my own fertility if
I'm eating food that is not able to
carry its offspring is not able to
produce the next generation is God is
that not just only not able to is got a
gene that that is a terminator that
kills it the the risk of cross
contamination not only from one plant or
the other but from one plant to bacteria
to other organisms and so on and so on
it's a you don't know what you are
unleashing you have no idea but what one
thing is absolutely sure whatever you do
it's completely irreversible you will
never be able to stop it again once it's
out there it will be out there if it's
working out in a bad way there's no way
to reverse this process I'm very
suspicious of GMOs I have to say I
always try to buy from local farms when
I don't get my food from my own farm and
then I know I can trust the food I know
that I can talk to the farmers and see
how it was made and you know understand
the attitude of the people who made it
so that's really important to me
GMOs have clearly you know they've
historically they've been associated
with using pesticides
they've been associated with you know
infertility of seeds and things like
that and exploitation of farmers so
personally they're clear with them as
much as I can but also in the UK as well
as in a lot of countries sometimes
unless you are buying organic it's
impossible to know because they don't
label that something has got GMOs in it
so that makes it very hard to always be
certain and the last thing is that it
you know now a time and time again it
proves that GMO doesn't work again it's
the question of sustainability the fact
that I saw maybe a field of of GMO corn
and it's grown a good crop one year it
doesn't mean that it will go food every
year a lot of GMO crops have proved to
fail they don't have higher yields but
and they still need to have pesticides
herbicides and fungicides and the result
of it is then you get resistant strains
like the super weeds like and and this
just becomes a it just becomes an
accelerating process so if you get super
weeds then you need to use more poisons
and more poisons and then you need the
weeds get stronger and stronger and
you're not really solving the problem
the problem is not really solved well if
you create a balanced ecological system
and acknowledge the fact that there will
be weeds that they will be pests and
there will be diseases but to keep it in
in a balanced way I think it's much more
healthier slightest interest in going
back to growing your own food or buying
from local growers you should try and do
it because
to me that is the future basically when
you live in a city and you live just
with technology all around you where
life is so very so fast-paced you
actually gradually completely lose your
identity and you completely lose a sense
of what life really is about so for me
the journey of returning back to nature
and to working with the soil and with
plants every day has just been an
amazing journey like I have had so many
moments in the last year year and a half
where I felt so content and so connected
and where I've really been able to feel
joy just being with color with yeah
sounds of nature there's so much more
than just nutrition that you get so if
you have a chance and I would say try
and leave that bubble where you're
completely blinded and numbed by
technology and just try and go back to
nature wherever you can find it really
it I think it states the only way for
its small scale growing a lot of small
farms aren't able to grow and specialize
in certain things and but grow also a
wide variety of food in vegetables it's
also fun you know it is I wouldn't
choose it if it wasn't I like it's very
seasonal it's very rhythmic you always
have the most amazing food right at your
fingertips
so I would definitely recommend everyone
get into farming but it is really hard
work and obviously if you're doing
farming and do organic farming because
if you are a young person living in a
city and you have a desire to find out
what it's all about you just need to go
onto websites like the woof websites or
help X or there are so many resources on
the internet now that can allow you to
go and stay on organic farms in your own
country even you don't have to travel
around the world but that you can go and
stay at places like that and get an
experience volunteering for a few months
or even for a few weeks that would be a
great thing to do or alternatively try
and find in your own City if there are a
lot months available community projects
community allotments like here in the UK
we have quite a lot of those projects
and even while I was still working in an
office I used to go and volunteer on
Sunday afternoons try and find some of
these projects and help thee allow these
projects to help you spark
something we need to change your
lifestyle I really understand organics
is about just five
you
[Music]
hi this is Bart from the no plot
no pod or today we're here at rounder
organic farms with out of silverstein
Meyer and at was going to take us on a
tour of this organic farm and teach us
some of the tricks that he uses
crops without pesticides or fertilizers
now most people when they keep chickens
they may not even have a single - you
can build a roosting pet and you kept
all the manure it's very cool see all
the manure that's accumulating great
fertilizer so basically if you look
around in this room that is the only
spot the chickens have to sit even
awhile other than the nesting boxes but
if you look like above the nesting boxes
how we did that slope over there that's
so they can't sit up there
I see they really spend all their time
when they're in here sitting over there
okay that's why all the manure
accumulates over there and then there's
a trap door something is a trap door on
the outside of the building you lift up
and you can shovel that manure out okay
how long does it take to collect that
much I mean that's like a year that's a
year okay depends on how many chickens
you have and but supposedly they're like
70 to 80% or more of their manure is
being dropped right there okay and that
manure is pretty concentrated very
concentrated hot fertilizer you probably
want to let it sit okay and I see
compost to that for a year how much
coverage would you get out of that much
fertilizer well I mean usually when I'm
spreading and I'm just spreading like a
quarter inch you know on surface and
soil are 500 pounds per acre okay
you don't really eat you this whole body
let's go around back here okay door that
they can get in and out of here huh over
the fence out here okay and they took
over the edge okay so okay your tractor
over with the bucket yeah the remnants
of the veggies you know yep and leaving
their fertilizer for us very nice so
that's part of it
[Applause]
and then I'm kind of a big believer and
just for taking care of your soil and
then if you have healthy soils that most
for the most part most soils have a lot
of the nutrients that the plants need
and a lot of times when you have poor
growth that's because plants can't get
at the nutrients that they need okay so
a lot of times just by working your
soils by tilling them by irrigating them
well in our case irrigation spreading
some manure you'll you'll start to
improve the soil over the years of just
just the factor of aerating them you
know just telling them growing some kind
of a crop even if you're just growing a
cover crop like a crop that's just to
improve the soil okay clover or alfalfa
and then later in the season just mow
that down or till that back into the
soil okay and that process kind of helps
rejuvenate the soils and so part of what
I'm doing is I've got you know 15 acres
but I may be growing veggies on five
acres and and the other acreage each
year is is either fallow it's unused or
it's been some kind of a cover crop
that's growing so and I sort of have
this slow approach I'm not real big on
fertilizers I kind of feel like the
chemical fertilizers time to pump things
up they increase the amount of water
that the plans I've taken crop gets
bigger but I don't think it necessarily
makes it taste better and I don't think
that if you're not in a hurry
then you get the same kind of yields
without the chemical fertilizers it just
takes a look maybe a little bit longer
for the plants to reach maturity but I
think they're healthier I think
sometimes if your plants are growing too
fast they're weak
so I kind of had this idea that plants
like people have an immune system and
that that they have a resistance to
things like pests but if they're weak
the pests will have at them and you see
that we I see that in the field because
often the ends of my badge the far ends
are the part where the pests do the most
damage and a part of that is the
pressure coming from outside the field
but part of is that the the ones the
plants that are growing at the ends of
the beds are always the weakest because
they get trampled as you walk you know
cut the corners with the tractor or they
don't get weeded as well or they don't
get watered as well because they're at
the edge of the irrigation set so those
plants are weaker to begin with and then
that weakness translates into them
having more pressure from pests huh
that's interesting
I got that from one of my teachers who
was really into the whole immune system
and immunities when they're weak and you
definitely see that as plants start to
decline the pests kind of will move in
the other thing big thing that we're
doing out here for pests really is not
mono cropping you know I do have some
crops like corn maybe we'll have a
quarter acre of it but for the most part
you know what you see little patches yes
the row of that field that are that are
mostly just grown for the birds that
like them I grow there's a couple of
crops that I grow like dill and cilantro
that I will let go to flower and those
flowers will attract beneficial insects
okay but the big thing about having the
diversity is just that you're you're
reducing the habitat for the for the bad
insects for your past so if you have a
you know 10 acres of corn and then you
have a pests it likes corn they're just
going to flourish in there and go crazy
in your corn but if you just have a
little passion then you have something
else to have something else that there's
different pests that like each different
crop so you're sort of giving them less
territory to move in
and at least in our climate a lot of the
pests actually they they emigrate and
each year they don't overwinter here so
each year they have to come find you
and if you've just got a little bit of
this and a little bit of that it's
harder for them to find you
very loose yeah and then of course
you're also you're putting yourself at
less risk in terms of failure if you
have one crop that fails out of 25 crops
that you're growing it's not as much a
problem as if you're just going to crops
and you lose one of them so that's
another way that diversity helps so it
sounds like diversity is a big part of
your strategy all the way around it is
and also for nutrients per pass for
diseases soil diseases so diversity also
plays into rotation where you're not
growing the same crop in the same land
over and over again
cauliflower
and there's the Crucifier CA which is
like the or Brassica brassicas they're
called broccoli cauliflower kale cabbage
all those are in that same family let's
see what other vegetable crops are there
there's the alliums which is like the
onions the garlic shallots leeks all
those other smelling I look I've got a
book that's a little more of a guy that
would give us like all the information
but but the idea is that each you know
there really aren't that many different
plant families that we have I think in
justify vegetables and they each one of
those plant families as you get to know
them as a farmer they really are this is
very similar you know broccoli grows
very similar to cauliflower they like
the same conditions they use the same so
really that plays into a very nice the
other thing we do for passes we use
these this reamain material that's gonna
be hard to come by in order stuff
through the mail but that is a like a
fabric it's probably something they
could make very similar but like we have
problems with a certain pass that gets
on our soft leafed like the taut soy's
and the BOK Choy's of stuff it's the
flea beetle will just eat those up so we
cover those crops with this very thin
kind of fabric it's an agricultural
fabric rimae and it allows the air and
the water and the sunlight
you have some of that around crawl
around the breakers but it's just much
much less okay so that's what it sounds
like is that you're never going to
eliminate your pass on an organic farm
but doing everything you can to
interrupt their lifecycle yep yep and
you know people some people are you know
we we have the benefit of growing in a
desert climate so we don't really have
the kinds of best measures that some
people have but like our organic fruit
tree growers and they're spraying some
kind of an oil that has some kind of a
plant extract in it that's sick to those
bugs you know okay and it's organic
because it's made with organic source
materials that still sort of be very
intensive it requires a lot of
intervention yeah mostly what I'm doing
is doesn't require a lot of intervention
I'm mostly succeeding by the diversity
like I mentioned and volume and also
choosing it to grow here where there's
not a lot of pests various yeah
do you bring in beneficial insects you
know I have before but for the most part
I've kind of stopped doing that it's
really most effective when you when
you're in like a greenhouse and you can
keep them from flying away you know and
they do sell like you can get these bags
of ladybugs and you go and you spread
them and they're ravenous when they come
and and then you just watch them go to
work but later they're kind of gone okay
move on unless there's something
most of what I try to do is just again
create that habitat for them so when I
grow these breaks of dill and cilantro
and the ladybugs are drawn to that and
then they'll they'll go out and find
other food okay so dill and cilantro or
your big favorites for a favorites there
there in Umbra philaret family I was one
family we didn't talk about the
character in that family what else is in
that family I'm bull philaret
it's and and they make they all make a
similar kind of flower that's it's like
an umbrella
okay I'm bull comes from and and those
flower heads
that's dill okay that's the classic
humble family so there's quite a few
plants that have that same shaped
sometimes they're white sometimes a
yellow but they always have that kind of
open up you know okay and do you plant
the dill in with other crops directly no
but what happens is it goes to seed
every year okay every year it's kind of
just comes up wherever it and if I don't
weed it out then it's it's there
okay in this case I specifically left
this I mowed over the tops and most of
this potatoes to knock the weeds down
but I didn't know this people would want
deal for their pickling projects I say
that worked out what do we have grown
over here that kind of diversity is more
just about people enjoying the different
colors we see these sections that's one
other thing that happens that works
against okay so I'll clump together
these breasts because even though
ideally maybe they would be more
separated you know these are all
to get water Dalton and that's probably
[Music]
okay rocks in our soil
have things come up in onedrive now over
over like several years of farming
you'll start to see different types of
weeds that you didn't have before just
because they're your soil okay and what
types of things can you deal with where
I can get the tractor set up and and
tear through there with blades behind my
wheels and and get a lot of the weeds
that way but for most of the crops use
in this pulling motion towards you the
biggest thing that I found about weeding
is that the timing is really critical
you have to leave before the weeds get
too big or you wind up doing a lot more
work and so getting to the weeds at just
the right point is really important in
terms of being efficient also the
moisture level of the soil is really
important when you're weeding so in our
climate where it's dry and we can
control the moisture level you know I
try to make sure that the soil that
we're we're cultivating hoeing is not
soaking wet because it'll just the mud
will just clog up your tool you also
don't want it to be super super dry
because the soil just gets hard when
it's dry but it's got to be kind of
somewhere in between a little bit of
moisture and then right after we
cultivate we want the weeds that have
been cut up to just bake in the Sun so
we don't want to irrigate for another
day or two after we wheat okay then we
can start to irrigate again you know
where you're where you're in a climate
where you're relying on rain you have to
really like be on top of okay like
today's the day we've got a weed today
because the conditions are right
so the weeding is most effective limit
conditions are
the weeds are at the right height the
moisture levels right so to me being
really successful about weeding is just
keeping at it all season kind of
starting early I start when the weeds
are just like tiny tiny weeds and you
can barely see them and we just start
and it's very quick like you just weed a
whole pad in almost no time because
there's not much but still it makes a
difference so I just kind of try to
start early and stay on top of it how
often do you weave
well you know it's it's kind of like a
part of our season like early in the
season we're doing green house work and
field prep work then were to get into
planting big time and usually by the
middle of May we're almost done with our
planting and we're really getting into
weeding and then we have a period of
about like a month and a half where
that's like all we do and I hire a crew
I bring people in to help us with
weeding because it's a big labor need
but we suddenly have and then it kind of
goes on you know it kind of trickles in
and it gets really big and then it kind
of goes on for almost the rest of the
season it kind of slows down towards the
end because we stop leading certain
crops and other crops we have to weed
again or maybe you know a second or
third time okay what do we have here and
they don't Trump on the crops too bad
and how many turkeys do you have out
here
are there any artichokes oh yeah here a
couple on the plant you can see the
ladybugs all over really cool you got
the ladybugs that are eating the aphids
and the other thing you get is so much
right now that you get ants that farm
the aphids the ants there's an ant they
bring the aphid eggs up and they put
them on the plant and then they come
back and they harvest the little baby
aphids to eat okay and then the the
ladybugs kind of key in on it and
there's a lot of wasps that come in too
and I mean these plants right now I
think it's just kind of cooled down so
it's slowed down but in the middle of
the summer I was just like crazy to
barely walk in here insects everywhere
and so ladybugs are pretty much your
primary beneficial around here it seems
like they're a big beneficial for sure'
to get really tough so what I'm trying
to do here is Hill it up I'm trying to
use the tracker to bury these things
with dirt and then that'll sort of
blanch them and make them turn white and
tender hopefully nice I can almost smell
the peanut butter and raisins
that's good so this whole section here
is all being irrigated with this drip
tape and this is like the most efficient
way to irrigate the waters just pushed
down into the tube and there's little
holes that are kind of pre-drilled into
this seam it allows the water to dribble
out and so for the whole run there's
like a little bit of water dribbling out
every 12 inches and the lines stay on
for a long time like five or six hours
until it's saturated it's very efficient
you're not watering you know in between
the bed so they don't so anyway that's
drip tape and so you've got some main
pipes and then you keep branching down
branching down and the drip tapes
obviously at the end of the whole chain
yeah we have a really big berry that
comes up in Judy's risers
every 40 feet and then on these risers I
can either go with a sprinkler line PPC
pipe and then go into the drip tapes
okay so it goes to PVC up at the other
end there okay do you have one of the
drip tapes starting off from the PVC
somewhere yeah okay it looks like well
and all I really do is I wasn't working
it's a very simple system I I drill a
hole in the PVC it's slightly smaller
than the outside diameter is - okay Mike
ran the tube in there drip tape and Fram
that you've been there and then you just
pinch off both ends of the drip tape
yeah I decided I'm not okay
they do make special fittings for all
this stuff you know they make a special
fitting for this bar they make a special
fitting for this kind of cheap way of
doing it if it works that's what the
line first fill it up we go down make
sure it's not
and I know that most types of sweet corn
for modern farming have been bred so
that there's only one year per block of
corn that's probably true is is that how
this corn is or no no this okay and what
variety of corn assist
oh yeah sunflowers sunflowers are really
trend pull it okay look what some of
them are bigger it's the type do you
have different varieties in here yeah a
lot of different varieties so this man
my little label say what the boys are
Atlas Danvers and Nan tez those are the
three varieties in this bed okay
the water there you go
yeah yeah look at that that's a
healthy-looking carrot mmm lots carrot
still he picked some basil and scallions
okay there's the rest of the beans those
were highly productive and we had to
just stop picking them cuz we just kind
of ran out of labor so these are onions
you were showing us one of the onions
you this picture from I plant them from
little onion transplant so someone else
grows them from seed they probably start
them in the fall they overwinter them
and then I when I buy them in the spring
for transplanting they're just tiny
little onion shoes this this was like mm
okay and what is this maybe an eighth of
an acre or something no not even now it
would be well about about 24 beds per
acre and it was just okay
here we've got a bunch of lettuce
is there anything tricky about the
lettuce tender I plant it over and over
and over again okay that's the big
secret it's just always having a fresh
crop so I have a lot of land here so I
fill up a new section and plant a new
section of salad about every week in
December okay maybe two weeks go by okay
and so your greenhouse is mainly for
starting stuff melons
do not really ripen up very well okay at
the end and open on the sides it will
retain a huge amount plus of course it's
much hotter in there during the day
you
okay so you basically just have two
tractors and these are set up to weed
the three rows that we throw in our beds
so these blades work the soil the the
wheel and this back are kind of rolling
along floating along okay these brackets
allow the plates to go to move up and
down I see and then this is this is
cutting into the soil so the idea is
this is just below the surface of the
soil this area here is being left
untouched in between those two blades
but but this is being cultivated this is
being cultivated and so there's three
lines that are left three parallel lines
and those are the where the crops are
this marker so when we're when we're
planting I will mark the fields with
these and that will give us three
furrows and then we'll drop our
transplants that we've grown like our
broccoli transplants or our lettuce
transplants into those three furrows
okay then we can come back with front
part and weed it without hitting you
know if you if you're not hitting one
row you're not hitting the other two
rows right because they're parallel and
then also with the big tractor the other
thing that I do that we didn't talk
about is I do some direct seeding of
that so I've got three Cedars that I put
on the on the bar on the bat and I can
fill those up with carrot seeds like I
was there are corn or beets or
there's a whole bunch of different crops
that I direct so these beans all those
things I'll dump those seats in the
cedar and then drive down and then
that's putting the seed right below the
surface of the soil again the spacing on
those three rows would match the spacing
of these and this may see my cultivators
okay I'm able to go back and do the
cultivating Louis we still cultivate
everything by hand but this allows us to
come through very quickly I can you know
in a couple hours
go cultivate a whole acre and you know
it's not a hundred percent thorough but
it's a eighty ninety percent kind of
thing and then come back by hand to
finish this job off well it seems like a
neat little tractor let's go see your
double digger okay series of eight lays
mine does it come in different widths
and what happens is the blades make a
motion kind of like this they shop
straight down and then they they kind of
loop back they're making a circular
motion and what happens is they're
they're chopping up the soil as you move
forward very very slowly with the
tractor they're slicing off like maybe a
half inch or an inch of a trench that
you're working and they go down for ten
or twelve inches maybe even more and
then as they make their backward motion
they catch the top half of that tilling
depth maybe five or six inches and they
they fling it backwards
pulverized and just like you get with a
rototiller now if it's too dry it'll be
you know it won't rise once your content
really is very critical on this
implement okay but if the conditions are
right what you wind up with is you know
you wind up with soil but you can stick
your arm down to your elbow it's loose
down that far the bottom half of that
tilling death has been loosened the top
half has been actually blended they
don't get mixed together okay whereas a
roto tiller would just mix them
part of what you're doing with the whole
thing I was talking about like the life
of the soil and trying to keep your
soils healthy you know most of the life
of your soil is just in those top couple
of inches that's where all the
biological activity where the oxygen is
permeating the worms are doing their
cycling up and down so when you when you
wrote a tilling or tilling down 8 or 10
inches and you're sort of blending it
all up it's not that you're killing it
but you're losing sort of your
concentration of your life you know so
if you can try to avoid that it's better
[Music]
sometimes the old technology works
better
and then to something I guess okay on
the bottom of the bed there that all
moves and as the chain runs there's like
a beater arm somewhere that pushes yeah
pushes this big wheel around okay just
like one notch at a time and that turns
the chain that is this all driven from
the tires from the tires and you have
control over various aspects of it with
these levers okay but supposedly one of
them what control like how much was
letting out and control how fast it was
moving
I see neat piece of equipment how old
would you guess that is
[Laughter]
like blog today so really appreciate it
I'll be ready next time
great thanks for coming out yep thank
you