okay my name is Julia Django I work with
the international life
research institute a theory based in
nairobi can i work with the team that
looks into animal genetics and breeding
basically am our vision and our goal is
to try and use livestock and the
practice of language ethics and breeding
to try and help change the livelihoods
of livestock keepers in developing
countries one of the developing
countries we've had the privilege to
work in is Nicaragua which is in Latin
America a totally different system from
what we would generally find in Africa
and Nicaragua is unique they keep
animals both for milk and meat products
because um they produce both milk and
meat for export all american countries
but also some to the united states of
america nicaragua's is a developing
country in terms of the livelihoods or
the incomes for their farmers are really
still no but livestock does contribute
significantly to their national economy
in nicaragua and we found that there
were a lot of livestock keepers that own
smaller land sizes with herd sizes of
less than 25 animals that's between 10
and 25 animals and these are the
livestock keepers of me felt would be
important to help target to to change
their their livelihoods as part of the
livestock and fish strategy the
objective was how do we use genetics to
help change the way in which the breeds
that the animal of the farmers are
keeping we produce products for for
their lives but because we didn't have a
lot of information on Nicaragua we had
to begin by trying to understand the
environment and the systems that we were
working in husk and following the
baseline and we immediately realized
that all the small almost all the small
holder farmers kept a bull
and the other thing was there was not
one single breed type that you would say
this is the main print type being kept
by the farmers but they had a variety of
crosses not really pure breds but
crosses most of the crosses were crosses
to Brahman but you had like brown swiss
crosses Jersey crosses holston crosses
and that immediately I'm raised raised a
lot of questions as to why and what
happened so following the baseline way
we decided let's go back to the
communities and talk with them and try
and learn from them and see what
influences that practices and what would
they need to do what would they try to
change if they were asked to change from
from experiences elsewhere the best way
to get farmers to to give you
information is using their animals so we
organized for the group discussion to be
held on a farmers farm so and we we
requested them to get a farmer who had
enough animals of the different variety
and to try and see if we could actually
at the same time give feedback and have
training on the choice and selection of
different pretax what struck us
immediately went for their follow-up or
the feedback workshop is that it's
mainly men who attended within the whole
group there was only one woman who came
and her peculiarity was she was already
an extension worker so she was an
extension worker as well as a life
storekeeper that was the only thing that
made her feel free to come and sit among
the men to talk but otherwise all the
other participants were men but the
farmer's wife and his children were
available to prepare the meals and cook
for the group that came so they offered
that service and they they were
subsequently facilitated to cook for a
group that came for the training as part
of them process of group discussions we
have developed a series of tools that we
used and small group work to try
first of all just share with the farmers
what we saw from the baseline the
different breed types and then we raised
questions related to the types of
animals they were keeping and the
practices that they they were using and
in in the smaller subgroups we got the
farmers to define what were the traits
of importance but particularly our
interest was the breeding practices
adopted to help change their heads and
what they knew about them the farmers
noted that here's they they understood
the use of AI because for cattle
production mean artificial insemination
is not really cause rapid and drastic
changes in the hearse over a short time
so they said they do know about the
practice but they don't really use it
much and the question came to why they
said well projects do bring up a I and
they adopt it but then after that the
air is not available so they don't use
it anymore and then we asked them what
do they like about the animals that they
use and they they choose that the traits
that they would desire in their animals
their vision was the order a mother
could produce about 15 kilos of of milk
and had good growth rates because the
curves that were born to their cows are
often sold off to other producers who
then raise them as animals for slaughter
so that way then they have been the dual
purpose nature of the animals but one
thing that was concerning each one of us
was their promotion also of different
breed types within the farmer hoods in
in the process of having the group work
we decide let's have a practical
demonstration so we requested the
farmers to go and actually look at the
animals at their farmer kept and we
separated them into groups and told them
to identify the two best in terms of the
traits that they felt were of interest
to them as livestock around breeders it
was very
interesting because when the farmers
selected their cows physically the end
of the day when we asked them why they
selected their cows and then we brought
up what they had listed in that
discussion it turned out that they were
kind of two different lines along which
they were selected because they selected
the live animals based on the color and
the physical appearance externally of
the animals without looking at the other
characteristics without looking at did
the animal have any records or
information on them without looking at
any historical background on the animals
and yet during the group discussions
these are the things that they had said
would guide their choices of which
animals they would use now of course
then that that for us are served as a
learning point at the point where you
could help guide to the farmers in terms
of these are the principles you look at
inbreeding so following that the
discussions we will go back to plenary
sessions but because the whole morning
and day's activities had been quite busy
took a break and decide let's have some
refreshment in some lunch as
facilitators we were given good
treatment and were asked please come and
sit in a separate room and so we went us
and said master bedroom and then what
surprised us was as the women served us
they said they had a question to ask and
so we said yeah I'll go ahead and that
question was you know this AI that you
talk about well when you use it how low
you have to wait you know when you see a
cow wanting to be mounted how long do
you have to wait before it has to be
served if you really want to get that
cough
so we asked that's an interesting
question have you tried to use the AI
which is this yes we've tried but we
never get a cuff so you no longer use it
because every time we try to use if we
don't get a car and so we asked what
what's the process when you try to use
the AI she says or well I see the animal
in heat then I tell my husband but
normally he waits until the following
morning and then he sends for the AI
technician wheel after all by then it is
too late because the animal is probably
cycled and lost the psycho says yes in
fact normally I'd then push it beside
the boon or near the labor spoon and
I'll get the cuff that I need but the
next question was where can I get
information on what to do so immediately
we notice that though the women were not
present at the workshop it didn't hear
that the women were not humorous to
manual or learn about the braiding or
the use of the different technologies
but it also tells me that the woman
didn't want to use them it's just they
didn't have the knowledge required so we
requested our partners on the ground do
you think we could try and have a
workshop where you just target or bring
the women together and try and find them
and this this was possible and it was
arranged and when the women will ask
what training do you think we should try
and organize for you immediate reaction
was trained us on how to manage the
production and use AI if we can use air
effectively then we don't have to keep
these bulls and maybe we could change
our heads
you