[Music]
I'm M dresser I own old turtle farm it's
located in East Hampton Massachusetts
and this is my assistant Farm manager
David
Shane old turtle farm is an 18 Acre Farm
we have 12 acres of crop Land We Market
mainly through a CSA with a little extra
going to some local grocery stores we
have 146 shares this season feeding 227
families cover crops are a real
important part of our farm we keep half
of our land in cover crop we use it
mainly for our fertility program since
we don't use a lot of other types of f
ility here on the farm we also use it
for weed suppression we graze our layers
on
it we have a flock of layers that we
pasture on our cover crop throughout the
season they are um Freer ranged within
an electric net that's moved every two
weeks and housed in Mobile coups that we
move every day they do um a lot of bug
control for us as well as create some
fertility we have a system whereby we
have um cover crop next to crop so we
use it for beneficial habitats as
well our field space is divided into
sections of 30 beds there's a section of
cash crop bordered by two sections of
cover crop the next season those are are
rotated such that the cash crops are now
in sections where there was a cover crop
each of our sections U contains 30
permanent beds they're mostly 300 ft
long by 45 in Center to Center we also
keep these permanent beds exactly where
they are we use a a spater um and drive
only on the pathways work walk only on
the pathways so the beds always remain
the same whether they're in cover crop
or in cash
crop after our cash crop we would seed
with Ryan
or just dry as the season gets colder um
then the middle of next season around
July that Ryan vet would be put down and
put into uh a cover crop that would
winter kill such as oats and peas or
sudex this section was in uh cash crop
earlier in the season and it's now been
spaded down and put into Ryan VCH we are
on a permanent bed system so the
pathways always stay stay in the same
place and the bed is planted with cover
crop we keep the pathways clean so that
we're able to find the bed the next
year uh we use a permanent bed system
mainly to reduce compaction and to help
with maintain good soil structure we
sewed this the middle of August and we
go by beds so Ryan vetch usually gets
put down um 5 lb of rye and 2 lbs of VCH
per bed and since we go bed by bed we
just mix the seed according to the
number of beds we're going to put down
at that
time this Ryan vetch will be allowed to
grow until it starts to head out and
then it will be mowed we usually have to
mow twice for the Rye and then allow the
vet to come back through and flour and
we mow again for the vet and then it
will be spaded down and put into a
winter kill cover crop such as oats and
peas this is is the equipment we use for
planting our cover crop simple drop
Cedar that we purchased from Market farm
implement it's made by shaper Brothers
it's adjustable according to the size
seed that um you're putting down we
incorporate it with a basket weeder we
use a pipe on the back of the tractor
that drags along the bed and that helps
to create the compaction necessary for U
faster seed
germination this is a field of oats and
peas was seated in the mid mid August
after space in down Ryan VCH the beds
are seated to about 5 lb of premixed
oats and peas per bed any of the legumes
that we put down we do inoculate them
prior to
seaing the other um part of our
fertility system is compost so um we
have to buy our compost in it's rather
expensive so we have been um using a lot
of lagoons in our cover crop and hopes
and hoping to uh reduce the amount of
compost we have to use
we've been experimenting with a
combination of sudex and red clover
planted after a cash crop the sudex will
winter kill and then the red clover will
come back through uh in the spring and
remain through the next season the sudex
was put in after cash crop the middle of
August the seaing rate is um 3 lb of
suex to 2 lbs of red clover per
bed sudex gives us a lot of biomass and
then the red clover gives us the
nitrogen and red clover is something
that we can leave in throughout the next
year we do not have to till it down and
put it into a crop that will winterkill
because couple times of Mowing and by
the following spring there's not so much
left it goes down very easy after the
sudex is winterkilled this is what the
field will look like the sudex was left
in place the red clover has been mowed
four times through the season will be
left here until spring when it will be
spaded down and put into a cash crop the
timing of the planting of sudex is very
important this sudex was planted in the
middle of August when it was still quite
warm this bed of sudex was planted two
weeks later when it had started to cool
off so it's obvious there's going to be
a substantial difference and the biomass
created by the sudex this section is an
example of needing to respond to uh
something that didn't work correctly it
was seeded into sudex and red clover
last year but this spring the red clover
didn't come through very well so in
order to um reduce our weed problem we
spaded the Clover in and planted it into
straight sudex the end of May we got a
great stand of sudex and this has been
mowed three times
um has created a very good weed
suppressive situation