soy beans or edamame are one of the
tastiest beans you can grow in your
garden
in today's episode we will show you
everything from planting soybeans and
harvesting them as well as a delicious
edamame recipe
so there are two ways to start soybeans
you can get seed packets from home depot
or loaves
and sow the seeds when the weather is
warm enough for soybeans to grow
spring summer and fall are the best
times
soybeans can grow very well in the
summer heat here in southern california
when starting from seeds you can sow six
to eight seeds in one whiskey barrel
container like you see here
the soil we have is a mix of compost
peat moss and perlite
after sowing the seeds make sure you
water well and now you're done sowing
the seeds the other way to grow soy
beans is to grow it from transplants you
can buy six-pack starter plants at your
local nurseries like the one you see
here and then plant them
buying transplants for soybean saves you
a lot of time growing it from seeds
once again we are growing this in a
whiskey barrel container and we are
planting six plants in one barrel
this container is 22 inches wide and 15
inches tall
holds about two and a half cubic feet of
soil
our planting mix already has a good mix
of organic nutrients in the soil we will
be using an organic liquid fertilizer
every two weeks as the plant grows as
well as some worm tea
links to all these products will be
provided in the video description
once planted water well so that the
roots can settle into their new home
soybeans grow best in temperatures of 75
to 85 degrees fahrenheit
in a few weeks from planting you can see
two things
the plant has problems with both insects
and diseases caterpillars spider mites
they all love the soybean plant making
growing soybeans a challenging project
in your garden
and here you can see a fungal disease
called rust which the soybean plant is
very prone to
it's a brown powder like fungal disease
on the plant you can also see spider
mite damage on the soybean plant in a
very short span of time
so what do you do
well it's neem oil to the rescue
neem oil is an insecticide to kill
insects it's a fungicide to stop rust
and it's also a miticide which means it
can stop spider mites
so a generous drenching of diluted neem
oil will give some respite to these
soybean plants
spray both under and over the leaves
and drench the plant completely
repeat this weekly
till you don't see any signs of insects
or diseases
and as you can see even after the weekly
neem oil applications the rust and the
spider mites have emerged stronger
the plant still has some damage due to
these
however does this really affect
production well we'll soon find out
soybeans grow in full sun so choose a
nice sunny spot with at least 6 to 8
hours of sunlight for your soybeans
we are transplanting six more soybean
plants into this raised bed
which receives a lot of sunlight
and here you can see the progress after
a few days you can see that the rust and
spider mites are still an issue here
with these soybean plants growing on the
raised bed
so it's been about two months since we
transplanted our seedlings and now you
can see the soybeans forming pods
and within these pods are the actual
soybeans or edamame so it's the time to
harvest
when harvesting remove the entire pods
and this is how soybeans look like they
look pretty good and i really wish these
plants were a little rust resistant
but overall for the size of the plants
we are getting a decent harvest
so what's the biggest advantage of
growing soybeans at home well they are
non-gmo they are much better for your
health than commercially grown soybeans
and they are very delicious as well
to get a good harvest of soy beans
remember to fertilize your soybean
plants with a good organic liquid
fertilizer as well as worm tea for good
results
and here is a harvest
as you can see we got a lot of soybeans
for the size of the plants we had so i'm
quite happy with the results if i had
grown more plants i would have gotten
more soybeans
the soybean plants growing in our raised
beds also gave us some soybeans
but you can see the plant had no vigor
despite us providing all the nutrients
as well as protection from insects and
diseases
let's open up these soybean pods to show
you how the soybean looks like inside
the pods
and these are the soy beans
that you can eat raw or steamed or
cooked
once the plants have completed producing
their pods for harvest you can go ahead
and remove the plants
what i wanted to show you here
is to pay attention to the roots
the soybean plant has roots that are
relatively shallow which means that you
can grow them in shallower containers as
well like the one smaller than the
whiskey barrel containers shown here
soybean plants fix nitrogen in the soil
they have bacteria in their roots that
fix nitrogen from the air and make it
available for the plant to use
since these plants had fungal diseases
like rust i will not be composting these
plants but rather they will go into the
yard waste bin
and now let's look at a delicious recipe
for our harvested soy beans or edamame
we are preparing air fried edamame first
we take the soy beans whole with the
pods in a bowl
then we add in some salt
i usually use himalayan salt but this
time i had sea salt so that's what we'll
be using
add in a little bit of oil
remember that very little of this oil
will be actually absorbed by the edamame
but adding oil gives a very nice flavor
to the pods when you're eating the
edamame and that is quite
amazing the oil also helps the salt to
stick to the pods more evenly
you can skip the oil if you do not want
it
you can preheat your air fryer if needed
i did not
add the soy bean pods or edamame to the
airfryer
set the airfryer to 375 degrees
fahrenheit and cook for about 15-20
minutes
tossing them around the halfway mark
soybean dishes are actually called
edamame because in japanese the term
edamame means stem beans or the
preparation where beans are still
attached to the pod when cooking
as you can see here the pods protect the
soy beans from overcooking
and these home grown soybeans will be
one of the best tasting soy beans you
will ever eat
soy beans are packed with protein and
are very important part of a healthy
vegetarian or vegan diet you can also
steam your soybeans and add a little
salt for a delicious dish
growing soybeans is one of the best
summer treats from your garden so i
highly recommend that you try growing
soy beans this season so there we have
it folks that was our episode on growing
soybeans in your home garden
if you like this video give us a thumbs
up
and if you have any questions or
comments post them in the comments box
below
a majority of you watching this video
are not yet subscribed to california
gardening so please take a moment to
subscribe to our channel to get all
future updates we'll see you again soon
happy gardening
[Music]
you