we're now almost one week after we
seated and behind me we've got a field
that's
and even to say the least now one
possible reason it could be uneven is
rats we do have a rat population here at
Erie I've got dr. grant singleton with
me who specializes in rats to tell us a
little bit more about our rats indirect
there I'm also thinking over here
looking around here there's an area with
a rat fence Oh to our to my left and now
that that can be good because if you do
have a rat problem last year there was a
rat problem just here it's good to have
what we call a trap crop where you plant
an area early about two to three weeks
early and then have traps with more will
capture traps entrances like this or the
rest they'll go in but can't get back
out again the other thing is yeah
where and when should you conduct direct
control the when is now because the main
we know from the breeding ecology of
rats for every female rat that to remove
at this time of the season it's
equivalent to removing about sixty rats
come the ripening stage of the crop
particularly after the fellow period the
rats there's a big disturbance during a
fallow period and the working of the
soil so the rats then get move out get
moved to the edges and they aggregate
and that's the best time to manage them
and so along these areas where there's
cover also here in the missus farm you
have irrigation canals underneath and so
the entrances of those canals because
they're good habitats for rats as well
so they need cover and they need areas
are not being disturbed now we have here
trap either rat and trapping is is used
often when I talk to farmers and will
show that they will enter into the trap
here and he will force his way through
and the right thing yeah trap is big but
see how they sort of crunch down and
rats can do that as well the only thing
that limits our rat so they can
dissipate their shoulder shoulder its
width of their head which indicates as
though how big the hole is they can get
in and with a mouse and push your finger
in a mouse and get into a hole we're a
rat it's more sort of a probably of a
large thumb so it's usually about 12
millimeters if you got a hole bigger
than that then the rats can get through
and so often you know you don't need a
very big opening here the rats will
force their way through hey when we
first seeded I came and I were most
concerned about rats what we didn't
think about was birds what do we know
about birds and their interactions with
suited rise in agricultural system there
were two approaches one is they will
will spread something to feed the
animals just prior to the crop coming to
the stage of seed the other approaches
is is going more here in the Philippines
and elsewhere in Asia often its is using
of what you've got here the flags to
this caused a bit of disturbance not by
the hedge scene not far from here where
they have they're all like a little
windmill the little ratchet on it making
a noise and that's to persecute the
birds away as well so it's looking at at
noise as a deterrent but really we don't
know much at all about the bird problem
and again one of the big questions is
where are they breeding were they
aggregating and tried to see if we can
prevent the problem before it does
escalate