hello my friend welcome to the farm life
today we will explore great solutions
for results from the garden to your
table guava is not only famous for its
sweet taste but also rich in nutrition
that we will introduce the billion dooll
guava growing process applying modern
agriculture technology to bring top
quality guava let's start the discovery
process the nursery in janga County
Taiwan is where guava cultivation Begins
the the process of growing Pearl guava
begins with the selection of healthy
guava
Sprouts these Sprouts are carefully
planted to ensure that they are firmly
attached to the soil which is important
for their early
growth when the Sprouts are about a
month old they are ready to be
transferred to the farm Fields where the
rayol work
begins each Sprout is planted by hand
it's essential to maintain a distance of
5 to 6.5 feet between each guava tree
this spacing allows for proper growth
and ensures each tree gets the necessary
nutrients without competing with
others after planting the guava trees
are equipped with a drip irrigation
system which is crucial for their growth
this system efficiently delivers the
right amount of water directly to the
roots water is sourced from nearby pumps
and filtered to remove impurities
ensuring it is clean and safe for the
plants nutrients can also be added to
support Healthy Growth helping the trees
Thrive as they
develop the drip irrigation system a key
aspect of Agriculture technology
conserves water while supplying
essential hydration to the guava
trees regular maintenance is required
for proper growth including pruning and
shaping when the tree is 4 months
old the grass around the trees is
regularly pruned to prevent competition
for nutrients and keep the plantation
clean pruning encourages better growth
by allowing the tree to focus its energy
on fruit production rather than removing
unwanted branches improving air
circulation reducing the risk of disease
and promoting healthier growth an
important stage in guava cultivation is
preparing the tree for fruiting D an
preparing the tree for fruiting when the
tree is ready to bear fruit farmers will
wrap the guava after cutting the tops of
the branches this directs nutrients to
the fruit ensuring that the guava grows
large and sweet which is essential for
quality in recent years Taiwan has
become a leader in producing highquality
guavas with over
34,500 Acres of guava Orchards spread
across the island each year Taiwan
harvests more than 440 million pounds of
guava with the most popular variety
being the Pearl guava weed management is
also important for tree
growth highquality Pearl guavas are
produced by allowing only one fruit to
grow per Branch a selective process
common in Japan that enhances fruit
quality the guavas are then wrapped in
nylon bags which protect them from Birds
insects rain and excessive sun exposure
creating a controlled environment for
optimal
growth the wrapping ensures that the
guavas develop without external
interference resulting in a more
consistent and higher quality product
the ripening period is about 1 and a
half months depending on the season
during summer when rainfall is abundant
guavas are more susceptible to damage
making wrapping even more
crucial meanwhile branches are
periodically pruned to maintain tree
health and promote better fruit
development production pruning is
essential for managing tree growth and
directing new nutrients to developing
fruits as harvest time approaches
Farmers check the sweetness of the
guavas to determine their Readiness
specific techniques are used to ensure
that only the sweetest and most mature
fruits are harvested which is crucial
for delivering highquality guavas to the
market quality meets consumer
expectations for Taste and texture once
the guavas reached the desired
sweetness the Harvest is conducted
carefully to avoid damaging the fruits
farmers use scissors to cut each guava
from the tree and gently place them in
trays to prevent
bruising known for its vibrant green
skin crisp texture and sweet taste this
guava is a favorite both locally and
abroad thanks to Advanced farming
techniques Taiwanese guava Farmers
ensure top-notch quality in every fruit
making their guavas some of the best
you'll find on the market whether you're
enjoying it fresh or in a dish taiwan's
guavas truly stand out for their flavor
and
quality after harvesting the stems are
removed and the fruits are thoroughly
washed in clean water washing the guavas
thoroughly is crucial for removing any
residues from the growing process after
washing the fruits are neatly arranged
in trays and wrapped in shock absorbing
foam to protect them during
Transportation this packaging enhanced
by agriculture technology ensures they
reach the market in perfect condition
finally the carefully packaged guavas
are loaded onto trucks and transported
to distribution centers from there the
guavas are sent to various locations for
sale marking the end of their Journey
from Farm to Market where consumers can
enjoy their sweet
flavor next we'll take you to the
bustling streets of Taiwan showcasing
the impressive guava cutting skills a
true art form in taiwan's street food
culture watch talented vendors
skillfully cut and peel fresh guavas
with remarkable precision and speed
guavas are transformed into bite-sized
pieces for eager customers showcasing
the traditional techniques of St vendors
in Taiwan this unique preparation
highlights the art of guava cutting
whether you're a food Enthusiast or
curious about street food this
demonstration will Captivate and inspire
you don't miss this glimpse into
taiwan's vibrant street food scene if
you enjoyed this video please like And
subscribe to our channel for more
delicious content finally we will make
delicious fresh juice at home you only
need a few ripe guavas a little sugar
lemon juice and filtered water wash them
cut them into small pieces put them in a
blender with water and sugar then blend
them to separate the pulp and you have a
glass of fresh juice the juice is rich
in potassium and vitamin C good for the
heart and increases resistance the
creators of guava juice a wonderful gift
from nature try making it at home right
away you are walking among rows of lush
green grapes under the warm Italian Sun
smelling the aroma of ripe fruit the
grape Growers are not just Farmers but
artists dedicating their heart and soul
to each bunch of
grapes we will also explore the
Exquisite packaging of these grapes see
how they are sorted packaged and
prepared so they reach you at their
freshest quality
you will feel inspired and more
connected to the origins of your
favorite
foods seedless raisins are among the the
most popular types of raisins today
accounting for nearly all of
California's production and being widely
exported about 150,000 acres in the San
Wen Valley near Fresno California are
cultivated by over 3,000 raisin Growers
to supply all of the raisins in the US
2/3 of this production is consumed in
the US and Canada while the remaining
third is exported to nearly 50 countries
primarily in Asia and Europe raisins are
made from seedless Vitus Viner grapes
which are typically sundried on trays or
left to dry on the
vine popular seedless varieties include
Thompson Selma Pete Fiesta and
duvine growing grapes starts with
digging holes to provide optimal
conditions for the vines many farms now
use mechanical technology such as hole
diggers to create uniform holes
enhancing efficiency and saving time and
effort selecting the right cultivar is
the most crucial step in raisin
production the grape variety impacts
yield quality and resistance to disease
and weather choosing the appropriate
variety optimizes raisin yield and
quality while reducing growing risks
have you seen this grape growing method
before if so leave a nine in the
comments if if this is your first time
seeing it go back to zero we look
forward to hearing from you after
digging the holes workers plant the
grape Vines by placing each one in a
hole covering it with soil and watering
it for moisture combining Machinery with
human labor at this stage boosts
productivity and ensures plant
quality after planting irrigation is
crucial for healthy grape vine growth
modern drip irrigation technology is
commonly used for precise and economical
watering providing nutrients through
organic and chemical fertilizers is
essential tailored to soil conditions
and plant types sturdy steaks are
essential to support growing vines
typically made of wood or metal and
standing six to 8 ft tall they should be
installed before planting allowing Vines
to be tied immediately afterward wire is
attached to the stakes to promote
vertical growth ensuring The Vines
receive maximum light and making
harvesting easier later on in May
California grape Farms begin to thrive
leading to the September Harvest when
dry hot weather enhances
sugar workers handpick each Bunch for
quality control enduring temperatures up
to 95° f after harvesting grapes are
sundried for about 3 weeks preserving
their sweetness and
flavor with technological advancements
many farms now use machinery for
harvesting modern grape Harvesters are
designed for Speed and efficiency saving
time and reducing labor
costs this method allows for the quick
Harvest of large quantities of grapes
making it ideal for large-scale
production once the grapes are dried
they are collected and transported to
the factory for processing and packaging
the processing involves cleaning the
grapes to remove excess stems and leaves
using conveyor belts and vacuum
technology next the the raisins are size
grated and washed before undergoing
laser sorting to eliminate unwanted
materials this ensures the highest
quality raisins before packaging if
you've enjoyed California Raisins share
your thoughts and don't forget to like
And subscribe to our Channel raisins are
not only a nutritious snack but are also
processed into various products
including grape juice and grape powder
grape powder is made by pressing raisins
through a fine mesh and heating them to
soften it can be added to various foods
to enhance flavor and appeal commonly
used in products like yogurt candy and
other
dishes grape juice is made from dried
grapes by soaking them in water and then
concentrating the liquid under vacuum
conditions it contains at least 70%
natural soluble solids from the fruit
and can be used in various food products
including beverages cakes and
desserts plus the magic of Brussels
sprout
harvesting at the heart of the process
are the incredible machines that are
changing the way we Harvest these unique
vegetables these machines can handle up
to 5,000 lbs of sprouts per hour making
the harvesting process not only
efficient but also gentle on the crop
this means less damage to the sprouts
and a higher quality yield for
consumers powerful Brussels sprout
Harvesters race through the fields
equipped with Cutting Edge technology to
pick sprouts with precision
after harvesting the Sprouts are
transported to a processing facility
where more specialized Machinery takes
over these systems are designed to clean
the Sprouts remove any foreign matter
and ensure only the best make it to your
plate these machines not only speed up
the process but they also represent
innovation in agriculture by minimizing
waste and maximizing
efficiency they help farmers meet the
growing demand for fresh produce while
maintaining high standards
so next time you enjoy your brussels
sprouts remember the amazing machines
that make it all
possible a combination of automated and
manual sorting ensures top quality
reflecting the perfect marriage of
Agriculture technology and the human
hand they are the unsung heroes of
modern agriculture ensuring we get the
freshest and highest quality Sprouts
thank you for joining us and don't
forget to like share and subscribe for
more inspiring stories meanwhile the
exciting world of carrot harvesting the
remarkable fent 516 vario pairs
perfectly with the Innovative ASA Lyft
carrot Harvester demonstrating the
incredible advances in agriculture
technology that are changing the way
fresh carrots reach your table the fent
516 Glides through the fields
effortlessly lifting two rows of carrots
at a time its sturdy design allows for
an impressive load capacity making
harvesting fast and efficient
imagine thousands of pounds harvested in
the blink of an eye after lifting the
carrots are transported to the yard by
the reliable fend 820 and 724 vario
equipped with salmon box trolleys for
Easy Transport this ensures the carrots
remain fresh and undamaged in the yard
the forklifts efficiently load the boxes
onto trailers pulled by the fent 415
taking them straight to the farm this
seamless process highlights the power of
team work and technology
in let's celebrate the Innovations in
agriculture technology that bring fresh
produce to your plate the world of
harvesting is in full
swing today we introduce the amazing CL
Jaguar forage Harvester nicknamed doggy
style for its unique crab steering
ability this machine represents
cuttingedge agriculture technology
perfect for harvesting Alfalfa and
forage
Grass at harthog in the Netherlands they
specialize in growing and processing
Alfalfa the class Jaguar harvests crops
efficiently capable of handling large
volumes as we watch the kronig m420 cut
a crop of young Alfalfa mixed with
spring oats we see how this combination
suppresses weeds and supports growth a
few days later a fend 412 vario and rrt
1000 conveyor combined Harvest three
rows at once demonstrating the power of
modern
machinery finally the class Jaguar 960
shreds the crop and loads it into
containers for transport to the drying
plant proving its efficiency in action
thank you for visiting the farm life
explore our engaging videos showcasing
modern don't miss out hit the like
button subscribe and turn on
notifications to stay updated with more
interesting the farm life content please
like And subscribe turn on notifications
to discover interesting