hi guys this is Megan from the blog
Wilson Thompson calm and today I want to
share with you guys some ideas of things
you can do before you have your
homestead do you have the home stink bug
but you are maybe still an apartment or
a city and you really can't do anything
but there is some thank you too
I'm going to share with you some ways
you can start and plan out your
homestead while you're still in any
situation that you're in there's so many
things that you can do before you're on
a ton of land to start homesteading when
we first got married we lived in an
apartment for the first year and I had
grown up right for the last like five or
more years of my life I had lived on
hope so did my parents and we raised
made me chickens and Barbados sheep and
we had milk goats laying hens and like
all these different things and so then
when I was in the apartment when we
first got married I had this really
strong urge to start homesteading but I
didn't think I could and then I started
learning about all these things that
really are home state but that you can
do in an apartment or anywhere so the
first thing you can do is to educate
yourself start reading everything that
you can get your hands on about
homesteading feet about gardening
orchards making a ultra types of farm
animals animals that complement each
other rotational grazing you can start
deciding what animals you would like to
have on your farm which ones will you
start out with make sure you are
knowledgeable about what kind of speed
that they'll need and minerals and
supplements and all the things that for
animals might also be a good idea to
read up on purchasing leave
dealing with wells lipstick pink and
housing options for books as you get
yourself on this enough so that when you
go to buy your dream homestead you know
what you're looking for and what you're
doing the next thing is use the space
you have to start I'm sitting now if you
have a really small backyard
space to garden or compost and probably
even raise some sort of small livestock
like chickens or rabbits or quail or
even some miniature goats I know that if
you're in a city it might be a little
frowned upon to have like goats bleating
in your backyard but rabbits are
something that's really really quiet I
think ylr - so depending on where you
are and how thick your ears are you can
find them nested extra quiet to have fun
we're an apartment then you can do some
container or vertical gardening you can
even do some countertop composting with
the focaccia box learn some home study
skills canning cheese-making sewing
cooking from scratch fermenting they
send your countertop things like kefir
and Kucha and we can start a bread there
is just a ton of things you can ferment
and I'm totally impossible you can learn
how to make buttermilk make your own
toothpaste there is pretty much just no
end to these amazing and practical
skills that you could be learning and
these skills are definitely going to
help you out when you are when you are
under homestead the next thing is to
create a budget are you saving for your
down payment on your dream homestead now
so that when something comes available
or you're in a position where you could
move that you're able to actually buy
something what about money for fencing
or animals or tools start living now by
creating a budget that allows for this
even if your homestead is years down the
road find a home setting mentor or
several mentors find someone that is
living the life that you want and ask
them if you can help out on our
homestead I learn about all the things
that they're doing they can teach you
all about planting gardens and
maintaining them in animal husbandry and
they could probably even help you with a
lot of the indoor skills like canning
this mentorship and having practice on
someone else's from said will give you a
really big head start create your own
there are so many people who possess a
wealth of knowledge about all of this
stuff and why not try to glean some from
them and then my last tip is to decide
where you want your dream
do you know where you want to settle
down what areas do you like the best
what areas have the best homesteading
land I know around here that there's a
lot of areas I have the key areas of
land but they're really Rockets they
would be the best for gardening unless
you're doing raised beds there's other
areas that have like the best pasture
land and rocky areas don't really make
the greatest pasture land as well as
treat areas good establish the community
as much as you can you can grow a
farmers market to meet all the different
local farmers and learn where their
homesteading and growing things and just
make sure that it's the right place for
you because once you start your
homestead you're going to want to say
that for a long time especially when
Xena guards planted animals are a little
easier to move by gardens thank you you
built all these reasons is that soil and
so I'm gonna just make sure that you are
ready for more permanently whatever
dream you have your mom said you can
totally start now there's so many ways
you could do it so I hope that this was
helpful to you guys for maybe some ideas
of things you can do now if you're
interested in learning about any more of
these skills that I've talked about just
follow along because if I share of all
kinds of practical homesteading tips and
tons of recipes so I hope you'll join
along
[Music]