foreign
just a textile cotton as a culture and a
way of life for hundreds of millions of
households worldwide cotton creates jobs
and incomes for Millions at the heart of
the supply chain eighty percent of
cotton is used in the apparel sector but
all parts of the cotton plant can be
used to produce food feed and energy
Cotton's diverse users create high value
opportunities for smallholders women and
young people boosting livelihoods and
contributing to food security
together we and our partners spend no
efforts to make cotton farming more
competitive for the cousin industry to
thrive we support small business
ecosystems and promote Innovative
technology we Foster sustainable farming
practices and boost employment we work
alongside producers to add value create
jobs and reduce the effects of climate
change we improve Farmers livelihoods by
strengthening Cotton Valley chains value
Edition and trade we oversee a
rules-based global trade pursuing a more
transparent and fairer International
concentrate
together we celebrate World cotton day
renewing our commitment to this precious
resource and reaffirming Cotton's role
in achieving the 2030 sustainable
development goals
[Music]