so you're thinking about wanting to own
the greatest tractor ever made well I
think you're in the right
[Music]
place you know these old Ford tractors
are pretty cool they've really lasted
the test of time and you know there's
still a lot of them around as a matter
of fact pretty sure it was the uh most
sold track
ever so that's pretty
cool a few years ago when I bought this
one I ended up paying 1700 for it and I
thought it was a pretty good deal I went
over and looked at it at the guy's house
that I was buying it from and we uh we
started it up and drove it around a
little bit and everything seemed to
function just fine and you know that's
kind of what I was worried about is does
it start do the Hydraulics work you know
and beyond that I knew there'd be repair
I mean it's 70 plus years
old you know and what's crazy about
spending the 1700 for it is uh if I
could have just been lucky enough to be
born maybe back when it was made around
1949 I could have had the luxury of only
spending about 1,400 to buy it brand
new it's amazing how much they've not
only held but increased their value all
these years
cleans up pretty good think I need new
tires been like that since I got it the
earlier models the 9 NS if you'd have
been old enough to buy one of those
brand new you could have done it for
about
$650 crazy you can't hardly do anything
for $650
now you know the truth is just like
anything else that you own there's going
to be maintenance and maintenance cost
money but honestly the maintenance on
this is not really any more than a car
you know oil
changes um hydraulic fluid changes you
know think of hydraulic fluid change run
you probably about
75 thanks for your help run you about
$75 for the uh tractor fluid you know
and then your oil changes just typical
oil and filter for that so but you're
going to have maintenance and you're
going to learn a lot that's that's one
of the important
things I had it for a year before I knew
it did
that pretty slick idea especially when
it's raining out you don't want a wet
butt you know so what are these old
tractors
worth you know or should I say what what
should you expect to pay well like I
said I paid 1,700 for this one I've seen
them as low as 500 well and almost free
I guess but they don't
run and I seen them as high as about
6,000 but I got to be honest that one
was completely restored looks brand new
probably better than brand new all of
the fancy stickers and everything on it
that you could possibly imagine and who
knows if that person even got 6,000 for
it but that sure was a nice looking
tractor but I think the thing is that
you got to remember is that you know
$1,400 in
1949 well that's going to be about
$188,000 now adjusted for inflation that
is and if you kind of look around you
know most of the tractors that are about
$188,000 nowadays are essentially this
you know some of them have buckets on
them and different things like that and
you can get Buckets for these as well
but those are some of the things that I
think you need to consider you know and
what are you going to learn with a new
tractor you know how to do donuts and
drive it around in circles you know with
an old one you get experience you know
you get to Tinker with it and tear it
all apart that's half the fun can be
frustrating at times but you know that's
most things in life it's got to look at
the positive be happy for the times when
it's actually
running you know when you're going to
have maintenance they call this thing
here a carburetor you know and I've had
that thing tore apart more times than I
care to even remember
you know but now the tractor's running
great and heck I'm kind of at the point
where I'm scared to even touch
it and if you've been paying real close
attention you've probably noticed that
uh this one here has a alternator on it
well they didn't come originally with
alternators they came with generators
and the reason this one has the
alternator on it is because I upgraded
to the 12vt system and you know looking
back to be honest I I probably wouldn't
have converted it to the 12 Vol system
over the 6vt in hindsight I don't think
it makes much difference but at the time
I was looking for something to do that I
felt comfortable with and the electrical
part was a lot more Comfort than you
know tearing apart carburetors or
manifolds or you know anything like that
you know and the crazy thing is you know
as many of them as they made they're all
just a little bit different they got
just a little bit different setup and
design and a little bit different look
to them you know different
transmissions and things like that never
really seen any that are absolutely
identical whether it's the dash uh the
gauges you
know previous things the owners
did you know what happened to it all
those years you know if you look at the
inside of this tank here or the H or if
you look at the inside of this hood here
at one point some somebody thought they
should have painted it yellow I don't
know what the heck they were
thinking you
know safety wasn't as big of a concern
back in the day as it seems to be
now these tractors can be pretty
dangerous this was the very first thing
that I bought once I took ownership of
this tractor this is a cover for the PTO
and it keeps that thing covered cuz
there's a little uh deal in there that
likes to spin when the PTO is turned on
and if you were to get an article of
clothing hooked into that or your shirt
or your hair or any other type of uh
maybe strap or chain that would not be a
good day you can uh ask my
great-grandfather about that
one I will uh put a link down in the
description to a video talking about
that you know while I'm back here I'll
talk about this back bucket um I had a
guy on one of the videos David he asked
a question about how I did it see uh
this uh this bucket wasn't originally
this design it originally faced forward
as all of the other Deerborn models uh
just like it did and I decided I wanted
one that I could back into instead of
drive into so I cut some pieces off of
it and welded some other pieces on and
this is what I ended up with so you can
see right here I welded these ears on
and uh have them back so that the arms
can come down and get hooked up on both
sides and then I took this top link and
I uh cut it and put this section in the
middle so that it was long long enough
to reach and then I uh welded on this uh
top link uh deal here and uh it seems to
work pretty good but uh I also I I cut
off a piece here on the front and uh and
used that somewhere else I'll show you
in a second but uh I'll take you over
and show you what it should originally
look like so you can kind of get a
better idea of what I cut off and where
I welded stuff on you can see here this
is the piece that I took off of the
another one and cut
up and you can see back here if I move
some of the the weeds out of the
way maybe not there we go this is where
I welded those ears on the back so that
the arms could come down and hook
on so even if you own one of these
tractors already but uh you'd like to
see something specific on my tractor and
how it maybe differs a little bit from
yours you know shoot me a comment down
in the comment section and if I can't
answer it there I'll probably throw it
in the middle of a video somewhere you
know some of these things about these
old tractors is kind of learning by
doing and I'll tell you this this right
here this is the dipstick for your
hydraulic fluid
and long before you'll ever even get a
chance to check that for the first time
you're going to sit down on this seat
put your heel down on that and bust this
little handle clean off not exactly sure
what they were thinking with that
design but if you like
tinkering and having fun these are
pretty good
tractors you
know I think 26 horsepower was what they
were originally designed with which in
modern times doesn't sound like a whole
lot of power but I think you'll be
surprised you'll get yourself scared
more than once or twice on it so if
you're interested in getting yourself an
old tractor I'd say with the ford8 in
the greatest tractor ever made I don't
think you can go wrong if you're
interested in annual maintenance on
these I'll tell you what I got a few
videos that I made on changing the oil
and changing the hydraulic fluid and
I'll put those uh videos down in the
description down below otherwise I
appreciate you watching today and uh
hope maybe you learn something and now
you can go out and get yourself a Ford
tractor just like this
one hopefully
better come on start
[Music]