there are very inspiring and exciting
things happening at the pine ridge
reservation which is home to the oglala
sioux
in south dakota this video is going to
introduce you to what they are doing to
restore resilience
economic independence self-sufficiency
and cultural revival among the lakota
people
being in alliance is about being
in service to each other and when you're
in service
it's about a yes of course attitude
being an
ally also means that because i'm
committed i'm going to explore further
and dig deeper and see whether where the
growth opportunity is there for me
and if i can actually add valued
everybody loves the cultural native
everybody loves the ceremonies we share
but when it comes to talking about
the hardships and the injustices and
the reality of what native people deal
with on a day-to-day basis
that native isn't so popular so being
willing to stand next to
that outspoken native that isn't always
talking about the most popular topics
i think that's what makes a good ally
i think showing up as an ally starts
with a contextual
understanding of not only what has
happened but what is happening
and i think it's really important to
remember that this isn't past tense and
these injustices are happening every day
and we're actually seeing them
unfold for people like we're seeing this
healing happen for people within the
camp
to this very day people don't have clean
water they don't have running water they
don't have
good food they don't have housing so
they're just really in this
mode where they can't thinking about
like intergenerational trauma and
epigenetics and
really hard to heal something when it's
like like you get a wound and it scabs
up and the sun keeps coming like ripping
it off and it's like
you know it's ongoing it's not like it
has it hasn't stopped yet it's been
going on for
like 500 years since then we've been
like in survival mode trying to just
survive and it's hard to really focus
on anything else you know like building
happy communities and having
healthy relationships with your children
it's just the willingness to help you
know the willingness to
ask questions when it's appropriate
showing a respect for the culture for
the land for the spirituality for the
people
if you treat the earth in a good way the
earth will treat you in a good way
and it's just a mutual respect is what
it is really
[Music]
oh
right now we've got the second annual
iwps convergence
we had one last year and the convergence
is really
our event to bring together folks who
are working on these different projects
who have these skills around natural
building gardening
and to just come together in community
to really show the power of community
and what
the interrelationships can create we
have people
from all over the world all
nations converge on pine ridge and
then we have community based projects
that they
help to implement on pine ridge i'd say
that this year we're really
deepening our relationships and we're
also
spreading to support these food
distribution
networks across the reservation so it's
not just one site anymore
this has now become the tool hub for the
reservation and we also have
other places where they are creating
gardens to heal emotional trauma
there are a lot of residents who come
over to folks from other residents
and we make it very accessible we'll
cover fuel costs whatever it takes i
mean it's free for all
native folk to really showcase what's
happening here to demonstrate it
and to use this energy to
activate and mobilize our projects
moving forward as well
we work on low-cost alternative
replicable models that any family can
implement with a little bit of help
across the reservation so we build with
tires and
a lot of industrial cast off and junk
basically people approach us and say we
have a piece of land and we want to do
this for a family
and then we go out and take a look and
if we if it's within our ability to help
them
to do their project then we partner up
on it
and figure out a way to get the funds
necessary to get things together
this is our experiential farm or place
to do
builds and experiments and then see if
they're replicable if they're
economic enough to use here on pine
ridge
and we're all food producers the hope
being that we can
put a dent in our food desert here
[Music]
when i heard the term permaculture and
that was many years ago and i said
what the hell it's nothing but but white
people
and they're going around the world and
they're you know they're taking the
best practices of all the indigenous
nations and they're putting in a package
and then they're
saying oh look what we invented
permaculture look at this
but really as as my brothers here
mentioned
it's something that the indigenous
people have been doing for thousands of
years
all this permaculture knowledge that we
have we're just trying to reiterate all
of it because we
are like i most of you know our
ancestors have been doing this for
thousands of years
my family we used to cultivate and we
used to plant
and it was communal it's huge
practically the whole
community came to plant these enormous
fields
we practiced crop rotating everything we
had more than four cornfields
and we would plant these fields like in
three days and then
of course during harvest that was
distributed to everyone
when we plant corn we plant seven seeds
one is for us
one is for family one is for the animals
one is for the birds
one is for everyone one is for the earth
that's how we plant
as we move from this egocentric
colonialist ideology back
towards this indigenous ancestral
knowledge
that is ecocentric that as we move
through that transition
we all recognize and forgive
our part in the equation and that we
actively work
towards embracing our humanity
reaching out to each other and
recognizing that we all
are part of the same tribe humankind
i didn't want anything to do with it
until i came here and i saw
how lovingly that this permaculture
crew touches the ground but you know the
important thing
among our people is to show up and to
show that you mean
what you're saying and that you're going
to walk your time
[Music]
i am so thoroughly impressed and
inspired by
the incredible work of everyone at the
pine ridge reservation and
i hope you are as well i would love to
see you
support them in their mission there are
links in the description to learn more
to get involved and support them so make
sure
that you do that and if you want people
to
see this and to be inspired by it make
sure to like
comment and share this video and if you
haven't already
make sure to subscribe to this channel
where there will be many more videos to
come
i love you all very much and i hope that
you will go out there and
make positive change and be a part of
this movement for a better world