folks have rounded up 10 hydraulic tips
for you today to make life easier when
owning a tractor this stuff can be
confusing and frustrating but if you
know what you're doing ahead of time
well you're going to shorten that
learning curve and make life a breeze
now I learned something new myself that
I thought and maybe it is relatively low
probability but it wound up saving me a
3 800 Bill well it cost me like 150
bucks or something but so save me like 3
650 I'm gonna make you wait for that one
just a little bit we'll tell you a few
other tips and then I'll tell you how
that one turned my frown upside down
tip number one just making it up on the
spot because I am reminded right now
that I need to do it on this one here I
lost my dust covers I need to get some
new dust covers for these two hydraulic
couplers they're just sitting there
just begging for dirt and dust to get in
there and then be a challenge to clean
it out or get into my hydraulic system
that's just a problem waiting to happen
so you can go online and order dust
covers just make sure they're fitting
the right size couplers that you have on
your tractor but how do you know what
size couplers you have on your tractor
that is a really challenging thing to
figure out
I tried to find I did some Googling to
see if there was hydraulic fitting size
chart something that's a visual
indicator where you can tell what size
couplers you're staring at it's pretty
easy to tell if they're male or female
but there's Pioneer there's flat face
there's 3 8 there's quarter there's half
inch there's all this other kind of
stuff and it's not
unless you really know what you're
looking at it's not easy to tell I found
a really handy chart over on tractor
Mike's website he's another YouTuber in
the tractor space as well putting out
great videos every week make sure you
check him out so we'll put a link to
that product page as well I think it's
actually in a different listing where he
has this chart up there but it's just
it's just easy to read easy to
understand and concise so take a look at
that if you're struggling to figure out
what fittings you have on your tractor
this one's a big one folks okay it's
going to happen to the best of us and
well this is one that you go through it
once and then you you hopefully remember
and don't do it again but before you
disconnect your loader or really any
Hydraulics that are on your tractor so
if you have a grapple connected or you
know hydraulic top link and you want to
take that off
turn the tractor off
rotate
this around you could hear it maybe you
can't see it moving but you're going to
relieve
the hydraulic pressure that's going
through the lines on both sides of those
couplers and so that's going to make
life so much easier when you go to
reconnect them back up if you don't do
that and I've done it myself all right
you're going to have a lot of pressure
on the the loader side of that line when
you want to go and hook it back up to
your tractor and you're going to have to
somehow release that pressure that's on
there and it can be dangerous can be a
mess because that pressure is built up
and so you want to wear the proper
safety attire on there and I've been
able to sometimes put a rag or a board
and push it against you know the loader
to a heavy piece of steel or something
on the ground like a board on the ground
to relieve that or maybe use like a set
of channel locks or nipex to pinch that
down or sometimes you can even use some
wrenches and crack that fitting and just
let it slowly leak out just a little bit
just to get that pressure out of there
otherwise it can be impossible to hook
up those Hydraulics again be prepared to
get messy if you have to do that because
there's hydraulic fluid that's going to
fall out somewhere but again it's one of
those lessons if you can avoid it
fantastic if it happens to you you're
not that alone has happened to pretty
much just about every tractor owner out
there before okay connecting hydraulic
couplers
seems pretty straightforward but
sometimes it's not okay and number one
probably the biggest issue that I'm
contacted about
is on backhoes where they're just not
working the Hydraulics are connected
just like they're connected here but
they're not working there's no response
and the reason for that is pretty simple
it just looks like it's connected but it
actually isn't all right and if You Yank
on it really hard you'll pull it apart
without you know pulling back the collar
and that's going to be a common problem
on the Kubota on the John Deere just on
hydraulics in general is where it looks
like it's just seated in there properly
but it's not and sometimes you'll see
hydraulic oil flowing out through there
too when you go to move a lever because
it's kind of sort of seated enough to
open up and have some flu some flu some
flow going through that direction in the
line there but it's not enough to make
it work properly so let's take a look at
some other hydraulic connections as well
so you can see firsthand how to hook
them up all right so this style of
coupler is called a Pioneer or an AG
style coupler pretty easy after you most
tractors have these okay the flat face
style is another very common one more
likely seen on construction equipment
sometimes on tractors too so you're
going to have a collar and a female on
the male side you simply pull back
I almost forgot work your joystick or
work your lever for the hydraulics in
both directions relieve any built up
pressure If there is some then you're
gonna pull or push back on the male
collar and you'll see some little
bearings in there and then you can pull
right out
gonna be a little bit of fluid all right
that's just nature of the Beast now to
reverse the process
here's a good look at that male side
if your pressure's built up you got to
push you got to detent this little pin
that's in the middle here to relieve
that pressure or crack the fitting and
let some fluid leak out
or the proper PPE now to reconnect
kind of just seated in there gently you
can't push it the whole way you have to
get that collar pushed back and then
it seats in there give it a little yank
to make sure it's seated properly and
Away you go okay so now we're looking at
flat face couplers again pretend one of
these is on the machine side and then
one is on the attachment exact same
thing going on you need to just pull
back on a collar to release
and there you go okay now what you see
the difference is the fact that these
are flat faces all right and so putting
them together is really easy you're just
gonna
take the male side and just push it in
to the female side okay there's no
collar that you have to push back or
pull back on you just simply push it in
there and it locks in place you can hear
that snap hopefully now for a lack of a
better term you have a DOT and a slot
okay and if you have that not aligned
you can't pull back on this collar to
release it it's kind of a I don't know
maybe a safety mechanism of some of some
sort if you align that just right like
this that's when you can push back on
that and everything releases just fine
and so if you if you can't get the the
coupler released from there maybe it is
a pressure issue where you have to
relieve the pressure or maybe you just
have to align that slot properly and one
of the things that I actually like a lot
about flat face couplers besides the
ease of connecting them is the fact that
they're flat faces all right and unlike
the Pioneer the AG style when we showed
you on the first one around there's that
big cavity there that they're not all
upright like this but no matter what
direction they are there's look there's
space for debris to get trapped in where
there's not really any space for debris
to get trapped here you can just brush
off the top flat surface pretty easily
and hook them up a little bit different
you don't need dust covers on these
versus the Pioneers here is a good
example of why you want these dust
covers on here it is like a it's like
the Dust Bowl around here lately so this
tractor we were doing some tilling it's
just absolutely disgusting but I want to
show you this last type of hydraulic
coupler kind of hard to see and this is
on the back of a Kubota and I don't know
what it's called I don't know anybody
else that has this style but I think
it's super stinking cool
you don't have to pull back in any
collar it's not a flat face though it's
still
some sort of pioneer rag style coupler
just trying to get all the debris away
from there so I don't clog it up and so
all I'm going to do and I don't know how
honestly I don't know how this works I
really don't but you just yank them out
and you push them back in there's no
collar of any kind it's not again a flat
face I I don't know the the sorcery
behind it but I like it
and then you could slap this
dust cover down right on it like that
really nice
pop that back open
and you're back in place
that was it that's it we're proud to be
sponsored by rim guard Solutions a
liquid ballast weight it goes right
inside your tires completely hidden
we're big on safety on this channel
these tractors are just too light and
Tippy right out of the factory not only
is it going to help with safety keeping
those rear tires planted on the ground
it helps with loader efficiency and
traction too the benefits of rim guard
include being the heaviest all-natural
liquid ballast weight on the market it's
not going to corrode your rims like the
old calcium chloride it's not going to
freeze and it's available at over a
thousand dealers Nationwide find the
dealer near you at rimguardsolutions.com
speaking of hydraulic pressure this is a
smart way to make sure that doesn't
happen to you where you you have too
much pressure in the line to hook it up
to your tractor the problem is is every
setup is not going to have a male and a
female so sometimes you can't swap that
out just swap out a fitting on your
tractor so you can have a male and a
female or same thing on your attachment
too but I Loop these together so that
that flow is going through both ways and
it's not locked in here at you know
behind the fitting on on each side that
can make it a super hard challenge to
hook up to your tractor actually with
these forks I didn't do this I forgot to
do this last year when we were shooting
a pallet Fork video I wanted to hook it
up to my skid steer and show you guys
how they worked how they went in and out
and I couldn't we were in the middle of
nowhere I didn't have the tools with me
to relieve the hydraulic pressure and we
couldn't get the fittings onto the the
skid steer itself so if you do this
though then you simply disconnect them
like that you can see how easy they
disconnected when they're sitting
outside I know it's good to keep your
attachments inside if you can but when
they're sitting outside especially with
temperature changes when they're in the
baking sun
well that pressure is going to build up
in there even more and want to expand
and make this even more of a problem so
do this if you had the opportunity to do
so but there is a solution if you don't
and that would be the hose end chamber
which is designed specifically for
applications like this when your
attachments are sitting outside and it
could be your backhoe it could be a
flex-wing mower anything that's going to
have hydraulic lines on it maybe that
are going to sit for a long period of
time in the exposed Sun situations where
you'll have these huge temperature
variations at number one can make it
challenging to then hook up to your
tractor or your skid steer whatever it
is when you need to use it but number
two think about those pressure
variations that are occurring and going
on
that's causing damage
albeit most likely slowly to the hoses
to the fittings perhaps to Motors
anything else that's on the equipment as
well and so if you want to avoid a
situation like that well there's a hose
end chamber that you can purchase plug
it into your fittings that are on there
it is basically going to be like a
little extra Reservoir so that fluid can
go in and out of there freely instead of
causing damage to the rest of your
hydraulic components okay there's a big
one here again it really did it saved me
38 3650 dollars
and all it was was a hydraulic filter I
I'm not kidding you we had the tech out
to our shop to look at the John Deere
4720 the rear three-point
um the the rear Hydraulics none of that
was working and he had gone through a
bunch of different things
troubleshooting all this and that and
basically came down to we needed to
replace a big hydraulic cylinder block
that's back there and it was to take it
out put it back in and everything else
gonna be 3 800 bucks and
I was like that's not cool and uh I was
I was pretty I was really frustrated at
that point because that's just a
ridiculous amount of money to make your
Hydraulics work and the weird thing is
is that a year ago maybe more we
reported in a video of a similar problem
with the 4720 where everything went from
working fine to just not working they
got it into the shop and took a look at
everything and couldn't figure it out
and it just was working fine for them so
it was this crazy kind of ghost problem
that we weren't sure what was happening
long story short
this this on-site technician said hey
you know what this could be a just a
Hydraulics issue maybe your hydraulic
flow is is just too low uh hydraulic
filter hasn't been changed in a while
let's swap that out and see what happens
and lo and behold swapping out that
hydraulic filter with a brand new one
got us right back in Action right back
in the game and everything is working
perfectly
I almost still can't believe it but
that's all it took you're looking here
at some DIY Hydraulics all right a lot
of tractors are not going to come out
with
the grapple hydraulics on the front and
the rear remote on the back the stuff
you need to use the attachments you want
like a grapple like a rear hydraulic top
link that we talk about a lot
the power beyond that's on here to run
that backhoe is not the same thing we'll
get into that in just a minute and the
challenges is that adding OEM Hydraulics
after the fact
man that's an expensive game to do and
so you can get do-it-yourself Solutions
like what you see here from Summit
Hydraulics you save five percent with
code GWT takes a couple hours of your
time but you save hundreds of dollars
it's hard to beat that and there's a lot
of terminology in this video we've done
a whole in-depth video focusing on the
difference in various kinds of
hydraulics okay and so this is actually
on the Kubota a third function an
aftermarket third function but there's
another kind that's called a diverter
like what's on the summit tractor and we
installed on the John Deere 1025r just a
a difference in how it works in my
opinion it's split hairs on smaller
machines they don't have a lot of
hydraulic flow anyway so they sort of
work the same once you get the bigger
tractors it's more of a difference then
you have power beyond you oops you'll
have a couple of remotes or a couple of
ports on the back side sometimes three
ports depending on the size of the
equipment
power beyond does not have a lever
anywhere on the tractor to control
whatever is plugged into those
Hydraulics you have to have a lever on
whatever's plugged in like how the
backhoe has two levers there to move it
around so that's different from a
regular rear remote okay which will have
a hydraulic lever on the tractor
somewhere so if you have a hydraulic top
link there's a lever on the tractor when
you have it plugged in to extend that
top link out or retract it back in and
then lastly hydraulic multipliers and I
absolutely love hydraulic multipliers
they're one of the best values that are
out there you can add on up to
additional
an additional five ports for like
like probably twenty percent of the cost
if you were able to do that through the
OEM it's just a crazy amount of savings
and
again another Summit Hydraulics product
that's there but I have one on uh the
Kubota M4 we put one on the John Deere
4066 that I had I'm also going to put
one on very soon on the summit tx25
it comes standard with one rear remote
which is pretty awesome but we're using
that on the hydraulic top link right now
I am fully expecting to need more
remotes next winter for my snow blower
if I want to hook up any other hydraulic
attachment on the back side and use it
in conjunction with the hydraulic top
link well you need to have more remotes
to do so and that's where a hydraulic
multiplier comes in handy now speaking
of hydraulic top links super handy item
again you can see this is a John Deere
2038r it's got two rear remotes you see
four ports there that's two remotes all
right
two couplers make one hydraulic circuit
or one remote you have to have flow
going this way and then flow going back
the other way all right this machine
here has a hydraulic top and tilt kit
very handy we've shown you these on
other tractors as well
working on getting you a complete kit
that you can add to your tractor that's
going to be sometime in the future we'll
get you more information on that for now
you can buy those hydraulic top links on
Amazon we have a bunch of links there
where we've bought some that have worked
for us and so you just want to basically
get the shortest length of your top link
and then unscrew it to get the longest
length and let that kind of serve as
your guide and try to find a hydraulic
top link that's
matches about those same dimensions but
it's staring me in the face and perhaps
I should have thought about this earlier
we talked about those dust covers but
some other ways to protect your
Hydraulics from exposure or from getting
pinched or from bending and kinking and
all that kind of stuff and just looking
cool maybe even identifying them Outback
wrap pretty good stuff this this helps
keep these hoses kind of connected
together and sandwiched together and up
out of the way it's a really cheap thing
to add onto your tractor as well and if
you're not sure which hoses go where you
color coat them with different colors
that are on here and also we did the
video talking about long-term storage we
are going to park our backhoe all winter
and you get some concerns about pitting
on these exposed cylinder rods that are
there and you can wrap it in this real
it's kind of a nasty tape but it's not
that bad but it's going to completely
protect your your exposed rods from from
corroding or from pitting over the
winter from long-term exposures to the
elements it sounds like that's used a
lot in Marine applications too
it was kind of pricey but potentially
compared to the cost of getting a
cylinder rebuilt it could be worth it
really quick one for you and honestly I
don't see this one I've never seen it on
a tractor definitely could be on there
at some point but this is a relief valve
all right and so you can pull that
to relieve the pressure the built up
pressure in there if you're if your
Hydraulics happen to have a little handy
pull tab like that give it a yank when
you're trying to disconnect things or
plug things back in and it could relieve
that built up pressure and make life a
lot easier something I wish all
Hydraulics had that's going to wrap it
up for us today folks hopefully you
learned something new it shortens your
learning curves it saves you some
frustration or maybe solves a problem
that you're you're facing right now but
that's what we do here folks we show you
new products give you the tips to
hopefully help you out make your life
easier
show you projects in action all around
the farm so make sure you check out
those other videos too and I want to
remind you if you are in the market for
retractor attachment something for the
front end loader or the three-point
hitch we'd love to earn your business we
sell and ship all over the country every
day of the week check out our website
goodworkstrractors.com I want to thank
you for taking time out of your day to
stop by and until next time stay safe
we'll see you soon
[Applause]
[Music]
all right
[Applause]
[Music]