hi I'm here at mosy and the sunflowers
are growing and maturing and we've got
one uh that hasn't actually uh
completely matured but it's enough that
we can show you the counting that we
want you to do when your sunflowers are
ready um don't do this when they're
still looking like this and they still
got the yellow petals and in particular
you can't see the SE pattern very
clearly in the middle you want to wait
until all these little flet things have
fallen off and you can see the black
seeds usually black seeds it might be
white L of the sunflower underneath
right so once you got to that stage um
uh for extra bonus points before you get
to that stage you can count the petals
but that's not the key thing we need
once you before you do anything else
just measure the height to the middle of
the head and I've got
98 CM plus 3 so that's 1 m 2 uh for this
sunflower now I've measured the head I'm
going to uh take it off I've taken one
off I don't know how easy it's going to
[Music]
be not very easy if the answer scissors
is what is what's recommended at this
[Music]
stage okay that's not going to work we
need
to
[Music]
um there we go okay so um as I said I
think this seed head actually probably
died and the the flower heads fell off
before it got maturity the other thing
that we'd like you to do you can't do it
on this one cuz they've got moldies
measure these green brats count the
green brats around the back but the key
thing is to look at the spiral counts so
let's see if we can do that on this
sunflower just I'm just brushing off the
flower heads so I can see the seeds
underneath and now we can see I think we
can see just about there's a pattern of
seeds here and there's a little spiral
of these four seeds all in a line what
I'm going to do is just so I can count
where I'm up to one
two
three four so I've taken out that spir
now the key thing that we're trying to
count we're not trying to just go around
the outside and go one 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
say how many there are outside cuz
that's not very accurate what we want to
do is count how many of these spirals
there are so I'll start at this one and
I'm actually going to call that zero for
reason you see in a minute so this is
one 2 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 I'll just pull
that one out so I can check later
on that's that's 0 10 1 2
3 hard to see cuz it's not very mature
one four five 6 7 8 9 and I think that's
a 10 there I've got a Rimer on the
camera who'll tell me if she thinks I've
missed any I think that's 10
okay once we once youve taken this
another way of a much better way of
doing this actually is to take a photo
of the seed head and then use your um
computer you can do it in uh in
PowerPoint to draw lines onto your photo
that way if you get it wrong you can try
again that's another one so where do we
start from 0 10 20 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
[Music]
okay and I can see already that we're
going to get in quotes the wrong answer
right so I started here at zero that's
10 20 30 31 32 oh no that is right 33
34 right so what we've done is we
counted all the way around the outside
of the um head the number of spirals who
started at at zero went up in 10 it's
got to 30 and then finished off with 31
32 33 34 before we had number one so
this has got 34 spirals around the
outside of its sample head which um if
you like Fibonacci numbers is good news
cuz 34 is a Fibonacci number now the
next thing we want you to do is to
notice which way that spiral is this as
you go out from the center outwards it's
curving around in a clockwise Direction
so we'll call that a clockwise spiral
and then the next thing is to uh look at
the spirals in the opposite direction
dire so we might need to zoom in again
right so we were counting spirals there
before but if you just follow my finger
there's another line of spirals here so
I'll pull out a seed to count that one
one two again maybe a good tool would
help here there now these are flatter so
there should be um less of these I guess
around the seed head so let's see if we
can count those by hand 0 1
2 this is what if you do end up taking a
photo you need to be really careful cuz
you see these areas around here where
the structure isn't very easy to see and
maybe if you rub off some of the extra
Gunk it's easier to see the little white
dots that really help your eyes see the
spirals so that's one two 3
4 five 6 7 eight nine and I think that
one is
10 oops extra one there by
mistake uh okay so that was uh from our
beginning 0 10
11 12 13 14 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 do you know I've done
this probably 20 times now on sunflowers
and I'm always just amazed every time it
comes out with Fibonacci numbers it is
just fantastic so uh the good news is
that the uh science museum is capable of
growing sunflowers which obey the
Fibonacci rules the big question is out
of all of these sunflowers how many of
the time how much of the time are we
going to find that that's true when it
isn't true what are the patterns going
to look like um so good luck with the
counting