hello viewers welcome to elim TV a
station where you watch interact and
also learn your teacher today is Mr an
agriculture teacher in today's lesson we
are in form four Lesson 12 and the topic
is Portrait production and the subtopic
is routine management practices in poy
on to the lesson objectives uh by the
end of this lesson you should be able to
explain the various routine management
practices in ptry uh number two uh
methods used in identifying a good uh
layer uh the routine management
practices in portrait include number one
feeding and number two control of
diseases and and um the disease that
you're supposed to control uh you're
supposed to control goomo then we have
nucum and uh you have full typhoid and
number three we have control of parasite
using appropriate method you can do
dusting also you can use a dust bath and
as uh the dust bath uh dusting uh and
also the waras so that you can uh get r
of the worms then uh we'll go to the
control of parasite and the control of
parasite you have the dusting as I've
said then we have warmers and then
number number four we'll go to egg
collection that is another control
management practices that is supposed to
be carried out during pot production
you're supposed to regularly control the
to collect the egg so that you can
control the vies of egg eating then the
perpetual egg eater and the Perpetual
cannibals are supposed to be deied uh
this is the process as I explained the
previous lesson of cutting short the uh
some section of the upper P to control
the egg eating Vice and also cannibalism
curling is also another one and we'll go
to the characteristic for birds to be
Cur what are the characteristic what are
the traits are we supposed to check so
that we can know that this bir is
supposed to be called and this is this
bird is supposed to be left to continue
with production uh the first one poor
growth those birds which have poor
growth should be C out then number two
chronic disease then number three old
age those birs which are old of age they
are supposed to be called uh by selling
them you sell them or you slaughter them
uh because they have a less level of
production they normally lay few eggs
and also so the body weight is also very
very small so they it is uneconomical
because they are feeding a lot but they
don't produce a lot of uh eggs then
portra VI uh that is also uh the eggs
which are the Potter which normally feed
on egg egg eaters and also the cannibas
are supposed to be C out then you have
the poor layer uh how do we know a poor
layer and a good layer how do we
differentiate a poor layer is the one
that allow only one egg in between the
pelvic bone well a good layer should
allow two to three fingers and that that
that is it then methods used to identify
good layer and poor layer as uh you can
see the first one is observation of
physical treat of the BL uh for example
the the peak those which have yob Bic
poor layers and therefore they supposed
to be eliminated then we have trap
nesting method and in trap nesting
method uh you can identify uh which bird
is a good and which B is but in uh trap
nesting method uh you put a nest where
the bird goes to R and upon laying it is
trapped there and therefore you mark it
then you remove it then next time
another B is is is U is trapped and
marked and uh after several uh occasions
you find that there are few Birds which
will remain unmarked meaning that those
birs which will not have any Mark
meaning that they are all poor layers or
they don't ex then characteristic of a
good layer we have coms and a large warm
wax and red number two eyes are bright
orange and the bird is very very alert
then number three uh vent is oval moist
red and active and number four
temperament they are alert and active
then bigs is pale and six space between
the kill and the pelvic
G pelvic bone or gido should allow two
to three fingers uh then broodiness is
rare for those good layers they rarely
come brooded then we have the space
between the pelvic gido you can see in
the diagram there for a good layer there
is a wider space and for
for n layer there is a smaller space and
also you can see the finger one finger
uh that is for a n layer n layer then we
have three fingers for a good layer then
the three fingers are supposed to fit
exactly in between that space then we go
to the images of coms and wats uh for a
good layer you can see these are good
layers uh then we have car of shuns uh
you can see this one uh the shuns are
red for a good layer and those that are
yellow is for a poor or n layer then n
BR and BR hand you can see uh Nan BR the
appearance of Nan BR and The Brood uh
you can see it in the second image and
you can see even in the third image we
have a brood head there and then uh
there is a continuation of good layers
you can see uh them the diagrams and we
have come come to the end of the today's
lesson and the following questions are
supposed to be answered by you number
one explain any two methods used to
identify a good layer and number two
discuss the routine management practices
in a port are four reference you can
refer from secondary agriculture
students book four and the publish is
the Kenya literature bu for more
information you can contact us through
the following addresses as well
Illustrated and displayed for you thank
you for joining me in today's lesson uh
until next lesson bye-bye