[Music]
hello everyone welcome back to our
Channel have you ever wondered how the
delicious almonds you enjoy every day
make their way from the orchard to your
table today we're going to take you on
an incredible journey through the entire
process of almond production from
planting the first seedling to
delivering the final product to
Consumers you'll get an inside look at
the fascinating world of almond farming
so grab a snack maybe even some almonds
and let's get started
[Applause]
the Journey Begins in mid-February when
Farmers plant almond seedlings this
timing is crucial as it allows the young
plants to develop buds during the
optimal growing season
[Music]
Farmers carefully plant each seedling
ensuring they have enough space to grow
and thrive
[Music]
protective covers are then placed over
the seedlings to Shield them from pests
like stems and to limit excessive
sunlight giving these young plants the
best start
possible over the next 2 years these
seedlings grow into young almond trees
during this period farmers must provide
consistent care to ensure Healthy Growth
almond trees are water intensive
requiring regular irrigation drip
irrigation systems are commonly used to
provide a steady supply of water
directly to the roots conserving water
while keeping the trees hydrated as the
trees grow Farmers monitor their health
looking out for any signs of disease or
pest infestation
[Music]
pruning is another essential part of
Almond Tree Care usually done at the
beginning of winter pruning helps shape
the trees remove dead or disease
branches and promote better air
circulation this careful maintenance is
crucial for the trees to produce high
quality almonds in the future
by the third year the almond trees begin
to Blossom typically between February
and March this is a magical time in The
Orchards as the trees are covered in
beautiful white and pink flowers but
these blossoms are not just a visual
Delight they play a critical role in
Almond
production during the blooming period
millions of honeybees are brought into
the Orchards to pollinate the flowers
this is a for the trees to produce
almonds the sight of bees buzzing around
diligently pollinating each flower is a
testament to the harmony between
Agriculture and nature without these
hardworking bees almond production would
not be
[Music]
possible after pollination the flowers
begin to develop in almonds over the
next 5 to 6 months these almonds grow
and mature on the trees drawing
nutrients from the soil and water from
the irrigation systems the almonds
develop a hard shell to protect the nut
inside which will eventually become the
delicious snack we all
[Music]
love when the almonds are ready for
Harvest typically in late summer to
early fall the orchards are buzzing with
activ
[Music]
ity hey
specially designed machines are brought
in to shake the trees causing the
almonds to fall to the ground this
process is quite efficient and is
similar to how olives or cherries are
harvested the Fallen almonds are then
collected ready for the next stage of
their Journey
[Music]
[Applause]
once harvested the almonds are
transported to a drying area in some
regions particularly in the Middle East
almonds are spread out Under the Sun for
about a week to dry this traditional
method helps reduce moisture content
ensuring the almonds are properly
preserved for storage and
[Music]
processing after drying the almonds are
transported to processing facilities
here they go through several stages
including cleaning sorting and shelling
Advanced Machinery is used to remove the
outer shells leaving the edible almonds
ready for further processing the almonds
are then sorted based on size and
quality ensuring only the best ones make
it to the final packaging
[Music]
stage the final step in the Almond
journey is packaging and distribution at
the processing facility the cleaned and
sorted almonds are packaged in various
forms whole sliced or ground depending
on consumer demand packaging is done
with great care to maintain freshness
and prevent
contamination once packaged the almonds
are ready to be distributed to markets
and stores around the world they are
loaded onto trucks and shipped to
various destinations ensuring that
consumers everywhere can enjoy fresh
highquality
almonds and there you have it the
complete journey of almonds from the
orchard to your table it's a process
that requires dedication precision and a
deep respect for nature the next time
you enjoy a handful of almonds you'll
know just how much effort goes into
bringing this nutritious snack to you
thank you for joining us on this
fascinating Journey we hope you enjoyed
learning about the incredible process of
almond production don't forget to like
subscribe and leave a comment below with
your thoughts see you in the next video
[Music]
he
hey
he he
[Music]