small machinery is among the innovations
that could be critical to st lucia's
food security
as autonomous farming promises to
produce more crops with less effort and
less environmental impact
farmers extension officers as well as
students recently completed a small
machinery training as part of the latest
feat of the second phase of the
enhancement of the efficiency of the
production distribution supply chain in
the fruit and vegetable sector project
also known as the seven crops project
participants learned how to operate
tillers and bunkers to perform primary
and secondary tillage for vegetable
farming
project coordinator for the seven crops
project adelinovic says the training is
in preparation for the shipment of small
machinery due to arrive later this year
as the ministry works towards adapting
to farm mechanization
in the past we've had several machines
that we have received but when it comes
to maintenance and how to operate the
machines properly it becomes an issue so
we have some young farmers today and
also some schoolchildren and extension
officers as well who are receiving
first-hand
training
in how to use these machines the proper
use of the machines so that when these
machines arrive we would have had that
done already so it could move
move smoothly into operations minister
for agriculture fisheries food security
and rural development honourable alfred
prosper says the introduction of small
mechanization particularly labor-saving
agricultural technology is aimed at
making the agriculture sector more
appealing to the youth
he notes that farm mechanization not
only saves time and energy but it is
also more efficient and can contribute
significantly to the development of
value chains
i've always said
that we haven't changed the way things
are done in the sector
farmers have been complaining of
the unavailability of agricultural
or family labor
to be exact
and
given
the old cross of the
is time that we
our farmers change the way from garand
all
in an effort to use a coastal production
farm machinery is one new technology
that i think is very very clear
because it drastically reduces the cost
of production a small machinery that you
see there will reduce the cost of maybe
if you had to use
manual labor what is happening with a
small machinery there
it would have probably
be done in one hour it may have taken
four days for one
worker to do
that is really going to be reducing the
cost of production of the farmer
farmers
[Music]
minister prosper encourages farmers to
adopt sustainable agricultural
mechanization methods as the agriculture
ministry leads efforts to address the
interconnected challenges of livelihoods
and food security
from the communications unit of the
ministry of agriculture i am anesia
antoine reporting