all right so I'm going to show you my
work area here you'll see here that we
have the buckets of the things that we
just sorted from the car these are our
different colored cloths that we brought
in and as soon as I sort them from today
then I just throw them inside these
buckets and then at the end of the week
I put some cleaning solution in there
and I soak all of the junk off of the
cloths and then I run an individual load
of each of those up here I do have my
oxyclean which is what I soak the aprons
and the uniforms in as we go up here I
have some special kits and then over
here we have our personal prote
equipment and that is every kit gets
some personal protective equipment but
we let the individual um house cleaners
check those out we have our shoe covers
we have our garbage bags and this is the
stuff that we need to pack our kits and
then over here we have our empty bottles
and these will be the bottles that we
restock tonight's supplies with and so
that is the setup that we have here and
like I said this is an operation that
will run probably 1 to three one to four
people and this is before you need to
scale and consider a bigger place