as a farmer we all look for a product
that all a crop that does not need much
of the capital and will give some good
returns within the shortest period of
time one of these crops is Los coco
beans the demand for beans consumption
has been on the rise as consumptions
increases most people are preferring
cereals and this has made it demand to
continue increase remember it's also
widely consumed by in
high schools and even some of the
primary schools so it's rare when you
farm this L cocoa beans for you not to
get good Market a bag of 90 kg of L coco
beans ages between 7,000 in high Supply
season to 15,000 or even 18,000 in a
shortage Seasons so this is a product
that you can manage to farm and get some
good results as long as you do it
collect remember having
cost does not guarantee profit you have
to do it right and also you have to
maximize maintaining your cost as low as
possible so that you
have good profit margin and also you
manage to get high
yield if you're new to this channel
consider subscribing I'm Kelvin from
farmworks we do Empower Farmers by
providing solutions to their daily
farming challenges consider subscribing
also don't forget to share these videos
with with your friends this is the only
way that you can help us continue
empowering more and more
Farmers now we jump right into it now
lose coco
beans are first draw to tolerant and
then also they tend to grow fast within
90 days in AA you need an average of 16
to 20 kg that's a seed rate also for
beans and this is a general rule for all
beans you don't have to do it in fertile
soils actually we have observed a be
done in deep fertile soils those
extremely fertile soils they tend not to
do well and by doing well I mean you
find that that bean it looks very good
it's a very healthy has a lot of forage
like it has a lot of leaves but the
number of PS that it produces are
minimal and even the bean size is very
very minimal okay and that's why we even
commend when you're doing beans if your
soil is very very fertile don't add
manure also we also don't add a lot
of Dap You just use very very small
amount and if you can manage not to do
with it it's still fine it's a way of
reducing cost however if you farming in
an area that is completely infertile you
need to add manure at to sustain this
crop beans tend to do well in Sunday L
SS and the tend to grow well in well
drained soils okay so if your soils tend
to flat or if the soils are cray and
they don't support much this may tend to
frustrate you so if you have a well
drained s soils that's okay for you you
can do L cocoa beans how to plant it
it's very simple and it's very very easy
you just need to do you can do holes or
you can do follows or the Met system
then
as Bing of let's say from one line to
the other you can do 30 to 40 cm then
from one being to the other you can do
roughly 20 to 25 cm personally I prefer
planting with both holes so that I can
manage to if the soil is infertile to AO
manure and then also I can manage to do
some good spacing and also it's not that
much involving it's easier to dig holes
than the follow
I put two seeds per hole so that in case
one does not germinate the other one
will germinate uh nowadays it's easier
they all certified seeds like the L Coco
glp to from Kenya seed and also
from East Africa seed and if you cannot
manage to buy these certified seeds also
you can buy from the normal seral store
St okay so the normal Rose Coco that you
buy for 18 you can still brand it as
long as as long as you select the one
that are not dented the one that don't
have holes and then the on that are very
very healthy once you plant them the
performance will still be super good
remember for the one that is certified
and this other one in CL store there's
no that much difference actually the
only difference that I observe is that
the certified seed is treated it's well
selected and these are that you buy from
it's not treated and remember you can
treat your own seeds with like Molano
super and still perform well okay but to
cut the cost I would go for the normal L
cocoa beans from the market they still
do very very well now after you've
planted don't plant extremely deep you
plant just shallowly if your sty is not
F you can also consider top dressing
with d
this is often 10 to 14 days after
germination for those who have watched
our previous videos you have observed
that we recommend you applying dap
fertilizers on 10 to 14th days after
sewing or even transplanting this
enhances faster absorption and prevent
reaching as the crop will have developed
substantial loot hairs that will help to
absorb the nitrogen and the phosphorus
in the fertilizers okay and also ensure
that while you're tring the C is wet and
also ensure that the fertilizer does not
come into contact with the leaves after
that you can continue doing your normal
weeding the farm should always remain
clean nowadays the good thing is that
you don't have to incur that much of
cost especially when you're doing manual
weeding there are a lot of selective
post and pre-emergence herbicides for
controlling weeds in beans Farms good
example is Bean screen and also Mr Bean
plus these are good selective post and
preim herbicides that work very very
efficiently the only condition with the
one is that you don't they don't work in
intercrop FS remember B you can
intercrop them with MS and when you
intercop the apping face selective
herdes will kill the m and leave the
beans alone so these herdes only works
where beans are planted alone okay it's
easier because it reduces the cost of
the cost of doing hiring workers to come
and plow to come and do the we and also
it does the efficiency because sometimes
you hire these workers they come and do
so I'm sure work of weeding but when you
apply this chemical it's cheap okay and
remember all these chemicals you can
manage to get them from our farm shop
and we do delivery Countrywide and even
outside the country so this is one of
the best method to control weight after
that there are things that you need to
control one are feet and the other one
is diseases such as the blight Lea flast
the common one is Lea FL and Lea Sport
and the likes of otheros now first for
AIDS what you can do is you apply ther
Inc side especially especially from from
20th day after sewing 20th to 28th day
you can apply Thunder and you can repeat
it after one week this will help you
manage all the outfits that may infest
your beans then from there for all these
fungal diseases you can use nativo it's
a good it's a good fun Fung side that
will help you control all these uh
fungicides especially the Lea FL you can
also use sometimes little meal for any
early or late bright and even sometimes
you can use
infinitor infin it's a very good it's a
very very
good fungicide that you can also use to
control all this remember I've not
mentioned the use of uh boosters or F
fertilizers because when you apply most
of these nitrogen Rich fertilizers on
cereal what they do they boost the
leaves development and the leaves growth
okay but your intention is not to
harvest the leaves your intention is to
harvest the pot and when you enhance
leaves growth and when you enhance Le uh
development what you do you minimize the
ability of the port and you minimize the
size of the beans form actually it
interferes with the leav you call it the
Le PS ratio okay so the higher the
number of leaves the lower the harest of
beans that you get but you can apply
some of this like the Bon that will help
in preventing flowers abortion the other
thing that I really want to warn farmers
you don't do weeding on beans Farm when
it's raining this to prevent the prevent
of fungal diseases that that tend to
destroy all your farm and that's why you
observe if you've done weeding when it's
training or there was some uh light
showers you will observe that they tend
to turn yellow after completing the
weding and most of the time they lose
the leaves and when they lose the leaves
also they reduce the ability of making
their own food and the beans as well
reducing and roaring the whole thing
okay the best thing is that at the end
of all once you manage all this you
control all the weeds bottom line is
that it is possible for you to harvest
at least 10 bags and above per of L coo
beans and remember you planted 16 to 20
kgs okay and the if you do the MS the
fertilizer the chemical you find the
cost are very very very minimal now
before I leave I I would really love to
hear your view and also your comment
have you tried it did it disappoint you
did it do well also we tell you Farmers
that this is a platform where we sharpen
each other don't if it did well for you
share the tips so that other farmers can
continue learning and we can continue
sharpening each other