hello everyone welcome back to our
channel so for today's video we are
going to do on monsoon
and its current status of the monsoon in
india as well as
its impact on agriculture okay so um
and we're also trying to do some few
questions we're going to solve them
as well as we're going to explain some
of the questions and
uh which is very important from the exam
point of view especially for this
aggregatology i think at least about one
or two questions high counselors of at
least minimum of two questions coming
from this
topic okay so guys watch this video till
the end
my name is hansa nora salman and i've
done my bachelor's
in horticulture and i've also completed
my post-graduation and dermatology in
agriculture okay
so before going further if you guys are
new to this channel please don't forget
to subscribe and you can also
press the bell icon for further
notifications
and do share with your friends and if
you guys have enjoyed this session
don't forget to hit the thumbs up button
as well
so um if your first slide we are going
to talk something about this monsoon how
uh so there has been an increase in
sowing
uh because of the good monsoon by 87 so
we're just gonna have a
rough talk and rough overview about the
monsoon in general right as well as in
the uh indian economy and agriculture
so the first line here sees about thirds
of the indus manufacturing outfit
which makes up about eighteen percent of
the country's gross domestic product
is linked to agriculture and therefore
into the food right
and the second point here is the monsoon
it is a lifeboat
uh basically for indian agriculture and
it depended on about
2 trillion dollars of economy and at
least half of the farmlands are rain fed
and when we're gonna talk about wing fed
rain fed areas are the areas or the
farms
where there is no facility for
irrigation no irrigating facilities
so they are totally dependent on
rainfall for the crop production
all right and now this in this
agriculture sector they also account for
about
14 of the country's uh 2.7 trillion
crammy which is the
one one uh which we were talking about
and about 42
of the total employment so agriculture
is a huge sector where
it gives about majority almost half of
the employment comes to agriculture
practices in india okay and 55 percent
of the indus arable land dependent on
precipitation right
so when you say 55 it means basically
it's a rainfall
farms or the rain fed lens okay um
so 55 of it these are
completely dependent on precipitation so
precipitation is just another word for
rainfall right so i hope this is clear
and now let's move on to our new
slides where we're going to talk why
there is an increase how
zarin increased so basically uh due to
the good rainfall in the month of june
the basic important key crop sewing
areas that have increased by about 87
and when we compare this percentage to
the last
year so there has been increased by 87
percent there is
huge range right so uh rice cultivation
is basically a curved crop
so right now in the modern season rice
is a major curry crop so they are
growing this
at a huge amount of number at a huge
area okay
so these are grown nearly 40 percent of
the total area during the curry crop
season and is up to about 39
okay so the oil seeds they have risen
more than three times
of its normal production and the
cultivation
and as if you're going to talk about
pulses then it has
had a piece of about quadruplet which
means four times okay
so um these are something overview about
these monsoons and especially as
rice is a very water intensive um
crop so i think a lot of water is needed
so
due to this uh good rainfall in this
year in june so
the right production is also high
chances of rice production as well
um states like bihar punjab and harvard
they are one of the major moving
agriculture states in our country where
they have
grown where they grow a lot of career
season especially for rice wheat maize
all of that
pulses especially these are the main
good monsoon they also helped the
farmers increase the sowing area
okay so these are some of the overview
and some of the impact
that this monsoon has on the indian
economy
is that these are um basically uh
the monsoon they have a direct impact on
the
country's agricultural gdp right so the
planting of this key career
season which is the season for now are
the summer crops like
rice sugarcane pulses and oil seeds they
begin with the arrival or the
onset of the monsoon rains in the june
right and
due to this when you have a good
production when there's a good rainfall
the quality
the quantity of and the sowing area will
also increase
and therefore there'll be higher
production and in the end they'll have a
better income
right so and even uh the summer crops
they also account for
almost half of indus food output and
delayed or the per me
monsoon it means issues and acceleration
in the food inflation as well
so this is also a problem so if you have
a
good output to the summer product uh
the summer crops they are the major
crops for the indus food output
and there will be if the monsoon is poor
the
production will also be lesser and
therefore there will be
uh supply issues and sublime as they
will be
having a smooth inflation okay so
another point
that i want to focus here is that
especially in a poor monsoon they'd also
not
lead to demand or to weak demand or
fast-moving
consumer goods as well if the
two-wheelers attractors rural housing
sectors all of these will also have an
impact
uh by the import of this essential food
staples and they will also force
the government to take measures like
lone waves and thereby
they will also put more pressure on the
finances as well
another important point is that a weak
monsoon is strong
correlate is strongly correlated to the
receding water table in the ground
and this will also worsen the farmer's
distress
okay so these are some of the impacts
that this monsoon has on indian
agriculture
and thereby on an indian economy i hope
this is clear
um now let's move on to another slide
where i've just given some
a variable uh brainful variability in
india right
so basically in rainfall where we talk
about the rate for variability in
the indian subcontinent they continue uh
they receive its
annual rainfall by the speculative
phenomenon um which we call it monsoons
right and
basically it's consists of a cyclone
that arrives
in the indian ocean okay and this uh
cyclone in the indian ocean they travel
in the northeast direction
towards that side and they enter the
peninsula region
along its west coast so the cup they go
around the whole
peninsula indian region and they enter
to the west coast all right so some of
the important
um radial variability or the type of
monsoon systems in
india that we can find uh the major two
ones are
southwest monsoon as you can see here
the first point and we also have a
northwest monsoon
right so we also have a winter rainfall
as fellas in the summer rainfall
and let me just briefly talk about what
this uh southeast monsoon northeast
monster exam
all of these are okay so um this
first thing this southeast monsoon this
is one of the most important
of monsoon season in india as it
contributes to about about
80 to 90 of the total rainfall in the
country
uh the this is one of the most important
cycles
of cyclone cycles and they usually occur
in the month of june to september
and this results in the mons summer
monsoon so it's southwest monsoon is
also known as the
summer monster right and now let's go to
our second point which is on the
northeast monsoon
so uh in northeast monsoon these are
these
august during the month of september and
right
so the northwest monsoon they penetrate
through northwestern
india and but it stays a full month in
the eastern
india which is in bengal okay so um
these are some of the things on the
northwest mountain i think that's
enough for you all to know and we also
have winter rainfall
so it's winter rainfall it is mostly
restricted to the northern area
or the northern indian and it is
basically uh
suppose if it's in the hilly regions or
the marlin regions then it will
form in the form of a snow and if it's
in plain regions
then rains or come okay
so these are something on the winter
rainfall and now lastly we're going to
talk about this summer rainfall
so in summer rainfall this uh the
rainfall is basically received in the
march
of march um to may okay
so so these are which is received during
this summer months
as a local storms right so these are
mostly received in the southeast of the
peninsula or in the west bengal right
so basically the western indian sign
they are not generally
affected by this summer rainfall or they
do not receive
this rainfall okay so these are
something important uh
points it's not really important from
the exam point of view but i think uh
it's very important to at least know the
types of monsoons in
india that we have all right
and now let's go to another question uh
over the question series the first
option says the crops region the crop
region they are classified based on
average rainfall okay
and which of the following range comes
under this semi-annual region
so based on the uh rainfall received
annually these field
uh they have classified these regions
into different
regions right um the first option given
here is
less than 500 number bc is 500 to 700
number c is 750 to 1000
number d is 1000 to 1500 and number e is
more than
1500 right so right answer for this is
700 500 to 750 okay so
based here if you can see the uh lower
table i've given on the left hand side
given the rainfall in the meter and on
the right hand side you can see the
climatic regions all right
so um this table is very important guys
if you guys are learning it for the
first time
please remember i would request you all
to take a screenshot of the screen
and you can also jot it down if you're
having a notepad besides you can just
pause the video and jot it down okay
so okay first thing less than 500 it is
in the arabic region right and we have
500 to 700
means in this semi-arid region uh 750 to
it's in the suburbs and more than 1000
it's in the humid so these are the lists
of the rainfall ranges as well as along
with the regions all right
so i think this is very important from
uh high chances of this question coming
and exam
okay another one here is on the
reflected solar radiation
without any change in quality is known
as
the options given here are the radiation
flux number b
is emission power number c is alberto
number d
is latent heat and we also have from the
huge safe
sensible heat affection okay so guys the
right answer for this is alberto so el
pedu what is this alberto it is
basically
just the measurement of the reflectivity
of an object
okay so the solar radiation enters the
earth right
and soft these are absorbed and soft
these are
reflected back so alberto is basically
the reflected pack without
any change these are the uh radiations
solar radiations which are reflected
back without
any change in its quantity or the
quality okay
so this is what an albedo is okay so in
other words if there's a measure
of the diffuse reflection of the solar
radiation out of this total radiation
received by an astronomical body so
according to this
definition we can say that every object
has different
alberto okay in this point i have given
this a very important point i've given
some of the alberto um percentages of
different elements okay the first one is
for the pure water so pure water is an
albedo for
about five to twenty percent okay and
we're going to talk about
vegetation it's about 10 to 40 percent
and for soil it's about 15 to 50 percent
and if we're going to talk about earth
we have about 34 to
43 so roughly we're going to talk a
static
average for earth then they say it's
about 35
okay and if it's for clouds then we have
about 55
and especially at this point if you're
gonna come down here
uh when you talk about plans for the
plant community this albedo
the absorption of sorry the reflection
of the soil radiation
they depend on the first thing is on the
age of the crop the second is the
percentage of the ground cover
as well as the last one is and the color
and reflectivity
of the foliage okay guys so these are
some of the points on elbow
that you actually to remember another
point is that here on earth especially
the albedo effect they have a very
significant impact on the
climate as well so at the lower the
elbow right to lower the percentage of
the elbow
the more radiation from the sun that
gets absorbed by the planet okay
and therefore the temperature will rise
but if the albedo is higher
then the earth is more reflective and
more of the radiation
is returned to the space and the planet
cools
so these are something on so you can
you're getting the pattern right it's a
vegetation it's about it's towards the
highest so
we have more vegetation ground cover
then definitely
the earth will be lesser um less cool
um sorry will be cooler okay so um
uh in the question you can see that we
have already come across a few of the
uh state a few of the definite a few of
the terms right
so now let us understand what these
terms are okay so base the first one is
and the radiation flux
so uh radiation flux uh these are the
amounts of gradient energy which are
emitted
as well as which are received and
transmitted
across a particular area and this is
known as the radiant flux okay
and the second one here is on the
emissive power
so when you have the radiant uh
radiation flux
the density of this radiant flush is
basically emitted by a source right
and this is called aster emissive power
okay so this is what an emissive power
is and
alberto we have already discussed what
an albedo is and
now we have a latent heat so a latent
heat is a part of an incident radiation
on the surface if absorbed and while
a part of it is reflected and the
remaining is basically transmitted so
these are
uh latent heat what a latent heat is
so we also have the last option was
given here
the last option given here is on the
sensible heat direction right
so sensible heat infection as well as
sensation heat the other types of this
energy
which are basically released or absorbed
in the atmosphere okay
but this latent heat these are most
related to the changes in the phase of
between the liquids the gases and the
solids
whereas in the sensible heat these are
mostly related to the temperature
which are of the gas or the objects with
no change in the face
right so an example all right so these
are some of the terms the definitions of
this
so try to know the at least the
definitions i think
just know your definition will offer
survives okay
all right so um let's go to another
slide which is
on which of the following crop is or
considered as a short day plan so this
is a very easy question
again but very important okay so the
options given here are number a
is potato we have b which is rice then
you have c
which is wheat
so guys the right answer for this is
rice
rice is the short day plant right so now
let us talk about this duration of
light right so based on the
classification
of these plants these are based
classified into a few groups three
groups mainly on the basis of
photoperiodism
and if you're going to ask what is a
protoperiodism a photoperiodism is a
response of a plan to the
relative length of the day and night and
this
is known as photopurism okay and this
would be radism it influences
the planned character the flow
realization or
development we'll have blood bulb and
rhizome production etc
so these are some of the fact and some
of the points where these photoperiodism
they affect the plant okay
um the first one here is a short day
plan we also have long day
and we have a neutral plant right so
this duration of the life they have a
great influence and the intensity for
the canopy as well as for the final
years okay guys
um it is very important to consider this
in the selection of the crop varieties
especially
the crop varieties and the short day
plans if you're going to look at that
these are the plants
which basically develop normally when
they develop normally when the for the
period is
less than the critical or maximum okay
so the critical maximum is less than 12
hours right so these are what short-term
plans are
and now when we look into this
long-distance these laundry plants these
are the plants which develop and they
produce
normally when the photo period is
greater than the max
critical minimum which is greater than
the 12
us so these longer plans they needed to
the length of about more than 12 hours
and now
the last one here is of the day neutral
plant and the day neutral plant
basically these are the plants or those
plants which are not affected by the
photo period okay
i hope this is clear and now let's go to
another a slide where i've just given
some of the examples along with in the
table
along with the short day plan long day
plan and day neutral okay
so let me just read out the for the
short term plans we
coffee have chrysanthemums dahlia
goose food we have hemp morning glory
poinsettia these are all flowers okay
guys
and we have rice soy bean we have
tobacco
we have violets so these are also
another flowers
and now let's look into longer plants
for long day we have barley
cabbage carrots hanbin we have lobster
these are also flowering plants we have
lettuce
onion petunia poppy these are flowers
raw dish spinach and beet
and if you're going to look into the new
japans we have balsam
these are also flowers okay and
we have beans chilies capsicum
to be sorry tomato cotton cucumber
a maize potato all of these these are
under the neutral plants okay um right
so now let's go to our fourth question
who is the father of agri meteorology in
india okay
so guys um the right answer for this
is okay so before that before giving the
right answer let me just read out the
options
uh the options given here our number is
m swaminathan we have
b which is ramdas c is bp
pal and d is jw leather and number e
is none of the above so guys the right
answer for this
is el eram does so he is the man who is
the
father of the agrimetrology in india
right so in that we try to study for the
fathers of
different other allied subjects under
agriculture we also have for soil
science agronomy
agricultural engineering try to list out
all the fathers of his respective
discipline and jot it down make it i
think it'll be more much more easier for
you guys if you can make a table out of
this
and get study in that way okay so um
my last question here i would like you
all to answer for this again
so which of the following range of the
wavelength they help in photosynthetic
and photoperiodic activity so we do have
certain
range of wavelengths which help in
certain uh growth and
production and for certain effects that
it has a particular function that it has
on the plant okay
so this question is based on that right
so
uh think carefully and drop it in the
comment section all right guys
so the options i'm gonna read up that
number a is 720
to 510 number b is 1000 number c is more
than 1 000.
number d is 500 to 400 number e
is 400 to 300. out of these which one
the longest range helps in the
photosynthetic as well as in the
photoperiodic activity
if you guys know the answer then do drop
it in the comment section so that i'll
be able to know
right guys and before going uh let's
just solve three of the
questions quickly right so i've just
given
the questions here and i think it's
quite small i don't know whether you
guys are able to see or not
if it's visible then but let me just
increase the size of this right guys
yeah
this is more visible now okay so um
number question number one was that
indian institute of tropical meteorology
iitm it is located in
putna right then it was established in
the year of 1962.
right and question number two is wind
speed is measured by
any moment rainfall is measured by rain
gauge okay guys
and we have a chemical which is used for
artificial
rainfall i think this is an important
question so you can jot it down i'm
gonna
put a star mark under this and
we also have um the word monsoon it is
derived from arabic
language and the last one says that the
radiation having thermal effect on the
plant
is uh the answer would be your infrared
radiation so these
are some of the questions that i've just
quickly jotted down for that which i
thought might be very important from the
exam point of view
okay guys um so that's all for today i
hope that you guys had a productive
session with me i hope it was clear for
you all if you guys have more doubts or
if you guys
want me to take up some topic in which
you guys are having trouble with or if
you guys
want me to explain those topics better
then do drop in the comments section and
you can also reach out to us we're
always there to help out
nice and um if you guys
have any more doubts and queries do drop
in the comment section okay
exams are also there they have just
given up for the nabard exam they've
just given out the tentative dates but
i'm not sure whether it's gonna be in
september or but
uh till then until the actual dates come
out i would like you all to
could uh request you all to continue
revising for the exam
as well as you can also uh have more
time to prepare well so that you guys
will have higher chances of doing better
in the exam
right so guys if you are new to this
channel please don't forget to subscribe
and you can also press the bell icon if
you like the video
do like uh do like the video and hit the
thumbs up button
and you can also share with your friends
right so let's meet for the next session
with another topic