guys what's going on today we are going
to talk about five
different tread patterns for tractor
tires this is a good variety here of
different patterns we're going to tell
you all about what you would use them
for
what the patterns are called price
points where to get them construction
all that kind of thing so stick around
oh yeah and if you haven't done so yet
hit that subscribe button right
underneath the video
make sure you read through the
description it's right down there as
well you're going to have links to where
you can buy
all these tires at get discount codes
all sorts of good stuff for you tractor
owners out there
and don't forget to check out the other
videos on my channel you might like them
let's go ahead and get the terminology
out of the way let you know what these
tires are called here because that'll
help you'll see these terms
used all over the internet if you're
tractor shopping or in forums or
different websites that kind of thing so
right here you have the
r1 ag style tire agricultural style tire
you can see it's a v-shaped bar pattern
here there's going to be different
variations of it but the general
tread pattern is going to be what you
see here kind of a v that goes back
very similar to what you see on all the
old style and current style but
farming machinery okay what's out there
in the fields doing the work that kind
of thing it's a very traditional style
of tread pattern and it's been around
virtually as long as tractors have been
around well at least with
rubber tires on them maybe maybe steel
tires too
this one here is an r4 industrial style
of tread pattern okay so it's going to
be a thicker bar it does share some
resemblance over here with the r1 but
it's going to be a thicker
flatter wider bar all right and so we'll
get into what the applications are in
the differences in a little bit but
that's going to be the difference that
you see here again there's multiple
variations of this depending on the tire
manufacturer and
maybe there's little hybrids or you know
specific applications that
would require something that's a little
bit of a different machine or even in
the construction world too but
r4 industrial this one here is called an
r3 tire all right so it's a turf tire
there's going to be a lot of variations
of these as well you're going to have
golf course tires flotation tires but
turf as you might expect is going to be
great for your lawns you'll see these on
a lot of garden tractors as well or lawn
mowers that kind of thing but
turf tire right here r3 next up this one
right here is going to be called the
hdap it doesn't really have an
r uh delineation that i know of but hdap
stands for heavy duty all-purpose tire
you can kind of see here it's a bit of a
hybrid if you look across here
a stab tire and the next one actually on
my tractor over here this is going to be
the carlisle
versaturf again it doesn't really have
an r delineation on there but
as a name might suggest turf you're
going to see it does share
some similarities with this style of
tire right here as well
so the big hitter is going to be the
application what these excel and what
they do bad and that kind of thing but
let's get to pricing first we can get
that out of the way
of course these are all the same size
tire here they're a 26 12 12 made for
the sub compacts
made for large garden tractors like the
john deere x700 series
your kubota bx the list kind of goes on
it's a very popular size here
for a lot of machines so if we're
talking the same size tire which this is
a really good example here
same price same price same price in
price more money okay so
you're going to have all your
traditional styles and you're going to
have a more advanced style the versa
turf over here
being the more money all right and we're
going to get into that as well however i
have links for all of these where you
can buy these tires whether it's on
amazon if you want tires and wheels
miller tire as well is a great company
links below to where you can get more
information on there get discounts as
well but
if you're looking for a tire in this
size links are down there
okay so now let's figure out why this
tire over here the versa turf is going
to cost more than all these other tires
right here
it's still a bunch of rubber right it
doesn't look like there's more material
there's really not anything super
special
about it if you're just looking at it
right the difference is going to be
underneath the construction of it
these are going to be bias right here
one two three four these are all bias
construction which is a
an old school way of doing it okay or a
cheaper way of doing it as well
and this is going to be a newer
technology it's going to be a radial
design which
michelin i think kind of came up with a
long time ago but this is going to be
fairly new to the tractor world
are the radial tires so you're going to
see those that terminology thrown around
a lot in
trailer tires and vehicle tires that
kind of thing but
in the tractor world it's fairly new so
if we take a look here at the general
construction of these tires you're going
to have a radial tire here the versaturf
versus a bias tire so a bias tire has
strands the elements that make this up
are going to go all the way from the
bead on one side all the way around to
the bead on the other side they may
come across at a diagonal 30 degree 45
degrees somewhere in that ballpark
but over here on the radial you're going
to have different strands different
elements that make this up and so your
contact surface that's up here is going
to have a completely
separate existence from what's over on
the side walls and what that means is
that
when you hit bumps and you go up and
down and the tire absorbs load and then
flexes and reshapes
you're going to have more contact
surface with the radial tire because
this is all one piece so as it kind of
ebbs and flows and it's almost like a
balloon
you're going to lose contact surface
it's going to increase you're going to
have a bumpier ride
you're going to lose traction at uh at
different moments as well
over here on the radial you're going to
have more of a little bit of a cushion
or a shock absorption so it's going to
be a more comfortable ride with
a radial tire but it's also going to
maintain better contact with the ground
which
is great for traction is great for
getting power to the ground
and it's going to just perform better in
those kinds of scenarios
so some of the benefits that come along
with that additional cost are going to
be a more comfortable ride because it
will absorb those shocks as you go over
it
you're going to have better traction
more power to the ground because of that
additional traction
and then longer tread life as well let's
go ahead and rank these bad boys on a
scale from one to five from best to
worst i'm going to put the information
below
let's cover lawns let's cover paved
surfaces let's cover
snow and ice and let's cover dirt and
mud all right first thing really quick i
want to touch on these versatiles here
if you have a larger tractor such as a 2
series 3 series 4 series
that kind of thing there or equivalent
kubota mahindra whatever it doesn't
matter just a larger tractor besides the
subcompact
right now you can't get the versaturf
however there are a couple others that
are out there
i just had them put on my 4066r it's
going to be the goodyear
r14 okay it's going to be a radial tire
again it's going to be very similar
you're going to see a lot of
similarities
to this tire pattern right here i just
put them on i just took my r4s off
the other one you're going to see out
there is going to be called a galaxy pro
r3 plus i believe it's called okay so
it's going to be an r3 which is this
tread pattern here but plus
so a little bit on steroids again and
it's galaxies take
basically on a radial like this as well
so radial construction
a bit of a hybrid there just another
option out there for you to consider so
you may have a hard time remembering all
this so i will put a reference down
below in the description of the video
too
let's go ahead and start out with lawn
now if you think of a lawn application
you want something to be gentle right
you don't want anything aggressive on
there so
it's not going to be too hard to imagine
that the turf tire here the r3 is gonna
be number one in my book
now a very close second or third you
know it's almost
a tie for second place but i'm gonna
give it to the to the radial here the uh
the versaturf radial here followed up by
the hdap
then we're gonna go r4 and then we're
gonna go r1
now a few notes here the r1 is going to
be bad on your lawn if you
enjoy a nice lawn if you have a nice
lawn if you don't want it to get ripped
up do not get an r1 tire and think that
you're going to be
just mowing your lawn and everything's
going to be hunky-dory this
here is designed for traction it is not
designed to be gentle on the lawn you're
going to have rust you're going to have
ripped up areas when you're turning
all that kind of stuff the r4 is
probably the most popular tire
out there right now for both subcompacts
and compacts it's going to be just fine
for mowing lawns
anything that you drive on your lawn if
it's going to be wet and soggy and damp
any of these tires here will cause
damage okay it doesn't really matter how
light or heavy your machine is
just don't drive on it when it's wet and
soggy so these two right here will both
give you a little bit of a problem if
you are doing circles
around trees in the same spot over and
over they're a little bit more
aggressive right just a little bit not
too much more than this but
that's why i'm giving this a nod and
these are second and third
okay next up let's talk about snow and
ice what is the best tread pattern here
for those conditions can you guess what
it is the best tread pattern far and
away the reason i ended up putting them
on my 4066r for this year
as well is gonna be this versaturf style
of tire right here
again on the larger four r series
tractors i end up going with a goodyear
r14
but basically the same very similar
tread pattern to that a radial
construction as well
i'm telling you these were amazing just
amazing in the
in the winter for the snow and the ice
around here last year you know
these tires right here not so much all
right so let's go ahead and rank these
really quick but we're going to go one
two three four and then five these are
the
absolute worst right here the r4 tires
they're just terrible i've gotten stuck
on the side of my driveway before
have been able to not make it up hills
but you're going to kind of see
a little bit of a similarity amongst
these three right
so quite similar in their tread design
turfs believe it or not are quite good
and i would take them any day
over the r4 tires in fact i would take
even the r1 eggs over here
these are going to be okay not super
great um but they're not going to be bad
the r1s so before the versaturfs were
around i ran hdap tires on my
john deere x7 series tractors absolutely
loved them i long wondered why they
didn't offer these from the factory
for the john deere 1 series the kubota
bx that kind of thing because i think
it's such a versatile tread pattern
so i'm really thrilled they came out
with this versatiff tire i give it the
edge over the hdac because it is that
radial construction as well one of the
biggest problems people have when
they're in snow whether they're pushing
it whether they're driving through it
whether they're plowing it
whatever they're doing is traction that
is your
engine your tractor your machine it's
got enough power to do the job all right
you might have the right tool
in front to do the job the weak link is
most often
that traction that point of contact to
the ground so tires and that kind of
application are
absolutely critical and while of course
traction is important in all
applications i feel like in snow and ice
it's really really put to the test
and it separates the really good ones
from the really bad ones
let's go ahead and talk about pavement
here really quick i want to include this
pavement being
you know whether it's asphalt you know
concrete you know
if you're in your shop if you're on your
driveway if you're in a big going down
the road if your main purpose is going
to be traveling on a road a lot or on a
hard surface that's where it's going to
kind of live
that's what this is really meant for so
this is going to be number five right
here your r1 ag tire this will be the
absolute worst for those paved surfaces
for the roads for concrete that kind of
thing
really beyond that i'm going to go ahead
and shuffle these three right here in
the middle
no particular order and then i'm going
to give the radial here the edge for the
absolute
best tire that you can get for paved
surfaces the reason the r1 here is
really bad
is not that it doesn't have traction
doesn't grip that kind of thing
but it is a little bit bumpy of a ride
just based on the construction of it and
it's also going to wear
very very quickly on those paved
surfaces it's just
it's a very aggressive tire and when
you're turning and twisting and turn
and just moving around on paved surfaces
a lot it's going to wear super quickly
and wear these out
and it's just not going to be very
practical you get into the r4s these are
going to be great
same thing with the turf same thing with
the hdap on your paved surfaces
going to maintain really good traction
they're going to wear very well
you're not going to wear through them
quickly they're going to last a very
long time
the reason i give the radial over here
the edge is because of the fact that
again it's a radial alright so you're
going to have a more comfortable ride
when you're on those hard surfaces there
where if you do come across bumps
you know dips in the road whatever the
case is that you run into
it's going to take some of that shock
out of there maintain better traction
across your whole
operating experience okay so dirt and
mud they kind of go hand in hand they
kind of don't you know whether it's dry
whether it's a wet soupy mess we're
going to go ahead and break this down
best to worst
the best tire that you can get for dirt
for mud are going to be the r1
ag style of tread pattern here they are
just an absolute beast that's just what
they were made
to thrive in you think about again go
back to farming you know you see the
tractor out in the field they're
planting all the corn harvesting the
corn whatever it might be
they're going to have this style right
on there because you never know what the
conditions are going to be
but you know it's going to be mud it's
going to be dirt let's go ahead and rank
these really quick you're going to have
the r1 being the best the versaturf
being the second best
the hdap being the third best r4 fourth
best and then unfortunately
your traditional turf tire is going to
follow up last now this is a little bit
different but i did have a skid steer
recently with these tires you got to
check out that video i got it buried in
mud
out of my hunting lease it was quite
humorous there but these tires right
here
they just they just have a lot of
limitations okay now
keep in mind a skid steer is a very very
heavy piece of equipment it'll sink like
a rock and that's exactly what it did
you know these versaturfs over here had
the self-cleaning cleats on here again
similar to the goodyear r14 or the
galaxy pro they're going to have just a
good
hybrid setup on there the h-steps again
have a lot of areas for grip they're not
going to clean out as well as
this versaturf is over here i just am
not a huge fan of the r4s
it's unfortunate they're on so many
tractors in the subcompact and compact
world
but of course you wouldn't expect a turf
tire like this to perform very well
in dirt or mud now on dry hard dirt if
you're just going into the woods down
the trail it's going to be just fine all
right
but if we're getting into those muddy
situations this is where it's really
going to fill up fast the cleats are
they're not going to clean out
and you're just going to be sitting
there spinning your wheels so a good
question that you might ask yourself is
why is the r4 tread pattern so extremely
popular okay and i think it's
a combination of reasons right because
tractors are used in a lot of different
applications you might use it
for mowing your lawn you might use it
for push and snow you might use it in
the woods
you know all the above on paved surfaces
so the r4
is really the all-purpose tire in my
opinion yes this is heavy duty
all-purpose hd ap
that's what it stands for but it's not
really viewed as a tractor or a heavy
equipment
tire so you get folks that see this tire
this is what they expect to be on a
tractor anymore
it's become so popular in the last 15
years or so that
probably 80 or more of the tractors out
there are rocking an r4 tread pattern
but they really don't excel at a whole
lot
except for not failing at most things
you know they're gonna give you really
good
uh where life you know you can go
hundreds if not thousands of hours
front tires are always gonna wear
quicker than back tires are
you know you're turning you're putting
more load with a loader that kind of
thing on there they're just gonna wear
out
they're smaller you know just everything
but the rear tires especially
you can go a thousand maybe even more
than that depending on the applications
that you're using it for
but i want you guys to see this from a
different perspective here that you
don't have to be stuck with the tires
that come
on your machine all right you have the
ability to change them out to keep a
second set of wheels and tires on hand
too
so if you have a spring and summer setup
and a fall and winter setup or
you have a month worth of projects that
you want to do in the woods so you want
to put a more aggressive tire on there
and then switch back to a different
tread pattern for the rest of the year
you can really mix that up just don't
stranglehold yourself and think
you have to stick with just the tires
that are on your machine right now
and now i know that does come as a cost
but it's something to kind of plan for
right
when you look at a machine you shouldn't
only be thinking well i get the tractor
and then that's it
tractors are just the the basic tool all
right you can outfit them in so many
different ways on the back end on the
front end and of course
even the wheels and tires well you got
to take a good look there
side by side by side by side by side i
think that's it
of all the different tread patterns that
are out there it certainly doesn't
encompass
everything that's on the market but it's
a pretty good variety and it kind of
gives you a little bit more insight
hopefully on where each
style of tread pattern will excel i'd be
very curious
very interested and i think the other
viewers would as well if you would leave
a comment below with your own experience
of these tires
i know we all have different experiences
this is just my two cents on the
situation i've used all these tires in
different
situations applications over the years
so it's kind of my own take on it
i get a lot of tractors in here hundreds
of tractors in here with different tread
patterns on them as well so
i can see kind of how they last over
time too just gives me a really unique
perspective to be able to share that
information with you
if you haven't done so yet hit that
subscribe button right underneath the
video
make sure you read through that
description as well okay links to where
you can get
all these tires and other really cool
tractor products and check out the other
videos on my channel
until next time stay safe we'll see you
soon now really quickly if you are
interested in getting more of that
lateral that side to side stability one
of the options you can look into on the
26 12 12 so the tires that are this size
all of them that we're seeing in this
video here are going to be a wheel
adapter for dual wheels where you can
fit it right inside there
just like this take a look okay it comes
with all the hardware you need where
you'll just
bolt it right through long bolts right
through that one right to your other
tire here and get
a lot of additional stability there side
to side you can use a dual wheel adapter
just like this to get a lot more
stability on hills okay
side to side can be very dangerous can
be very concerning for a lot of folks
out there so whether it's wheel spacers
dual wheels you know there is a
potential there to shorten the lifespan
of the rear axle of your machine but
really that's a decision that you need
to make as the operator right
if you're going to choose safety if you
have really dangerous situations there
where you need to accomplish your work
you can either add spacers or you can
add dual wheels get that safety measure
there and just take the risk
use common sense regardless if you want
to get this dual wheel adapter kit you
can do so at millertire.com link below
you get five percent off with discount
code gwt