three ways to get rid of ants with
things you already have lemon juice mix
one part lemon juice and three parts
water and spray around to any place
where they might be coming in or just
save your Peels and scatter them around
the house this will mask the ant scent
Trail and stop them cinnamon studies
show that cinnamon actually contains a
compound that repels and kills ants just
a little sprinkle will do definitely
better than all those harsh chemicals
salt sprinkle table salt in their path
to repel the ants or spray them with
salt water this will dehydrate and get
rid of them because they're actually
more gross than you might think and
often transfer E coli to food surfaces
which can make you really sick