people are concerned about pesticide
safety they've heard stories about
people getting cancers or other
illnesses due to the pesticide exposure
and so we're gonna talk a little bit
about the time in which people get
exposed to those chemicals most often
that is going to be during the mixing
and loading portion of your pesticide
application one of the things we take a
look at is that are you using your
personal protective equipment many of
the labels are actually most of the
labels are going to tell you what
personal protective equipment is
required if it's going to be chemical
resistant gloves if it's gonna be
goggles or a face mask or maybe it's
that you wear long sleeve shirts or
maybe in this particular case a Tyvek
suit when you're making certain
applications within your pesticide and
program so mixing and loading why is it
so dangerous it's like most of us can
understand the concept if we stick the
hose into a spray tank that there's
water that's going to go into the tank
where we see most of the problem is
though as we take our chemical we mix it
we measure it and then I will suddenly
want to watch it go into a spray tank
and then we get splashed back into our
eyes unto our face and we have very high
concentrations of chemical to get on to
our body so you need to have the
personal protective equipment on to
protect yourself from those exposures
also in mixing and loading we want to
make sure that you're going to do things
correctly North Dakota like many states
puts out a weed control guy there's
actually a formula on page 96 that will
tell you which of the products goes in
first
and so apples is the formula that we use
in agitate then you put the different
chemicals and add to the
into the spray-paint in a particular
order when we go out we start spraying
you have to realize that even though it
chemical might be a restrictive use
which is bidipi seen on the front of the
label right by the label made these
chemicals are going to be more dangerous
because they're more persistent however
that does not mean the general use of
pesticides don't come with the gun with
risk many of us had the conversation
about glyphosate is it dangerous or is
it not dangerous so we are going to try
to teach you here is that it is your
responsibility if you haven't received a
pesticide license you're basically
saying that you are going to read and
follow the label many Extension agents
are people that have taught pesticide
classes emphasize that the label is the
law and it's something that you have to
do as an individual producer or
applicator is to read it again I wish we
would talk more with the general
applicators as well because the big
story is about glyphosate which is not
restricted use but there is still still
potential risk with it and it's because
people don't read the label the chemical
companies has spent millions of dollars
to figure out how to keep the
applicators safe during those chemical
applications and now it's your job to
read and follow the label like good
applicators would