folks today on the Stony Rich Farm
Channel we're going to show you a day of
fun chores and we're going to get Uncle
Jesse started
wo dude that cow is peeing and the
wind's blowing so hard the pee blew and
hit me in the face yuck hey buddy boy
what are you doing my little friend are
you hungry come here give me a hug good
gracious yeah
[Music]
go ahead let's go eat breakfast I ain't
afraid to
work I ain't afraid
to I ain't afraid to get the job done
and do good my own damn
way ain't afraid of
Li times like
this if you mess myed I tell what you
can kiss good morning everybody welcome
back to the Stony Ridge Farm awesome
gorgeous day here getting ready to get
out of Sunshine a high of
67° today spring is in the air the grass
is starting to sprout up and we're going
to take you guys along with us today
this is going to be a little bit of a
different video than we've done in a
very long time we're going to take you
around we're going to show you just what
a day is like here this video was
prompted I'm setting my junk down here
on my on my blue Honda here but this
video was prompted by a comment from a
viewer and uh thank you Michael R for
asking this question if I could take you
around and show you just what a general
day is here on the Stony Ridge Farm so
we'll set these goodies right here
they'll probably blow off on the ground
wind is whipping at about 20 M an hour
and uh we've got a little bit of work to
do so I've got the Unicorn Dodge truck
sitting out here big te we're going to
be in that tractor in just a minute we
got cows to feed track uh four-wheelers
to move tractors to move all sorts of
fun stuff so and we got to make a road
trip it's going to be a fun day go ahead
and the kenel
go ahead in the kennel I've got a cinder
block on top of my dog food uh container
here and if you guys don't know these
make the best ever food containers for
Animals these are the brute food
containers and this is my little
concoction of CBD oil so I'll give Buddy
a little scoop right here he doesn't
mind the flavor of the CBD oil I think
it kind of stinks I think he really
likes it so we'll just dab a little bit
on there that's probably uh plenty for
Mr
Buddy and into the food bowl we go ready
happy
boy
free such a smart dog just a great
animal I hate that uh that he's doing so
badly but you know about the time a dog
gets good you know what I mean by the
time a dog gets perfect it's about the
time they start having health problems
and I really hate that we're going to be
taking the Unicorn Dodge here in just a
little bit on a road trip so stick
around let's grab the ATV we're going to
run up to the shop open the garage door
I'm having trouble the wind catches this
door this is a crappy situation right
here I need to put an automatic door
closer on here that's coming soon oh in
this bag are oil filters for my ATVs and
I keep a stockpile of oil filters and a
few things on the four-wheeler here so
let's fire this puppy up this is a blue
Becon
[Applause]
on close that garage door back or the
cats will get in
there shut her down Beaver every day I
take up a new tiny load of tools these
are called ratchet scrunch they're
awesome chainsaw tool and we'll go on
inside the shop real quick
here open the door
aloro okay ratchet scrunch goes in the
catch all table you guys have one of
those and this is my Honda oil filters
and Honda
parts dump all those oil
filters in there and I can't throw stuff
away I have a problem throwing stuff
away
so I just got motor oil in my mouth I'll
save this so when I uh take some beef to
a beef customer I have a nice bag
good heavy duty bag from the Honda place
this is where the beef for the farm is
kept I'm running a little bit low on
beef right now however I am going to
take out uh as you guys can see the
freezer is almost totally empty I'm
going to take out
uh got a ribeye or two I think I'm going
to take out I've got these are my last
RI eyes right here and uh I think I'm
going to take a few
out let them thaw this is a ribeye right
I'm having a with my Butcher and the
reason I can't sell my beef is because
of my butcher this is not a ribeye that
is a ribeye okay that is a ribeye that's
a New York strip but that says ribeye on
it that says ribeye on it and that's a
New York strip that's not a
ribeye what else we got down
here I don't know those I don't think
those are ribe eyes this is a ribeye
that's what do you guys think I'm a
little disappointed
you know what let's just use that bag
it's a good thing we got that bag ain't
it I'm going to take and load my freezer
up at the
house nice chuck roast I'll throw that
in the uh insta pot and I'll have some
good food for
tomorrow excuse my mess this shop is a
wreck it's always a wreck I come in I
work and I run and I go and I work and I
run and I go there we go that's food for
the week
Good Old Farm Fresh beef back in here we
got some tools we need to gather up H we
got a good battery in that this is a
Milwaukee M18 tire pump you'll see why
we need that in a
second all
right um I need my battery charger and
my portable power
station is somewhere somewhere shammers
so this is not sponsored by the way this
is a blue Eddie portable power station
we'll turn it we got 100% power right
here just unplug that guy that's going
out with
us that's
heavy now if I can just remember what I
did sun's really bright today if I can
remember what I did with
my battery charger I've got a hundred of
them but one works best it works better
than all the rest and it's just a little
cheapy here it is so I've got it over
here keeping the vent track battery
topped off we'll be mowing here pretty
soon there we
go unplug responsibly you'll see what
this is for in just a second all
right stay I know there's something else
I
needed but I can't remember what it
is you know how that is there's
something else I needed from in here and
I'll remember it about the time I get
over to the cows
H well let's just give you a quick shop
tour while we're in here this is a mess
this is my shop and it's a total
absolute disaster of a mess it won't be
that way for long and if you guys follow
the channel this might be interesting to
you this is where I do some of my videos
right here and we've got lighting
lighting lighting uh and this Mount
right here which holds a microphone and
a camera and then we've got a table
right here where we do a lot of work so
I rebuilt the chainsaw on that table and
I do a lot of stuff like that that's
what I need to do I got a chainsaw
scenario going on out here I'm going to
grab me a pair of
gloves
glovis we're going to go out to the
outdoor
kitchen this is the outdoor kitchen from
Carolina Barn builders awesome awesome
outdoor kitchen that's called a gather
Grill I'll post a link this is the
coolest Grill I've ever seen underneath
here we got a griddle and a grate and
you build a fire and this thing rotates
around so it's like a lazy Susan it's
patio furniture and it's a grill it's
expensive and it's worth it I did a
chainsaw video out here gosh months ago
and the chainsaw has been sitting here
ever since so let's put the chainsaw
back together real quick this is that
tool that I just brought in it's called
a ratchet scrinch it's a ratcheting
scrinch chainsaw tool really cool I was
out here working on chainsaws trying to
get everything ready for winter and like
I said it's been several months uh since
I was out here got a big gooey ooey
gooey mess off every chainsaw leaks Bar
Oil if you guys know a secret to make
them not leak let me
know it's just every chainsaw I have all
right this is a husa 460 Rancher the
first chainsaw I bought when I bought
the
farm ouch
good good
right let's make sure this puppy fires
up good pull our choke chain breake
contact oh come
on right on it's all I need to see now
put our Scabbard
on gra all of
our tools
you guys hear the cows mooing I can hear
them it's like your babies crying you
can hear them even in your sleep if you
raise animals like this we got to get
over there and take care of those uh
mows set this in here oh the rest of the
saws my chainsaw toolbox I will get to
that later going to clean the grease off
this table
too tubble towels
good for
everything this thing is
gross you don't use tub of towels you
just ain't living right the cows are
over there mooing and it makes me very
suspect that something is wrong like
jumper has jumped the fence again they
are mooing in a distressful way so we
got to get over there first got to get
all the this other stuff set up here we
go
[Music]
contact oh
yeah if you guys haven't seen this this
is Uncle Jesse Uncle Jesse is pretty
cool 19674 dump truck going to be
working on this guy very soon it runs
like a top but but it's got Flats flat
tires
everywhere one of the most handy tools
I've ever had on this farm and any piece
of property needs this uh this is a
Milwaukee tire pump I put this extra
accessory on here I'll post a link for
you guys in the video
description we'll get this guy up and
rolling you simply put it on there and
you can set it and forget it so I going
to turn it on I have a memory I've set
set it at 40
PSI that's it set it forget it walk away
when we get back my tire will be up
unless it's off the rim
[Music]
[Applause]
this is George George has got a battery
issue let me show you real
quick George's battery is dead as a door
nail that's how we call it here in the
southern regions of the United States
reason he's dead is because I left a
switch on thanks Josh good job make more
work for yourself already got the hood
up and I tried to jump this off of the
jump box the other day battery was too
dead to jump with a jump box so this is
the solution and it's really
cool this is a power station portable
battery bank I will post a link to it
it's the elite 200 and all I do is take
my battery charger set it right up
here so I plug it in and then I hook it
up and it'll charge this car battery all
the way back up to full charge with
fingers crossed I didn't destroy the
battery plug it
in
negative
positive power on
99% AC power on you're hooked up to our
battery we have 1.6 volts
sh put that thing on the slow
charge right bring our Hood down put
this food over here looks like Buddy's
having a little bit of a fun time
lounging what you doing
friend hey boy what you doing friend
come on let's
go come on go to your bed go to your bed
little
boy he's getting up the stairs pretty
good today good job good job I'm so
proud of you steak thaing out good deal
deal can you believe it's almost been an
hour already we just burn burn burn burn
through time here on the farm pretty
crazy we're going to hop on the blue
Becon head over to the cows and see why
they're so upset they are not happy
campers right
now
y content clear
prop you charge now
oh hard LIF Clyde hard LIF
[Music]
really windy over here looks like I've
got a mineral block already out in this
little pasture we'll scoop it up and
take it to the cows they are probably
balling because they want their
minerals there we go cows are all right
there now there there's buzzards in the
air above the cows this means there
could be a situation with a pregnant
cow
huh let's
see hey
bud hey big
bud uh-oh fourwheeler there we go hey
big bud you okay this morning huh you
okay good boy good boy all
right want to try this want try some
salt
block or you want to butt it you want to
butt it with your head or you want to
try
it we'll check that out
there this is the one that's balling
that's Cindy I don't know why she's
crying but she just going to have to
cry every day I roll out hey to the cows
today they get an afternoon bail
tomorrow they get a bail in the morning
and in the evening so we're stretching
out three ba over two days they get a
bail and a half every day that's how it
works and they're ready you guys
hungry
woo dude that cow is peeing and the
wind's blowing so hard the pee blew and
hit me in the face yuck
Lew Lew the farm runs on ATVs low
pressure talk about that in a second
this is a Greg Judy bail un roller
green pastors
farm.net you guys are GRE Judy fans tell
them you saw me talking about them on
Stony
Ridge all right we're going to back up
we'll hook up to this hay B
[Applause]
[Music]
that Cindy is really fussy over there
she normally not like
that oh it's a tight squeeze I'm too
fat here we
[Music]
go come on
sometimes the hay bale sticks to the
ground pretty good raises the
fourwheeler up off the ground a little
bit timbero
w
[Music]
[Laughter]
come on little
girls come on
kids come on
kiddos this is called net wrap these are
all net wrapped Bales they keep better
Outdoors than a twine wrapped bail
okay take the net wrap off cows can get
that in their stomach we got to be
careful not let them get any in their
stomach make them sick could kill them
shake it
up stuff it on the
fourwheeler unhook the great Duty bail
unroller take my
arm tip it up and we unroll you kids
ready for some snacks hey butthead how
are you this morning little good girl
[Music]
so that's how we unroll the hat to the
cow it's pretty simple takes about 10
minutes a day keeping 50 cows like this
and it's round about 50 typically takes
me somewhere between 30 minutes to an
hour a day depending on whether I film a
live stream uh now typically I'll hook
up to another bail but today we're
running and gunning we got work to do so
we're going to leave it alone and get it
in the morning first thing 7
[Applause]
a.m. oh that's good that's good
[Music]
workout 10
WS
2 we're ready for the next bail now you
want real farm chores you want real
world I pick up 10 rocks a day every day
no matter what every day at least 10
rocks on the farm so we're on a quick
Rock hunting Journey you see I've got
some rocks here we're going to toss
those in a gully in a
second all right all
right here we
go
one oh come on come on
here two
[Laughter]
three four five 6 7 8 9 10
overachiever Award right here I get my
gold star today let's take them and
Chuck them over in the
ditch good
cows good girls and
[Music]
boys quick head count we got 10 babies I
counted them there's Tammy wait a minute
another bonus Rock hot dog a
man that was a miss this is my video
game for the day right right some people
are gamous I'm just a rock picker
uper see all the hay that scattered out
on the land right here along with a lot
of manure on the land what this does is
allows us to farm regeneratively okay
there's Hay all down through here in
gullies and ditches and on the top of
the hill think about it okay we're
putting the hay up on the top of the
hill the cows eat on the top of the hill
they poop eat on the top of the hill and
it rains and the nutrients wash down the
hill a't that cool it's a lot of knowing
and doing and smars going
on these are remnants over in here you
see a bunch of rocks that's remnants
from an old Tobacco Barn that used to be
right
here
and simply going to pull right up here
shut her down Beford we're going to
Chuck these rocks over in that there
ditch we keep chucking rocks in the
ditch the rain comes in we get a little
erosion the dirt catches next thing you
know that ditches a flat spot we got
more
pasture
what hey Stony Ridge farmer don't you
have a rock picker how come you ain't
using a machine to pick those rocks up I
can't ride around here all day picking
up little bitty rocks with a machine
there's not a machine for everything on
the farm that's a common misconception
these Mega Farms make folks think that
everything's done from the seat of a
tractor and it's just not the case on a
small farm guys share your stories with
me it's not the
[Applause]
case all right cook my electric fence
back that's my fence charger this is
pretty cool check it out going to have
links to this soon this is a electric
fence monitor from sensor Tech got guys
awesome I can tell every day every
morning when my fence is working and
when it's not working and actually that
setup right there shuts itself down at
about midnight and starts back up at
sunrise every morning I had no idea
until last night this is a first day
trying that new sensor way cool let's
get back on the blue Becon we're going
to go back and we'll move the uh tire
pump to another tire
[Music]
those two blue balls that you see
floating right there two little blue
things that tells me my water system is
working properly we're also checking the
water system over on the other side
where the cows were too long as those
two blue balls are sticking up like they
should be then we know the water system
is working all the water on the farm is
pumped via solar so we have a solar well
it only works during the daytime so so
the cows have enough water storage in
those tanks to keep them watered
overnight they don't really drink a lot
at
[Music]
night just riding by the chicken coop
there I can tell they need a little bit
of water we're going to get feeding
water here in just a little bit might
check the honey bees real quick too we
lost one beehive this year but there was
still honey in there and I'm letting the
bees gobble that honey down check it
[Music]
out there's a lot of bees man I ain't
hanging out for
[Music]
that let's check on this truck see if
that battery got any more voltage we may
have to give it a boost because I really
killed that battery and it's not a new
battery and it's a Walmart never start
battery too let's see what we
got well says 12 volts already 80%
charge no no way no way we're going to
boost it hit it with a
booster no way it's 80% charge
that quick find that hard to
believe let's just
see no
way here we go yeah right my sneaking
suspicion is this battery is so fried
this truck has been sitting here and I
haven't used it very much I've just been
working on it and fixing it it's
actually going to be sold here soon
great truck 5.0 L but uh it's not a AGM
battery there we go uh 50 L I just don't
drive it I don't use it I've got too
many vehicles as it is and uh I think
it'll make some young man or some young
woman a good truck or somebody a great
farm truck too yeah let's check on the
tires on Uncle Jesse
[Music]
lock would you look at that would you
look at that we're all pumped up and it
shut itself off how much battery do we
have left three bars awesome put our
valve stem cap back on this truck has
really crappy
tires this is going to be in future
videos um I just haven't had time to
work on it I need to make time to work
work on it really all right this one is
a pain and you know what to find the oh
there it is okay we got to go up around
and backwards let's see how this works
there you go there you go little
friend memory 40 PS
on Just for
Giggles let's see if Uncle Jesse will
fire up man I think Uncle Jesse might
just fire up
okay got a pull choke
here
and Uncle Jesse's keys aren't in here so
we can't have
fun a the fun
police
ran I know where his keys are let's go
get the keys and see if Uncle Jesse will
start
oh keys
please
yeah this thing sucks
shifting another chore I needed to do we
got a lot of high wind last night this
is
all old Lumber that I reclaimed these
are all Oak boards and such they came
out of a barn that was here on the farm
and I've got Oak uh hand hun logs up
under here all up under there right so
all that stuff is going to be future uh
construction materials for the barn
dominium that we're going to be building
out here I hope you're subscribed to the
channel let's get this covered up so it
doesn't rot and go to waste stinky
just like that trash bag I can't throw
stuff away I just can't do it I just see
potential in everything I don't know why
that'll catch up with me one day or when
I have grandkids that have to clean this
place
out oh the dual tires are pain in the
butt to get air in a come on there we go
uh so I got to climb down here and get
the other
Tire if I
can I know it's around here somewhere
shammers
shammers there it is right in there
go memory
40 hit it look at them
tires it's a bad set of tires oh all
right what do y'all think
Uncle Jesse going to start or is Uncle
Jesse's battery super dead
too oldie but
goody call this truck Uncle Jesse
because it looks like Uncle Jesse's
truck from Dukes of Hazard I don't know
kind of
fun what's life without a little fun
she's a four on the floor buddy come on
back here we go that ain't the right key
here we
go yeah yeah
yeah might be out of
gas fuel pump fuel
pump man come on there buddy gosh we
should not give up on
this let's go get a gas can
just in
case glug glug
glug I spy Uncle Jesse has an issue a
drip drip drip from the tube there got
to replace that I said we put a splash
in the
carbonators come on now oh let's see
that this truck has a dull
heavy this is the dirtiest engine bay of
any vehicle you've ever seen
guaranteed look at
that oh man let's try it without putting
gas cuz it's so nasty I got to super
clean this entire thing look at that
that is so gross come on now Jesse oh
let me
down number two attempt number
two
choke pum that
gas battery's a little
weak this dude's got very little gas in
it it ain't got no gas in
it oh come come on now Jesse all right
this ought to make that starter sing
baby put that jump box on there here we
go yeah you're ripping it now rip it and
rip it
baby to the
floor oh man come on
Jesse this Gulu box has a boost
feature hit that boost button that makes
it that thing sling it started to sling
that motor
around come on Jesse come on little I
know what I need to
do wonder if I have enough fuel in that
gas
can let's open up this here breather
thingy make sure ain't no squirrels in
it air
filters seen better days get a little L
of water in that carburetor a little bit
of that spark of juice in
there just a little there you go bud
just a
little come on go okay here we go
Senor yeah Daddy it's a fuel issue for
sure fired right up soon as I got
fuel I wonder if the choke is
you ripping
it come on give her some
gas it's got to get fuel all the way
from the empty gas tank all the way into
here we know it runs I can't give up
what do you guys think should we give up
should we go get another can of gas
we're eating up some battery on this
Gulu oh
yep got a leak here that thing spraying
gas all over me you ain't living right
unless you get a little 9 and3 Octane on
you get her
done all right I'm not sure how much gas
went in the gas tank and how much gas
went in the
floorboard got to get that filler neck
handled got to pour it all there we go
get a little bit in
there
gosh poured it all in the
truck nobody ever accused me of being
that
bright here we go come on
baby I didn't have the choke on
before come on baby just keep running
just keep on that's six gallons in there
it should pick it up fuel pump pick it
up
bro
bro do I have to go down and get
another like thing of gas I don't want
to do that it's flooded I can smell it
all right well we know Uncle Jesse runs
and we've overheated the uh jump box
stay tuned for a future video this truck
has a dump bed and I need to just clean
it up get it squared
away and uh use it on the farm it's a
dump truck man great dump truck I bought
it from my neighbor actually did a
little horse trading for
it oh
well see what she
says
1% we'll put her own engine
starter she said
ready oh no no no she not
ready all right we're going to let that
charge while we
go we got to grab a tractor across the
farm here bring it up here and get it
filled with fuel that way it's good to
go we're going to be running the Sawmill
[Music]
tomorrow this door is about to make me
mad man it what happened was the wind
caught it it sprung it it broke this
hook right here that holds it in place I
just need to go buy a new one I think
but what happened it sprung the hinges
all the way back and now it's not
shutting like it should oh now it shuts
like it
should oh
man good it's getting a grab when it's
real cold outside these steel buildings
tend to swell and shrink and sometimes
I'll find that door just blown open
and it just basically tries to rip it
off I was saying we're going to go over
the other side of the farm and uh grab a
tractor and bring it over here but I
think we're going to take the fuel to
the Tractor not the tractor to the
fuel this is the Unicorn Dodge
truck this is my fuel set up right here
and uh it's a little bit janky janky
shanky that's okay
now the reason I call this the Unicorn
Dodge it could be more of a unicorn if
it was a sixspeed and a one ton douly
but it's not
contact but it is a cumings baby she
sounds good so why am I filling up this
tractor it seems unnecessary right well
I'm going up to Virginia that's what the
Virginia folks call it Virginia Virginia
and and we are going to fill up the fuel
tank in the back of the truck here
because fuel is about 20 cents cheaper
per gallon in Virginia than it is in
North
Carolina uh we're going to use off-road
diesel but it's still cheaper up there
it may be under three bucks a gallon
yeah I'll fill this diesel tank up
probably three times a year and that's
all the fuel that I'll need for the year
here on the Stony Ridge cows do most of
the work but I got to come in and clip
behind the cows
Sawmills way over here this is my land
that's my neighbors's land we're pretty
cool I take care of their property for
them most of the time um they just
reimburse me for fuel I've talked to
them about leasing uh their pasture for
the cows and at some point we may do
that or May moh but for right now I'm
just mowing it keeping it up keep it
pretty the cast loader is right over
here I'll show you guys what a cast
loader is this is why I didn't drive my
nice truck down through here it's muddy
right here and that truck just got a
wash job try to keep my trucks clean at
least the ones that I use
anyway if y'all remember we'll get you a
little footage right here of uh building
this bridge built this bridge last year
while we're walking this is the log yard
there's some trees down here I've got to
get cut up you'll see that in a future
video These are logs that are going to
go on the Saw Mill all this is going to
be milled into 2x4s so we can finish out
the Tool Crib in the mega shop that you
guys were just in just a minute ago this
is the cast loader and this is the wood
meiser lt40 and I've already been over
here making a little bit of lumber you
can tell but this is a job for tomorrow
cast loaders from TNA Distributing we
got a triel grapple on the cast loader
that we're moving our logs and all of
our brush with we're going to have a big
old bonfire pretty soon pretty awesome
this is a mini articulating loader
meaning it bends in the middle so it's
just a mini loader cast mini loader um
again from topnotch equipment out of
Minnesota contact
yeah and it's way low on fuel I ran out
of gas in this thing one time not fun
not cool and don't don't don't leave the
door open I busted the glass out of it
one time too so check it out when you
steer see how the tire gets
closer okay we got a loader and then we
got a button on here that extends the
loader so the boom extends
our uh forward and reverse is right
there and that's just how easy a cast
loader works very fun my fuel light is
on on this thing which means not good
got to get over there and get this thing
filled up the reason I didn't uh drive
it across the farm was cuz I was afraid
I was going to run out of fuel with it
this thing will turn on a dime check it
out there's a sawmill I mean look at
that that's so
[Music]
cool hit
it
yeeh this thing's a little sensitive on
fueling up up it does not like full
trigger pressure when I fill it
up it'll kick back a little bit so I got
to be
careful you know what I just noticed a
little something here the tire is low on
this so I just so happened to bring
over the tire pump we're going to go
ahead and fill this tire up see a little
bit low right there well a lot of bit
low that's pretty soft
again if you don't have one of these
pumps on your farm you just need one
even around the house we're going to go
to 24
PSI ask me how I
know I've I've had to fill that tire of
at least 20 times just got a slow
leak okay it's cool
[Music]
be careful don't mess up my pretty
truck let's give the news baby
[Music]
oh
let me show you something this looks
like a 2000 Dodge commercial man this
truck is so
nice ain't she
pretty gosh
told them when they bury me dig a hole
big enough for this truck and put me in
it right
here clear
prop we're off to Rural King and here's
what we're picking up at the Rural King
oil is cheaper there I'm picking up
hydraulic fluid for the Gale
rt210 and it says hydraulic fluid
capacity
21.5 Gall and I got all the specs right
right here so I get the right
stuff things are cheaper at Rural King
it's worth a
drive we just passed Martinsville
Speedway right back there got some
pretty cool arcade tractors sitting out
here I wonder if anybody will recognize
their friend Stony Ridge Farmer in the
store here today fingers crossed this
used to be Kmart my brother used to work
here at Kmart back in the day and uh had
a lot of fun in this parking lot doing
donuts in the snow after
hours back in my high school days got my
wallet this one's going to be
expensive I know it
is uh I have to question the sanity of
Starbucks you know Starbucks has a brand
new Starbucks right here in the Rural
King parking lot they ain't Starbucks
people come on now come on here
this is going to get pricey save five
bucks though I like
it all right I got to read my specs hvv
LPD 46 hydraulic 0530 I guess it's 5W30
[Music]
boys and girls that one stung that's a
$500 bill right there ouch ouch ouch
let's see how much fuel we pump it's
going to be an expensive day again I did
buy two batteries I happen to know
there's a new F350 coming to the farm
stay tuned for a future video we're
rescuing a 7.3 L Power Stroke F350 you
guys are going to love it
por rinds that's my
vice can't go in ryal king without
getting a snack all right let's pump
some
diesel woo that was expensive off-road
diesel
$35 cents baby yeah
I put diesel power service in it every
single time no matter what ever since
I've been doing that I have had no fuel
problems on the farm before I did that I
had fuel problems all the time I'll post
a link I use this with every tank no
matter what
guys one half of these will do about 50
gallons this says it treats up to 250
gallons it's 100-gallon tank see how
expensive this gets
$222 that's a $700 day let's go get on
the tractor and get busy mowing man I
got a 10-minute drive
home h
go eat be free be
free I love him chickens
mhm Let's Get Busy
mowing water uh-oh that water bottle too
big
oh man oh there's my there it is
contact
[Music]
wo my butt hurts
oh man we got her all mowed up
everything looks awesome uh let me just
show you guys I got the lights on on the
tractor camera makes it a little
brighter than it actually is we have a
beautiful sunset here on the farm and we
got the pasture mode out here in front
of the house I promised you so stick
around after the credits after the
bloopers and uh we're going to try to
start that truck up but everything looks
great that's a day in uh in the life of
every day here on the Stony Ridge Farm
it just goes goes goes goes goes and
there's always more work to do when
you've got a piece of property like this
and you got a farm there's just always
piles and piles of work to do so a huge
shout out to my viewer who wanted to
have me take you guys around and just
show you what I do in any given day and
that's what it is we spent probably
close to 800 bucks today filling up Fuel
and trucks and tractors and everything
like that um got new batteries for the
new Power Stroke truck you guys are
going to see very soon tractors are all
full I've got one more pasture to mow
first thing in the morning and I got to
run over and check the cows before it
gets too dark so let's go up there and
uh we'll try to start that truck guys
thanks a lot for joining me here on the
Stony Ridge Farm please hit that like
button subscribe to channel and be sure
you tune in for the next video when
we're working on Uncle Jesse the dump
truck and
that new power stroke that you guys
don't even know about awesome see you
next
time don't R away everybody let's not
start this day like that don't be too
quick to walk away this is heavy a four
on the floor buddy come on back here we
go that ain't the right
key dude that cow is peeing and the
wind's blowing so hard the pee blew and
hit me in the face yuck Le
Pew Le Pew subscribe to channel and be
sure you tuned and be sure
you just for shiggles oh I got
dizzy oh Uncle Jessy cute cute cute
hydrate it's very
important got a leak here good than
spraying gas all over me you ain't
living right unless you get a little 9
and3 Octane on you I sure am hungry
recking what you got good eat in there
you got french fried potatoes hey gety
gety we got big old fat kitty run I'd
like to talk to you about your your car
warranty it's expiring your car
insurance what you doing
boy come on kitty I'd like to talk to
you about your your car
warranty shut her D Beford she's sucking
mud thank y'all for sticking around to
the end let's see what we got in the
battery
Department I'm going to say
1% it's so bad why does it keep going
over to gel battery it's not a gel
battery all right we're going to put on
a 100 amp booster here to start it and
I'm going to get my Gulu I'll put a link
to that Gulu uh jump starter uh for you
guys that thing is an indispensable unit
too between the Gulu jump box and the
M18 uh tire pump there I'm going to tell
you what I use every both of those all
the time between those
two that's probably the the two most
used uh items on the farm when it comes
to maintenance and vehicle
stuff let's see what happens here if we
double
up I don't even know what'll happen 28%
ready
boost all right we got a boost boost
please start please start please start
please start please start
contact
W that's what I'm talking
about
awesome all right we're going to move
this truck out of it's stuck in the yard
it's like halfway in the yard that's why
I needed to move it it's sticking out in
the yard thanks guys see you in the next
video Woo
[Music]