foreign
water scarity water accounting is a
critical approach to set the information
basis to achieve safe and sustainable
water use effective water accounting
allows Water Resource managers and
Farmers to determine the impacts of
their strategies and practices and track
the effects of changes
to summarize the ability to effectively
account for water use is essential in
helping water authorities and Farmers
Drive Improvement and become aligned
with external stakeholders expectations
as well as their own efforts to advance
sustainable Water Management especially
underwater scarity scenarios
we talk about water accounting
and we ask ourselves why that is
important and we ask ourselves that
question at many different skates
at the basing scale at the Irrigation
District scale at the farm scale and we
are not always aware of the importance
of knowing the water that we use we
consume and we return to the system to
the hydrological system we are not aware
of the of the importance of each level
so each
responsible of water management at a
giving scale
has the need of knowing the water that
is used for different reasons
one because it it cost money
pumping transporting water is costly
second because we deal with a Water
Resource that is limited
and third because by not doing a good
use of water we can damage the
environment where the irrigation
activity takes place
so a
now we have to understand
in the water accounting process the
principle of the water balance
in the water balance we distinguish
different components we have our
resource the water that we are applying
to the field and now we are going to
focus on the field scale
once it is on the field that water
store for for a given time in the soil
to be consumed by the plant but not all
the water that is applied is consumed by
the plant part of that water is lost
through the evapotranspiration process
or it can return back to the
hydrological system by Deep percolation
or Surface drainage
so
how can we
evaluate these different components some
of them are easy or relatively easy to
measure
others can be estimated with good
accuracy others are really difficult to
measure or estimate so we make use of
the water balance to compute our
accounting and we obtain those
components as the residual of the water
balance that's why the water balance
equation is is so important everybody
has heard about different methods of
estimating evapotranspiration
we are aware about the damage that we
can cause with
drainage water and deep percolation of
water if it is loaded with agrochemicals
that's very difficult to to evaluate and
what we do can do is to measure the
applied water
and for that we have to consider how the
water gets to the to the fill and the
irrigation method that we are using in
general it's easier to measure the
applied water if it comes through a
pressurized pipe then we have very
standard methods
based on on a propeller a current meter
or ultrasonic
principles or the um
magnetic flow meters that can be
installed at the a pipe in a proper
position and we can obtain the flow rate
of the cumulative applied water that's
not difficult anymore
um it is being implemented in most
modernized irrigation districts in many
Mediterranean countries maybe the
difficulty comes when we apply the water
using surface method again that is more
complicated but the principles came from
the old days when the Hydraulics were
developed and now we can combine the
classic Hydraulics with water level
sensors that can be used in a continuous
Way recording those water levels and
give us for those flumes or Weirs that
are installed in the open channels
measurements of flow rate but also the
water that has gone through that device
in a given in given time so there is no
excuse for not measuring the plate water
even when we have open channels although
we have to recognize that that is more
difficult
as we've seen there are several options
at different scales to account for water
given its relevance more effort should
be made by the different stakeholders to
establish a proper water accounting
system adapted to the local conditions
that allow making informed decisions
under water scarity situations
[Music]