South Dakota's educational effort to
raise awareness about the importance of
soil Health continues the USDA natural
resources conservation service entered
into a Cooperative agreement with the
South Dakota noil Association and igro
South Dakota State University extension
for delivering these seminars with the
latest soil health and productivity
technology to South Dakota farmers and
Ranchers
okay well our next presenter Dr Cheryl
ree was raised on a farm near Hancock
Minnesota she received her undergrad and
master's degrees at the University of
Minnesota and her PhD in Agronomy from
SSU Cheryl currently teaches soil
science and Agronomy production courses
and advises undergraduate and graduate
Agronomy students at southa State
University and her topic today is going
to be salien in sodic soils
understanding the difference and manag
solutions everybody hear
me hey thank you for um inviting me to
speak in Mitchell here today my topic is
going to be a little bit different from
a lot of the other topics on the agenda
you're going to hear a lot about cover
crop from Dr Peter seon and D Wayne
other people are going to speak but
today I'm going to talk about something
a little bit different I'm going to talk
about s and soda soil management right
so how many people have problem with
solve here okay okay so I see a lot of
people have Sol okay so
and we've done a lot of work on this
we've done work
here we've done some
work by and I'm going to CL
here so here's my outline I'm going to
talk a little bit about the caus of the
problem I'm going to also talk about
testing for Sol what should you look for
in a soil test I'm going to talk about
sampling for a little bit about how deep
should you go what do you need to look
for there and then I'm going talk about
some management that we have and of
course it's going to involve some cover
CS it's also going to involve PL C Sy as
well too so I have quite a few slides
here um I know we're running ahead of
time I won't take more time if you guys
Ruth how do you guys want to do question
do you just a little
B is that better is that better no you
can hear me now yeah now can hear me
okay so Ruth how do you want to handle
questions at the end or did you want
people have questions what during when
I'm speaking whatever is more
comfortable for you you want okay I
teach uh the college so I'm used to
getting questions so if you have
questions if you really want to if you
see something on the slide just let me
uh know I'll try to watch the audience
here um so let's get going here okay so
salt problems we have a lot of salt
problems and they seem to be getting
worse every year
uh especially you know these spots they
in a field they start out small and then
each year they grow a little bit bigger
right and so what's going on there so
we've had a lot of changes in the
climate since the mid 80s I mean um from
North Dakota you guys haven't seen the
rain your father probably didn't see the
rain that you guys have seen in the last
say 15 years you're kind of up in that
Northeastern you know South Dakota area
by wave where we've had all this rain a
lot more rain Okay so we've had a lot
more rain these last few years
um we also in the 70s and stuff ' 80s we
did corn and soybeans we did a lot of
tillage all right we did a lot of
tillage there uh tillage is going to
destroy our soil structure right so
we're doing with the tillage we're doing
something bad for the soil we're
destroying the what you've seen with
your water and everything we're
destroying that soil structure that
allows water to go down into that soil
profile all right the other problem is
that we have Sals that are indigenous to
this area okay when it wasn't wet when
we weren't tilling okay those salts were
down in the soil profile but they
weren't coming up uh the salts have
always been deeper in the soil profile
okay so here let's just take a look at
South Dakota right here a very good
pointer okay so here's South Dakota
right here all right here's where you
guys are up by Lisbon up there in North
Dakota we're all underlaying there by
what we call the pure Shale all right
and there's different formations
underneath here the very top one is
called the Bearpaw shale it's the upper
deposit of the pure Shale so we have
this Shale here that's below the
majority of our state okay
here that to
go supposed to come out there there we
go okay so here we look in the Upper
Midwest right up in here all right so
this is a precipitation map right here
so here's South Dakota right here here's
North Dakota we can see that and then
you look at your decades here if we look
up here in the ' 80s and the '90s
we've had just a massive increase in
precipitation okay so what have we done
we changed our our cropping system from
typically it would have been you know
something like wheat uh you know grazing
phow we've done a lot more tillage and
we've added you know corn and soybeans
in there okay corn being a short or
soybeans being a short season
cop sorry here right here okay so here's
the pure shell this is in spank Colony
right here so this is a geologic map
right here and this is spin County up by
Redfield South Dakota what they did here
is they came through here and they did
some sampling this is done with the uh
South Dakota Geological Service and they
came through here and they sampled
across the county site one 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
9 10 and so what they did is they did
some deep sampling here and what they
did is at each of these sites one 2 3 4
5 5 6 7 8 9 10 there were what what type
of formations do we have underneath
there all right so that red line right
down here the KP is the pure
Shale and if you look along the left
hand side here it says elevation and
feet above mean sea level and here's the
ground surface right up
here so you can see right up here on a
lot of this just across this one
transect here in spank County you have a
lot of that pure shell that's close to
the surface well those salts are all in
that pure Shale that's where they are
those salts are indigenous in that pure
shell okay and so what we do here is um
seasonal use of the Tall Grass Prairie
water was greater that and corn and
especially soybeans and wheat rotation
okay we also had very very deep roots
with these prairie grasses that remove
the water from deeper in the soil
profile and I'll show you that here at
the end how those uh perennial grasses
really can pump that that water out so
here's what's happened basically we've
had this abundance of precipitation the
'90s through the
2000 we have those salts that are
indigenous down there okay they're not
very far down what we do is in in soil
and when I teach my soil science classes
we call this capillary rise all right so
lots of soil science terms here for you
guys today because I teach soil science
all right so capillary rise right here
what happens is is that groundwater
comes up it dissolves those salts from
that Old pure shell the calcium the
Magnesium the gypsum the sodium salts
that are there it dissolves those salts
from that pure shell and then what
happens is based upon what your soil
texture Is So based upon if you have a
silk a silty LOM soil if you have a
silty LOM soil those salts become
dissolved in that water down there from
that groundwater and now they start
creeping up due to capillary rise it's
kind of like if you look at like a
really thin tube or if you look like
look at a um a thermometer and it has
water in there you'll see that it has a
meniscus in there so it's climbing up in
the soil because it would rather be more
attracted to the soil uh above the
surface that's in the groundwater so
capillary rise occurs it comes up
against ravity okay depends upon your
text depends up on your texture and your
soil Pro and your and your paracity so a
soil that has a lot of play in it okay
you're not going to get water creeping
up as much a sandy soil you're not going
to get water creeping up okay it's in
these intermediate textured soils like
these silt LOM and these types of soils
where we see that water start to creep
up the waterers the salts are dissolved
in there the water comes to the Surface
starts to warm up in the spring the
water evaporates where are the
salts where they're on your Fields right
they're right on your fields and that's
how they get there okay so that's a
little bit of a background about how
these areas develop okay so now that we
know how they develop what can we do to
manage them how do we figure out what do
we have okay so now what we have to talk
about is the type of salts that we have
all right we have calcium magnesium
salts and we have sodium salts all right
so with the Sodium salts sodium means
just like your table salt sodium all
right what that means we call that a
sodic soil and we call that a sodic soil
we have the problem that plants will not
grow and the soil is dispersed so
dispersed means that you don't have that
nice soil structure out there you walk
out there and it looks like pavement
okay there's no the the the the the the
the agnet stability is not there all
right so that's what it looks like this
is a field up by Pon so you get a
rainfall or something like that and you
get this you get this it'll it'll start
drying out this has a high clay t some
of this does on the surface and
nothing's going to move through here it
looks just like caves right plants will
not grow in the soil as dispersed okay
with uh staline soil you have calcium
and magnesium now you have plants that
well you're enj plant problems but
usually in a saline uh situation with
calcium and magnesium salt usually your
water will move through that area Okay
so if you have an area out in the field
where you don't have any water moving
through it and nothing's growing there
if it looks like concrete then you might
want to look at testing for sodium all
right saline uh problems typically we do
have some structure there the problem is
here is that no matter if it's a saline
or sodic soil problem we have a high
water table this is up by pant South
Dakota here in we did some Field Days up
by pure Pont we done some soil pits here
this is a has a buried soil horizon but
down right in here is about 6t feet down
and we have water down here you can see
how white that surface is there on that
on those salts right there so that's
where the that's where the problem comes
from so what type of salts do we usually
have here in South Dakota we have
typically a lot of our salts are sodium
uh uh sodium sulfate and depending on
where you are you may have some gyps up
we also have lime too as well okay but
typically we're not when we look at the
solubility here right there we're not as
worried lime is usually not not a a salt
problem because of the low solubility so
what does solubility mean solubility
means how much of that salt will
dissolve in water okay so what is the
solubility of that salt the salts that
are really soluble are the ones that
move up fast okay what happens is a lot
of these sodium salts down here sodium
chloride they have a high solubility so
the higher the number here the more
soluble the salt so the sodium will move
up fast in the soil profile it gets up
to the top it causes the soil to
disperse it seals up now you have a big
problem how you going to get that Sal
out of there right um like I said
typically we have these salts right here
calcium magnesium salt and then of
course we have our sodium salt salts but
different problems and different
management based upon if we have a
calcium or magnesium salt based if we
have a sodic salt there so when you're
testing and looking at your salts and
your soils you got to find what type of
salt problem do you have
first okay and this is what I'm talking
about with this dispersion okay so
what's going on here all right so when I
talk that a sodic soil is dispersed it
means that the soil the clay particles
are pushed apart at pretty much equally
spaced so that soil is so evenly
dispersed there's really no paracity to
that soil there's no channels for that
water water to move down into that soil
profile okay so you can't get anything
to move through it the terms that we use
are floculation versus dispersion all
right floculation means that the soil is
held together in Aggregates that there's
pores between those individual soil pads
for water to move down through it okay
when we have sodium that aggregate
stability is
destroyed I okay said just some pictures
here so saline straps calcium and
magnesium you guys all have seen areas
like this in your field all right high
pH droughty conditions it's salty the so
they salty water will not move into the
those plant roads we can't get anything
to germinate there poor germination poor
growth but if you look at this soil here
it's not great but there's a little bit
of there there's a little bit of you can
see a little bit of structure on the
surface it doesn't look like pavement
okay right here these are where we have
these sodium problems right here pH
typically higher than 8.2 a lot of
dispersion no water movement anywhere
into that soil profile okay we have
erosion and we have limitation because
this soil is so dense and so hard this
is a field with a farmer that we work by
up by pure Pont South Dakota um he's had
a lot of issues with this field right
here he does do no tail uh up here in
this area here we have a a kind of a
little bowl area here and he hasn't been
able to get anything to grow here for
quite a few years last may he had about
3in rainfall that came down washed all
this out remember we have these sodic
soils where we don't have any water
moving in this the soil profile so
what's it going to do it's going to run
off as it goes down the slope it's going
to increase in velocity you're going to
pick up that speed okay so what happens
here is you have a little bll shaped
area up here trying to divert the water
over to the ditch well now we have some
problems here where uh it it uh some
junk got in the ditch there so now it
flows out over here flows into this area
right here concentrated flow this is
looking North right there from the area
where we had the bull shaped area this
is looking Sol this big here Gully right
here was not here the previous year okay
so lots of problems with managing these
areas the big problem we get with these
sodic soils is we have a lot of erosion
problems okay so like I said just the
difference between saline and sodic soil
just to Define what these are so you
guys have this definition in your hand
okay salvs tend to help a soil
flocculate okay a saline soil typically
does not generally become a hard set we
typically will get some water movement
with that you can see those salts uh go
a little bit farther down into that soil
profile if we get some rainfall so that
white area will appear and disappear
based upon the moisture okay based upon
where the moisture how much moisture you
had rinf okay um water moves similarly
compared to normal soils plants may be
more negatively impacted in Saline
soils sodium soils disperse or they
swell they become hard step they come
become like Pavements water cannot move
there have a lot of huge erosion problem
it can impact fertility because of this
restrictive layer this high density and
this low fertility so that's just a
summary of what these soils are so we're
looking at when we look at salts and
soils we need to deci decide is it a
calcium magnesium salt problem or is it
a sodium problem what is the problem
okay so in South Dakota you guys all
know where your uh some the saline
issues are but when we look at the
sodicity here we see that up here by
aine and County here 20 to 30% of
these soils have sodic Horizon deeper
down in the soil profile sodium in there
here's Aurora County down here also a
problem down here um more up here you
know there's more coming up here we have
not as much here but really you know the
red and the yellow you know 10 to 30% of
those soils in any given area have
sodium deeper in the soil
profile okay so is there any questions
on what the problems are and how they
differ before I go on doing
questions okay all right okay so soil
testing for
salts uh some terms I'm just going to go
through this I didn't know what my
general audience would be so I wanted to
Define these terms before I started
talking about them uh electrical
conductivity is the measure of the total
salts in the soil we add salt to water
it increases the conductivity same thing
with soil we can measure that in the
soil testing lab cation exchange
capacity how many you guys remember that
Okay C exchange capacity all right so
that is going to be the soil's ability
to hold on to positively charge
cat Okay um s so the sodium absorption
ratio it's a number that we calculate
based upon the relative concentration of
sodium to calcium and magnesium okay we
typically do this from something called
a saturated past and then the other one
that we more the most more soil testing
Labs use that you're probably going to
see the exchangeable sodium percent okay
we measure the sodium on the exchange
sites from the uh P exchange typically
here um I'm going to talk a lot about
this right here today in South Dakota we
in South Dakota the reason we did this
project is because we we know these
salty areas are getting bigger also when
I would teach my soil science classes
and I would get soil in from up by pure
Pon these saly soils and I'd had my
students go in there and and uh we test
them and we come up with these SS that
are are fairly low okay five or six s
okay five or six s they are dispersed
soil we try to run water through them
they were dispersed nothing would work
we've always used in South Dakota these
guidelines right here all right so we
use an S of 13 we say if it's greater
than 13 it's a sodic soil well I never
saw that when I bring my salty soils in
and have my students try to run water
through them the S was five or six that
soil was dispersed I could get anybody
to run water through it it's like what's
wrong are these numbers wrong all right
and then the ESP the same thing these
numbers are very very similar so we uh
we know this becoming a a lot bigger
problem in South Dakota all right with
the sailing areas I knew from working
with the soil that I get from salty
areas in South Dakota from my so from my
class it's like what's going on here so
we wrote Grant nrcs and we had some
money to study these areas and so what
we did is first thing we did like okay
we need to test do these numbers work
these numbers of determining the cut off
values for Saline sodic soils were
determined by the National cinity Lab
out in California so we needed to do it
for South Dakota so these numbers here
are old numbers here from South Dakota
or from from California the numbers that
we look at now if our s is greater than
four we consider it sodic if our ESP is
greater than five we consider it sodic
these numbers are too high for South
Dakota okay so just a little bit of a
review what's going on here okay so CAD
exchange capacity so soil science here
you know 200 so what's happening with
can exchange capacity just a little bit
of a review what happens why why do we
have sodium problem okay um past
recommendations said that when 15% of
the cash exchange sites were occupied by
sodium be classified it as a sodic soil
so cation are are clay soils here are
negatively charged due to how the
formation process the geological
formation process so we have negative
charges that reside on these clay uh
sheets here and of course we have
positive cats that can be occupied on
these sheets right so what happens is is
when we get greater than now in our case
we're looking at 5% South Dakota not 15%
we're looking at 5% we're looking when
we get greater than 5% of these exchange
sites occupied by sodium these soils and
end up just like a refrigerator magnet
right so they're negatively charged and
we need these positively charged cations
on here to neutralize that charge and if
we get calcium and magnesium but
especially calcium we'll actually
flocculate that we'll form a bridge
negative charge on one clay iell
negative charge on another throw a
calcium in there positive to negative
just like a refrigerator magnet what
happens it's together we have Aggregates
um stability form formation okay we hold
that soil together okay when we put
sodium in there okay sodium has a
positive charge on it but the problem
with sodium is that that positive charge
is insulated it's completely insulated
it's a small atom you put a lot of
sodium in there you have that negative
charge on those on those clay uh clay my
cells those clay Aggregates what happens
nothing in there neutralize it dispersed
okay so that's why we have the problems
that we have that's why we have the
dispersion just like refrigerator magnet
when we have too much sodium in there we
have
repulsion okay so what we how do we
figure this out right so how do we
figure this out what we did is we took
large Columns of soil and we brought
them in from the field from different
places that was so and then what we did
is we did we did some amendments as well
we we worked some uh soil amendments I'm
going to talk about that in just a
minute but what we did here is we looked
at okay based upon what the S is so down
here it says initial soil S A initial
sodium concentration so here is five
here is 10 here's 15 and here's 20 then
what we did is we started running water
through this okay so permeability milles
per or milliliters per hour is what we
looked at here all right so what we saw
here in southa
that when we saw an s on these big soil
columns that we brought in we brought in
there about this big round about this
deep our grad a student um did this work
on part of his PhD and what he did here
is he ran water through this these
initial one so we saw slow infiltration
um at an S of greater than four we're
doing this work with Tom dutter you know
tomter up in North Dakota the soil scien
have you ever heard of Tom at all before
or not okay he's doing a lot of the salt
work up in South Dakota up in North
Dakota we did this work with Tom dter
he's looking at the number he's using
for North Dakota is five so remember we
said this used to be 13 it's way lower
for our soils than than than 13 so right
here uh considering 1 Mill per hour uh
as a threshold the data suggests that s
greater than four can be considered
sodic because once we hit this much
sodium in the soil we can just see how
much oops
sorry you can just see how much there
that our water infiltrations blows
down okay so that's the problem that's
the problem and here here's how we're
trying to give some terminology and
describe the the extent of our problem
with some of these soil testing values
so in South Dakota here uh all numbers
are soil e to measure the tot salt we
used four with a saturated paste greater
than four we call it a saline soil
that's what saturated a past we talk
about that in just a minute too okay s
of greater than 13 with sodic ESP
greater than 15 with soda these are old
numbers we are going to we are rewriting
all of this we're going to work with the
nrcs to put out some bulletins on this
new nrcs research project for North and
South Dakota we're still going to go
with four as saturated pce of the saline
soil but here we're going to use in in
North Dakota they're using five in South
Dakota we're using four es of five okay
so a lot of different numbers here than
what we originally thought and that's
why when I go get the soil the the soil
samples uh from from these salaries from
out in the field and I bring them in to
my for my students to work on you're
doing water infiltration I'd have an S
or five or six and it's like that's why
the water would go through it it's
because there's too much sodium in those
soils already at an S of four or five
okay so now when you're testing for
salts okay there are some questions you
need to ask the soil testing lab because
what we're going to do is we first of
all we have to determine the total salt
content and then we got to figure out
how much sodium is in that total salt
content all right so just a
percentage so when they extract for salt
soil testing Labs will either use most
of you use a one to one extract so what
does that mean that means that you take
100 gram of soil and you mix it with 100
gram of water and you mix it together
that's a one to one extract okay then
you let that sit for a little while and
you'll put a a EC probe in there and
you'll measure the electrical
conductivity um with a saturated paste
that is totally different with the
saturated paste what we do is we take
the soil and uh my kids love to do this
all right you guys probably all did this
when you're little your grandkids do it
you take a cup of soil
and you mix it with enough water just
until it looks like melted chocolate
okay and that's called the saturated
paste you let that sit that settles out
and then you measure what the EC is in
the top of that saturated past so we
have two very different ways of um
determining EC here we have a much more
dilute method than what we have over
here if you're not going to if you take
one to one take 100 gram of soil 100
Millers of water and mix that together
you're going to get a fairly dilute
solution here remember we're going for
melted chocolate with the saturated
paste okay why is this important because
the EC is used to C estimate the total
salt so if we're going to calculate
their percent sodium we need to know the
total percentage of salts that are there
you can use our EC to do this okay but
we have to make sure that we understand
the method that we're measuring the
total salt okay because if we look at
concentration of sodium in the in in the
on the top of the fraction and the
concentration of total cations in the
bottom if we have a different number
down here that's going to make our
percentage
different right so um because EC is used
to count the total salt is required for
s or the ESP okay so here this is how
this kind of goes if I'm reading a uh EC
of four and that is aoic soil on a
saturated past that is going to be
equivalent to a EC of two in a 1:1
delution okay and remember we're looking
at the the our criteria for a saline
soil is EC = 4 on a saturated paste it's
not EC equals 4 on a 1: one
solution okay so here and if we go take
that some Labs may do a 1 to five
delution once again we're diluting that
out an EC of four on a saturated paste
equals an EC of two on a 1:1 delution
equals an EC of
0.72 on one to five solution so
understanding how the EC is calculated
is very important when you're trying to
determine the am total Sals that you
have out in the store okay this needs to
be taken into account when making
management recommendations okay so
here's a little graph and I also should
mention too I have a very technical
article uh it's available out on one of
the tables there's only about 60 copies
of it but a lot of this information that
we are that I have here we are put in
where we have a core manual that was
very poor when it was initially made and
we are rewriting that completely and
we're going to have the the chapter for
Saline sodic soil management that draft
chapter Ruth you have that out in the
right there I'll put them on the
registration table we've got two two
different ones but they'll both be yeah
and there's also a really good one there
from North Dakota so if you're
interested in some of these the stuff
that I'm showing here if you want some
information about this to take home and
read U Roose will have that back out on
the on the table back there
okay so just a little general guideline
too texture is really important too when
it comes to measuring our EC versus our
uh we're going to do it with a saturated
paste or one to one delution okay this
Dave Franson did this back in 2007 soil
scientist up at NTSU so keep that in
mind that when you are testing for salt
you're going to ask for the EC the EC is
going to estimate your total salts in
that soil okay what that number number
represents is going to be different
based upon your extraction method so
when you talk to a soil testing lab you
need to know their extraction method now
we've contacted a lot of our soil
testing labs around here about Iowa
State is about the only one that's
running the saturated pce so if you go
to North Dakota University of Minnesota
egg viice Ray Ward lab pretty much
everybody's doing one to one right
here now what type of sodium index are
they calculating there what types of
values are they looking at there well
pretty much everybody egg Vice Labs up
in North Dakota Minnesota Valley testing
W lab pretty much everybody there is
running pretty much everybody's running
in
ESP so that's what you're going to
probably that's the type of dat you're
going to get okay so now soil sampling
for salts all right so where you going
to stand the top 6 in you know is it
going to be like phosphorus where it
doesn't move is it like nitrate or
chloride where it's going to move so
what do you to think about soil sampling
for yourself okay so when we look at
soil sampling okay now I'm once again I
teach soil so I got to use some soil
terms here everybody okay all right
taxonomy soil scientists you know when
with Biology you know we have a
taxonomic system where you classify you
all the different types of organisms
well soil scientists also have their
taxonomic system as well too where they
come up with this long name right here
uh that describes kind of what the soil
is I'm going to use an xline and an
abine soil these soils are more common
uh up in the up probably up north up by
Red field and up in that area here you
guys your soils down here probably be
like a beetle soil or something like
that down here your soil series name
spinetic Fric leptic naad dool okay
that's our xline soils it's the soil
series name that you would see in your
on the on the nrcs soil survey map and
an aine fine IC frigid glossic natur
doll so what does all this mean right
here fine texture lot of clay whole
climate differences are here all right
natur
natric uh sodium that means you have
sodium in it where you have quite a bit
of rainfall and this means that it was
derived from a grassland soil okay so
what is the basic difference between
letip and glossic when we look at this
okay lepic means that you have the
absolute worst sodium conditions that
you could have blosic would be the best
tiic would be in the middle okay right
here here is an example of leptic soil
these slides are from Tom D Suter up in
North Dakota because I didn't have any
good as good of pictures as it as him
okay so the sodium is very close to the
soil surface with sodic soil you get
this columnar structure so if you see
something like this out in your field
this kind of columnar structure that
starts to form and the soil is really
really hard and down
you most likely have sodium there
okay glossin means that that that that
sodium is deeper in the soil profile so
you get it down in here or something
like that where you see pan in that hard
pan anywh you get these hard pans
forming here in South Dakota and a lot
of times those hard bands are due to
that sodium in there making that soil
really dense so nothing will Groll
through it okay like I said here and of
course these areas are going to be
interspersed between each other okay
these areas you know in your field are
small okay and they can they they're
they're they're scattered out okay and
the degree of of of sodium issues you
can change in a very short short period
of time so here's the lectic where that
sodium is more on the soil surface right
there nothing's going to grow there and
here's that glassic over
there so soil samples how deep why where
and where are we in the soil
sample okay agronomic is 2 ft typically
that's what we're looking for okay
now I know there's a lot of different
opinions on tile uh tiling in the in in
the audience here all right if you
tiling with these sodium sodic Fields is
is something that kind of tricky okay
can cause problems okay at least 3 feet
to figure out where that sodium is okay
if possible to the depth of the tile why
do we want to do that it's a lot of work
why do we want to go that deep if we are
going to tile we want to invest in that
tile we want it to
work what happens
is if you're evaluating for a drain tile
there then you need to look down at
least 3 ft deep here's why okay so
here's a picture this here are three
different types of xline soils up by
aine up in that area there um right here
we have the S right here and then the
surface below um the depth below the
surface okay here's your X line right
here okay so here we had not very high s
at all all the way down all the way down
to 30 in almost 3 ft down here on on the
X line one we started about four okay so
North Dakota says that five there
dispersed we come down here well about 2
ft we're at
10 with this last X line right here you
started about six 10 in down we're about
s of 15 about 18 in down foot and a half
20 in or S of 25 and at almost 3 ft
we're at an S of almost 27 okay so now
you go put a tile line in here okay you
put that tile line below that sodium
Horizon think you're going to get water
to flow in
there get your sodium Horizon here get
your tile line down here is water going
to
flow no yeah so why isn't going to flow
what's what's that sodium doing to that
subsoil surface what's this
doing it's dispersing it right it's
dispersing it okay so here's the problem
right here that we see uh that's why I
don't know if thaing is a very good idea
in South Dakota with with the types of
soils that we have so when we have uh
it's a it's kind of like a balance you
can think it's a teer pot so if we have
quite a b bit of sodium in here okay in
the soil and we have a high EC we'll
have a dispersed soil all right because
we have enough calcium and magnesium
over here to flocculate that soil and
have some soil structure
there if we take and we start tiling and
we start moving some of those other
salts out of this water we start moving
some of that calcium that magnesium out
of that soil through that tile water
remember the sodium it's going to move
up and down pretty fast but once it gets
up it's going to disperse the soil and
still move if you get water through
there you can't get water to go through
there because it's dispersed okay so
right here that's the problem so you
know um May negative impact you know
pull of water from a tile line you know
water doesn't flow from tile uh from the
tile if the F field Still Remains wet so
that's why when it comes to tiling and
South Dakota you need to know what your
subsurface soils are you need to know
what types of soils you have there you
know because if you do have sodium down
deep piling it is not really a good
option so any questions so far about
that
stuff all right so soil management how
can we manage this right and I have
until how long do I have until like 15
minutes okay all right so it sounds good
so how do we manage this so we've looked
at this a couple different ways okay
we've looked at this by putting soil
amendments on and we've looked at this
by putting perennial crops on and trying
to put cover crops out there okay uh
studies that we've done we've worked at
Pier Pont we worked at an Andover we wor
we had we're going to put in Falon so
Pier pont's been Greg toppel I have to
give credit to the farmers we're working
with here pure PO is Greg toppel and
over is Roger and Grant rips um Redfield
is going to be we're working with Jim
Miller craft consultant there and then
uh Kenny Selman is the uh he Farms the
land and Jerry West is the land owner
that's who we've been working with here
and then down in your area down here
we've been working with David Gillan at
White Lake so these are the farmers that
we've worked with you couldn't do this
research without them right so what
we've done is we've looked at okay now
if we have too much sodium there if we
add some calcium can we improve that
floculation okay so what we've done is
we've taken and we put out our studies
where we put all these plots out we
design them so we can do statistics on
it because we like to do statistics you
know so um four blocks and the
treatments that we put on are going to
be calcium sulfate or gypsum Elemental
sulfur calcium chloride or no salt those
are the types of salt that's the
treatments that we're putting out there
okay and then what we've done is we've
done two cover crop treatments of course
we got you know there's no there's
nothing growing out there okay because
the salts are so high drilled into corn
uh in Redfield we've had some luck we
have more of a saline soil there you can
but a lot of the cover crops we just put
into the soil if we drill it into corn
we're putting it into V6 but we're
always putting the cover crops planting
them probably about mid mid to end June
uh with after these Sals ands have been
put on okay so now you say I have salt
you tell me to put more salt out there
all right that doesn't make any sense
right I have salt and now you're going
tell me go put more salt up there okay
well here's what's happening okay the
salt most of them have a a component to
an either sulfur or in the case of
chloride okay where they're going to
lower the soil PH all right so if we put
anything with sulfur on so if we put an
ammonium sulfate if we put gypsum on if
we put Elemental sulfur on what happens
is we lower the soil PH we release
calcium from the lime and we hope to be
able to exchange that with the Sodium on
the exchange set so that's why I showed
you that picture of uh C exchange that's
what we're trying to do we have too much
sodium on those exchange sides we're
trying to lower the soil PH bump a bunch
of calcium off flood the system with
calcium and through cat exchange now we
have more calcium in solution will
promote the movement of the sodium off
that exchange site get it in solution
and now once sodium is in solution we
can get it to go down if we get rainfall
okay Elemental suer takes longer to work
than gypson okay so if I'm going to put
out when we look at this we we when we
look at the tempar elemental sulfur and
gypsum Elemental sulfur you need to
oxidize that down to sulfate to form
acid to get the calcium up so typically
when you put amendments on if you're
going to apply amendments you put them
Elemental sulfur on it's going to take
about 6 months to work compared to
gypson so El but you need less of
Elemental sulfur right so anything so
what here's what we're doing any
Amendment with sulfur lowers the soil PH
releases the calcium cation into that
solution to exchange with the Sodium
okay and we have to have formation of
that hydrogen
of the acidifying of that soil to get
that calcium off that Elemental sulfur
when it's applied it's straight As we
need the soil bacteria to oxidize that
into our sulfate so we can have that
acid formation so that's what we're
doing I'm asking you to apply a salt but
I'm really not asking you apply a salt
I'm really asking you apply something
that has an acid in it to lower that pH
and get that calcium off okay so here
let's take a look here I just did some
study here so this is pure pant celic
coder right here this is our
there we go
uh right here so I don't have a very
good pointer in the red box up there
here's my pure Pon site sodium right
there
4,846 parts per million s of 19 bad soil
okay that's the first thing I'm going to
talk about uh what we did here is we had
this is what the plots look like right
here these sub PL this was put on
um a year after after these photos were
taken okay so here's site number one no
treatment no salt Amendment no cover
crop looks pretty ugly looks like it
looks like concrete and those are the
white salts on the surface so that's the
first one right there this one here is
calcium chloride we had some cover crop
on the surface you can kind of sort of
roll it right there we had a big
rainfall that came down through here
after we planted our cover crop kind of
roll it a little bit there cover crop we
planted with barley and sugar
bead so that's that one right there
here's gypsum down here so gypsum down
here you can roll it a little bit better
right there you can roll it a little bit
better there that's the gypsum right
there P salt on the surface and here's
our Elemental solf for right here and if
you look at this Elemental sufur right
here you can see that that soil doesn't
have quite it doesn't have the white
salts on the surface if these other ones
do so at least in this study with the
conditions that we saw at pure Pont
where we had the high sodium the high is
now we have a lot of magnesium in this
soil too okay that that has an influence
as well too but at least here we saw we
put an elemental so for a year before we
came out and planted a cover crop in
there a barley and sugar beads The
Barley grew way better than the sugar
beads
did I agree and you know what Greg toel
has a huge problem up there he's just
like he I asked him I said can what can
can we work in this field he says you
can do anything you want is what he said
so yeah and you know if we what would
happen is if we start growing all these
weeds for a cash crop then they start
get diseasing and die yeah that's
exactly what would happen okay all right
so um right here Elemental sulfur you
know Bary germinated go pretty well
gypsum some of the barley germinated
calcium chloride salt so how much should
we put on we do these calculations based
upon an S A lot of times we rather use
EC or ESP to do the calculations um we
drips them we put on to lower that uh
almost uh you know 4 tons per acre right
there cost 12 cents so it's not cheap uh
calcium chloride works really fast okay
you can put calcium chloride on calcium
chloride is highly dissolvable in the
soil you should not put calcium chloride
on if corn is growing there I learned
that the hard way um so but it came back
I thought it was going to be dead I we
we put some on I told the gradu soon I
said make sure you put it down the
middle of the row I said do not put it
near the corn plant so what they didone
broadcast it all over you came and
looked at the corn plants of the kisum
chloride they look like they were gone
but they fortunately we had a big
rainfall two days later all the calcium
chloride went down the corn started
looking a lot better so I felt a lot
better about that so you know so mother
nature interven um Elemental sulfur you
don't need as much all right um so
that's a little bit cheaper but it takes
a a lot longer to react and of course no
Sal that doesn't cost any money if you
don't do
anything now so how are these rates
calculated so I'm running out of time I
only have 5 minutes left I if you're
interested in learning on how you
calculate these the information you need
from your soil cast is the C exchange
capacity of the soil you need that
measure and you need the ESP I would
prefer the ESP versus the S and so what
we would want to do is we want to reduce
the ESP in that surface soil down to at
Le at least 5% if not less okay so I'm
not going to go through these
calculations CU I'm running out of time
here if you want to go through these if
you're interested in this from a you
know from a Consulting point for
applying gypsum I can show you how to do
it it's also in that guideline up there
there's some nice boxes and step-by-step
details on how to do it but there but
this is the method where we used the ESP
and what we're basically trying to do is
we're trying to take that we know this
is the total salts on the surface we
know what our ESP is we test that we
want to go down to five what's the
difference between what our ESP is to go
down to five that is going to be uh
that's the the math that we work out to
determine how much of an amendment that
we put out okay like I said I'm going to
run out of time okay now Bas since these
amendments are a little bit different
the word we use when I teach soil
science is molecular weight the mass um
you can put on just like with lime a
different lime product you can put on
different rates based upon what their
math is so if I put on one ton of gypsum
I can put
on19 uh tons of sulfur um if I put sulur
sulfuric acid I put 57 calcium chloride
86 and so on okay so last one I just
want to mention is this here I know I'm
almost have the time do I have five
minutes yet or not three okay talk M
okay right okay so here David gillet
he's a great producer is he David Gill
here I don't I didn't know if he's
coming today okay so here's an area in
his field right here white salt 2010
contacted us we got some money from the
corn Council what can we do okay so s we
did a field day down there
2011 tall wheat grass right here looks
just beautiful that's this old white
sight right here got a soil pit okay
look at this here it it look like snow
out there in August 4 in down very very
few salts right there no salts on the
surface right here down at the bottom of
the pit soil scientist you like to talk
about redo features okay redo features
means that you have this Orange in here
these orange colors like can't really
see them but right in there right in
there that means iron has been oxidized
if you have a piece of old equipment
that sits out in the woods you don't pay
any attention to it what happens to it
it what happens to it over time it will
what rust okay when iron in the soil is
in the present of oxygen it does the
same thing it turns orange so I know
that where I had those Sal problems that
was the 4ot in my soil profile I have uh
reduxx features that are orange there
hasn't been water there for a few few
years soil water water table is deeper
down here here is a pit that we do right
by his cornfield in his cornfield as a
matter of fact sorghum corn a soybean
rotation water at the bottom of the pit
okay white salt right up by the surface
up there okay so here's what's going on
um oh shoot okay right here uh white
great here's our soil White Lake right
here that we did this in August right
here the weat by this uh the S by the
site right there uh I'm hting too many
buttons right here the S was one sodium
is 179 here the right in the the the pit
in the cornfield Horizon 1 2 and three
sodium
1296 s borderline right there he we have
a we have sodium issues there okay so
like I said I talk a little bit more
about this but I'm running out of time
Bruce KY did work with uh looking at n
as soil scientist looking at water table
depths here where is the water right
here these lines are where the water
table depth is based upon precipitation
look at this where we had alala and
grass 2010 we had all that rainfall we
had the same problem with South Dakota
you guys did okay too much rainfall even
when we had all that rainfall where we
had that
and where we had that Al Alpa right
there that water that um that soil that
water table was considerably lower so
I'm going to end there because I'm
running out of time I'm going to go here
and I'm going to give credit to all my
the people that they help with our
research then right there okay so like I
said I really appreciate coming and
talking to you about cell here I think
it's an important subject we two quick
questions if anybody has quick
question
be around yep I'll be around Y and so if
you're interested in talking more about
that I'd be happy to answer
questions