hey we're at the home of one of our
sprinkler warehouse customers today
we're making this instructional video
for you on how to install a sprinkler
system where every valve every sprinkler
head and the controller are supplied by
our good friends at Rain Bird sprinkler
warehouse doesn't do installs we just
sell apart i'm adrian sanchez your
sprinkler warehouse pro let's get
started
[Music]
the first task is to flag the location
of each sprinkler valve according to the
sprinkler system design using different
colored flags for each zone will help
simplify the installation marking spray
will show the exact location of where to
dig the trenches after turning off the
water supply dig up the main water line
near the water meter
the reason we're next to the water meter
is we want the most amount of volume and
water pressure to feed our sprinkler
system so here we are at where we've
split off our main line into our
irrigation line it is a one-inch pipe
with a ball valve now the ball valve is
there so we can turn off water to our
irrigation system while maintaining
water flow to the rest of the home we
also got this valve box that goes over
our ball valve and once we fill it in
with dirt and we need to work on it
later
we'll be able to loop the lid right here
and get in and turn off our water
without having to mess around with
digging it all out trenching is the most
time-consuming and physically demanding
part of this job do-it-yourselfers
you're gonna want to get several friends
to help you dig so there's a backflow
prevention device this is a pressure
vacuum breaker or a PV B now most cities
or water districts require some kind of
effective prevention device when you're
installing sprinkler systems because it
keeps contaminated water from flowing
back into your drinking water source so
whether use an anti siphon or pressure
vacuum breaker
we recommend some kind of backhoe
prevention all right so now that we've
installed our ball valve and our
mainline we can turn the water onto the
rest of the home as you can see the
roots on this property posed pretty
significant challenge so what we did is
removed one
the way of our valve wire make sure to
use schedule 40 PVC pipes between the
pointed connection and the inlet set of
valves alright this is a premium
manifold kit from sprinkler warehouse
attached to our valves here we're using
that in our in our irrigation system for
this home now for this as opposed to
hard piping it in this is much faster
and easier to replace and to install
take it in now you do move in the
premium kit right there but if you need
to replace the valves it's as easy as
this you dig it up
you unscrew it you pop out one valve
bring in another valve that is a lot
quicker than having to glue and to cut
this entire thing apart in back together
if you're trying to replace your valves
or even just installing them just screw
it on and you're good to go after the
valves because there's a lot less water
pressure it's safe to use class 200 pipe
to feed the sprinkler heads and that can
save you a little bit of money to run
the pipe under the driveway we recommend
using a water-powered boring kit that we
have a sprinkler warehouse what you do
is you put a high-pressure nozzle in the
end of your class 200 pipe and you
slowly push it in there and the water
pressure pushes the dirt all the way
creating a tunnel for the pipe to go
through and then just connect that to
the rest of your system so if you were
to have your sprinkler head attached to
an old-school nipple riser like this and
never get run over by a vehicle or a
really heavy riding lawnmower you would
probably break your nipple riser
possibly break your sprinkler head and
even worse break your PVC pipe this
swing joint right here completely
prevents that as it's flexible and it
can move at the joints and it also makes
it easier for adjusting the height of
your sprinkler head just in case the
grass clippings were to change the
height of the ground right there you
just dig it up put a little dirt
underneath it and swing it up a little
bit and adjust at the joints
here we are with our our wire this is
direct burial wire which means we do not
have to run a conduit in order to bury
this underground
we got three red wires right here for
our three valves right over there we
have some obstacles in addition to
everything else here in this yard and
I'm standing on this sidewalk right here
is actually a big obstacle for our wires
and our piping we've gone underneath it
right here with a conduit and some water
pipe as well and we're gonna run our red
wires and one common wire through this
one piece of PVC pipe to our valves and
all the way around to the backyard and
to our controller that's inside the
garage so this right here there's a
little coil now what this does is as it
adds a little bit of a extra protection
against power surges boom coil and you
do that to all of them in order to avoid
electrical shorts when connecting the
direct burial are to the valve wires
make sure to use waterproof silicone
filled wire connectors so you want to
overfill your trenches when you're
filling them back in otherwise when the
soil gets wet and begins to settle it'll
sink down a little bit you want to tamp
it down to get a nice and compact that
way you don't leave any signs of
trenches in your yard so facing the bed
a crush rock under your valves can help
with drainage and provide a nice solid
foundation in case anything heavy ever
rolls over on top of it so here I am at
the eave the house installing this rain
sensor we want this to be above where
the sprinklers are going to be spraying
because we obviously don't want water to
get into here otherwise it's going to
turn off her controller
now in order to protect your wires from
damage you don't want to run it through
some PVC conduit from where it comes out
of the ground all the way to your smart
control next we'll flush the cyst and
open the test on the backflow
device leave the air and make sure to
turn the water on very slowly at the
backflow preventer to avoid any pipeline
damage alright now we got all the wires
running to our controller we have our
rain sensor wire right here we're gonna
hook that up we got our common wire
we're gonna hook that up as well we're
gonna turn the power onto this thing and
then what we're gonna do is we're gonna
strip the red wires one by one and we're
gonna touch them to a powered terminal
what that's gonna do is gonna start to
isolate which wire goes to which zone
because we don't know which wire goes to
which zone at this point so if we turn
on terminal number one and start
touching a wire to it what was gonna
happen is it's gonna turn on one of the
zones in our yard so let's just say it
turns on zone number five then we know
that that wire goes to zone 5 so we'll
count 1 2 3 4 5 and we'll connect it to
zone 5 over here and we'll strip another
wire touch it to the power terminal and
go on down the line until we know which
wire goes to which zone and then we
connected to that corresponding zone
[Music]
Rainbird is applied all the sprinklers
for this install today we're using Rain
Bird variable arc rotary or our vans and
a chi or high-efficiency van spray
nozzles now they all come in a variety
of throw distances so here we got the
Rain Bird our van adjustable rotary
nozzle these are the our van 14s 18 and
24 those numbers indicate how far these
actual nozzles can throw water so the 24
is gonna shoot 24 feet
the ATS gonna shoot up to 18 feet and
the 14 up to 14 feet and you can adjust
it down if you only need to throw it a
little bit less than that
all right I just installed the H evant n
now that's a spray novel that shoots up
to ten feet and can cover an entire 360
degree plane but it's adjustable down to
the angle that you need we're in the
center of a flower bed here so we're
gonna go full 360 and it's not quite ten
feet wide so we're gonna do maybe about
six or seven foot on this alright so
here I am in front of two nozzles that
are right next to each other now why
would we need two nozzles right next to
each other we're gonna want to water our
flower bed every day except for the days
when the yard goes off when the yard is
being watered that's gonna cover the
flower bed as well and we're not gonna
need to have this one running so we're
gonna use our controller to program it
to make sure we get exactly the kind of
water we need so let's take a look at
this achieve an eight right here now H E
stands for high efficiency this one is
12 inches high that way we can go over
our flowers and cover our entire flower
beds and then over here we're gonna put
the arvan eighteen in and that is gonna
shoot at 18 feet cover both the flower
bed and the rest of the yard all the
grass and everything - lets get that on
here just unscrew stick that in there
there we go get that on there
and that's how that goes that's why you
have two of them right here alright so
now we're gonna adjust these sprinkler
heads they might not be pointed in the
right direction and they might be so
over spraying have a wide angle we're
gonna try to make that angle be just
right for this flowerbed so first we're
gonna adjust it this way the Rain Bird
our van and a chi band nozzle spray
patterns and distances are easily
adjusted by hand without tools the
rotating stream technology delivers wind
resistant large water droplets without
misting or foggy and water usage is
reduced by about 33 percent that is
money in your pocket remember sprinkler
warehouse has everything for your
irrigation needs so your trees lawn
flowerbed and gardens are lush and
beautiful and if you have any questions
remember to speak to one of our superb
customer service agents on sprinkler
warehouse.com
they really know their stuff and they
will get you squared away
subscribe to our YouTube channel for
helpful tips tutorials and general
sprinkler instruction I'm Adrian Sanchez
your sprinkler warehouse pro see you
later irrigator