good afternoon everyone and welcome to
today's session how one country sought
to combat the harm of burning sugarcane
my name is rocio ortega and i am the
events associate at propublica and i'll
be your host today
today we'll be testing out a couple new
exciting features for accessibility
closed captioning of the program is
available and can be enabled by clicking
on the closed caption option
on the bar towards the bottom of your
screen
this program is also being broadcasted
in english and portuguese courtesy of
hani souza
to select your preferred language please
click on the button that says
interpretation below it is important
that you select that appropriate
language so that you do not miss any of
the conversation
you should either select english or
portuguese and be sure the option is not
set to off
we'll get started in just a few moments
we're just waiting for a few more people
to sign on
thank you so much for your patience
today pro-publica video journalist nadia
sussman and seattle times reporter lulu
ramadan will moderate a conversation
with experts from brazil and florida
about alternative approaches to
harvesting and what those might mean for
the glades for more than half of
america's cane sugar is produced
and it looks like we have enough folks
on now so let's go ahead and get started
again if you're just joining my name is
rocio ortega and i'm pro-publica's
events associate welcome to today's
session how one country sought to combat
the harm of burning sugarcane
thanks to mckinsey and company for their
support of today's event this event is
being held in partnership with the palm
beach post and wlrn
today we'll be testing out a couple new
exciting features for accessibility i'll
share some of the notes that i shared at
the start of the session closed
captioning of the program is available
and can be enabled by clicking on the
closed caption option on the bar towards
the bottom of your screen
this program is also being broadcasted
in english in portuguese courtesy of
hani souza to select your preferred
language please click on the button that
says interpretation below
it is important that you select that
appropriate language that you don't miss
any of the conversation you should
either select english or portuguese and
be sure the option is not set to off
for those new to us propublica is a
non-profit newsroom dedicated to
investigative journalism
last year reporters at the palm beach
post and propublica investigated the
impact of sugar cane boring in florida
the harvesting practice helps reduce
more than half of america's cane sugar
but it sends smoke and ash into largely
low-income communities of color in the
state's heartland
in their reporting the journalists
learned that other countries have found
ways to harvest their crops without
those burns
they traveled to brazil the world's
largest producer of sugarcane to learn
how and why they switched to another
method
i'd now like to invite our panelists to
join us on screen
thank you so much for being here today
dr christopher holmes is an associate
professor of meteorology at florida
state university
his research examines the global cycles
of air pollutants and greenhouse gases
and the interactions both with climate
change
is a technical advisor in the presidency
of state of sao paulo environmental
agency his work includes analyzing
environmental licenses and permits as
well as developing policies and
procedures on pollution prevention and
control permits
dr elena kibero is a professor of
environmental health at university of
south paolo
her work focuses on the subjects of
environmental health health geography
and air pollution
dr rafaela josetto
is a scientific researcher at agronomic
institute of campinas she did a post
doctorate at the university of florida
in belle glade where she worked with
crop options for bioenergy her work
focuses on soil fertility and
fertilization as well as use of waste in
the cultivation of sugarcane
our moderators today are propublica
video journalist nadia sussman and
seattle times reporter lulu ramadan
as an additional note the session is
being recorded and a link to the video
will be emailed to everyone who
registered thank you all so much again
for being here today and i hope you
enjoy the conversation i'll let nadine
lulu take it from here
thank you so much racio
we are so pleased to welcome this panel
of experts including two that you saw in
the video
and we wanted to start off by talking a
bit about what happened in brazil
health concerns were one of the factors
that led lawmakers to phase out the
practice of burning before harvesting
so this first question is for dotora
elena
i think your camera is still turned off
dr elena are you saying here i cannot
start my video because you close at me
ah
well let's see if we can work this out
oh there you are thank you so much for
joining us dr helen
sorry about that
um
so
dr elena giber you studied the health
effects of sugarcane burning in several
cities in sao paulo state
what were your major findings especially
with regard to disease hospitalizations
and mortality
well i had started studying
air pollution effects on health in the
city of sao paulo in the late 80s but
then around
2000 the year 2000 i started to study
the effects of biomass fire especially
because of the
great expansion of sugarcane plantation
in the state of sao paulo due to the
development of the flex fuel engine for
cars
at that time mainly small cities had
this problem
of
receiving the effects of the burning of
sugarcane
and so we selected some municipalities
in the state of sao paulo the first one
was the spirit center the turvo in the
west part of the state and we started
mainly direct effects because sugarcane
burning can have also indirect health
effects as climate change
uh caused by greenhouse greenhouse gases
in
car accidents due to the reduced
visibility but our studies focus
on direct effects and
mainly respiratory diseases
i also
advise that around eight dissertations
and teases on the team
on this team of and i had two large
projects financed by the ministry of
health of brazil and minister of science
education
the first one was undertaken in 2004 and
in a municipality
where 100 percent of sugarcane
plantations were still burned in spite
of the law in 2002 because the
plantations were not adapted to receive
the machinery
at that time we met we installed air
pollution monitoring equipment at the
school at the city school
and we study uh
air pollution during hazard harvest time
and non-harvest time and we also study
respiratory symptoms in children from 10
to 13 years old
and our findings indicated that in spite
of the the level of pollutants
they were not over what
brazilian legislation allowed at that
time now brazilian legislation is more
strict but at that time it was permitted
the prevalence of respiratory symptoms
in children was very high among 28
symptoms that we studied
22 of them were higher than we had found
in this metropolitan regions of sao
paulo
and those symptoms were
mainly cough most days cough without
cold
wheezing bronchitis asthma ear
infections and allergies
those neighborhoods were usually
low-income neighborhoods
where population lived in simple houses
without
much protection for air pollution and
also
sugarcane harvest occurs in winter where
you have the problem of
more virus because of the cold that
starts
and also
temperature inversions which
difficult turns it difficult to
dispersion of air pollution
after that first studies
we undertook other studies in araraquara
which is the north part of the state and
we studied children uh
until four years old from zero to four
years old and old people
uh
65 years old and older
and we studied using a job processing
techniques
geographical information systems with
data on
sugarcane area
number of
fires
by
satellite image or by
set asb data which register the fires
hospital admissions by age and by
by
classification of disease and also the
social uh data on the population
affected
and and we found
that in
most of the studies that there was an
association with
sugar cane fires and respiratory
symptoms and a hospital admiss higher
levels of hospital admission during
sugarcane harvest
and especially in uh during or a few
days after
the
fires were allowed by ceteste which
allowed agriculture to to
put the fire on sugarcane before
harvesting
the other finding was that
the population was affected was mainly
low-income population
which had more difficulties in getting
to a
basic health system so they
save more days before getting to the
hospital and they would get a worse
health situation
uh
and the problem was also worse for
children and for old people that were
those were the main findings but uh
since those projects they lasted for a
while
we could see that after 2008 which was
five years after the law when
part of the the sugarcane plantation
could not be burnt anymore and from then
on there was a reduction in the number
of fires in the state of sao paulo and
there was also reduction in the
admissions of respiratory
due to respiratory diseases
in the population we could see that year
by year
this reduction so it was important to
see
uh how it happened uh i told about arara
kwara but we started in presidential
prudenti region and we study in the
northwest region of the state
where 25 municipalities
had large areas in sugar cane and in all
those areas we noticed this reduction in
fires and reduction in respiratory this
is
admission in hospitals with using data
from soos the brazilian unified health
system
uh we also at inara aquari we had
studied
uh airborne polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons to see the the cancer the
risk of cancer due to the pollutants of
the
sugarcane uh
fires and we identified that there was a
tolerable tolerable tolerable risk of
cancer
in the areas
where sugarcane was burned
and but this risk also uh decreases
along the time the data
with the the
the when we measure pollutant in 2002
was higher than in 2010 so
in the meantime
the law
brought benefits for the population
thank you so much that was very helpful
similar to what you've just described dr
elena
residents in florida's gleeds region
have raised concerns about negative
health impacts from cane burning
that was the driving factor behind the
lawsuit that was referenced in the
documentary and now that lawsuit was
recently dropped at the agreement of all
parties
and the major sugar companies in the
region say that the air is good and
meets federal clean air standards
but as we've reported the epa is
currently considering whether those
clean air standards are adequate to
protect public health
uh now dr christopher holmes thank you
for being here
your research examines the global cycles
of air pollutants and greenhouse gases
what kinds of pollution does sugar cane
burning produce in florida and what are
some of the challenges in tracking it
my research group has spent some time
looking at
data collected from surface monitoring
sites in south florida and also from
satellites which orbit the earth and
observe south florida as well as the
rest of the world
and
the first thing we looked at was uh
respirable uh particulate matter which
is also called pm 2.5
and this particulate matter can reach
deep into the lungs and cause a variety
of health
problems
there are
dozens of monitoring stations in florida
because it's well known that pm 2.5
causes disease
and we looked particularly at several
sites that were close to the sugar cane
fires
and at two sites near the sugar cane
fires we found that
the concentrations of this pm 2.5 were
higher during the harvest burn season
than they were in the rest of the year
and this was unlike any other sites in
south florida showing that that the
concentrations were higher closer to the
fires
this corroborated what other studies
have found in the past some researchers
at florida international university
measured concentrations of uh pahs which
uh dr ribeiro just discussed
and uh those were uh characteristic of
emissions from burning vegetation and
those were many times higher in the uh
sugarcane burning region than elsewhere
in south florida
it's now established from many other
studies that
these
small particles and pahs cause quite a
few different health impacts and dr
ribeiro listed
several of them
but i would emphasize that they are
associated with
cases of asthma bronchitis emphysema
other respiratory infections heart
disease heart attacks lung cancer
obviously this list goes on
but also things like um premature birth
of
and
low birth weight of of babies
um several of these can be fatal
and um
using these past studies in other
regions
that
relate the concentrations of particulate
matter to uh
mortality and health outcomes we
estimate that there's probably
about one to six deaths per year uh as a
result of the sugarcane burning
emissions in south florida
for the scale of these emissions i think
it's interesting to
compare them to something like motor
vehicle emissions from the area of sugar
cane that's burned each year we think
there's about 5 000 tons of particulate
matter produced in these fires and
that's pretty close to the emissions
from all of the motor vehicles across
the state of florida but the sugar cane
fires of course unlike the vehicles are
tightly concentrated in just one small
part of the state surrounding a few
different communities
thank you so much
that was really illuminating
environmental concerns also played an
important role in the decision in sao
paulo state to transition away from
burning and to harvesting raw cane
nearly all the cane in the state
in sao paulo is now harvested without
burning
so uh dr rafael joseto
what were the agricultural challenges
and the benefits of switching to raw
cane in brazil can you tell us what that
period of learning and adaptation was
like
opportunity
the first challenge was that we have no
machinery to harvest sugar cane
especially the moment the government
decided that we had to change things we
have no machinery for this reason we
have decided to create a timeline
and use a 10-year period to help us
adapt to the law
and while we were purchasing that
machinery we have learned how to do the
work in the new system
first we just thought that we would
no longer hire people and just use the
machines
so we
we were faced with new solutions and
lots of learning
so the first
challenge was machinery and the second
was
hiring people
because we knew that we would no longer
hire so many people because the machines
were there
luckily
the sugarcane sector was expanding and
we have hired people to do work in other
areas with
sugarcane expansion
later on the next challenge was that
sugarcane productivity
lowered because raw cane has lower
productivity than burnt cane
later on we understood that
the
machine
would
stamp on
the cane
or even the machine would cut some part
of the plant
so we have improved quality of the
machinery in the process
also we have resorted to gps and we no
longer
have the machinery go on top of the
sugar cane line
later on we had other
other challenges linked to pests
the only advantage of burning is that
burning kills off pests
and as time goes by
the past
are faced with their
uh natural killers
basically we need to be patient we need
to learn and try to calibrate the system
also we have developed some pesticides
that we used in the beginning and
nowadays we are phasing out
the use of pesticides
we
currently we only use pesticides where
we have problems with certain pests
also we have changed
some plants that were harmful to
sugar cane
we have developed new techniques to
fight those plants
also we have changed fertilization
because the straw is really
nurturing for
the soil
we
need to be careful when adapting and
using new types of fertilizers
we've learned so much
over the first 10 years and i dare say
that now the system is still a work in
progress we're still improving our
techniques we're still
using
new machines
i've told you about the challenges but
now i'll tell you about the benefits the
benefits are we have more protection for
the soil we have better
soil humidity now
we have better soil
conservation and better physical
qualities for the soil as well as
biological life for the soil
a large number of micro
organisms have developed because of the
straw
and all of this has
brought more organic material and more
life to the soil
and i
can tell you that the biggest
advantage is to raise
environmental awareness in the
sugar industry i think that in brazil
there's nobody who thinks that
sugarcane burning is the best technique
nobody agrees with that anymore our
grown agronomic engineers they have
shown us
how good it is to
use the new techniques
and whenever we're faced with challenges
they
they help us see that
the new method is much better thank you
thank you for listening to me
thank you that was really informative
um
so brazil's sugar companies seem to have
embraced that transition to not burning
as you mentioned
throughout the course of our reporting
florida sugar companies have denied that
pre-harvest burns have a significant
impact on air quality or public health
now prior to this event propublica asked
florida crystals and u.s sugar the
largest sugar producers in the region
for their perspectives on brazil and
alternative harvesting methods florida
crystals did not respond
and us sugar provided a statement but it
did not address our questions
the company said
u.s sugar proudly stands behind the
safety and integrity of its farming and
processing practices in addition the men
and women of u.s sugar are also employee
owners of our company with jobs that
meet the world's highest standards for
worker safety environmental stewardship
sustainability and technological
innovation
antonio queros this question is for you
you work with the state environmental
agency in sao paulo that regulates
agricultural burning
in brazil
what was the reaction of the industry
when regulators first announced that
they were going to end sugarcane burning
and how did that change over time
the question is that sugarcane industry
was having a lot of claims of the
population nearby due to the all the
health problems in this city so the
problem due to the burning of the
sugarcane leaves so it was not
a new question
satisby is the state company
in charge of control pollution sources
of course a big burning is a pollution
source so when satellite has a question
of the justice of the population about a
large burning causing very big problems
so the company needs to take action and
please do not burn now because we have a
very low umt in air we have a very low
content of humanity
below 20 percent you cannot burn now
justice also start actions against these
farmers just asking you cannot burn it
you are
causing a big health problem so it was
not a new question to these companies
when in 2002 we got a state law
um just trying to ban the fires
this law was as raphaela said
really well done because it gives to the
companies time to make these adoptions
we got a
period of time of 20 years to burn the
fire and the places where harvest could
be made by mike mcqueen
and 30 years where the harvest should be
manual due to the inflammation of
the land
so
companies start to burn the fire and in
the beginning it was a big mess because
we were working on paper
just try to imagine
large
companies bringing maps on paper
saying fear is the 20
of my area that i'm not going to burn
this year it was almost impossible to to
monetize to give to communicate
and the company
developed uh
a way to make everything by the internet
and
a system that we got all the maps of the
the farms and the farmer just put this
is the area the 20 of the era that i am
not going to burn in this five first
years of the law
so what happened was that when the
companies start
having this machinery they start
improving this
mechanical harvesting
and
just talk with the environmental
agency and talk hey
we are expected to end this burning in
uh 2020.
let's see what if i just make it earlier
so
the the companies just talked with the
agency and we got a environmental
protocol to anticipate the end of
burning because when they start
to buy this this machinery when they
start just you need you need to to make
big changes in the way you plant if you
are going to
use machinery harvesting you cannot have
level curves you need to make everything
flat so the machinery machinery can pass
through the cane just making the harvest
a better way so why do not accelerate
this process
and also these companies just uh and the
problem that they had with the
municipalities nearby and the population
always claiming about this fires in the
burning especially in the dry season in
brazil that is our winter
so
the sugarcane sector did not
try not to to
to
ban the files they just had to have
their time to make this the patient and
it was really a success
meanwhile in one of the regimes of the
state in jawa there was a
action as this election and it went to
the supreme court of brazil that
said that it was forbidden to burn in
all that region right
but a lot
before the
date that the law stipulated
so it was very important for the sector
to say hey wait a little i am doing my
job i am banning gradually and i'm
making it enough
in a way that i can maintain my economic
creativity and we will have the same
result in 2017 for us the
last year that we got big fires and the
bigger farms today we have only very
very very little burning in the the
properties where it's impossible to make
the mechanical harvest so it was a
process it was not very hard it
took a lot of work but
it is done
yeah well yes you mentioned a lot of
work and um in the united states
similarly we often have conversations
about that balance between
regulation and the economy
and in florida many people are concerned
about the economic impact of making that
harvesting transition
how did you as a state regulator
evaluate that dynamic in brazil
balancing health and safety with jobs
let's see it in two ways in two
different ways well you have an industry
and then you buy a very very new
machinery and you need to dismiss 200
employees
oh
i'm so sad but i importantly you lose
your job all right what's the problem no
okay
why because i just need to have my
profit okay it's a way to see it
if i say to you well now you have a new
regulation i need you to have a better
pollution air pollution control and you
say whoa but i will need to to to spend
a lot of money to do it yes but it's for
the help of everybody
so i'd like to understand why one can
just sneeze people in name of a better
profit and one cannot have a less profit
in behalf of all the population and it's
not a new problem you see here in brazil
we have a licensing process that has a
previous license an installation license
and operation license so the first one
says well
what you want to do is possible in this
place the second one says well you can
build your factory you can build your
plan and the third one well start
operating but you need to renew your
operation license in three five years or
two years it depends upon how dangerous
is your your activity for an environment
well here in brazil there is no such a
thing like a acquired right to pollute
because when you come to renew your life
your operation licensee i can say to you
well you know your
air pollution controls are not so good
in this last three years
we have another technology much better
and i want you to improve your
your control your your air pollution
control so the review of the operation
license can ask for the the
the industry to buy different operations
to buy new equipments and to attend to a
high street standards
because in brazilian constitution
they it's granted to all brazilians the
right to a healthy environment
so i need to grant it that's my
that's why my duty as a
government agency and health is one of
the most important things that we must
look when we are licensing an activity
so of course in some activities you will
have some sound pollution some water
pollution some air pollution but you
cannot compare any pollution from an
industrial activity to a burning of
hundreds and hundreds of thousands of
acres of sugarcane in the free space
so
for us it's really a question of a
health environmental event
thank you so much antonio quiroz
in florida uh the agency so somewhat
analogous to the agency that you work
for but in florida the agency that
regulates sugar harvesting practices is
the state department of agriculture and
consumer services
we invited florida's agricultural
commissioner nikki freed and her staff
to participate in the panel today
they declined saying they were short
staffed in the middle of a legislative
session
in the past commissioner freed has says
she believes it's possible for quote
unquote green harvesting or the
harvesting of raw unburnt sugarcane to
be feasible in florida but they still
need to examine
quote pest and plant diseases worker
safety florida's ecosystem and soil
composition and industrial demand for
green harvesting
dr rafaela joseto you spent a year
working in florida's glades region and
given these concerns pests worker safety
the soil etc do you think a transition
to harvesting raw unburnt cane would be
possible in florida
i know
agronomists in florida
i think they are as good or even better
than brazilian professionals
and if brazilians
have managed to overcome the technical
problems i'm sure
american
agronomic engineers are also going to
make it i think that you have to start
you don't need to start with 100 of the
areas you could start with 20 of the
areas you could um you know learn from
the process maybe in five six years ten
years then you overcome the burning
and not having problems with past or
infestation
you
need to take action now
you need to take action and do you work
little by little and you're going to
overcome the challenges as they come
and you can learn from us here in brazil
we know that issues are regionals but
you know
we offer a case study for florida in any
way
i think that it's important to take the
first step and then you
tackle the problems the problems are not
that hard because the hardest problems
are
offering people work
and we know that
in the u.s you have machine harvesting
already so what's the problem of stop
burning
maybe the
machinery is going to be slower to do
the harvesting
you know it's going to take some hours
more
to
harvest raw cane
than it would with burnt cane
there will be some past but it's
something temporary that you can
overcome in some years
natural natural enemies are gonna
come up but i think that you have to get
started florida
can
lead the way and
show people clean techniques
and
eco-friendly practices
here in brazil one thing that was really
good is that
the
plants are proud of saying they have
modern
ecologic practices that they do socially
responsible work
environmentally
right work and they use this to showcase
their success
it's so good that the largest industries
the largest plants in brazil they have
embraced it and they like to show they
protect nature
thank you so much for that perspective
dr rafaela that was really insightful
we are coming up on the 20th anniversary
of sao paulo's original law to phase out
the burns
meanwhile in the u.s we've never had any
laws banning sugarcane burning
lawmakers have taken an interest in air
quality however
last month three u.s representatives
introduced a bill that would create a
pilot program for air monitoring and
low-income communities and communities
of color
among the sponsors of the bill is
florida representative kathy castor
in florida's sugar growing region there
is only one government-run air monitor
dr holmes as an expert in air monitoring
and modeling
you've said that the government should
take a closer look at the air in
florida's sugar growing region
what should additional government
monitoring look like
given the short duration of those burns
and what might that monitoring tell us
right so in urban areas across the us uh
we have
typically an urban area will have
multiple monitors
and that allows you to map out the
concentrations of particulate matter and
other pollutants
in various neighborhoods
the
area of florida where sugarcane is
burned has multiple
different communities
and
the one official monitor there is not in
the center of any of those communities
um
and so i think if you want to know what
the concentrations of these pollutants
are obviously you want to have
a measurement in in the center of of
each of the communities or somewhere
within the the general population area
um there is a
rising
availability of low-cost sensors which i
know the
pro-publica worked on deploying several
of those in
in the
area and those are a
tool that can be used to supplement uh
the
regulatory monitors they aren't as
accurate
but they um our they are um
or they can be reliable so
uh they have to be checked carefully but
but they can be used for mapping things
out and uh that's being used routinely
in in a variety of other states and
and cities to map out air pollution on
fine spatial scales
we also use satellites because
satellites are
peering down from space all the time
and what we've seen from space
uh
re reinforces what we saw from just the
the couple of monitors that are in the
in the
area where sugar cane is burned uh
the
thing that i mentioned earlier was that
the concentrations of particulate matter
are higher
at the two sites that are
near the
sugar cane fires and the satellites
further showed that the area of that
elevated particulate matter coincides
very closely with the boundaries of the
sugarcane fields so the satellites are
providing spatial information uh that we
can't get from current
sensors on the ground but it really does
again support
the conclusion that
there is a source of particulate matter
in the sugarcane burning region
thank you so much for that i'm not in
lulu for beginning to take us through
that discussion um we're now going to
turn it over to our audience q a but
before doing that i'd like to just share
a quick link to our event survey in the
chat box that i am dropping in now we
really appreciate your feedback again if
you'd like to ask a question click that
q a icon at the bottom of your screen to
submit it to us
we already have a few in so i'm going to
go ahead and pass it back to nada to
deliver that first question
thank you so much to all of our
panelists thank you racio and thanks to
everybody who asked questions
um so i'm going to start with one it's a
bit of a double question
is the reluctance of the florida sugar
industry to invest in machinery thus
costing them money a part of the problem
and did the price of brazil's sugar
increase after the burns stopped
and so for the first question about the
machinery i just want to say that
florida's sugar is already harvested by
machine so in brazil you saw the manual
cutters in the video that practice has
been replaced by machine cutting in
florida already
antonio queras maybe you can answer the
question about the price of brazil's
sugar and if it went up after the burns
stopped
i i don't know if if you have a rise in
the price with the stop of the bernies
but the truth is that the industry
sugarcane industry in brazil look
forward a green protocol just to be able
to sell to markets where these
worries with environmental subjects were
really important just to close man just
to to open markets and not to close down
so when we talk about the green protocol
that industry just assigned with the
environmental uh
departments of sao paulo state this
brought a very a very good marketing for
these companies so these companies could
say i am a green company i have my sugar
without burning i have my sugar in a
very very strict law observance so that
was the uh the improvement in the to the
company profile i don't know exactly
about the
the compartment of the prices but i
i heard it of many of these big planters
that they say no i want to have a green
seal on my sugar because europe wants it
because all the markets won't see i want
to be a green product and it's a good
way
thank you and thank you to all of the
attendees for the excellent questions um
we got one here for you dr holmes
um
uh the attendee asks uh any time that
health outcomes and the relationship
between burning and negative health uh
health outcomes are mentioned
uh they're told that the data does not
support a negative health outcome you
mentioned this when you were speaking
earlier can you speak a little bit more
about that link between mortality and
morbidity and burning cycles
right
we know from lots of studies in urban
areas
across especially in the us but also in
europe and many other countries
that um inhaling particulate matter
is harmful to your health and
dr rivero has done some of those studies
and she spoke directly about that
you can think of this as
analogous to
smoking cigarettes
which are also sources of um particles
and um tobacco is of course a plant and
so
there's some not a not a tight analogy
but there's some analogy to burning it
to
uh
inhaling smoke from a cigarette which is
well known to be uh
toxic
and um inhaling smoke from other burning
vegetation whether that be a wildfire or
an agricultural fire
and so we know that the
injuries that come from that depend on
how much of that smoke you burn
we have
now established or the scientific
community has now established that that
the
there are harmful effects of burning
excuse me of inhaling
particle particulate matter down to very
low concentrations at least
concentrations of
five micrograms per cubic meter and uh
i bring up that specific number because
the
the way that air quality is generally
regulated in the us is based on a
threshold system called the national
ambient air quality standards and um
that's set by the us epa
and they pick a threshold
above which uh there are consequences
and below which um there there are not
and there's a lot of
um
factors that go into setting those
standards but the current standard is
that um
the air quality should have
concentrations of 12
micrograms per cubic meter or less of pm
2.5 so
the scientific literature shows that
there are
harmful effects of inhaling particulate
matter at concentrations that are below
what the ambient air quality standards
allow
so
when i have said that you know we expect
that there are
uh impacts of inhaling smoke from sugar
cane and from other burning sources
even though the concentrations in
the
sugarcane burning region are indeed
below 12 micrograms per cubic meter we
still do effect expect that there are
going to be
um
uh health impacts from those
thank you and and just to throw that
question to dr hibero as well um
you mentioned that that threshold for
what's healthy and what's allowed under
the law in brazil also changed over the
course of the discussions so what does
that look like what did that transition
look like when
research and
new information emerged in brazil
well brazil now is in the process of
adopting world health organization
thresholds
which is slower a little lower than the
american apa standards
and uh but we we have
a time like we did for the sugarcane
harvesting in and using fire we have a
period of adaptation for the cities
especially
and
for
car engines to adapt
to the new standards the state of sao
paulo has a progressive
[Music]
process with intermediate phase and
phase intermediate phase one two and
three
until we get to the world health
organization
uh thresholds for controlling air
pollution
[Music]
but but as i said it's not only the the
pollution at the ground level it's also
the greenhouse gases that
the burning produces and this is not
being discussed
the forest fires in the amazon are so
much discussed and around the world and
and why
a volunteer fire like that is not
discussed because it produces methane
co2
seo
and ozone
which are greenhouse gases and this may
affect
uh climate and
increased temperatures around the world
so i i guess we we need to have a more
encompassing discussion regarding the
indirect effects also
dr elena hibero thank you so much for
that um
so
you know in the short time we have we
probably won't get to the fully
encompassing discussion that you're
talking about but it's definitely
something we should continue to discuss
in the future
we have a question that i think would be
good for dr rafael joseto
have the transformation processes away
from burning been published in english
and is it available so what resources
are out there based on the experience of
brazilian agronomists engineers and
others who work in the sugar cane
industry
about transitioning from
using prescribed burns to having a no
burning harvest
yes
most of
um scholar work is written in portuguese
but we have plenty of material in
english too especially as regards to
straw
you know
nutrient cycles based on straw the
changes in terms of fertilization all of
those agronomic
processes are documented in technical
journals
you know if you google information
lots of um
scholar work is going to show up for you
we have plenty of
scientific material on that
thank
you um there are a couple questions here
about employment and some of the
repercussions of making that transition
in brazil um perhaps this question is
best for you antonio queras um
what happened what was the feedback like
from those who potentially lost jobs
because of that transition and what did
the employment trends look like overall
with the sugar industry
when they made that transition away from
burning
as i said it was a slow transition so we
have something like 15 years
before the total ban of big fires in sao
paulo state and this job of cutting raw
con the the sugar cane it was not a good
job right people came from northeast
brazil the poorest region in brazil came
to sao paulo state and to the southwest
just to cut sugarcane and then can go
back to northeast brazil this job
requires people to stay in a very
reclined position and
making this this
sharp too to cut the sugar cane and it
was expected from one person to cut
something like eight or ten tons of can
per per day
not a good job not a healthy job so this
transition was not of a good job to a no
job it was from a a a not so good job a
job that only provides you some money as
uh
as rafaela said some of these people
were employed in sugarcane industry from
this this and this
2002 to 2007.
we got a big growth of sugarcane
industry in sao paulo state
so we got sugarcane uh going over the
west of the state so some of these
people went to these activities and the
others were just absorbed by the market
all right it was the question of do it
in uh
in the time to to give time for people
to find jobs but it's completely
different from the situation you have in
florida you do not have people you are
going to lose no jobs if you stop
burning sugarcane then you will have
only the good part you will have the
aeronautical benefits that rafaela said
and we will you will not have this
health risks that elena said so i
i see no problem in this
in this question of jobs for florida
right
i would if you if you permit me i i
looked in the chat and i saw a question
about uh somebody asked uh if uh there
is in our constitution the protection of
the help of the people yes
this we have a very very large
constitution and then his 220
article
we have this protection of environment
if you allow me i will read it to you
everyone has the right to an ecological
balanced environmental
a good for common use by the people and
essential to a healthy quality of life
imposing on the public power and the
community the dirty to defend and
preserve it for the present and to true
generations so this is a constitutional
command
right
environment is a good of common use and
we need to protect and we need to grant
a health
environment so article two to of our
constitution
thank you so much antonia
i saw that there was a question
have there been health studies in
florida and how large is the exposed
population so i wanted to ask dr
christopher holmes about that and then i
wanted to follow up afterwards for some
of our brazilian panelists to learn a
little bit more about how their studies
came about so let's start with dr holmes
please
so my research group has done some of
that and we have um articles that are
in peer review at a journal so
i uh yes the studies have been done but
they haven't been published yet um so i
will be able to share more about that
hopefully soon
um
in terms of the population that's
exposed the most heavily exposed
population are the people that live in
the in the cities of mel glade and
clewiston and pahokee
and uh i believe there are about 40 000
people that altogether live in those
communities
um the smoke however is not confined to
those communities and it does drift both
east and and west
and so um
we do expect that even though the
concentrations of smoke are
low over the coastal cities
and uh further to the west into uh
glades in hendry county we do expect
that there would be some health impacts
in those regions and um
i
noticed reading through the questions
that you know some people are interested
in having more specific details and um i
i expect that within the next
uh few weeks i would be able to share
some figures that that would address
some of those uh questions that i'm
noticing in the chat
thank you so much dr holmes
and dr helena gibero you mentioned this
a little bit but
you did a number of studies related to
sugarcane burning and health effects
specifically
and i think you had mentioned that some
uh had done in partnership with or
funded by government agencies so i just
wanted to ask at the state level or the
federal level to what extent is this
something that government
is
trying to pursue as a research matter in
brazil
well
i had
mainly
funding from federal agencies
like the the ministry of health has a
health surveillance
secretary with it has a
secretary it's called vigiar
the air surveillance and in this program
uh it has it open beads for
studies regarding air quality and i
enter in one of those bids for financing
part of the study
other parts of this area were financed
by cnp which is the research brazilian
institute which belongs to the ministry
of
technology of brazil
and some of the the students the phd or
massage students they got financing from
the ministry of education campus or from
fapezp which is the state
agency
but during this time we have partnership
with cetasb sometimes which allow gave
us the data
or with
even the the sugar industry which
allowed us to put a monitoring equipment
in
in the sugarcane plantations
and
we had all the freedom to publish the
results
and one thing i wanted to mention is
regarding the labor we had one of our
research we interviewed
la uh workers
from the sugarcane plantation because
there are many small towns in the state
of sao paulo that have
like a rural population that work in
sugar cane plantations and
and we we did study in one of these
villages and we interviewed them and and
they were at
the same time relieved that the the uh
manual harvest and was
finishing because that was a very
stressful labor but they were anxious
about finding new jobs
and what we we
found was that the unions
of sugarcane
growers
provided courses
for them
at night
on weekends they could
learn
to use computers or they could learn
agriculture practices so they were
prepared for other jobs
when
they were expecting to lose their jobs
and many of them got employed as antonio
said in sugarcane plantations in other
parts of the state
for
planting sugarcane
or uh
they went to soybean plantations or to
work in
uh
tree planting you know reforestation
areas in the state of sao paulo and
those who came from the northeast of
brazil
i guess they stayed there
because
tourism was developed during those years
also in the northeast so it was easier
to find jobs
in the northeast area of the country
so
we don't see in the the cities of the
state of sao paulo a process of
impoverishment because of lack of jobs
of
formation of favelas or things like that
on the contrary we we see that there is
a
increased dynamism in those cities
middle-sized cities that have suggest
meals around them
thank you thank you so much for that um
so we have one last question we'll try
to keep it brief if you can
um but several questions have been posed
that mention the um political
donations and sort of
the power of the sugar industry and
their opposition to
shifting away from burning and perhaps
antonio you can speak to this but was
there a large-scale
um
resistance to cain burning being phased
out in brazil and how did you counteract
any difficulties that you did that you
were confronted with and if you could
keep that short we're closing out here
but
there was no such resistance
just no resistance at all
because
industry had time to do it it was
something that everybody knows it should
have an end
everybody was seeing the problem you you
cannot have an idea of the area what
sugar came in sao paulo state we're
talking about a large a really large
area so when you were traveling in the
countryside in june or may
it was possible for you to just drive in
a cloud of smoke
in the road it was a big problem
apart is everywhere you went in the
countryside you could see
the ashes
in the house
in the swimming pools in the gardens in
the whole city and everybody could think
well these ashes that are in the ground
maybe part of them are in my lungs too
it was so obvious that this was not a
good thing to be done that there was no
opposition
the question was
other
how do you make a good monitoring on
meat
how can i prove that
this sugar cane that burnt
was not born by my fault
someone just threw a cigarette from the
car and it start burning and you see
this is a sugar cane planted in a place
able to receive the harvest the
mechanical harvest for me it's not good
that it burns now i do not have
equipment to wash this
this stalks
before milling them so this was
these were the big problems the the
planters said well you are charging me
with a penalty because i i burned
in a place that i was not
authorized to burn but it was not me
i could say this was the biggest problem
so we started a
question of this
this uh
this fact
my sugarcane burnt but it was not me
that was the biggest problem we have
also we got some problems as to how each
one give us to the agency the place as
well here is my twenty percent i will
not burn here are my thirty percent here
my fifty percent how we make it in the
maps it was a
little hard to do but
it went but never we had an opposition i
want to to
continue burning we have no
judicial plane i want to to burn because
i have the right to burn it was almost
impossible for one to win a civil
erection with this but we have no head
no
so
we got no opposition
it was a
case of success all this is
i believe some power statement must be
very proud
uh
so the agency as the the sugarcane
sector that we do the right thing like
this
what a note and um that is our time for
today and i want to thank our panelists
we are so honored by your president by
your presence such incredible insight
just knowledge that you've shared here
today
and of course our moderators nadia
sussman and lulu ramadan thank you so
much for navigating us through this
complex uh discussion
i'd like to give a special thank you to
mckinsey and company for support of
today's event and of course to our
partners the palm beach post and wlrn
thank you to our audience for joining us
and all of your thoughtful questions
that you've submitted today again this
event has been recorded so you'll
receive an email with the full video of
today's events we'll also be posting the
recording on the propublica youtube
channel and from all of us of republica
thank you so much for joining us this
evening have a great rest of your night
and we hope to see you at our next event
thank you take care everyone