[Music]
and my life.
Namaste and welcome to the video course
on watershed management. Today in module
two on sustainable watershed approach
and watershed management practices. In
lecture number five, we will discuss
about the agriculture practices and
watershed management.
So the topics covered in today's lecture
includes watershed ecology and
agroecosystems, soil and water
conservation management practices,
sustainable land management practices,
crop management, nutrients and pest
management, integrated farming, and
finally a case study. Some of the
important keywords in today's lecture
include agroecosystems,
agriculture management, nutrient and
pest management and integrated farming.
So as we discussed in earlier lectures
like sustainable water management or
sustainable land management or uh the
sustainability issues are all very
important in in watershed management. So
uh in in any of the waterershed which we
consider one of the important land use
is the agriculture. So we have to see
what are the important issues as far as
the uh agricultural management is
concerned. What are the important issues
in sustainable agriculture management.
So uh as far as watershed uh in many
parts of the world are concerned uh
watersheds are experiencing pressure
from high population growth, climate,
land use change and overexploitations of
natural resources. So you can see the
effect of population growth and then the
land use change all these are directly
influencing the agricultural practices
uh within the watershed. So as we
discussed earlier to stop the
degradation of natural resources and to
understand the sustainable agriculture
management practices we need to deal
with upstream and downstream resources
management challenges. So what are the
major challenges within the waterershed
as far as various resources are
concerned how we deal with the uh the
management of those resources. Then uh
the sustainable agriculture management
is concerned. Uh we have to deal with
the uh to identify sustainable land use
practices to increase sustainable
agriculture production uh and to
increase opportunity of rural
livelihood. So we can see that in most
of the the uh areas the rural people are
living mainly based upon the
agricultural or the farm outputs. So we
have to improve this farm output in a
sustainable way. So uh for that on a
watershed basis we have to see that the
agriculture is sustaining and then the
the the land use is sustainable and
water use is sustainable. So uh within
that we have to see that how we can have
better uh agricultural or agriculture
water management or agricultural
practices. So let us see some of the
issues as far as water management in
agriculture is concerned. So this uh
deals with the interactions and
interplay between food, people and
nature sectors. So we have already seen
earlier when we discussed about the
sustainability issues. So the important
sectors are food, people and nature. So
out of this the food sector produces
biomass and influence ecosystem most of
the time positively and sometimes
negatively.
So you can see that as far as
agriculture is concerned the water is
concerned major use is consumptive. So
this is uh can be directly through
irrigation or otherwise. So as far as
irrigation is concerned there can be
major or micro irrigation and many times
farmers use excessive irrigation and say
this irriated water
are largely uh recycled. Then some of
the other issues like use of fertilizers
and pesticides and then corresponding uh
problems like non-point source of
pollution in the water either surface or
groundwater. So like this we can see
that agricultural water use is concerned
a large number of issues are there which
we have to deal um as far as the
particular watershed is concerned or
waterershed management is concerned. So
uh you can see that when we consider the
the three sectors like food people and
nature. So the requirement of water for
the people is relatively small. uh so uh
you can see that say for example if you
can see 1 cm per hectare per day for as
far as irrigation water is concerned
that much water is sufficient for uh
thousand people domestic or other
usages. So if you consider say the world
average as far as agricultural municipal
and industrial water usage is concerned
the ratio is 70 to 15 to 15%. But say
for example in developing country like
India this usage is 85% for agricultural
uh only 8% for municipal use and 7% for
uh industrial sector. So that way you
can see that say for example in a
country like India major portion of the
water is used for agriculture purposes.
So if we can save uh the water available
water say by doing appropriate
agriculture management practices
effective water use in agriculture then
we can save lot of water. So uh but you
can see that in most of the time
whenever uh we consider the farming
sector for a sustainable agriculture we
need irrigation since as we discussed
earlier the rainfall is
say distributed only for say four or
five months. So time wise variation is
there then special wise variation is
there. So that way we need um regression
for sustainable agriculture. uh so that
way if you consider say for example the
global withdrawal of water for
agriculture industry and municipal use
and then its total use uh in liter say
for example the data from 1900 to 1995
for about 95 years you can see that uh
this uh curve shows the total withdrawal
and then you can see that this just
below this this curve shows the
agricultural withdrawal and the
municipal usage usage age is much
smaller. This white line shows the
municipal usage and then this gray line
shows the industrial usage. But
especially in agriculture lot of water
is lost in different ways. So that way
with respect to the total withdrawal you
can see that the effective
water the total water usage is much much
less compared to the total withdrawal.
So that way if we can save the water
which we are using for agriculture by
appropriate management practices approp
optimal irrigation management practices
we can save lot of water and that can be
utilized for many other purposes and
then also we can use say for for example
for further irrigation and other
purposes. So if you consider a world
average the world average for irrigation
is concerned irrigated area covers about
40% of arable lands in the world and
rainfford is the rest that means about
60% of the uh arable land in the world
is say the water is obtained through
rain and only 40% is obtained through uh
irrigation. Say for example now if you
consider India's agriculture scenario
and irrigation is concerned uh so India
has about 2% of world's land 4% of fresh
water 16% of population and 10% of its
cattle so this is the the major issue as
far as a developing country like India
is concerned we have only 2% of ranch uh
but we have 16% of population and then
10% of cattle and only hardly 4% % of
fresh water and the geographic areas
concerned
say India's 329 million hectare of area
of which only 47% is cultivated 23 23%
is is forested and 7% under
non-aggriculture usage and about 23% of
the land is wasteland
and uh if you consider with respect the
population the land availability is
concerned per capita availability of
land 50 years ago that means In about
1950s it was about 0.9 hectare but now
due to the population explosion uh this
will be reduced to about.14 hectare by
2050. So that way the land availability
compared to any other country it is much
much smaller. So that way India is a
major problem as far as the the the
sustainable practices as far as land um
water and agriculture is concerned. So
whatever available we have to do it in a
better way and out of the cultivated
area in India uh about 47 40% is
irrigated which produces about 55% of
the food requirement of the country and
60% is rainfford producing uh about 47
45%
of about 250 metric ton of food required
presently. So you can see that 40% of
the reated area produces 55% of the food
and 60% of rainfed area only produces
45% of the the 250 metric t of food
produced. So in 40 years say for example
by 2050 uh say government of India wants
to increase the reation level such such
that we can have more food production.
So the irrigation we we want to increase
up to at least up to 50% so that 50% is
um irrigated area and 50% is of the
arable land is um the rainfford area so
that that ratio of food production 75%
can be produced from reed land and 25%
from the rainfford land for out of the
500 metric t of food required by uh
2050. So this is the Indian scenario as
far as the the agriculture and uh
irrigation requirement uh is concerned.
So now uh let us see what are some of
the uh the agriculture related issues as
far as um especially India is concerned.
So uh in India after the independence in
uh there is
large increase in agricultural growth
rate. Say for example in the 1950s if it
was about.3% 60s and 70s or 80s it has
increased to 3.5%. So this has mainly
happened due to a large number of
irriation or reservoir projects
implemented in the earlier five-year
plans. So that way the irriation
capacity has increased and that way the
agricultural growth has increased. So
then another important issue is say say
in the la the first first few five year
plans say in 70s and 80s government of
India put a lot of efforts to uh improve
the agriculture sector through
introduction of new high yielding
varieties that is say we can call it as
first green revolution in ' 70s and then
in second green revolution say in ' 80s
uh government of India through its
agriculture and other ministries concent
center on the genetic engineering uh
through organized input management and u
say farmer services and extension and
then also um better seed varieties were
implemented in the agriculture sector.
So that way we can call this um say
1980s as second green revolution. So
that way lot of improvement were taken
place in the agriculture sector but of
course lot of issues are still there uh
in the agriculture sector. So some of
the negative trends in spite of the
positive trends as we discussed here the
negative trends are say per hector yield
is low. So compared to other countries
like uh USA and China the per hector
yield is much lower. Then infrastructure
facilities in the farming sector sector
are concerned are poor. Then uh say the
uh total management aspect is neglected
in most of the farming sector. And then
also uh you can see that still in rural
area
the farming is not mechanized. So people
are using different types of traditional
equipments for farming and then say most
of the time the rural farmers are not
adopting scientific farming. uh so that
way uh say lot of issues are there as
far as the agriculture in India is
concerned.
So uh some of the important constraint
as far as agriculture
sustainable agriculture India are
concerned are listed here. So these are
decline in per capita land availability.
So as we already discussed that per
capita land availability is decreasing
due to population explosion. Then stress
in water resources. So available water
uh is not sufficient for irrigation um
due to lack of um say better agriculture
management practices, water management
practices or lack of availability of
sufficient water. Then degradation of
soils, the lack of efficient water
management, uh monocropping in many
areas farmers are with the same crop. So
that way uh there are lot of problems as
far as nutrient management and then
other soil related issues are concerned.
Then lack of crop management um
negligence of sustainable agriculture.
So um say as far as especially most of
the farmers are concerned they are not
bothered about the sustainability issues
as far as agriculture is concerned. And
then of course people's a that means the
farmers are indifferent to various the
scientific farming or mechanization and
other issues due to of course various
other constraints um the due to lack of
availabable resources or due to lack of
education and other issues. So that way
these are some of the important issues
especially in a country like India as
far as sustainable agricultural
management practices are concerned.
So now let us see the water the
agriculture management practices within
the perspective of watershed. So the we
have already seen that uh agriculture
practices are very important in in any
of the watershed management plans. So uh
the agricultural practices
following within a watershed uh the the
the whatever waterershed plans or
management issues we are making. So that
will definitely uh affect. So that way
let us discuss about the watershed
ecohydrology and agroecosystems.
So this agroecosystems uh we can define
as a subset of ecosystems
that defines functional uh
representation of coherent agricultural
activity uh including interaction of
living and non-living components
involved uh within the uh watershed. So
we are considering a subset of the
ecosystems as agroecosystems.
uh then we can do various sonation
according to the the ecology according
to agriculture practices and the climate
system. So that way we can call these
zones as agroecological zones which are
defined as uh land units carved out of
agroclimatic zones based on major
climate superimposed on length of
growing period. So so particular crop is
concerned a particular uh say climate
season is concerned. So accordingly we
can say define this agroecological
zones. So this mainly depends up on the
moisture availability. Say for example
India is concerned we can classify uh
India into 20 agroecological regions and
60 agroeco sub regions. So as we defined
here agroecological zones indicate uh
the various uh issues as far as the
agriculture is concerned with respect to
land with respect to climate and other
issues. So each agro eco sub region has
further been classified into eco unit at
district level for developing long-term
land use strategies. So when we
discussed about the sustainable
agriculture practices these
agroecosystem or agroecological zones
are very important since we can
implement or we can sort out many issues
uh by considering these agroecological
zones or agroecological
uh sub regions as we discussed. So here
in this slide you can see the
agroecological regions of India. So
these various colors indicate various
zones. So these zones are delineated
based on physioraphy, soil, u length of
growing season and bioclimate of the
region. Say for example we can say uh
the agriculture ministry has put various
nominal culture also. So for example a
zone means say a son is called aer zone.
So there the it is numbered as A13 EH1 A
stands for physioraphy 13 stands for
soil scale. EH stands for bioclimatic
zone and one st stands for length of
growing period. So that way we can put
various agroecological
zones. Uh so AE zone A13 EH1 is referred
as western Himalayas here. So the some
of the important characteristics of the
zones shallow skelectal soils hyper
climates with the length of growing
period less than uh 60 days. So that way
by by considering this agroecological
zones uh we can uh look into various um
sustainable agricultural practices or
issues and then we can go for planning
and management. It can be watershed
based planning and management but by
considering these type of zones we can
implement or we can have various plans.
So as we discussed so what are the
necessities or what are the need of
agricological classification. So the
needs are listed here. Uh to assess
yield potentialities of different crops,
crop combination in agroecological
regions or zones. Then to formulate
future plan of action involving crop
diversification to disseminate uh
agricultural uh research and agro
technology to other homogeneous areas.
And then to determine the crop
suitability for optimization of land use
in different agroecological regions or
zones. So as we discussed so this
agroecological region or zones um uh say
indicates say what kind of crops say
what kind of climate
climatic region or what kind of soil
pattern is there then we can put plants
say like what kind of crops can be grown
there what should be the crop period
length so like that various issue can be
put according to the agricological ical
classification or agricological zones or
regions and then we can come up with the
plans as far as sustainable agriculture
practices are concerned.
So now uh as far as sustainable
agriculture practices are concerned soil
conservation and water conservations are
two important issues. So let us look
into some of the important principles
and issues as far as soil and water
conservation are concerned. So soil
conservation important principles are
based upon rainfall of high intensity
then erosion of top fertile soil takes
place. So we have to stop this soil
erosion. So that is uh uh the so by
various practices we can reduce the soil
erosion. So that is the so-called soil
conservation. So we can have uh various
measures like condor farming and then
say
we can plant trees or grass to reduce
the soil conservation. So various
measures are measures are possible like
biological measures like a conservation
tillage deep conservation farming and we
can go for mechanical measures like
terasing uh water disposal uh other low
cost measures. So like shown here we can
say reduce the soil erosion and we can
go for soil conservation using uh
various uh techniques. So then as far as
water conservation is concerned the
principle of the water conservation is
say where precipitation is less than
crop requirements what what we have to
do. So uh then where precipitation is
equal to crop requirement or where
precipitation is in excess of crop
requirements. So accordingly uh these
three classes we can uh have a
particular um say intervention or
particular uh strategy uh say according
to the the climatic or rainfall
conditions. So in the first case where
precipitation is less than crop
requirement the strategy includes land
treatment to increase runoff onto
cropped areas uh following water
conservation use of drought tolerant
crops uh suitable managing practices. So
this is when the precipitation is less
than crop requirement. Then second case
where precipitation is equal to crop
requirement. So the strategy is local
conservation of precipitation maximizing
storage within the soil profile and
storage of excess runoff for subsequent
use. So this is when precipitation is
almost equal to what is required as far
as crop requirements are concerned. And
then the third case uh where
precipitation is in excess of crop
requirements the strategy is to reduce
uh rainfall erosion to drain surplus
runoff and store the surplus water for
subsequent uh use in summer season. So
this way as far as uh water conservation
is concerned we can uh make particular
strategy depending upon the region
depending upon the case. Uh we can have
either whenever precipitation is less
than crop requirement or whenever
precipitation uh is almost equal to crop
requirement or when precipitation is in
excess of crop requirement. So
accordingly uh we can go for particular
strategy as far as water conservation is
concerned. So now uh based upon uh these
issues now let us uh discuss the
sustainable land management practices.
So we have seen the for to achieve
sustainable agriculture practices um we
need to go for sustainable land
management practices. So uh sustainable
land management practices
that gives um knowledge based it is a
knowledge based system which helps to
integrate land water biodiversity and
environmental management to meet rising
food and fiber demands while sustaining
ecosystem services and livelihood to
meet requirements for the growing
population. So we can uh define the
sustainable land management like this.
So it is a holistic way of sustainable
approach as far as land water uh
biodiversity environmental management
and then uh say the requirement as far
as the growing population is concerned.
So this sustainable land management or
SLM enhances the productive capabilities
of land in crop and grazed area. So if
you consider the various issues
appropriately and we can increase uh the
productivity uh the crop yield and then
forest forestry can be improved or the
the grass land or grazed area can be
imbroved. So through sustainable land
management uh we can have actions to
stop reversed degradation or at least to
mitigate adverse effects of uh earlier
misuses. So whenever we discussed about
the waterershed deterioration issues and
related problems uh we have seen that uh
say here say the waterershed will be
degraded say by various problems various
issues as we discussed earlier. So uh
through sustainable land management
practices we can at least uh reduce what
is happening and then also we can
reverse the trends so that uh we can
have same overall uh sustainable uh
development. So now let us look into
what are the objectives as far as
sustainable land management practice are
concerned. Some of the important
objectives are listed here to increase
land productivity. So that means
replenish soil nutrients uh by lying or
other means uh and then maintain soil
cover. So like cover we can use cover
crops and residue recycling. And the
second objective is to provide adequate
quantity of water. So there is no
scarcity of water. So we can use crop
forage or tree species with higher water
use efficiency. So that depending upon
the uh available water uh we can uh go
for uh say water resource management
using particular crop then to maintain
water quality. So water quality is also
an issue. So uh here we can protect
vegetative filter areas in the
repairarian zones to remove excess
sediment and nutrients and then also the
non-boyant source of pollutions all
those we can reduce and then uh third
objective is to reduce flooding and
flood damage. So as we discussed earlier
flooding is always a problem. So we can
through sustainable agriculture
management practices or sustainable land
management practices we can plant deep
rooted weightation to enhance
infiltration and water consumption by
the plants and this also may decrease
the soil erosion problems. So these are
some of the important objectives as far
as sustainable uh land management
practice are concerned. So now uh let us
look into the sustainable agriculture
issues. So first one is the the crop
husbandry. So crop husbandry means the
practices of uh growing and harvesting
crops uh based upon scientific
principles and careful management and
conservations of uh resources. So
whenever the the the cropping pattern so
we have to consider the cropping pattern
what type of crop is to be used then the
various issues uh say as far as soil is
concerned water is concerned and then uh
the
the health of the crop is concerned. So
here the crop husbandry includes soil
enri en enrichments
usage of hybrid and improved seeds and
better cropping pattern. So some of the
techniques used for improved crop
productions include uh soil enrichments
by bofertilization.
Uh then introduction of micronutrient
management uh then usage of hybrid seeds
uh achieving optimum plant population so
that better production will be there.
Then timely and effective we control. So
we say in agricultural practices we be
control is very important. So we have to
timely do the we control then pest
management. So these are some of the uh
important techniques which we can
utilize in crop husbandry so that we can
achieve sustainable uh agricultural
practices as far as various uh crop
management or crop husbandry is uh
concerned.
Then uh the next issue in sustainable
agriculture is nutrient management. Uh
so as far as nutrient management is
concerned uh it is important to tackle
problems like use of inorganic
fertilizers. So last few decades farmers
are using lot of inorganic fertilizers
like ura then phosphates
like that. So whenever we use
without say optimal use or without
scientific
say knowledge then what happens is that
it decrease the soil fertility and then
also it become a pollution source as far
as soil and water is concerned. So then
other issues as far as nutrient
management is concerned to stop uh we
growth uh to avoid crop diseases uh
improve crop yield. So these are the uh
the main uh issues as far as nutrient
management is concerned. Then as far as
nutrient management is concerned, it
includes uh disseminate knowledge of
nutrient and its function to plant
growth. uh so most of the time say in a
country like India the farmers are not
well educated so we can disseminate the
knowledge say why we had to study a
nutrient analysis as far as particular
area particular waterershed is concerned
and then how to improve the nutrient
say in the soil so we can disseminate
the knowledge and then its function say
in plant growth as far as nutrient
management is concerned. Then assessment
of nutrient availability as far as the
waterershed is concerned and then
nutrient management like supply
deficient nutrients to the soil also
avoid excess use to protect the
environment. So as I discussed for
example the nitrate phosphate and then
sapotage nk is concerned. So you can see
that the last few decades um many areas
farmers are using this um uh this the
important nutrients like NPK. Uh so what
happens when it is overuse is there it
becomes uh an environmental problems and
when whenever underutilize underuse is
there so then it becomes a deficient
nutrient as far as the particular area
is concerned. So that way we should look
into an effective nutrient management as
far as a particular area or particular
waterershed is uh concerned.
Then let us further look into the
nutrient and its functions. So uh there
are two basic types of nutrients. One is
so called macronutrients. So these
macronutrients
are available in soil in large larger
percentage. So for example nitrogen,
phosphorus, potassium, uh sulfur,
calcium, magnesium etc. Uh so then other
one is so-alled micronutrients. So this
is available in soil in minute percent
uh percentage. So like um iron, copper,
zinc, manganesees
etc. So that way uh this depending upon
the requirement for the particular crop
say depending upon the availability of
that particular nutrient for the
particular area we have to uh provide
that particular nutrients um to the soil
so that the crops can grow in a healthy
way and it can give better yields. So
appropriate nutrient management is uh
very important.
Then let us look into what are the
important functions of nutrient. So some
of the important functions are listed
here. Uh these are it include an
involvement in photosynthesis and produ
produces uh carbohydrates.
Then early root formation and growth. uh
then nutrient helps plants to survive in
uh bitter environmental conditions like
um the environmental conditions like um
drought area or the increased saline
area. So like that so the nutrients can
helps plants to survive in this
particular areas. Then increasing uh
water use efficiency. So if you give
appropriate nutrients
appropriate levels to the plants or to
the soil then we can even increase the
water use efficiency and then important
role in reproduction of plants. So these
are some of the important functions as
far as nutrient is concerned. So we
should have better nutrient management
plans as far as the particular area or
particular waterershed is uh concerned.
uh so then uh say particular area is
concerned we should assess the nutrient
availability and then uh we have to
provide nutrients to the soil for the
particular crop is concerned. So the
various tests are possible as far as the
assessment of nutrients are concerned.
So some of the important tests are
listed here like traditional soil tests
uh including test like P for pH uh
nitrogen phosphorus potassium uh
electric conductivity etc. So this type
of test traditional soil test we can uh
perform uh in every 3 to 5 years so that
uh depending upon the the the non-avity
of this particular uh nutrients we can
provide these nutrients according to the
requirements. Then another important
test is called nitrous nitrate test. So
this uh involute the pre-planned nitrous
test for additional nitrogen uh deep
nitrate test how much nitrogen has
already less below the crop rooting
zone. So this test we can do and then
accordingly we can provide appropriate
um say nitrate treatment as far as the
soil is concerned.
Then next one is traditional plant test
like a chlorophyll meter to quickly
determine the nitrogen status without
destroying any uh plant tissues and then
also uh we can go for irriation water
test and then electric conductivity and
pH test. So these are some of the tests
used to assess the nutrients available
for the particular area particular soil
for particular c crop growth. So then
accordingly we can go for nutrient
management by supplying uh appropriate
nutrients and appropriate levels or
appropriate measures to particular area
for the uh given uh crop. So now another
important issue in sustainable
agriculture management is uh pest
management. So the pest management the
main object objective is to uh say how
pest management interlates with climate
uh water crop and soil management uh say
for farmers to understand. So the
farmers should understand how the the
pest management will help them then to
incorporate uh this pest management
techniques um and it's so its decision
making process as far as the farming is
concerned. So this is another important
issue. So some of the important
necessities as far as pest management is
concerned uh that include a critical
component of conservation practices. So
it is very important the pest management
the negative impacts of pesticides. So
if overuse is there then lot of issues
can be there. Uh then ground and surface
water deterioration due to non-point
source of um u source of pollution like
pesticide contamination. So this is a
very important issue as far as water and
soil is concerned. Then environmental
risk uh like um say for example uh
burning crop residue for disease and
then insect control. So these are the
necessities as far as the pest
management is concerned. So then for the
considered area considered crop we have
to go for appropriate uh pest management
as far as the the sustainable
agriculture management is concerned. Uh
then generally we use a term called
integrated uh pest management. Uh so IPM
so IPM approach is to uh to pest control
that combines biological uh cultural and
other alternatives to chemical control
with the judicious use of pesticides. So
instead of overuse or underuse of
pesticides we have to judiciously use
the pesticides by considering the
various biological cultural and uh other
chemical issues are concerned. So the
important goals of integrated pest
management uh includes uh maximum use of
naturally occurring control forces uh in
the pest environment. So particular area
particular crop is concerned we have to
consider whether uh we can control the
pest naturally. So if if it is not
possible only we have to go for
chemicals. Then first focus on
non-chemical measures. So whether
biologically or with say natural control
whether we can reduce the pest. So first
focus is on non-chemical measures. Then
use of chemical pesticides only for
preventing severe damage. So as far as
particular uh farm is concerned or
particular agriculture is concerned. So
we go for indicated pest management so
that um to reduce of course the damages
due to the pest but um we have to see
that um whether without non-chemical
measures whether we can reduce the pest
problem and then if chemical measures to
be adopted then it should be in a
controlled way so that uh there are very
less environmental problems so that we
can achieve sustainable agricultural
management for the particular area is
concerned.
So now finally let us look into what are
the important issues uh as far as
sustainable agricultural management
practices are concerned. So some of the
important issues are listed here. First
one is uh biomass management. So for the
particular area uh what kind of crop is
to be considered for the particular
region and particular area depending
upon the soil depending upon the water
availability and also uh like crop
rotation. Then second
issue is concerned better conservation
practices as far as land and water is
concerned land and water concerned we
have to go for better conservation
practices. Then uh conservation buffers.
So for sustainable to achieve
sustainable agricultural management we
can uh consider uh conservation buffers
like forest buffers at particular area
and then grass waterway uh then we can
go for filter strip then vegetative
barriers then conservation barrier for
wind etc. So various conservation
buffers we can consider
for the particular watershed or
particular area is concerned to achieve
sustainable agriculture management. Then
as we discussed earlier we can go for
crop husbandry by considering the
various crop management practice or
concerns. Then uh we can go for nutrient
management. So as we discussed in the
previous slides nutrient is very
important. So we should not overuse and
we should provide sufficient nutrients
as far as the particular area or
particular crop is concerned. So
nutrient management is very important in
uh sustainable agricultural practices.
Then integrated pest management. So
first we have to see whether we can go
for pest control without chemical use
and if chemical use is required then we
should go for on a scientific way
controlled way. Then of course as far as
sustainable agriculture practice are
concerned we can go for modern
technology like molecular biology uh
then and genetic engineering. So now
these two branches of science like
molecular biology and genetic
engineering uh have been grown um
consider considerably in the last few
decades. So uh the expert expert the the
scientific
uh it's a availability of this uh
molecular biology and genetic
engineering or its practices. Uh through
its practices we can have better
sustainable agricultural management. We
can go for uh say for example seeds are
concerned we can go for hybrid and
imbrove seeds and then we can go for
tissue culture. you can go for uh say uh
hybrid varieties. So like that uh
various uh things various due to the
development uh in molecular biology and
genetic engineering we can uh use the
the various available technique uh
techniques uh for sustainable
agricultural or agriculture management
uh is concerned.
So now uh another important issue in
sustainable agriculture management is um
whether we can go for integrated farming
system. So uh say integrated farming
system or IFS some of the issues are
listed here in this slide. So uh say for
example mixed farming system we can go
for mixed farming system. So mixes
farming system combines crop and
livestocks enterprises in a
supplementary and or or a complimentary
manner. So uh for a particular watershed
or particular areas concerns
uh it is not only crop we can have a
integrated uh way of saying mixer
farming as far as crop is concerned as
far as um livestocks
are concerned. So we can combine
together so that we can have
better
say economical achievements as far as
the watershed is concerned. So
integrated farming system means
integration of uh various agricultural
enterprises uh like cropping uh animal
husbandry fisheries forestry etc. uh so
so that we can have uh better economical
achievements as far as the particular
area is concerned uh and this gives
great potentialities uh in the
agricultural economy. So some of the
important components of integrated
farming system includes uh crops,
livestock, birds and trees. Uh so uh
depending upon the area say for example
crop is concerned uh we can have a
monocrop that means only one type of
crop or a mixed uh or ind crop and then
multi-ter crops of cereals legumes or
pulses and oil seeds forage etc. So crop
is concerned we can have not only
monocropping we can have different crops
together. Say for example say wherever
coconut farming is there with the
coconut we can go for say we can grow
pepper. So like that various crops can
be combined
with within the given area so that the
farmers um can have
more products and better benefits from
their particular farms. So the main
motto of integrated uh farming system is
maximize food production and then
overall development of a waterershed. So
uh say by integrated farming we can
achieve uh say uh overall development of
the area since the farmers will have um
say better profits since v through
various crops in the same area so that
we can maximize the uh food production
and maximize the benefits.
Then integrated farming system is
concerned. Some other uh same issues
like uh indropping, mixer cropping,
strict crop cropping. So as far as crops
are concerned, we can have uh three ways
of integrated farming. First one is
indropping. So here crops are grown in
space available in between the plants.
Say for example, turmeric can be grown
in mango gardens. Uh so like that say uh
some crops will be already growing like
this. You can see that here the in the
mango garden here mangoes are growing
and then here other types of crops. So
this is so called inter cropping. Then
second one is mixer cropping. So here
alternative rows of different crops we
can use so that say we can improve the
crop yields then preserve soil
fertility. Then the third one is strip
cropping where long strips are used for
growing crops on leveled birds. So like
this as far as integrated farming is
concerned cropping is concerned we can
have intercropping mixer cropping and
strip cropping. So like this uh say by
using integrated farming system we can
achieve sustainable agriculture
practices or sustainable agriculture
management for the uh given uh
watershed. So within the perspective of
what we discussed today sustainable
agriculture management practice are
concerned let us look into a case study.
So the case study is Adasha water
studies in Kotaprai village in Andhra
Pradesh. uh it is spread to over 465
hectares and uh the uh say an indicated
water management plan based upon
sustainable agriculture has been done by
in this area. So the details are taken
from these website details are available
in this website.
So the main objective of uh this um uh
watershed intervention uh was to link
strategic research in natural resource
management with the development research
to increase productivity uh of rainfood
agriculture through enhanced efficiency
of natural resources while maintaining
the uh resource base. So this was the
main objective as far as the waterershed
intervention in Adasha waterershed. So
uh finally uh through this uh the aim
was to increase um the productivity
through adoption of improved soil water
nutrients and pest management as far as
the area is concerned. So the area is
shown here it is taken from this
website. So the important strategy in
this watershed uh was to link uh the
research with waterershed development
schemes to enhance effectiveness of uh
community participation and in this
watershed a multi-disiplinary
multi-institutional
um consortium approach has been utilized
uh and various developmental projects
were implemented by research in this
area. So they used an islanding approach
uh through micro waterershed as upfront
demonstrations
managed by farmers with technical
backups. So uh technical advice given by
in this area and then uh say the farmers
implemented these projects
then the uh the watershed is concerned
onfarmm strategic research was conducted
by Chris in partnership with the
farmers. So some of the important
watershed details are uh said 270
farmers out of which uh in this area 136
are small land holding uh up to one
hectare and 60 are medium land holding
and 74 large land holding about two
hectares. Uh so this as far as the
distribution of land holding as far as
farmers are concerned in the Adasha
waterershed. Then u some of the other
watershed details like annual uh
rainfall is about um 800 mm uh say 85%
of it occurs during June October. So
soils are predominantly black soils in
this area. Soil depth varies from 30 to
90 cm. Uh the general slope of the land
is about 3%. And some of the important
crops grown include sorghum, mice,
cotton, sunflower, PG&P, soya bean in
rainy season and sorghum uh sunflower
vegetables in post- rainy season under
rainfford condition. And then in some
areas um say the the farmers grow
turmeric, onion and rice cultivation
depending upon the uh water availability
and then uh irrigation. So all these uh
details were taken from the cryat
website.
So let us look look into what are the
important interventions done by the
therat authorities. So here they they
conducted a complete resource mapping as
a first step and then they identified
the various problems as far as the
waterershed is concerned. They discussed
the various issues with the farmers. So
uh some of the interventions done by
chroat include continuous weather
monitoring. Uh they implemented a number
of automatic weather stations in the
regions and then uh say conducted
scientific soil analysis. So that soil
according to the soil analysis the soil
has been classified uh and then they
identified which type of soil is
suitable for particular crops.
Then uh also a cropping system analysis
has been carried out. So that how much
crop yield is possible then what is the
cost for farming and then what will be
the uh benefits from the particular uh
crop in the particular area. Then
cropping has been uh done according to
soil. uh then uh the cost effectiveness
of particular cropping has been also
analyzed
so that um uh whether say better crop
yield can be achieved through various
measures.
Then another aspect which has been
implemented in this watershed is
intercropping.
So we have already seen what is
intercropping. It is not only one crop
various crops were uh same done in the
same area. Then use of nitrogen fixing
plants. So that uh so instead of
providing uh say nitrogen through
artificial fertilizers. So if the
nitrogen fixing plants um give nitrogen
to the soil. So this has been
implemented. Then ver composting then
organic farming. So all those things
were done in this particular
waterershed. So also integrated pest
control uh through natural control
measures were implemented in this
watershed. So that was one another
important aspect of uh the success in
this um uh watershed. So then finally
the cryat or the nos's
uh carried out capacity building and
then they gave a training to farmers so
that farmers know what kind of cropping
to be done and what particular area and
then uh say scientific way of farming
then by using soil testing and then then
nutrient management then integrated pest
management. So these are some of the
important watershed interventions done
in this watershed. So then now let us
look what are the important impacts of
this measures interventions done by the
theat in this adasha waterershed. So uh
the analysis showed that crop yield
considerably improved in many of the
areas then considerable improvement in
water vability including groundwater. So
they implemented rainwater harvesting
also in this area. So that improved the
water availability for the area. Then in
integrated nutrient and pest management
were carried out. So that way farmers
are using um very less artificial uh
fert fertilizers
uh but they go for organic fertilizers
and then better nutrient management and
then they go for u better say uh
scientific pest control and natural pest
control instead of going for uh say
chemical
say using chemicals for pest. management
then continuous monitoring. So as far as
the watershed is concerned it was
monitored using remote sensing and then
GIS platform has been also used for uh
overall better management. Then holistic
watershed management uh the holistic
approach as far as land water
agriculture and people are concerned. So
that way a holistic development approach
has been uh um say done in this
particular watershed. Then this
watershed has been declared as a role
model of integrated sustainable
watershed management through sustainable
agriculture management by various
agencies. And then so this has been
replicated in many villages in India and
abroad. So another important aspect in
this watershed is capac city building
and training has been given by the NOS's
to the people. uh so people
participation was another important
aspect and then overall socioeconomic
upliftment has been taken place uh in
this watershed through uh various
interventions. Uh so as far as this
today's lecture is concerned some of the
important uh reference are listed here
including uh various uh websites.
Then based upon today's lecture uh here
I have listed uh one tutorial question.
So the question is illustrate necessity
of sustainable agriculture management uh
practices as far as overall waterershed
management plans are concerned. So uh
you can do through a systematic approach
some of the steps are mentioned here. So
identify the components then uh uh the
possible scientific interventions as far
as the agriculture management practice
concerns then identify the problems then
identify the role of uh uh modern
techniques like molecular biology and
genetic engineering. Uh then uh
importance of nutrient management then
role of indicator pest management. So uh
most of these issues we have discussed
in the lecture.
Then uh some of the self evaluation
questions from today's lectures lecture
are listed here. Uh first one is discuss
agriculture water use and compare world
and Indian scenarios. Uh second question
is what are the major constraints in
achieving watershed based sustainable
agriculture management. Then discuss the
agroecological classifications in India
and its importance. then illustrate
sustainable land management practices.
So uh for most of these questions the
details are available uh in today's
lecture.
Then a few assignment questions discuss
Indian agriculture and irrigation
scenarios. Then explain waterershed
ecology and agro systems. Then explain
important uh issues in soil and water
conservation. then discuss uh importance
of nutrient and integrated pest
management and related issues. So most
of these questions can be answered uh
based on today's lecture. So finally one
unsolved problem is uh listed here for
your waterershed area. Study the scope
for integrated farming systems in your
area. So this uh we can do in a
step-by-step procedure. So first you can
identify the suitable integrated farming
system practices for the area for
integrated uh sustainable agriculture
management. Uh then carry out
stakeholder analysis uh consider
traditional practices of the farmers.
You can go to the field and discuss with
the farmers and identify then suggest
scientific methods uh various
methodologies how we can go for uh
integrated farming systems. Then
identify soil and water conservation
measures for the area. Then identify
proper monitoring and evaluation
strategies for the area and uh involve
how we can involve the local people uh
to achieve indicated farming systems for
the uh given watershed. So this is you
can do it as an unsolved problem. So
this is uh today's lecture we discussed
about the uh sustainable agricultural
management practices and then its
important uh importance in water
management. U so we'll discuss further
the variable various issues as far as uh
sustainable water management or
sustainable waterershed management
issues are concerned in the uh next
lecture. Thank you.
And my
[Music]