well folks there's some things I'm just
not very good at and I still show you
anyways because uh I can stand to learn
a thing or two and I don't know probably
some of you guys can too and then the
folks that know how to do it out there
can give us some pointers and hopefully
improve but today I'm doing something
I've never done before and that is
actually plowing a field now I've tilled
many a field I have discs Fields never
plowed never turned soil like this
before and uh when you see the farmers
doing it they're doing big old tractors
but we've got a single bottom plow here
doing it on a little tractor just to see
how it does and it is a learning curve
and I think we did four rows and I think
by the fourth row
I was getting better at it
not great but um you got to listen to
your tractor first of all I mean there's
a lot of strain going on when you're
using a ground engaging tool like this
one here I was going too deep I wanted
to take a full depth pass with it but
it's just it's just not going to happen
with a small tractor like this just
doesn't quite have enough oomph and so I
was trying to find a sweet spot there
with it raised up a little bit and you
know trying to make sure the
it was level front to back and I tweaked
that with the hydraulic top link a
little bit here and there
and I could tell that when I was going
faster it was really letting that the
side and the soil kind of spill out and
roll over like I think you wanted to do
but there were times when it bogged out
and it was it was challenging to keep it
going that constant pace
which I think is pretty visible in the
video now this patch of grass here is
what we're going to turn into a food
plot or a part of a food plot here later
this summer for the deer we had Jeff
Sturgis out with Whitetail habitat
Solutions and we've been talking about
him a bit and that's a lot of what we're
doing is putting his plan into place out
here with the intent of making it better
deer hunting and that it's not for
everybody but that's one of the reasons
I bought the property and it's um it's a
lot of fun to kind of do this stuff and
so while my results today are probably
not ideal keep in mind it's my first
time doing it only four passes and each
pass is getting better and I think it's
going to make good results in the end
here turn the soil over I don't know if
it's ever been turned before this was a
pasture for cattle
previously with the prior owner that
lived here and um
it's a good chance to try out a new tool
with the summit tx25 tractor iron craft
we've been talking about them lately
they're a new partner and manufacturer
that we're working with where you see
something on their website you can buy
it through us
we're going to have it shipped right out
to you
and this single bottom plow here really
caught my eye get a decent amount of
requests for a tool like this for
smaller tractors they make a double
bottom or a two bottom pile as well
and so I was really curious to see how
it worked a few things about this iron
craft plow one of the
the first things that I was looking for
a feature when I looked for anything is
going to be if it's quick it's
compatible and this was not quick hitch
compatible but the reason for that
was legitimate and so the reason it's
not quick hitch compatible is that well
that first row you're on level ground
you know both the left and the right
side you're on level ground that's just
fine but after that you're putting your
right tires down in that Furrow that you
had just plowed out and so the tractor
is leaning and just the geometry of
everything you need to be able to
offset and use your side lengths to
rotate everything
and get the plow level even though the
tractor's out of level it's kind of an
awkward thing but it makes sense once
you visually see it happening and so
that's the reason it's not quick hitch
compatible there it is sheer bolt
protected so if you whack something you
know a big root or a big rock or
something on the ground it does have
that shear bolt protection on there so
that will break right off and protect
the rest of the three-point hits the
rest of the tractor from something
catastrophic happening to it we didn't
have that happen here yet I would be
surprised if it does happen we have
pretty good soil that we're working with
in our area in Southwest Michigan and so
it is rated for tractors in this
horsepower range you know the 25
horsepower range that we're using on the
summit but it is near the low end of
that and
I think it's suitable for it as long as
you're not taking a full depth
pass with it that's going to be where
you're struggling down is becoming
really unusable at that point they do
make deeper plows as well in both the
single bottom and the two bottom uh plow
on there too so you can get different
setups for different size machines out
there to suit your needs but you can see
similar to a long time ago when we used
a dirt dog subsoiler
these these tools that go down to the
ground they require a lot of horsepower
not just that but then the weight to get
the traction to the ground as well and
even for that big 70 some horsepower
tractor that we had pulling the two
bottom sub soiler it was just about
everything I had to pull that thing
along and so it's it's not really a
knock on the tractors whether it's a
bigger a small one it's just that it's
just what you're asking it to do that's
a big job for it and a more extreme
scenario now we're going to be shooting
this area here into uh into some greens
some some brassicas and some buckwheat
and some radishes and all that kind of
stuff and making a big old food plot to
draw the deer into the center of our
property and then kind of hunt the
oh the travel corridors that kind of
come in from all the the bordering
properties around there and you know I
could have just sprayed this off and
disc and tilt it but I wanted to try
something new and see how it went and
I'm learning something different and
then someday the hope is to be able to
master this tool which is some tools are
easier to use than others and
this one is it's tough it was tough to
keep in a straight line when I on the
first pass when there wasn't anything to
follow along uh the whole tractor kind
of one almost turned sideways or angle a
little bit
the subsequent passes were easier to
follow that line because you're you're
right down in that row following along
but man it's not uh
it wasn't for the faint of heart but it
was a satisfying thing to do nonetheless
so I read somewhere online because I
don't know what I'm doing that you
should start in the middle of the area
you want to plow up and then kind of
work your way out from there just around
around the circle and so
I was like all right I'll go down in the
middle of this and then do that I'll
just go around in a circle and work my
way out from the center but as soon as I
got done with the first pass I was like
this doesn't make any sense because I'd
have to go over that huge mound in that
whole row there that has plowed and so
in hindsight I think I should have
started on on the outside
and then just worked my way over from I
guess what the right to the left but I I
think in my mind
you have to always come back and start
at the other end unless you just started
well you can work your way outside in I
suppose couldn't you you work your way
outside here and just keep going outside
and inside and to the inside of the
inside yeah I don't know some things my
brain's not working
right now but maybe that's a possibility
too anyways I'm sure you guys will fill
me in you won't let me off the hook
there
and that's okay because uh
I'm sitting in my tractor
having fun in the summer
playing with a new tool I'm not
complaining anyway so I got more work to
do more learning to do so I'm going to
get back to work and try to knock the
rest of this out but if you know what
you're doing or you want to figure this
tool out for yourself go to our website
you'll get more information pricing you
can place your order and if you're
looking for anything else for your
tractor for the front end loader or the
three-point hitch we're happy to help
you out we ship all over the country
every day of the week and for just about
every tool we sell we have videos of it
too so you can get a close-up of it see
what it's all about see it in action see
if it's the right tool for you for your
situation and your projects so I want to
thank you for taking time out of your
day to stop by and until next time stay
safe we'll see you soon
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
foreign foreign
[Applause]
[Music]