all right guys uh welcome back to this
channel uh if you're new please enable
you subscribe to this Channel and uh
check out for great content on this
channel of everything you need to know
about P farming profitable P farming and
not just Pi farming alone we'll still be
bringing to you lot of great content on
several other agricultural Venture well
in this video we want to talk about uh
the best breed for commercial Peak
farming what are the best breed you need
on your farm if you're going to run a
commercial Peak Farm this is a question
on the mind of several individuals and
uh because honestly I can tell you that
um if you can get it right with your
genetics with the right breed you are
50% good to go in your of course there
are other things to still pay attention
to but at least having uh the right
genetics plays a very big role in uh in
getting uh a good and a profitable pig
farm now uh first of all let me start
with saying that ensure that you don't
buy breeds that you don't know what they
are or what type of breeds they are make
sure any breed you get on your farm you
know exactly what they have I see that
how there lots of people just see pigs
and all that matters to them is just
that these are pigs and uh pigs are just
pigs and uh if pigs are pigs then we can
just get them I think that's the mindset
of of some people obviously because you
see that they just see p somewhere they
don't know their origin they don't know
their genetics and they just get them
that's a very poor way to start Peak
farming I would never advise you to
start your Peak farm with any breed you
don't know what they have what type of
breed they have don't get diminished
breed I've often said this on the farm
on sorry on this channel don't get
diminished breeds on your farm you are
starting with on the on the wrong tone
because those breeds will not convert
well for you make sure you get good
breits now this right on this video I'm
sure you can you can remember if you
have been watching this channel you can
remember uh certain uh time when we
release vide on these uh animals if I
want you to look at their sizes you'll
be so surprised this is less than a
month on this farm and you can see how
uh robust these guys are are so their
their conversion is so much is so
massive you know I've always told you
that the key to Pig farming is feeding
them right you need to feed your pigs
right these guys they they feing on the
what we more like the feeds that's
what they are on right here and I've
told you already that when you are
feeding your piglets especially your
piglets you want to feed them at libidum
and I explain to you that that means you
want to ensure that they always have
feet in their troughs that you can see
they just they keep eating and eating
when they want to drink water they get
to the nipple Drinker to drink water
they they go back there they they heat
as much as they need to heat this is
less than a month about less than a
month and they are so they have they've
grown so massive so to my own surprise
personally so this is the African uh
South African large white right here and
we got them from a very reputable Source
the woman is extremely diligent when it
comes to uh uh Pig farming you can if
you get to a farm you would love it so
much she did it very well she
constructed the pens very well and she's
not really growing pigs for fattening
she's doing them for she sells the
piglets majorly so these pigs were
gotten from the F so uh types of the
best breeds for you to use on for in
short best breeds for commercial Peak
farming now the top one that is most
common not just in Africa in this in the
in Africa but even around the world the
top one breed is the large white breed
large white breed is so common it's so
common and it's one of the Exotic uh
breed that uh is very good for uh
commercial Peak farming the large white
the large white uh in another video I
will tell you the characteristic of the
large white but the large white is uh
known for a very large liter size they
are very prolific they give bir to a lot
of to lots of piglet and uh they are
also you know they are strong they are
they they are resistant they have good
resistance so people it's so common lar
whes are so common this also are the
large white this is also the large white
right here this is the large white breed
we have here so I will tell you the
characteristics in subsequent videos
this is the large white so major majorly
on on this Farm is U the large white
breed now another uh the second uh breed
that is extremely very good for
commercial Peak Farm is the land the
landra pig is uh very good also for
commercial pig farm the land R uh and
the large white I would make a video to
tell you the difference between them and
which one you should prefer on in in in
stocking In Stocking them to your farm
so the large white number one the land
race number two the land R also is very
prolific and has uh it also Hardy that
means it's as good resistant so it's uh
it's very uh advised you can get the
large rise on your farm now another uh
breed that uh you can also get is the
Hamshire the Hamshire breed is also a
common breed that you can get now uh I'm
I'm seeing more of what I'm talking
about here is for the African
because uh you need to understand that
these breeds are majorly uh sometimes
suitable based on location there are
some of them that can work in almost any
location but not all of them there
certain breits you don't want to bring
to certain climates so but I'm talking
from the African side of things and
these are uh that's where I'm making
this video from but obviously we have
other different types of pig breed that
some may do very well in certain other
areas that uh may not do well in the
African side so so the large white the
land R the amsh that's uh those are
three breeds that I would really advise
you to think about if you want to get
into U Pig farming now there's a there's
one that uh I would really really advise
you should consider and that's the
tn70 the tn70 is one of the latest uh
Pig breed out there and when I say
latest I don't mean like yesterday but
you know it's one of the recent uh
modifications that occurred recently in
the Pak farming world and it's a cross
of both the large white and the L that's
the tn70 and uh you can imagine taking
the C of both the large white and the
land and see how great that breed will
be the tn70 is so massive it's so
beautiful and uh very prolific so uh I
would really advise that if you want to
get your hand on PE farming and you're
looking for what breeds to get you can
consider getting the T
7 now uh another um Pig breed that uh is
also very very suitable for commercial
Pak farming is the curo the crock the
the the crock is very is also very
massive it grows very big very very big
and uh we will be stocking obviously we
we stocking lot of great breeds on this
Farm very soon we're working on that uh
one of the breeds we aim to bring to
this Farm is the crock the Cambro we
want to bring the cro because it's also
very very good when it comes to breeding
it's very good when it comes to um um
breeding and when it comes to fattening
so you can even maintain a Pure Line of
the crock if you want to or you can
decide to cross breed uh uh heat now
many of these Pak breeds I've mentioned
the large white the land R the am the t7
the cro one of the great thing about
them is that they are very good for
cross breeding purposes so you want to
have this breed if you are interested in
crossbreeding programs and uh if you if
I will advise you on what kind of V what
kind of me pig you should have on your
farm if you are going to be doing the
crossbreeding purposes well I would if
you have the money I would advise you to
go for the last Peak breed I'll be
mentioning here and that's the D Rock
breed the dck breed is the last um breed
that I advise you to go for commercial
Peak Farm now I'm not sure I would
advise you to have uh to to go for the
Pure Line of the Dr bre
and just be breeding just a Pure Line
alone well if you want to be selling uh
to other Farmers that mean if you want
to run a breeding Farm a a more like a
just yeah like a breeding Farm where you
you you more interested in just selling
the piglets to other Farm well you can
go for the Duro line and just be wearing
the dck alone of course there is a
demand for the Duro B majorly the dur
bra in this side of the world because
the D bra are very very uh excellent
when it comes to um cross breeding they
they they put in their genetics so much
on other breeds that and you know one
important characteristic you need to
know about drug breed Pig breed is that
they grow fast and large you know he one
thing to grow large but take time but
these guys grow large and they grow fast
so they attain that level of largess in
record time so is the reason why you may
want to get them on your farm because
they will pass on trait to your
crossbreed animals so on the hybrid
animals you produce from maybe the Duro
and the tn70 or the large white they
would have that characteristic of
growing very fast which is what you want
if you are running a cross breing
program because you want to be able to
fatten those animals in record time also
latest 6 months you want to send them
out of your farm so the Duro breed is an
excellent um B that you should have you
can have on your farm but it's on the
high side is very expensive so if you
but if you don't want to use a durug bre
you can use any other um Pig you can use
a tn70 b to make your other this thing
or any other U maybe the large white b
or any you want to do it so it's uh
these are the uh best breeds I would
recommend for commercial pig farm in
this side of the world now there's one
last breed I will mention which is
Uprising and that's the patrian breed
the patrian breed is uh is also a fast
growing Pig it's uh it's more it's not
so new but it's getting the Limelight
newly that means it's just coming into
the Lamplight newly and not so many
farms have the pan breed but a breed
that it's getting increasingly common in
this side of the world so uh um very
soon I'm sure it will it will become
much more common and people will be able
to get them easily so this are this will
be all for the video best Peak bridge
for commercial purposes if you want to
start a pig farm commercial pig farm you
should look out for uh this breed I've
talked about to either run a pure
breeding line or a cross breeding line
any whichever one the program you want
to make you are free to use any of these
breed to do them all the breeds I
mentioned are very excellent when it
comes to uh reproduction they give birth
to a lot of piglet and they are very
Hardy they are resistant they have the
right characteristics they convert well
and um all these Bri I mention are the
pure breeds obviously I'm not talking
about a diminished breed the pure breeds
are the ones I'm referring to here and
uh would not advise you to run a dck
Pure Line uh because obviously you if
you are going to be fattening for the
market because if you're not going to be
selling The Offspring to the
to to the uh other Farmers you don't
want to because you may not be able to
sell at the price that the uh the matur
Duro will come out with you may not be
able to get buyers for that in the
market you know I mean in the slaughter
house so I'm not saying everywhere in
the world I'm talking about this side of
the world because other sides of the
world the the Dr breed is more common
that means you can easily get the Duro
breed but in this side of the world is
not yet as common so it's still more
like a very expensive animal so if you
are raring the Duro bre for Market
purpose it may not pay you so much
because you may not be able to sustain
that uh uh the the price it to be going
out with but again if you desire that
it's still up to you thank you very much
if you're new to this Channel please end
you subscribe to this channel lots of
great videos on profitable p f will be
coming your way please ensure you click
the Subscribe button don't leave this
video without clicking the Subscribe
button all right thank you very much
bye-bye