[Music]
Sundiata nog is a 62 year old single
rice farmer growing traditional variety
in a hectare farm located at barangay
bank Isaiah Noonan and southern lady his
farm was earlier dug for treasure
hunting but nothing was found because of
his continuous learning through seminars
and sustainable agriculture him exists
land more productive and sustainable
through the application of
diversification and organic farming
he's burning interest to make things
better were simply irresistible the
challenges he faced was his area it is
flat and prone to flooding hi
concentrate laser and pesticides drought
an unpredictable weather and profit
animal integration in the farm as a
solution
he started container gardening as kami
change adaptation and mitigation
measuring floods he locally innovates
Asante formulated organic fertilizer and
natural pesticides to improve plant
vigor and depicted in sick repellent
he modified multi-story cropping by
placing container-based each eye under
the trellis of opal then he integrated
Korean pig racing into the farming
system and used the composite buildings
of the piece as organic fertilizer he
worked hard to establish an organic farm
established immediate de l'épée a pond
and learned that a local snail qahal
constitute a nutritious feed for tilapia
when mixed with rice bread the pond
water is also used for his farm during
dry season planting abroad twists and
legumes are used as wind breaks and a
source of green manures vermicomposting
as a source of organic fertilizer
recently the agricultural training
institute provide additional support
like sprayer vermicompost
facility free-range native chicken and
ducks and cross site visits to the
project's farms with similar
undertakings with this innovative
concept and farming experience his farm
was transferred into bit size model for
all interested farmers willing to learn
and adapt he became a resource person
his income before the technology is
thirty-five thousand pesos per year
derived from rice farming alone now he
earned more than eighty thousand pieces
per year organic farming takes time but
with far bigger rewards learning doesn't
stop when technology is applied
technology adoption does actual
observations plus experience
as well to innovate equal effective
location to good agricultural practices
[Music]