thank you okay welcome to the largest
screen in the Russell Senate Office
Building
um also thank you for coming to the
fifth and final briefing in our five
part series farm bill in Focus I'm Dan
Brissette I'm the president of the
environmental and energy study Institute
and today our look at the farm bill
continues with conservation practices
from farms to forests and wetlands
you could say perhaps that we saved the
best for last in other words we've
conserved
the LA the best briefing for last that's
about as punny as we're gonna get today
if you came to the forestry briefing
there was a lot a lot better puns but
just wanted to at least get that out
there also like to say huge thanks to
the office of Senator Peter Welch for
having us secure this room today uh and
for hosting and for bringing us all
together for this really excellent
conversation eesi was founded in 1984 on
a bipartisan basis by members of
Congress to provide educational
resources to policy makers about climate
change topics that means next year is
our 40th anniversary and we're still
going strong
briefings like this are probably the
highest profile thing we do we do a lot
of briefings and we cover lots of topics
even Beyond Farm Bill topics so while
this is a five-part series about the
farm bill we've also recently covered
Department of Energy's nuclear energy
programs office of Energy Efficiency and
renewable energy programs we did a
four-part congressional climate Camp
series earlier this year we looked at
public polling about climate change we
talked about non-cot in-house gas
emissions and other pollutants the
budget and Appropriations process so not
just substance also process and then
also the fourth briefing in that series
was the implementation status of the
infrastructure investment jobs act and
inflation reduction act this will be our
last briefing for a little while but
we'll be back on July 18th on the ninth
floor of the heart building for our
Congressional renewable energy and
Energy Efficiency Expo that is going to
be an All-Star series of panels we're
also going to have a fun reception after
the event so I encourage everyone if you
haven't already to sign up for that and
with everything we do the best way to
keep up and sign up for our programming
and things like that is to subscribe to
our bi-weekly newsletter which is called
climate change Solutions and you can do
that by visiting us
um on our visiting our website at
www.esi.org
our programming is really designed for
the Congressional staff person we know
what it's like when it's you know four
o'clock on a Thursday and the boss stops
by and wants to know hey tell me all
about conservation programs in the farm
bill and you're like I have a did a
reservation at six okay
ESI has those resources to help you
answer those questions we we pride
ourselves on being timely relevant
accessible and practical and our
resources come in all shapes and sizes
we do briefings we also do a lot of
writing we do a lot of articles for
example we do fact sheets we just
released a fact sheet
couple weeks ago about heavy duty
electric vehicles it's a real it's a
must read we just posted one today about
the renew America's nonprofits program
which was enacted as part of the
infrastructure investment jobs act we do
side by side by side comparisons of uh
eventually when we get House and Senate
marks of the farm bill we'll compare
that with existing law to help you
compare not just what the two Chambers
are proposing to do but also how those
compare to each other we do a lot of
issue briefs if you haven't read our
sustainable Aviation emissions or
sustainable aviation fuel Aviation
emissions issue brief that's one of our
most popular resources so pretty much if
your boss comes to you and has a
question about a climate change topics
I would go dollars to Donuts that we
have a resource from the last year or
two that will help you answer those
questions and do it in a non-partisan
science-based way if you like what
you're seeing visit us online all of our
resources are free and available uh if
you visit us and my colleagues and I
we're all wearing our little lapel pins
and so if you have questions that we
don't you know whether it's conservation
topics or other things catch up with me
and Molly and Nicole and others we'll
all be hanging out after the briefing
and we'd love to get to know you and
learn a little bit more about your
interests and your boss's priorities
the conservation title of the farm bill
is what brings us here today and that's
because it contains important programs
and policies that help agricultural
producers Forest managers and Rural
communities take advantage of
opportunities to reduce greenhouse gas
emissions and build resilience to
climate impacts and that happens while
also generating other benefits for
example improved water and air quality
soil Health biodiversity and jobs
conservation of public-private working
and non-working lands can take many
forms from regenerative agricultural
practices to conservation easements and
our All-Star panel today will help
everyone understand what that looks like
in practice and some things that you
might be thinking about as a House and
Senate start to really get to work on
putting pen to paper on the farm bill
but before we get to our panelists we're
joined today by two special guests via
pre-recorded introductions the first is
representative Nancy mace representative
mace represents the first district of
South Carolina in the U.S House of
Representatives she grew up in Goose
Creek and earned accolades as one of the
most fiscally conservative members of
the South Carolina general assembly and
one of the most pro-conservation
lawmakers in the state representative
mace was the first woman to graduate
from The Citadel which is the Military
College of South Carolina in 1999 and
earned magna laude otters she also
started her own business and brings
extensive experience in technology
public relations and marketing and
Commercial Real Estate to her service in
the house so my colleague Dano will get
the video up and running and we'll hear
what representative mace has to say
hey everyone hey everyone this is
Congresswoman Nancy Mays from South
Carolina's first congressional district
get a little South Carolina flag right
there I want to welcome everyone to the
eesi briefing uh where the convergence
of energy and environment really are
Paramount uh to our nation's future as a
as a conservationist and as a
conservative and as someone who
represents the coast of South Carolina I
recognize how important it is
um in terms of energy efforts screen
energy efforts all the above approach
protecting our environment these things
are so important to our way of life and
our future we appreciate your expertise
your knowledge your subject matter
um policy ideas Etc our door is always
open we're willing to work with anyone
who's willing to work with us on these
issues that all of us in the room today
care about I wish I could join you maybe
next time
thanks to representative mace for
joining us and her great staff for
making her participation possible that
brings us to her second special guest
representative Charisse Davids
representative David's represents the
Third District of Kansas in the house uh
when she was sworn into the 116th
Congress representative Davids became
one of the first Native American women
to serve in Congress she studied at
Johnson County Community College in the
University of Missouri Kansas City
before earning a law degree from Cornell
Law School and a special relevance to
our briefing today representative Davids
is a member of the House agriculture
committee subcommittee on conservation
research and biotechnology
hi everyone it's great to be one it's
great to be with you today thanks to the
environmental and energy study Institute
for inviting me to share a few words
with you for folks who I haven't met yet
my name is Charisse Davids and I
represent Kansas's Third District in
Congress I also serve as a member on the
house agriculture committee
look I uh my understanding is this is
the last conversation in the farm bill
briefing series and I hope this has been
an informative time for you all you know
that mindset of learning and listening
is exactly the approach that I've uh
taken over the past year to prepare for
the upcoming Farm Bill reauthorization
I've had the chance to travel my
district in Kansas on a farm bill
listening tour and I don't have enough
time to mention all the fun and amazing
stops but some have included a meat and
poultry farm a co-op a no-till farm a
small family-owned farm a Livestock
Auction just so many things and many of
the agriculture professionals that I've
spoken to uh mention the need for us to
protect our lands so that Future Farmers
and producers can support their
businesses and families as well as our
economy for generations to come and that
includes combating climate change and
extreme weather events like flooding and
drought which can devastate our
agricultural community in Kansas and
across the country you know conservation
programs administered by the U.S
department of Agriculture have proven
instrumental in achieving this goal this
includes the conservation Reserve
program and the Environmental Quality
incentives program which gives farmers
and producers the tools to mitigate the
effects of climate change in their
communities and to ensure that they can
continue to feed the rule can continue
to feed the world
uh yeah these programs Empower
agriculture professionals who know their
land best
um it empowers them to protect and care
for it and as a member of the
subcommittee on conservation research
and biotechnology I'm glad that we can
talk about the benefits of these
programs and and how and how we can
continue improving them moving forward
now the conservation title has long
enjoyed bipartisan support and I'm
really glad to share this space today
with my colleague congresswoman mace as
we work to ensure that programs that
support farmers and protect our lands
are funded adequately and and managed
effectively through the 2023 farm bill
so thank you again for your time and I
hope you enjoy the rest of today's
session and I'll look forward to talking
to you all soon
tight squeeze back here sorry panelists
you've you've drawn the short end of the
of the stage today Short Straw
um while my colleague Daniel puts the
slides back up uh one last piece of
housekeeping and that is uh after we
hear presentations from our four
panelists today we'll have an
opportunity for questions and answers
and so everyone in the room will have an
opportunity uh to ask questions uh about
conservation programs in the farm bill
and related subjects uh but we'll also
have an opportunity for our online
audience to ask us questions and so if
you're on our online audience today you
can send us an email an email address to
use as ask that's ask
eesi.org you can also follow us on
social media at ESI online and we'll do
our best to incorporate those questions
into the discussion
that brings us to our first panelists
today Samantha Levy leads the
development and implementation of the
American Farmland trust's climate policy
agenda she leads the trust's efforts to
advance adoption of new regenerative
practices on Farmland protect Farmland
from development encourage smart
renewable energy sighting on farms she
also works closely with the farmer's
combat climate change initiative which
elevates the role of farmers to adapt to
and mitigate the effects of climate
change in 2020 Samantha was appointed to
serve as a member of the New York
Agriculture and Forestry advisory panel
to The Climate Action Council to develop
recommendations to reduce agricultural
greenhouse gas emissions and increase
carbon sequestration in soils and she's
also served as a member of the
governor's racial equity and diversity
and agriculture work group Samantha
welcome to the lectern I will turn the
clicker over to you and I'm really
looking forward to your presentation
you Dan I'm a good on sound this is all
I need okay great
great thank you for having me thank you
ESI for having me thank you all for
coming and spending your time here this
afternoon uh just to help me get a sense
of who's in the room how many of y'all
work for a House member
great senator
NGO
excellent farm group
okay thanks
um
so uh Dan already did a great job of uh
talking about what I work on my
portfolio covers soil Health
conservation solar sighting renewable
energy siding on farms so in case you're
hearing about that from constituents
um that's what I work on for our federal
team and I support our state and
Regional staff at aft in doing so as
well
for those who aren't familiar with
American Farmland Trust
This Is Us no Farms no food stickers
that represents our mission our mission
is to save the land that sustains us
please take a stack of stickers on your
way out I brought enough for everyone
to accomplish this Mission we do it in
three ways by working to protect
Farmland promote sound farming practices
and keep Farmers on the land
and we work we've got a an office in DC
we have state and Regional Offices
throughout the country probably in many
of the places that you represent
and we work directly with farmers and
ranchers and we also work on policy at
the local state and federal level we
often say we work from kitchen table to
Congress
and I'm part of a federal team of five
our farm bill work encompasses what I'll
talk to you about today but also the
agricultural conservation easement
program land access for a new generation
of farmers Business technical assistance
Farm viability and smart solar and I
left some resources on the front table
about that but like I said I'm going to
focus on sound farming practices and
I've been asked to give a one-on-one
what they are why they matter and the
programs that support them and then I
can't help myself talking about the farm
bill given where we are in the time of
year
so first what is soil Health how many
folks are familiar with soil health
definition practices great well then I'm
glad I included this slide so the
definition of soil Health from the
natural resources conservation service
at USDA or nrcs is the ability of soil
to function as a living ecosystem that
supports plants animals and humans and
then here this very large graphic from
nrcs as well depicts the four principles
that farmers and ranchers may follow to
improve their soil health so that's
maximizing biodiversity that can look
like integrating animals into Crop
Production or diversifying crop rotation
growing more crops
reducing disturbance so that can look
like no-till as congresswoman David's
mentioned or reduced tillage maximizing
cover like planting cover crops in the
off season in between cash crops
maximizing living Roots like planting
cover crops or planting perennials
so there's your soil Health 101
why does soil Health matter so many
benefits from soil Health to the farmers
to communities and to the taxpayer as
well and I'll talk about each of these
in turn so
top graphic you see here is from aft's
soil Health case studies ESI has
resources which will link you to these
on the website we found that over time
investment in soil Health practices can
generate a three to one return on
investment for producers can take a few
years to find that benefit that return
on investment but it's quite good as you
can see
there was also a 2021 study that showed
under extreme drought conditions that a
one percent increase in soil organic
matter which is a chief soil Health
indicator
can increase yields under those drought
conditions by 33 bushels so soil Health
practices promote resilience how many of
you are seeing more extreme weather
across the country
right I see a lot of head nodding a lot
of hands going up
under drought and flood conditions these
practices are super important for
helping build resilience on a farm or
Ranch
and to stabilizing yields under those
conditions co-benefits for communities
improved water quality reduce soil
erosion on the farm keeps it out of our
our rivers and our waterways flood
mitigation same reason water
infiltration into the soils keeps it
away from impervious surfaces and
communities and increased carbon
sequestration to help fight climate
change literally drawing carbon from the
air into the soil
and I mentioned taxpayers I'm sure many
of your bosses care about taxpayer
dollars in 2019 the economic research
service at USDA came out with a study
that looked at the expected cost
increases to crop insurance from climate
change and extreme weather and they
found that under a business's usual
scenario expectations for those costs to
increase by 37 percent this Century but
if Farmers adopt adaptation practices
such as soil Health practices it could
go down significantly to only as much as
22 percent so these are really important
for a lot of different reasons
but
they're not very widely adopted for
example as of 2017 only six percent of
eligible Acres that could have been
planted with cover crops were
leaving 94 percent of Acres bare in the
off season
why is that
farmers are working really hard to feed
their families to feed their communities
and they face a lot of important
barriers that need to be overcome to
changing from tried and true methods and
adopting new practices and Management
Systems
chief of which cost cost of new
equipment
cost of seed cost in time figuring out
how to do things risk perceived or real
risk of yield loss
information gaps and barriers what do I
do how do I know how to do it no access
to the right information or lack of
knowing where to look cultural barriers
so it may just not be what has been done
though I will acknowledge there are many
producers that have been doing practice
that have been practicing these
practices for centuries even and then
insecure land tenure I mentioned that
sometimes it can take time for these
practices to pay off how many of you
rent or have rented in your in your
lives you're less apt to invest in
improvements if you're renting right
versus if you're owning because it's not
going to really benefit you per se over
the long term so insecure land tenure is
important to address as well
what we're here to talk about today
there are programs that are out there to
address so many of these barriers and
I'm going to talk about nrcs programs
today
conservation Reserve program this is
administered by the Farm Service Agency
or FSA this is a
term retirement program that provides
Farmers with rental payments if they
were to enter into a CRP contract for a
length of time
the rest of these are administered by
nrcs so you've got the Environmental
Quality incentives program which invests
in shorter term contracts to address
identified resource concerns on the farm
then you've got the conservation
stewardship program just kind of like
the next level graduation step two this
invests in longer term contracts perhaps
around five years to invest in
maintaining those practices and adding
new enhancements
the asep program agricultural
conservation easement program which my
colleague Chris coffin works on invests
in permanently protecting Farmland this
also can help with Farmland
affordability and access and then the
regional conservation partnership
program which invests in Regional or
Watershed scale
um projects that are proposed by RCP
folks who apply to the program to
implement conservation on a regional
scale and maybe in more innovative ways
that's the ideal for the program
this pie chart gives you an idea of the
funding relative funding for each of
these programs in the last Farm Bill
so you can see CRP was about a third
and same with equip about a third of all
the funding that went to these programs
CSP about a quarter and then a smaller
share for rcpp and for ASAP and for
equip and CSP in particular producers to
gain access to that financial assistance
to overcome those cost barriers they
need to work with somebody who is
qualified to provide them with technical
assistance so that could be an nrcs
staff person it could be someone else
that nrcs has entered into agreement
with aft has some of those planners on
staff and they work with the producer
directly to identify what are the
resource concerns that you want to work
on what practices that nrcs supports
funding for can we invest in and then
helps them find financial assistance for
those
hopefully everybody's clear on the 101
so
um back last year aft uh held Farm Bill
workshops with farmers and ranchers
across the country with service
providers researchers and others and we
learned a little bit about what's
working really well and what where we
have opportunities for improvement for
these programs and so I've written a
white paper with my colleagues and we
just released this last week I have a
few copies in writing here if folks want
to grab them after but also available
from ESI by link
and at a very high level
these are locally LED locally
implemented programs with well-vetted
science-based standards so if you want
to practice no-till there are
science-based ways that they have
identified for you to do that
on the needs for improvement they're
highly over subscribed a lot more demand
than funding available
and perhaps even more demand for
technical assistance than agents
available link the application processes
Farmers have reported facing gaps in
support whether it be by production type
or region some Equity challenges we
heard a lot from small scale producers
small operations that they struggle to
access this assistance and there there's
some limited room to invest in
Innovation because they're supporting
the really tried and true practices with
the exception of rcpp and conservation
Innovation grants within the equip
program
for example between 2010 and 2020 only
30 percent of equip applications were
able to be funded so less than a third
and there was also a study released in
that showed that between 2009 and 2018
only 17 to 27 percent of funding from
equip one towards soil Health practices
so they're investing in a lot of
different resource concerns so just a
small share of the overall pot there
we have developed some goals
recommendations that I'll just touch on
briefly you can find more information in
our white papers
um and those like I said those links are
available from eesi and our goals in
this Arena are to support producers in
increasing long-term adoption of
conservation practices that will improve
soil Health address climate change build
resilience
to make nrcs programs more accessible
and equitably available and to benefit
or to build sorry farmer to Farmer
learning networks and I'll say a little
bit more about that
so first on our checklist providing
sustainably increased funding to meet
farmer demand for conservation financial
and technical assistance the inflation
reduction act injected a lot of funding
into these programs but that funding
sunsets in 2026. so you know solving the
longer term how do we meet the funding
demand problem hopefully something we
can do this farm bill and streamlining
program implementation and like I said
you can find more on this here
oh there's some uh animation okay so
increasing support for Farmer to Farmer
learning we see this as kind of the
missing piece we're investing in
technical assistance and financial
assistance it helps with cost barriers
this can help with information barriers
cultural barriers can even help with
land tenure farmer to Farmer learning is
so critical to this conversation it
really helps to overcome the adoption
barriers by having someone with
first-hand experience address perceived
risks to yield and more that may prevent
a farmer from trying a new practice it's
as much about what doesn't work as what
does
this is already happening organically
across the country informally formally
in coffee shops Etc in the field
according to a survey that we did in New
England over 50 percent of farmers that
we surveyed were learning about
conservation from other farmers and
that's something we hear across the
country ask any farmer Rancher where do
you learn about conservation nine times
out of ten first thing they'll say is
another farmer
so we have a proposal to build this into
the farm bill there's more information
on the front table or I can provide it
creating a program that provides
matching funds for state and tribal soil
health programs so there are Innovations
happening there are locally LED programs
being developed at the state level I can
we have another white paper on that that
gives you tons of examples of that we've
done a webinar as well you can find more
information on that or just ask me
creating a program in the farm bill to
match those funds to augment them helps
to augment Innovation for locally LED
programs build off of nrcs programs and
to fill gaps for example many states
invest in equipment purchase for soil
Health practice adoption and that's a
really big key barrier
oh and I should also mention there are a
couple of bills the agriculture
resilience act includes this in the bill
and there was a bill introduced last
week by Representatives Gallagher Nunn
and Huffman uh it's called the noemits
act that includes a proposal for this
and the area was introduced by Senator
Heinrich and representative Pingree
amongst others and you can see on this
memo just incredibly broad support I
have a little pointer incredibly broad
support for this across the country
finally I mentioned we heard small scale
operations struggle to access some of
these programs so we've been working
with Senator Booker Representatives
um I'm sorry I just my card but I can
remember Representatives uh Strickland
Adams and McGovern to introduce a bill
which was introduced recently the office
of small farms establishment Act
that would basically look through USDA
program policies and make sure that
small-scale producers are able to access
not just conservation programs but all
the services that USDA provides
and so I encourage you to keep in touch
this is my contact information you can
look on our website for all these
resources and like I said some of them
are available through eesi we're also
working on crop insurance and
conservation happy to talk about that
and like I said ASAP land access
Business technical assistance and solar
and thank you so much
[Applause]
for your fabulous presentation and if
anyone would like to revisit that
fabulous presentation I have two
suggestions one would be to go to
esi.org and download all the great
materials and presentation materials
that Samantha just presented and
referred to you could also watch the
archived webcast will be up in a few
days so if you want to go back and
revisit anything that Samantha just said
or anything that our other panelists are
about to say that resources available to
you including the the white paper that
you that you mentioned
um our second panelist today is Eileen
Shader Eileen is the director of river
Restoration in American rivers in 2015
she relocated to her home state of
Pennsylvania where she leads American
River's National floodplain flood plain
restoration program Eileen spent most of
her career at American rivers advocating
to Congress and the federal government
to support sound floodplain management
policies prior to joining American River
she held positions at the National
Wildlife Federation the National
Environmental trust and U.S EPA Eileen
is a certified floodplain manager and
works to reconnect rivers to their flood
Plains and restore natural floodplain
habitats my lean the clicker is yours
take it away thank you thank you very
much
thank you
there we go
um thank you very much for having me and
really appreciate the opportunity uh to
participate in this briefing and talk
about uh the farm bill and conservation
practices so
um today I'm going to focus on
um a program that is technically an
emergency
Protection Program under the nrcs but in
reality is a conservation program and
how it is applied so
um if you're not familiar with American
Rivers we are a premier National River
conservation organization that works to
protect wild rivers restore damaged
rivers and conserve clean water for
people in nature
um and then Stan mentioned I lead our
national floodplain restoration program
uh which is uh focused on working with
partners and communities across the
country to implement nature-based
Equitable and multi-benefit floodplain
management
programs and projects so that can
include anything from we have staff
working directly on the ground to
reconnect rivers to their floodplains
restore natural habitat to working at uh
advancing state level programs that
support multi-benefit projects that both
reduce flood risk and ReStore Habitat
for floodplain dependent species
and working on federal policy
initiatives like the farm bill and Water
Resources development act and National
flood insurance program but today we're
going to talk about floodplain easement
under the nrcs
um
my colleague Olivia Dorothy who lives in
Illinois and leaves our Mississippi
River program wasn't able to be here
today but she led the effort to produce
a report on the multiple benefits of
floodplain easements that looked at
their use within the Upper Midwest
states the Upper Mississippi and then
assessed how floodplain easements are
utilized and how some of the challenges
with that program so
um if you are
well one thing I would say about the if
you're not familiar with the floodplain
easement program
essentially it works where the nrcs will
put their voluntary program we'll put an
easement on a flood-prone land
agricultural land
and then the landowner
enters an agreement with the nrcs to
restore that land to more natural
conditions so we're restoring the
hydrology so that the water is able to
soak into the ground restoring natural
habitat and Native vegetation in order
to improve the capacity of that that
land to provide benefits to society
uh when we talk about flood Plains I
know many people think about a flood
plain as the hundred year uh as
floodplain as defined by the national
flood insurance program and where you
might need insurance but for our
purposes we're talking about it more as
an ecosystem or a landscape so the lands
next to rivers and water bodies that
gets flooded on a regular basis and uh
some people think that flood Plains are
interchangeable with Wetlands that's not
quite correct you can have Wetlands on a
flood plain but not all flood Plains are
wetlands flood Plains tend to have much
more diverse ecosystems there will be
some standing water there may be some
side channels and streams there may be
some areas of high elevation with
different kinds of trees and and Native
vegetation and one of the most amazing
things about flood Plains is that many
of our Wildlife and Fish and birds are
evolved to exist on a flood plain some
part of their lives cycle depends on
access to a floodplain in order for them
to thrive so they're really really
undervalued or underappreciated I should
say ecosystem within our within our
nation and the world
um and one of the great things about
floodplains is they provide so many
different benefits to society when they
especially when they're in their natural
condition
um they are able to sequester carbon
into deep root systems of native uh
species or native plant species
um they help to clean and capture
um Clean Water by capturing excess
nutrients of nitrogen and phosphorus and
and these these uh pollutants that we're
trying so hard to try and manage within
many of our agricultural waterways
um and they're really amazing places for
fish and wildlife which then produce
recreational opportunities which are
economic drivers for many communities
so what made us start looking at
floodplain easements as a program that
maybe needed some improvements
um so our Interest really was sparked by
um this one incident in um dog tooth
Bend which is uh in Southern Illinois
it's a
area this is the Mississippi river
flowing down here and this is a very
heavy agricultural area this Levy
District I believe is about 17 000 Acres
farmed in corn corn and soybeans and
they experience regular flooding it's a
it's protected by a levy and we saw Levy
breaches just happening over and over at
this place in short because the
Mississippi River wants to cut through
there so it was a place where the the
river wants to go where it wants to go
and it's going to take out that Levee
and it did multiple times in 2016 the
Army Corps of Engineers decided that
they weren't going to read about Levy
anymore it was just not economically
feasible to continue doing this and that
they needed a new approach
so for the farmers that are left in this
area
um what can they do with their land what
options do they have so many of them
started looking at conservation programs
and could they put this land into
permanent conservation since they just
weren't going to be able to farm it
anymore I mean this is uh part of this
area after repetitive flooding I mean
it's just like sand dunes there's just
all sorts of material deposited all over
the place and well that's not a wetland
doesn't qualify for Wetland Conservation
programs so what else can they do so we
started looking at floodplain easements
um but the challenge is that there was
no money in the floodplain easement
program that was available for them so
some Farmers started applying
um and we're told that there wasn't an
opportunity right then
part of the challenge is that the way
that this program operates as an
emergency program is that funding is
only appropriated and goes into the
program when there's sort of a major
disaster declared so when there's like a
Stafford act declaration if anybody's
aware of how that works
um and
if there's no disaster declared there's
no money put into the program so even if
Farmers apply they're not going to be
able to access the funding
um when we looked at the Upper
Mississippi river States we found that
over the last decade even though there
was over 2500 agricultural disasters so
in these rural areas there's flooding
disasters only one time had there been a
funding allocated to the floodplain
easement program
when we looked a little deeper and I'm
going to throw a couple of different
graphs at you but looked a little deeper
at the data one of the things we saw was
that
um
the enrollment of floodplain easements
within this program over the years
pretty low
um so uh you know a couple of years
where we had a funding allocated and a
decent number of floodplain easements
enrolled for the most part I mean we're
looking at under 50 easements being
implemented every year and this is
across the country for these numbers
when you compare that to the number of
agricultural disasters that are declared
in counties in agricultural areas it's a
very small amount of easements that are
available in these areas that are being
flooded particularly ones that are
flooded regularly
so one question that folks ask then is
well if people aren't getting easements
is it because there's not demand
um and that's not accurate um there's
definite demand when you look at the
number of
um Farmers that have applied to put
their their land into a floodplain
easements
um there's a significant unmet demand
and this doesn't just apply to the Upper
Mississippi States if we've pulled some
preliminary numbers from all states
across the country and
um these track that there's always a
significant amount of applications and
just not enough money and availability
to go around so there are just
definitely a number of farmers around
the country who do
these are farmers who just don't want to
deal with their land flooding over and
over and over
um so it's we're talking about Farmers
that voluntarily want to put their land
into to a better use rather than just
continue to farm and then get crop
insurance payouts every couple of years
um
can't see this one up here but um just a
couple of other things um points I
wanted to make is that flooding is
continuing to increase we all know this
giving more severe
um and the cost associated with flooding
and repetitive flooding continue to
increase due to climate change I think
this is a point hopefully we're all well
aware of and when that happens that also
means that our payouts for things like
crop insurance and that it's damages to
crops is going to continue to increase
as the years move on
um within the Upper Mississippi river
um we've seen that uh the producers are
particularly hit by flooding we're
talking damages and and payouts in the
billions of dollars for many of our our
most heavily agricultural States
um and this then applies to the cost to
taxpayers Across the Nation
um in terms of how much is being paid
out in crop insurance and in the funding
for responding to floods and responding
to disasters every year
but when we're talking about the
floodplain easement program it's not
just about cost although that's
certainly one reason to be interested in
this
um for American Rivers we are of course
interested in conserving and restoring
more natural flood Plains for those
benefits that can provide to society
so just a couple to touch on
um wetlands in particular are incredibly
effective at helping to store water
convey flood waters slow down how the
water is moving through a watershed the
more Wetlands you have within a
watershed the slower your flood waters
will move Downstream and it will help
reduce the damages to communities and to
infrastructure Downstream
uh I mentioned nutrient pollution before
many of our conservation
programs don't count floodplain
restoration as a best management
practice even though much of the um the
scientific literature demonstrates that
they do an incredible job at capturing
nitrogen and phosphorus and helping us
reduce our or improve our water quality
um and these the orange ones up there is
floodplain restoration compared to many
of the other best management practices
and then I mentioned before uh flood
plains as being really key in helping
with biodiversity and restoring and
protecting some of our most vulnerable
species
um
I mentioned before that some of our our
species are really floodplain dependent
when um there's some really amazing
research that's been done where
endangered many endangered fish send
their their
um spend part of their life on a
floodplain
um at Key times and that's really
important because it's slower water it's
much more
um there's more food there's much more
shelter and that can help them to grow
faster and Thrive and having access to
floodplains within our watersheds where
we have a lot of endangered species can
be really important aspect to help with
that recovery of those different species
so one of the things that American
Rivers has been doing is talking with
different offices about the
opportunities to try and enhance the use
of the floodplain easements program a
couple of uh key
areas where we see an opportunity one is
to figure out how to get this program
funded on an annual basis so it's not
going to be just dependent on having
Congress allocate funding when there's a
major disaster declared we need to get
money into this program annually so that
it's available when when Farmers need it
um
second would be making sure that farmers
have an opportunity every year to enroll
um as we've seen these unmet um unmet
need and uh opportunity to have
um the farmers that need it in any
particular year be able to access and
apply can help us help them address
their needs of how they need to manage
their land
um and a third idea is uh to really be
able to focus on some of the most
repetitive flooded properties so the
ones that
um are are experiencing some of the most
repetitive payouts in crop insurance or
experiencing the most investment in
terms of Emergency Response funding
those are easy opportunities to be able
to adapt to climate change and ensure
that we are investing our funds
appropriately while having an
opportunity to protect and restore the
land around them so
um that is about it um I have uh our
reports that we published on this we
have some copies out on the front desk
and happy to take any questions thank
you
that was great I
we want it to stand up rather than sit
down and I'm glad I did because that
catfish photo I think if I had been
sitting in the front row I would have I
would have shrieked a little bit that's
a big catfish
um as a quick reminder
um we have some questions coming in from
our online audience so if you're in our
online audience and you have a question
you can send us an email the email
address to uses ask that's ask esi.org
and of course for folks in the room
we'll have them we'll be able to take
questions after our fourth panelists
today
our third panelist however is Paula
Yvette Bonita Carrero uh she's with us
today on behalf of the Hispanic access
foundation's Latino climate Council and
she's a licensed agronomist with a focus
in animal behavior and Welfare she
explores the socioeconomic limitations
to achieving food security and how those
issues can be addressed through
Community engagement agriculture
extension programs and education thank
you so much for joining us today I'm
looking forward to your presentation
hello to all and thank you for being
here today my name is
I mentioned I'm an agronomist an animal
scientist and an educator from our
Puerto Rico my areas of Interest are
integrating social Equity food
accessibility and creating agriculture
engagement and extension by creating
better connection with the farmers and
producers and the communities they serve
I have wait let me let me put my
presentation real quick
um
perfect awesome so I have been a part of
Academia and I have also engaged in
public policy but most importantly I've
been part I've been working in the field
as an agronomist both in areas of the
DMV and in Puerto Rico and something
that I realized in both situations is
that there is a clear gap between the
efforts that Academia and public policy
do towards the Improvement of
Agriculture versus how that is
translated into the producers and the
farmers it is crucial to reduce these
gaps because and visibilize the issues
that these producers and Farmers point
forward because at the end of the day
thanks to them we have food in our table
so that's what I'm going to be talking
about today I'm going to be focusing on
Productions and pharmacological products
in Puerto Rico and how they have
implemented conservation practices
before I begin I want to thank all the
farmers and producers who took the time
to have these conversations with me as
well as team member of the USDA
Caribbean climate Hub and The Institute
of agricology thanks to them I have this
presentation
so there is no clear definition of
agroecology but rather a set of
disciplines and knowledge that and how
they're integrated
agroecology takes ecological concepts
and applies them into farming it is a
global movement that emphasizes
um ancestral and Campesino knowledge and
it's honored and applied and it breaks
away from the industrialized
industrialized Paradigm where there's a
hierarchy of who are the experts are
it's basically a multifactorial approach
an inclusive approach to the way we
produce food
agroecology
and it's in prioritizes long-term
economic viability by ensuring that all
parts of the economic production of food
is considered whether it's marketing
technology distribution and
accessibility it also prioritizes
conservation by protecting and
regeneration regenerating our natural
resources it looks for Technical and and
Technical
ways to use our energy more practically
and also it tries to stem away from
external inputs agroecology all the and
centers around social Equity because it
promotes dignified salaries for the
workers It Centers an uplift previously
marginalized communities like black
indigenous people of color who are
farmers and producers and aims towards
food sovereignty which is not the same
as food security food sovereignty is a
fundamental right for everybody
everybody to have accurate adequate
culturally appropriate affordable and
healthy food and It Centers the people
as the decision makers for their
agricultural systems and their food
I'm sorry I move a lot so I'm gonna try
to work on that so
there are multiple conservation
practices I cannot name all of them so
I'm going to focus on the ones that the
Farms that I will be talking about
focuses so agroecology mimics natural
ecosystem and that way they have more
resilient and diverse systems they
diversify the crops and by adding local
native plants and cover crops which
usually are deep rooted perennials that
provide structure integrity and
nutrients to the soil by diversifying
these crops they build stronger
um lands that the differentiate from
monocropping the things that we usually
see in industrial Agriculture and
monocropping make plans
vulnerable and more dependent on
external inputs like herbicides
plagocytes and synthetic fertilizer
contrast to Industrial agriculture
agroecology uses organic matter as a
natural fertilizer of the soil adequate
water management is crucial for
agroecology as we are facing a very real
Water Crisis it focuses on reducing
Water waste reducing soil erosion and
also preparing the land for inclement
weathers like mentioned before of floods
and droughts and lastly the
reintegration of livestock is crucial
for agroecology given that we do need to
follow the thought of more crops less
land more outputs less land
so now I'm going to take the opportunity
and talk and highlight some of the
projects that are happening in Puerto
Rico
these projects are usually small scale
and family products so I want to point
that out as well
so I am working with this this farm
right now it's called Finca El Simon and
lares is a family operated farm that
practices sustainable agriculture by
integrating animal husbandry and
vegetable farming their main purpose and
focus is the reintegration of livestock
particularly this native cattle breed
called the India criolla this breed is
adapted to the tropical climate but is
also a dual purpose breed where the
catalysts used for milk which they
produce cheese and merchandise it as
well as the oxen is used for plowing or
tillage of the land this is much more
less aggressive than heavy machinery is
cost effective and The Oxen are
fertilizing the soil with their manure
as they walk
so other than this cattle breed they
also integrate a variety of crops they
do Grace rotations to the Landis and
saturate they do conscious tree clearing
for to promote native trees and practice
silver pasture they also have other
types of husbandry like cattle like
goats chickens and turkeys and they're
also part of the making of compost which
then they in fact use from crop
harvesting so it's a cyclical practice
that they do and their mission is to
protect this cattle breed promote the
oxen plowing which is a cultural
practice that has been lost and stem
away from heavy machinery use
this other Farm is called fin kaplanito
in Las Marias it's a non-profit
educational project they have multiple
conservation practices from permaculture
to bioconstruction but they have a
really smart water management system
because they're in the mountainous area
and we know that mountainous area when
there's heavy rainfall water falls with
a lot of energy so they follow the soil
and embarmed approach as well as counter
farming oswail is basically a grassline
depression that allows the water to pass
through and dissipates this energy and
it prevents runoff when the when there's
Heavy Rain the barns are land Earth
walls that are close to the ditch and
they're in charge of retaining that
water and allowing to infiltrate the
soil this in addition to Contour farming
which is basically preparing terrorists
or plowing the land in a way that
follows the natural landscape and and
slopes this reduces erosion it makes it
easier to work in the land because your
fall playing the the landscape and
integrated is a passive Water Management
tool that should be implemented in many
other places that have the issue with
droughts and flooding
so now I'm going to mention other Farms
that are specifically benefiting from
the USDA conservation programs
so this Las thinkas in Rio Grande is a
woman-owned agribusin status focused on
the the racing of cattle for meat when
they first acquire their land it wasn't
prepared for agriculture but thank you
thankfully to the USDA nrca conservation
program they have had the opportunity to
begin the efforts to reach their goals
some of the things this is some of them
they have they received a couple of them
but one of them some of them was the
tree shop site propagation program that
allowed them to start planting trees to
create shade and reduce heat stress in
animals
prescribed Grayson which basically is
harvesting and maintaining healthy
pastures while maintaining soil healthy
soils and you do that while having
grazing animals
forage and biomass planting to improve
pasture quality the pasture that they
had had low possibility palatability and
low nutritional value so they're trying
to create Nate to add native pastures
that are better for the animals
their beef fruit the fruit beef
production is a niche market in Puerto
Rico and they Center it in the
protection of Natural Resources
and focusing on animal well-being and
creating good Quality Meats so it's
important to promote
um conscious agroecological animal
production not only Crop Production
because we need to eat right
so the last one I want to talk about is
there are pioneers in Puerto Rico for
agroecological farming and education
they basically do all the practices that
I mentioned before but most importantly
they have been classified as primer
Farmland by the nrcs program due to its
soils with high fertility and excellent
agroecological output less than five
percent of the world have
disclosification and I have to remind
you how small
Puerto Rico is so that's really
impressive so the conservation and
protection of this soil is crucial they
also produce over 21
000 pounds of food in 2021 in just a
three acre land so they service prove
that sustainable agroecology can fit
communities and it's done in a really
small space so the opportunities are
endless
they also offer a
agricological promoter course which I'm
taking right now which is an intensive
theoretical and practical course that
teaches all audience how to start a
vegetable garden from scratch
the principles of agroecology and the
students work in different farms around
the area I feel that this type of
courses should be implemented worldwide
whether you want to have a project or
not because there is an urgency to shift
our agriculture production and people
Everybody Eats the more people are aware
of our situation the larger scope we can
impact
they've also benefited from nrcs
conservation program although their Farm
as you can see is open we do have
variations in weather in Puerto Rico we
have an intense dry season and intense
rainy season a rainy season
is hard to produce we have incidents of
mold and plaques and it just is hard to
maintain so thanks to the high tonal
initiative they were able to create a
shaded structure with a waterproof roof
that allow for stabilities in the crops
and allowed for them to be able to
produce even more types of crops that
are that do not depend on the actual
season while still practicing
agroecological practices
so like everything there are challenges
I'm first going to talk about the
challenges in Puerto Rico and then talk
about challenges in general
so we are currently going through a land
access and land tenure crisis like Sam
mentioned it is gentrification and
displacement have spiked the prices of
land making it really inaccessible for
the Puerto Rican sunlit in the island it
is not feasible for everybody to put out
a loan to buy a land because of a farm
is a high risk investment so people are
struggling to have tenure because it's
not really feasible to to rent a land
that you're not promised that you're
gonna save your rewards also entries
like the land of authorities don't
really have an accurate census of the
available land so and Bureau credit
limitations really makes the process
even more arduous and tedious secondly
and while we've been struggling for
centuries are austerity measures like
the Jones act it really limits the scope
from which producers can compete at the
market when we have second class lower
quality imported food in the supermarket
that will not ever be able to compete
with good quality organic produce that
are the formal agriculturists are doing
also it really limits and inhibits their
opportunity to export their goods
other issues are we need to increase the
public policy to protect Farmers from
inclement weather and natural disasters
we need to update our curriculum in
universities that are specialized in
agriculture so we can have degrees that
are specific for regeneratory
agriculture social economy social
economic disparities and
inaccessibilities have made processed
food more common than fresh food so
that's another issue that we face as
well that the as the dwindling practice
of eating seasonally
and lastly and the reason why we're here
we need to expand how much the reach of
Agriculture farmers and and incentivize
them for the conservation practices
and this is because conservation Farm
practices involve many types of people
and needs there is a need for Technical
and educational assistance performance
because not everybody has access to
computer social media not everybody and
we shouldn't focus on the people that
have that access to be able to implement
this is where agriculture extension
comes into place we have to focus our
we need to focus on small-scale Regional
production
and to conclude intensive and
conventional agriculture that we've seen
for the last 60 years is not a viable
production of food it has proven that
it's not capable of feeding our
communities and has caused irreparable
damage to our ecosystem now more than
ever we need to uplift the communities
and the farmers that are doing our
feeding our communities are working
against food insecurity and food deserts
wow
regenerating regenerating our natural
resources agroecology is not an idea it
is not a concept it is an applicable and
effective practice that could protect
our natural resources and feed our world
thank you
[Applause]
thank you so much there's nothing wrong
with the with Sr 188 it's a perfectly
fine place for briefing but we might
have to talk about maybe doing our
briefings in Puerto Rico because the
photos you display that's kind of nice
it's pretty amazing those are great
great shots that you provide thank you
um we have our final panelists joining
us now and I'm really pleased to
introduce banae calic binay is an
enrolled member of the Palma band of
Louisiana Indians and a promise proud
descendant of the week old people of
Jalisco excuse me over the last 35 years
Binet has represented Indian Country in
various political cultural and
administrative capacities
she has served as the repatriation chair
since the age of 21 and her life's work
is to preserve the culture and
traditions of her people through various
roles benek interacts with the youth
culture public and political relations
of her tribe she has established and
served as board chair and president of
onopo strategies of multifaceted
consultancy and holding company with
capabilities in Economic Development
technology procurement distribution
business strategy marketing and
environmental and agricultural
management and for people who joined us
a couple weeks ago at the rural
development briefing Benet also
introduced us to Dwayne who stole the
show along with Alia and our other
panelists uh so thanks very much for
that as well Bene welcome to the lectern
I'm looking forward to your presentation
so
I'm the I'm the
the last person which is a really hard
position to be in only because these
women here did an amazing job
so I really appreciate that um
uh no wrong beneath like no um so um
what I just said was hello how are you
um
and how are you and that uh my name is
banay kalak and I'm from Palma so I born
and raised I'm well wasn't born on
reservation down the road but pretty
much raised all my life on my
reservation
um served Tribal Council or three terms
um was raised on the reservation
uh in the mountains in the in the in the
uh in our River well it's not river it's
a stream I guess but um it was raised in
a good way so I'm I'm really honored to
be here
I am a person who you can ask me any
question I think sometimes and for the
people who do work with representative
Charice Davis you probably um have a
she's an amazing person and anybody
who's worked with uh Deb Hollins um
honorable depaulin she I was had the
pleasure of meeting them prior to them
being here so even at that time they
were just so amazing but I am the kind
of person who wants to
um be asked any question that you think
may not be politically correct or an
uncomfortable it does seem like
sometimes as tribal people we're still
held under a glass
um that there's that um I'm still to
this day get the question of you know uh
that we don't exist so I'm really
thankful and honored to be here as well
as I'm sure if you were here when Dwayne
Sherman was giving his presentation he
definitely stole the show
so honorable strategies as a company
organization that helps tribes and
outside organizations with tribal
engagement
we um if you see here on the on the
screen or maybe it's not their own
that's it
so I I just wanted to share a little bit
about these photos
um that's actually a young girl from the
um Pine Ridge Indian Reservation that's
where horse she's an amazing horse
um her horsemanship is amazing but um
you know
they obviously struggle with a lot of
issues and they are huge Farmers but
they deal with a lot of water issues
um the picture of the basket is
um a basket of the Whirlwind and it's in
regards to perpetual motion
and that our people believe in and when
it comes to our gathering rights um we
have still difficulties to the to this
day so I wanted to be able to show you
just a little bit about us as a people
I'm going to
stay pretty close to my time I think and
and just FYI
being on Tribal Council
and I'm sure this is a way for you guys
as well we're always insured or when we
provide a presentation or someone
provides a presentation to us uh
it's direct here's the information
um although I'm a little jealous because
there are some really great pictures I
was like man I should add more pictures
but I did not I'm just really I'm
actually stepping back a little bit
OnePlus strategies also we are the
ambassadors of
um the nation of Hawaii the nation of
Hawaii is that who I'm out of Oahu
Ottawa Manolo obviously there's a lot of
people for the nation of Hawaii but this
specific group is responsible for
re-establishing the rapuno and they are
total Sovereign so if you want more
information on that I can share that as
well so what I wanted to do was kind to
kind of take you back because I always
want to make sure that people understand
the beginning in order for you to learn
um how to walk you had to start at the
beginning
in order to learn you how to start at
the beginning
so that's extremely important for me
and it is amazing that a lot of people
in regards to when they talk about
manifest destiny
that's actually one of the first things
that we as tribal people learn
um about Manifest Destiny not too many
people really understand the definition
to that
um my young daughter my son and my
nieces and nephews understand manifest
destiny
um and I won't go into the definitions
and and please if you guys get a chance
um
you'll really grasp a concept
about our tribal people if you
understand the different arrows that had
gone through and um in this is I'm going
to tie it into the farm bill and
conservation
so quickly after Manifest Destiny
there's Discovery and Conquest treaty
making you know I don't have to read
them to you but the removal and
relocation act that has a really huge
effect on us in regards to
um taking action Regard in in farming
because when you remove a people from a
land and then you put them on a smaller
one they then have to create another way
to address or their feed their families
and then we have a cultural tie we have
a cultural tied to the land
the land that we sit on is tells a
creation story of the people that were
here this was their beginning place
and so there's there's a large
uh and there's a disconnect so for
allotment and assimilation
that was uh again at a difficult time
for us to try to re-engage back into
um into farming into agriculture into
supplying for our life and and for our
people the regular
reorganization act and self-government
uh was an opportunity for us to be able
to re-establish who we are although it
didn't really
um happen that way and then you suffered
the termination act the termination act
where there were tribes where they were
just no longer in existence
the United States government said
you're no longer a people
and um so that was devastating
and then we came obviously to the
self-determination act and um that is
actually to the present time
so again I'm you know I'm not going to
go into details to them but when we talk
about the federal responsibility and the
power of Indian Affairs we as tribes
and I'm sure many of you everything how
many of you met with tribal leaders or
tribal staff
not too many of them so although tribal
leadership doesn't want to meet with
staffers they want to meet with you know
the representatives but I think it's
extremely important that you do engage
it's extremely important for you to
engage with what is happening with the
tribes so
the federal government has a fiduciary
responsibility
to address tribes and you know I don't
need to go into detail what you guys
know about us as tribes but so um
the next page is I wanted to give you
guys a little bit of insight on on
um
our phases or just phases of Engagement
sorry go on here here it is these are my
notes
so
um
I think that's probably one of the the
hardest things for
the outside communities to understand
and this isn't our this is in regards to
[Music]
um
a process and and understanding the
tribe's needs
especially around now that there's a
there's a huge interest in in tribes and
conservation it's not just an interest
you have DOI stating that we as tribes
have a place and we need to be heard
so um
and and I don't know if any of you guys
know in here that there are over there's
574 tribes within the United States
um that doesn't mean that that includes
all of them obviously I'm not talking
about the ones that have been terminated
so there are some states that don't have
trials but that doesn't mean that that
was in tribal land at one time so when
you engage with tribes
um the phases of it or I call it phases
but
you know tribes are
um tribes are key to the success success
of conservation
and the efforts for the with the United
States is is trying to establish the
reason why is we
have
um we have we hold the knowledge and
it's not just the tribes here it's the
indigenous people but we hold the
knowledge of traditional ecological
knowledge
I've heard tribal leaders say well if
they would have listened to us
then that probably wouldn't happen right
the flooding probably wouldn't happen
the burns probably wouldn't happen
um you know we would have had a lot more
to you know to sustain our our people
and that's just not the people of the
reservation but that's the people of
this United States
so
um again these are just suggestions
and I said it earlier to initiate
conversation among small groups tribal
leaders tribal technical experts but I
can ensure that you understand that it
is extremely important to talk to the
right tribal person
do not assume that Binet is here
speaking for all of Indian country
because I in no way can do that
or am I even allowed to do that
so it's extremely important to find the
proper one and I know that's a little
difficult because our world is pretty
um
can get a little crazy but um you know
you have people like myself and I know
you guys have talked to tribal people so
I'm really excited that they did mention
that
and and when you go into the next phase
so the first phase of that is engagement
and hearing the stories of the people
the second phase would be
um
again that were important to
conservation efforts into oh that's the
same thing isn't it but it's feedback
right I'm sorry that's the same thing
I'm like
I think I copy and pasted the wrong
things I apologize you guys but I don't
need that phase two is just comments and
feedback you want to be able to engage
with tribes to hear what their story is
you want to have them tell you their
issues
um how many of you in here know about
tribal water rights
it's huge that is going to be a game
changer when it comes to the farm bill
in conservation
that that I would
um
do your do your studying on that because
it's extremely important and they're all
different for every every tribe
so um my tribe is was in a 45-year Water
lawsuit against the federal government
we there was five of us the Soboba tribe
which is out in Southern California they
were in the 73-year
lawsuit which again
uh
water rights is described that we as
tribes would have that but
it was obviously taken from us
so in regards to like step three and um
which is in the next next steps once you
do engagement once you do conversation
once you hear the story and you build
um you maybe collaboratively build
policy
but you also Implement what was what was
established
and um those are those are things that
I've seen in being extremely successful
in uh conservation efforts USDA I know
nrcs is everywhere and they're doing
some amazing jobs but again out of the
574 tribes maybe 20 of those tribes are
seeing those efforts and so again my
goal here today is to emphasize on uh
engagement emphasize in learning your
community
um and and understanding that you don't
have
um you may not have all the answers or
you may not know who to go to but
I'd like to Simply say is there's 50
states
there's 50 governors
there's 574
tribes
pretty sure not all 574 tribes get to
talk to
whether it be the president or the
Congress or the Senate so
it would be nice but I can understand
the difficulty of a program or a
representative in in wanting in needing
to talk to individuals
um
so
well wrong one sorry
um
so the in in the past probably three
years I've been doing a lot of work in
regards to national monuments
land conservations
um different efforts in in developing
policies around that even most recently
uh discussion at the National Congress
American Indians on the farm bill and
the need for water rights
but um this is something I wanted to
provide you guys kind of like as an
Insight you know to learn the purpose
and the process of of public lands and
their efforts you know that's what
should be either conveyed to the tribes
or having an understanding of what the
tribes are how they're looking at it and
then another part is to learn from one
another and learn from tribes what they
see as opportunities to collaborate on
protecting lands and other natural
resources that are important to the
tribe and to ngos and USD USDA efforts
and advocacy groups and I mentioned that
because the
um
as just most recently
we when you talk about water rights and
then you talk about lack of access of
fishing or
um
or any any foods one of the things that
I think salmon brought it up
was oh no it was um Elaine Elaine is
like right Eileen excuse me was the
um was talking about
flood Plains
so
and this is again I'm just going to give
you guys examples because it does affect
all of us in different ways
the
live view to zero tribe was up in from
upper Michigan
they are affected by the damning of some
of their lakes and they now lack wild
rice
which was a main source of food for
their people
they now lack walleye the main source of
food for their people
and like every culture food
the land the animals ties in to our Our
Lives
they are also suffering from being shot
at by simply fishing
off of their
um their traditional lands it may not be
their land but
they have the rights and so they're
dealing with that in 2023
amazing but it you know what happens so
um extremely important to hear the
issues that you know tribes are dealing
with when it comes to
um
again the different the issues that are
happening
um so
to emphasize uh the next one is to
emphasize on the significance of tribal
involvement going forward in
conservation efforts and to convey ways
tribes can be involved and stay
connected that's extremely important
because
as tribes or
governing the rest of their people's
lives they now have to address this new
thing that's coming about
and um most of the tribes well not most
tribes you have level different levels
of tribes right not all tribes have
this large budget or not all tribes have
this extensive structure of government
not all tribes have the technical
assistance or the funding you know to do
those type of things there are some
tribes that are only 12 members
there are some tribes that are 75 000
members
and and so it's it's it's there's
they're so diverse
so
um
and again and one other thing I think
it's extremely important is you know
in strengthening tribal engagement
consultation and capacity building
implementation and process to ensure
that whether it be conservation efforts
or in regards to the farm bill as well
as efforts are responsive and engaging
with tribal communities engagement is
key so what should tribes expect to
engage with and this is not just with
NGO and conservationists but also UCA
communities
in groups is helping shape the planning
process and be used to develop the
management and develop management plans
for conservation efforts
tribes historically have been
have policies
in laws written form and then it's put
in front of them and say here you go try
I wrote this for you now you have to
abide by it it is extremely important to
have the tribes at the table to be able
to develop those policies and it's a
tribes will collaborate with others
because I obviously you guys are doing
it and we obviously need to talk because
I'm totally gonna send your name out to
everybody I know
um so it's extremely important because
it you know talking to a lot of tribes
that I work with you know that's the
that's the last thing they want is not
to be involved in a policy that's
supposed to oversee
um any lands or traditional lands that
they're that they're addressing or
concerns and so and then one final thing
is
as we start to work on these
policies and plans
the burden or maybe it's a conservation
effort the burden now lays on the tribes
shoulders
where is the funding going to come from
when the tribes are asked to even review
a document maybe they don't have legal
counsel to even do that so that is
something that has to be really
considered is
you may be expecting the tribe to
have a seat at the table but
where's the funding and the expectation
coming from
and
just the tribe have that capacity so
tribes need assistance in funding
technical assistance assistance training
and capacity building to address the
asks of either ngos conservations
um goals and efforts it's extremely
important I am I've asked a couple of
different people and told them that was
coming and the biggest thing they said
is if you're going to talk to the
staffers ensure that they understand to
carry the message
that
funding is extremely important
and capacity
and to understand the structure of the
individual tribe that you're working
with or the individual community
so
am I on time because you can cut me off
anytime
share this and
um
so we were extremely honored when
representative Deb Holland
um and secretary I'm sorry secretary Deb
Holland was
placed at the Bureau of Indian Affairs
so the comment that she says
is
our community our communities deserve
fresh air to breathe clean water to
drink and and a livable planet but right
now
in action on climate change is putting
everything at risk particularly in
communities of color
and so I saw that and I thought you know
you can't help but repeat that several
times
the the the the uh below the the couple
paragraphs that I put in there are
actually
statements from the chairman of the Fort
Mohave tribe
chairman Tim Williams they most recently
were able to establish
um evict
which is
um
uh for their people what was their
beginning place and it was an it was an
amazing opportunity
to help preserve the land so
um just really quickly these are just
examples of USDA I know I'm getting shut
cut for a time here and then
um a couple others there's the Ute the
Cheyenne
um Cheyenne River and then that's my
name but
I just wanted to add really fast I tried
to when I thought about the 12 minutes I
was like holy crap
um
but in regards to the insurance
one of the things that I wanted to make
sure that people understand is that when
it comes to tribal land we sometimes
can't
have house insurance or flood insurance
because of the way that our land is
established
so when I ex when I share the importance
of really understanding the tribes it
really is important to understand each
tribe and its individual capacity
because it's we don't have the luxuries
you know not all of us are you know um
you know at that point but again there
are a majority of us that can't afford
that so
so that's my name uh that's my company
and I'm I hope I helped out
[Applause]
read all the time American Indian
American Justice it's by blind delorea
he writes a lot of
all right
um we have maybe time for one or two
quick questions from the audience if
there is one I'm not sure if there is
but we are at time unfortunately
um I think since maybe since it's been a
little while since we've heard Samantha
and Eileen uh especially since you were
our first two panelists let's wrap up
with a quick lightning round
um question before we end for the
afternoon and that lightning round
question is
we've covered a lot of ground today
I suspect there are lots of things we
could suggest to improve when it comes
to conservation programs but
you could change one thing
with existing programs to promote
conservation what would that one thing
be Samantha we'll start with you and
then we'll go down the line and I'm
really interested in what you have to
say
can y'all hear me great
thanks again for all the time today
thank you for to ESI for having us I
would say especially after hearing my
colleagues speak
there's a lot of information in the
white paper hope you all grab a copy
read it but
our proposal to support farmer to Farmer
learning
seems most relevant especially to be
moving outside of the sort of existing
technical assistance really
science-based strategies and to provide
some capacity building for communities
that are historically marginalized from
accessing those programs so I would say
building up more farmer to Farmer
engagement and learning providing
funding for those purposes and capacity
building that would be my number one
thing
um I think we can there's probably a
million different suggestions we could
make about how to make all these
programs easier to work with and things
like increased sustainable funding
um but for for me and um for American
Rivers I think one of the the
key changes that we would love to see
within many of the conservation programs
within nrcs is to align them to be to
work with rivers and recognize Rivers as
a dynamic part of our ecosystem and that
land around them the flood Plains and
the riparian areas as being really
critical to the health of our society
and our clean water
um so doing things like enhancing the
floodplain easement program and
improving that and making sure that all
of our other conservation programs work
with the rivers and help to protect and
restore them as valuable ecosystems that
they are
hello okay so
um I want to mention because of the
gentrification and displacement that I
mentioned before this is usually caused
by Americans coming from the United
States as well as the Jones act that was
imposed by our Colonial
impose well Colonial status so I feel
like conservation programs should
prioritize on create a type of senses
that prioritizes farmers that are from
Puerto Rico living in Puerto Rico as a
type of preparation because we are a
little bit behind than other farmers in
the U.S because we have struggles we
have to go like through a couple of
struggles before we get to even knowing
about this conservation programs so
create an accurate senses of who because
basically if I am from an American that
moves to Puerto Rico and creates an
irocological project I can benefit from
a USDA conservation program just like a
humble family from the middle from a
rural part of the country so creating
that reparation and that
type of responsibility towards the
people that have been
basically marginalized in these programs
is important and also understanding that
is equity and not equality when it comes
to Puerto Rico in relations to us
Benet you put a lot of things on the
table that we could euphemistically call
opportunities for improvement uh but
like to give you the last word of our
briefing today
thank you I would
um ask that
it take a Grassroots effect with in
conservation effort because
of what it creates which is opportunity
equity and
growth but it also causes a riff
and so you have large farmers who are
looking at it in a different way and
it's affecting their their bottom line
but there has to be an understanding so
I would ask for that holistic approach
to be a main point
thank you very much
um we had a tremendous panel today I
think our panelists deserve a round of
applause for their contribution
I'd like to say once again special
thanks to Representatives Mason Davids
for joining us with the pre-recorded
video intro marks introductory remarks
big thanks to Senator Welch and his
great staff for helping us get the room
today although next time maybe we'll try
to get ourselves supported me though
that looks like a pretty nice place to
be today
um also there are two people in our
online audience who helped us assemble
the panel today big thanks to Shauna and
Nathan uh you know who you are
um great friends of the organization and
we really appreciate your assistance
also
um there's a really significant size to
team at ESI who pulls these briefings
off I'd like to say big thanks to Dan
O'Brien Omri Alice and Anna Molly and
Nicole as well as Aaron who is our
newest member of Team eesi he is
hopefully watching on the live cast
because he hasn't quite relocated to DC
yet but Aaron welcome aboard and we have
four tremendous summer interns uh
Georgia America parathav and Sydney
thank you for joining us and all your
help parthav was just
taking the most studious notes I've ever
seen of the of the briefing today and
all the live tweeting and everything
that goes done so thanks very much I
know that because I was sitting next to
you I wasn't I'm not spying
um this is our last briefing for a
little while but we'll be back on July
18th that's a Tuesday all day ninth
floor of the Senate Heart Building for
the renewable energy and Energy
Efficiency Expo we'll have six great
panels uh tremendous speakers Executives
from across the clean energy sector and
the climate advocacy space uh it's going
to be something you don't want to miss
and at five o'clock the lights will turn
blue and there'll be a reception so even
if you're a little bit too busy to stop
by during the day that's okay you can
still come by and network it's fun to
network on Capitol Hill uh and we'll
help you with that
um let's see there it is right there uh
this is a survey link
um at the end of every briefing if
you've come to our briefings before we
always post this survey link uh if you
have a moment to take that survey
provide your feedback was there stuff
that you liked today didn't like today
did you have any audio problems video
problems uh anything like that ideas for
future topics please um take a moment we
read every response and it means a lot
to us when people take the time to
participate in our survey we'll go ahead
and wrap sorry for going a few minutes
over but uh really really great panel
today learned a ton about conservation
programs in the farm bill and uh can't
wait to um to keep learning about all
sorts of great stuff when we get to the
Expo and when we get back after Labor
Day we've got a really excellent slate
of congressional programming that we'll
uh underway so hope everyone has a great
rest of your Wednesday and we'll see you
on July 18th hopefully for the clean
energy and Energy Efficiency Expo thanks