Good agricultural practices or GAP. It's
a concept which been developed by the
United Nations Food and Agriculture
Organization FAO. And the aim for GAP is
for looking at agricultural commodities
and developing a safe and healthy
product at the end of the whole supply
chain. Now to do that one has to then
develop what is the best agricultural
practices both pre and post-h harvest
for a particular commodity.
The GAP approach has been used quite
successfully in horiculture but now it's
being applied to commodities such as
rice. Now one of the challenges is that
to develop a uh approach which is
ratified at a national level so that
farmers can get accreditation but also
to have that approach so it's ratified
at an international level and meets
international guidelines um and there
are quite a number of different
guidelines for example the international
um compliance for plant protection. So
we're looking at a process which is
providing a product which is not only
safe but also consistent with something
which is sustainable in environmental
context. So we're looking at sustainable
resource management.
So in currently there is rice GAP being
developed in Vietnam and also in
Thailand and there's a lot of other
interest in Southeast Asia in developing
rice GAP but we're still at the early
stages. In Vietnam at the moment,
there's about a 100 farmers that have
been ratified, usually as groups and
they are ratified at by a a national
committee and those farmers are able to
get a 20% premium on the rice that they
produce.
But whether that can be sustained
because if you have lots of farmers who
become ratified then maybe might be
difficult to maintain that economic
incentive. But more importantly is if
you're an exporting nation such as
Vietnam and Thailand
to certain markets such as Europe then
is expected that the exporting nation as
is providing a product which is ratified
as being consistent with GAP. So that is
an expectation which is going to develop
even more so particularly in Europe
European Union there any product that's
imported has to be certified to be GP.
So that is the incentives and the need.
So it's an incentive at a farmer level
but also at a national level. But with
countries like the Philippines which
don't export but import, it's still
important to have GP because the GOP
also is an indication of society demands
and society is now demanding more and
more particularly from the cities that
they have a product which is safe and
safe and nutritious for them and their
families. So if you're a farmer in the
Philippines that's producing rice for a
domestic market, then there's also going
to be as time develops uh an a need an
essential need to develop rice under GAP
practices.
In Vietnam, we have a study site in
Anjiang in the province in the Mikong
Delta. And that province is seen as
being a um it's a model province for
good agricultural practice for rice. And
so part of that JP is developing best
practice both pre and post-h harvest. So
we're working very closely with the
Vietnamese government and the provincial
government in Anjiang as a model where
we're bringing in our natural resource
management technologies from the
irrigated rice research consortium and
helping them to develop the best
practice for pre and post harvest. And
so now we've been rolling it out um
since the beginning of 2009
and now it has been labeled under a five
reductions one must do initiative and
that is now taking um place in Anjiang.
It's generated lots of support from the
provincial government and now the local
the national government is looking how
that can be diffused to other provinces
in the Mikong.