first thing I'd like to do is thank all
our sponsors that helped us put together
my input and my upper teeth that I'm on
the streets or the less South Dakota
wheat commission Farm Credit Services of
America wheat growers Mustang seat
Montana first agencies next level egg
LLC billboards needs lacrosse needs the
capacity add Rodney Plus farmers
Alliance missile first coat of National
Bank CB operations of the experiment
stopped replying content that's
unlimited for our County Conservation is
B Davidson County Conservation is we had
to Comicon survey statistics output on
sale Association SDSU extension USD and
NRCS and pioneer hi-bred the DuPont so
let's give them all over welcome
Corey Cronin Casey Cronin and we're
seeing such a big value in bringing
livestock into our farming operation
because it was a few years ago we
decided that wasn't the thing we should
do and now we're going to excuse me if
you guys can't see but you know that
Casey and I are going to kind of
tag-team this but you know and see the
data on the bottom 2007 so we've been
grazing the coverage since 2007 the more
we learned the more questions we have
we're trying to put cents to this in
dollars wise because that's what we
really feel we have to do you can say
whatever you want to do but it still
comes down to about $2 they said they
said but on the Leopold award you guys
in and you know besides Janet could
she's a young one but just look at right
here cut this in half and look at the
age of these people right here everybody
on our farm understand soil health what
we need to do to make soil health and
when we talk we talk a lot of carbon we
talk a lot of soil health because soil
health is a driving force and if a
person doesn't think it is if we keep
doing what we're doing the next 10 years
we're going to every year we see it so
soil health is it is it really a driving
force Katie's going to hear Corey Casey
know we've got about 775 cows cow cats
that we have out every year we run on
about 8,500 acres mostly along the river
here and pastures and then we we take
them back up to the farm in the
wintertime and that's where we do all
our cover crop graze and corn stocks get
out on the field
so this slide thought was pretty
interesting this is I didn't ever
understand that well why can't we just
mold this pasture off what's the big
deal with that I mean it's there it's
going well this pretty much explains it
once I got used to that where if you are
leaving something you're going to have a
lot more to graze later on you know what
I then and I
really appreciate what Casey and Cory
are doing and not saying money wasn't
there also but they're really
understanding the the divide tenses in
the movement and different water systems
and sold but I mean not I just think
that's something you guys you don't
think about that but just think I mean
that's and this is something that you
know you can't put a value on this is
Casey and Wylie you cannot put a value
on what the what Casey's doing to build
for the future because that's what we
have to do you know but the one thing is
is so there are three generations to
build the lasting legacy so on our farm
we want everybody to understand what's
going on we want to understand why we're
doing this we're not doing this just
because it's it's it doesn't cost as
much whatever we understand and we're
all building soil health you know one
thing we talked about rain and
everybody's gets everybody talks about
well yeah you got this rain we got this
rain and so you know 19 inches as our
norm but so we these are our pivots down
here so in in May June in July we had
half as much rain that's what we
normally do in the last 30 years so you
need the soil health you need to have
the good growth you need to capture
every bit of water you can do and that's
where pivots come in because it usually
used to be corn bean guys and we found
out where that really isn't what we
should do and then another thing and we
will protect our resource we we farm we
ranch up along this river and we are
going to protect that resource so these
are some of the rotations but this is
the neatest thing about the rotations if
any time we can we come back with a
cover we come back with the cover we
come back with that cover it's a graze
and cover Casey
so this is done yahooza pointer okay
here's a green so we can tell each other
apart we can do all here so this is one
of the the circles down on the river up
above we planted peas on it
combine the peas and went in with a with
the six-way mix like it says there we
luckily had the the pivot on it we
watered it up and then we ran ran our
cows on it for a couple weeks and then
after that we turned in we fenceline
Wiener calves which would really like
and they were we turned the cows in
their cows around the other calves were
on the other side of it and the college
just went to Eton and everybody just
kind of weaned themselves after that we
harvested the lower circles the cows
went down on that we put the calves in
for a couple more weeks on that and got
quite a bit of value on it calves did
great on it really really excited to do
some more of that so you know another
thing and what Doug brought up and we'll
get into it later too is the neat thing
about grades and covers I mean I figure
I'll take in 20% we're always going to
lead part of our residue we're going to
leave a third of our residue that's
carbon now it's protection to the ground
we're never going to graze it in the
ground we've got at least 10% but you
guys are snow here so they Casey what
you probably kept the calves out of the
feedlot for another two three weeks and
then just touch once on on grades and
younger cattle how they how they adapt
where the older date yeah so these gaps
well we went to a fence light weeds and
your 2015 with the first preview did it
and those jobs they just seem to take
off by themselves and they're out there
on that grass they're doing what they're
supposed to you haven't been sending a
lot and now we're having out there well
this be the second group of peppers that
we tapped out and those house they spend
more time out grazing on a field that
everything we get them up to the place
and anything with ever app they'll
they'll go after that stuff pull your
tracker laying out there that's where
they want to be an update I feel it
attributes to the best line weaning
event get them out early office of
profit college students
you know there's totally still appease
from and you know it takes a while to
click especially for me because I'm I'm
old and gray haired I listen to it I
don't believe it I don't believe it
don't believe it's the fourth time I
said well you know there is something
here but you know all you're doing in
cycle and you residue faster and you but
you want to leave that third but you
want to cycle that residues faster to
make it available for next year's crop
I'm going to talk some on carbon because
carbons are tremendously important
things this whole system we have to
harvest carbon we have to harvest carbon
and what do you how you do that is you
do it through plant management carbons
the key ingredient to organic matter
everybody talks about organic matter
carbon is 57 percent organic matter 57
percent carbon so the only way we're
going to harvest carbon is we're going
to help things grow under their green
we're going to take in the carbon from
the air so and I think that there's just
not enough emphasis put on this because
with us we've got a full system
approached where our covers you're
harvesting carbon we don't want to we
want to leave our residue so it's up
it's a kind of a holistic approach you
know this is a nation that destroys that
soil destroys itself so this is the way
we were this is the way we were and but
now I don't know so what's that grandpa
telling his grandson he said I made a
mistake it took me about 10-15 years of
mining your organic matter but I made a
mistake it's up to you to fix it it's up
to you to fix it and this is the best
way we can do it with covers I'm not
saying only farming but as long as we
think about the carbon it's just a
win-win this is what we've done in our
place not going to spend a lot of time
this is grass soil sample it was been
grass put in after the 30s and so that's
kind of what we've done on our place
benefits of organic matter water holding
capacity is a huge one and then the I
just
you just can't emphasize what organic
matter will do
what a percent of organic matter will do
we've got to start a great deal of
carbon once stored in the soil no store
in the atmosphere we need to retain this
back into the soil assume us just have
to do that so I'm not talking about
building organic matter I'm talking
about building soils on our full season
covered this is a shovel full of soil if
Casey's holding the shovel but so what
we're building soil so it's residue
humans good job Casey organic master
topsoil so you know and I never you know
how things kind of slow I'm slow but I
hang around during Dwayne Beck we went
to Montana for a week great week geez
just unreal but one thing he said he
said when if you guys ever noticed when
you walk along down in the in town and
all of a sudden the sidewalk down in
this and you say boy that sidewalks sunk
that sidewalk didn't sink the organic
matters building soil so you're building
soil so when you walk out in our fields
even the ones that we they're grazed all
the time with your with so if you manage
it right it's just like walking on a
really nice shag carpet you can feel
that cush well what you're doing right
now is you're building houmous you're
building organic matter it's just a
win-win situation you've got to feed
these Doug talked on that you've got to
feed these so this is a mistake
in 2006 we planted her first field of
cover crop everything went 2007 it
rained and boy that's a nice field but
you know where the mistake was made we
didn't pay any attention to the carbon I
went in there with a very low carbon no
carbon so all of a sudden I was paying
it took me about three years after that
to make up for that proof so now anytime
we talk about cover crop we want we want
the carbon nitrogen ratio to be up there
carbon you know and then so these are
just three different mixes
I will get back to Casey someone said
Casey and I are going to talk and he
said yeah I feel sorry for Casey so
cover crop and carbon nitrogen this came
from Ray Ward and this all makes sense
the one thing you guys and this is where
the NRCS has got to help help and they
will when you start talking about a
cover crop with a carbon and nitrogen
ratio what you want I want a 24 to 30 a
lot of people tabled why you even
talking about that on a cover crop I
think you have to talk about that on
cover crop but we have to find out what
plants because if you get into the
middle of August towards the end of
August you can't plant a it's hard to
get a high carbon it's hard to like a
forage sorghum it's too late in the year
so yet like a notes is a good one but
also get mature so you have to
understand how late you can go on this
season with Phil your carbon to nitrogen
ratio so this is where we want to be I
want to be like right up in here 26 to
one because our soil is reactive enough
I want to slow things down I want to
slow things down when I did at the other
time I was right down in here and we
just speed up
these are kids from Gettysburg FFA the
teacher he just look like oh the ones a
teacher could would the teacher want to
raise your hand okay
you guys find us find a chair there's
chairs around you know these are two
good books you guys and I really
especially this one any question you've
got on how much carbon what you're going
to do you could download this as a PDF
you can download that off the internet
it's just a really good book okay Casey
so so this is it's not have all this but
we're on this is kind of the chunk the
pasture we have most of it you know will
never ever be farming because it looks a
lot like that it's pretty rough country
thank goodness great great but now back
to the rotational stuff when I got back
it was well I think we should probably
move on well we don't have one health
road let's just open the gate
no moving so well after a couple weeks
of that you got it turned in on
everything you have so what we've done
is we started cross fencing we're
nowhere like doug is but that's kind of
the end goal is to try to break
everything up it's going to be a lot
easier to score
I run all the cows through us to handle
them in smaller pastures like that water
is going to present a challenge but
we're working on that and I've been
bringing them home Casey yes and then
this is where we bring home too with
this trail across country you're
bringing home this is where we run on
that home now
back to when I got home again when we
start a girl in cover crops in 2007
we just threw them on everything that we
have around there so they go when they
need the green stuff first and then you
know they're they're taking too much so
now we're starting to cross fence that
let them have certain things and then
we're controlling how much garden how
much we're reading we're taking 2/3
leading in thirds and that's our goal
we're seeing a lot more benefit than
that rather than just turning them out
lesson great let's take a cheese
you know what's new for 2016 and Casey
I'll let you touch on this this is the
helper you can't quite see the top but
it's the heifers yes so our first half
after is bringing hold a bell run this
is a full team right out back some kind
of a I don't basically a 38 a lot is
what is so they'll grades is down it and
we don't control this this is where we
be another thing
and then this is where they run but
there's also a porter out to the last
year that was planted because we went
back to cover drop the grades on that
and then to the north where that this is
this important stops and they also ran
on that now everything that's covered up
to gauge they'd open for them because
they they once they got through all this
we got covered up with snow
now that we've melted off they've headed
right back out to that cover and they're
dating tourism and hammering away on
that again so really really like reason
okay
you know this is something I did so I
talk about carbon talk about carbon look
at this cover crop mix there's no carbon
what I like is this price here turnips
I'm uh you know I think we're going to
go to a pod you turn up because the
purple top it grows but I mean it cattle
will kick it out easy and a pod you'll
get more of a tuber on it more relief
more of a grazer
I love plaque to mycorrhizae the for
HP's I don't know if I'll do that again
it's just because of the we have we have
a pulse crop center rotation I don't
know if I'll do that again but the
reason I did this is this is 7080 bushel
stripper headed Shelbourne stripper
headed what if we stumble so we had all
kinds of carbon we had all kinds of
carbons from that old straw so all I was
trying to do is put some low carbon and
another thing when that first flush of a
volunteer wheat came when I wanted to be
able to take it out with collected them
so you just take the grass out and you
leave everything else alone this is what
it was the for each piece had a great
year my big worry was is what was going
to happen now because with the cattle
eat this in case they'll let you do this
and they sure did yeah dispensed out and
out there there was a live field that
our planet that wasn't going to our full
season cover with this year next to this
and they just they hit open well but
they finally capped out on this move
them along through that before we got to
LOC this is the cow bouquet
now there were where we take our gas to
and start background you know we had a
hundred and eleven acres to this is
instead of our feedlot area here not
sure but this is the five way mix that
was planted our goal is to get out on it
but we thought we had more time than
what we did and it's no different we
just didn't get it done so it's a goal
to be able to at least for the calves
that we're keeping for our replacements
even grazing on that as long you know
and another thing in case you already
said this but our cattle really under
our or I'm I'm the cow but their cattle
really understand electric fences I mean
they respect and they really understand
them and the kids can move a offense in
a hurry so in 2016 we're going to have a
full season grades this sounds really
good on paper and it was will work on
paper but so we're going to have a full
season graze so this is our mix and
there's a reason for everything in here
what I was trying to do see the carbon
and nitrogen ratio was 32 to 1 that was
real important to me the buckwheat you
know a lot of people if you got
buckwheat if you have wheat next you got
to have a two years off wheat
otherwise the wheat can be rejected if
there's buckwheat and export I don't
know probably I like what it did
enhances phosphorus the old career is
going to go away the and then and then
the turnips is going to be a bit of a
podge of turnip kale I love kale a half
a pound the kale goes a long ways it
gets it will stay green until November
gets tall and then but you'll see all
these after the mycorrhizae association
and i think that's really important and
I'm not saying we're ever going to have
it to where
we cut out phosphorous altogether but
it's really what that'll do is you'll
actually go out and it'll it'll go it'll
trade carbon and they'll go and it will
trade it for organic phosphorus but look
at here the microwaves I so look at the
root system 700 times more root system
on the micro as I plant and I just think
this is something we just have to keep
keep in the back of your mind I mean you
guys that I hope there's no seed dealers
in here but if they do I hope you learn
from what I say is don't ever be
satisfied but the guy goes in and saved
this is what you need to plant you
research it and you'll be able that you
know enough what's going on where you're
telling him what you want this is a wee
planter and testable we we took a
cutting to tap off and then we always
leave the second cut and come back and
so the cattle graze this there's about a
foot of snow so there's a foot of
stubble left I mean they weren't on it
very long our cover crop mix everything
goes together
July 10th we're going to get rid of the
okra
I like this the it kind of scares you
and you look at the plan at the shorter
is just shorter brown mid Rhea but I
like brown midrib because of the press
ik acid it takes some of that threat
away or paretic acid and this is our
field layout and I wanted to find out so
there's a three-way mix known in and
then the rest of this we put on we had
40 units of we had about 80 units of in
on this and a lot of people said you
know it's it's you shouldn't have to put
fertilizer on covers and so we just
wanted to see so that's the full season
graze July 29th
there's our in our non end strips
there's a biomass 214th
so we did a Jason Miller came up in
August 14th we did a biomass and then
this is kind of what bothered me a
little bit because within there's 70 100
pounds of biomass and without the under
70 600 pounds of biomass
but you know you stop and think about it
the without the end the others does the
undergrowth like the forage peas and the
and the cow peas and everything they had
more chance to grow because they didn't
have the competition for sunlight so you
know I thought well did we waste our in
second biomass eleven twenty eight weeks
old
I really recommend everybody you do a
biomass if nothing else just to find out
where you're at so we just took a yard
square went out but you can see on our
twelve ways within look at the
difference there that went away but look
at here so 25 to one I said I wanted to
be 26 27 but I was still happy 11
percent crude protein but this is
something that we've got to get answered
and I don't know how we're going to
answer this right down here we had 80
200 pounds of biomass left 960 pounds of
protein or 144 pounds a.m. so how are we
going to get that back to next year's
crop someone said don't worry about it
but if you're if you're talking
financially you have to be thinking
about it so what we're doing is we're
grazing it so you're grazed the top two
thirds you leave the bottom third that
cycle through the cattle and so it
should be more available we still
Jason's we're going to work on this
quite a bit next summer we're trying to
get an answer to this on our farm so
here's our here's a great board and one
thing I like about sending down there
and I know there's a lot of good labs
but he'll actually give you a carbon
nitrogen ratio so I mean it's just uh we
felt really good about our mix so here
we go so we had a yield biomass we're
going to graze pounds had eighty eight
hundred forty thousand pounds six
hundred fifty twenty six pounds a day if
the temperatures right so we had forty
six pounds of grades and that sounds
easy without to slam dunk so we had $147
that's charged yourselves around one
hundred forty seven dollars into the
cover crop mix so we're going to it's
going to cost seventy-five cents a day
11% protein and here we go I mean
slam-dunk dollar 65 20 degrees to feed
through the wagon so that's one hundred
seventy two dollars an acre so let's
just write that down because we've
already made that I mean that's that we
you know so I figured on seventy bushel
spring wheat which that field would have
gone to at 475 we would indebted seventy
six dollars an acre so you know we're
kind of making headway plus he left the
manure on the field there's a lot of
benefit of what happened on the field
Casey suddenly he got into the winter
and Mother Nature has a different plan
Lord we started out well I mean nine
times 2020 to put it was back from home
for the river sooner and got on this
quicker and you know we would have had
all that but it started snowin and
between the snow and the beer the beer
itself it took away one of the paddocks
for us but it just we didn't get
everything out of it that we thought
plus it was cold so they were eating a
lot more than anticipated
this is a Fischer after 70 degrees in
one of the paddocks now you'd say well
you didn't leave a third there well that
smells a couple feet deep to it a lot in
Fletcher but the cattle I was happy with
them once we got them up there no summit
never ever left it I mean it you got
it's just out in the open on the
blasters not a lot of protection and
they dug through it got to get it out
again so I'm very happy with that part
you want you know so we've got another
one so we got to make sense to this we
have to make sense to this so just like
right now so you increase your feed is
the temperature drop so this is 24
degrees refrigerator is going to take 23
just about 24 pounds a day ok so now all
of a sudden we at we are average
temperature with the windchill was minus
3 what we were on that so you take that
so I take 31 pounds a day did they
really need it we're not going to let
our cattle go backwards their cattle
didn't go backwards right Casey so so
this is our average we had average
temperature average wind speed wind
chill but look at our max when speed is
you know so I mean it was a it was just
a tough winter you guys tough winter but
another thing 36 inches of snow and
everybody knows that Christmas what two
quarter inch of rain will do and so we
were still grazed in this so we had to
keep working at it yes and we might have
created a few months
by me but like I said we didn't wanna
let her account slip like I said earlier
some of them cows never ever left come
back and we were putting out through the
language but not a little silence made
and then we feet pieces or protein just
just so they were given up to keep
everywhere and then yeah so it says loss
of $35 per acre is kind of what we
figured that well but there again I mean
you gotta look at it as you're kind of
doing this for the future - so what is
it going to do this year for our crop
and a few things like that it's hard to
put a value on some of that go ahead
yeah we've got a lot of deer are doing
over I wouldn't recommend a deer or
until but we have my dad left his Ranger
in the tracks so if he didn't figure you
need them in Arizona so we use that
otherwise we probably would have wore
out those snowshoes but a lot of our
chain but they tore down our fence
pretty much every day the cows stayed
pretty good they didn't they filled it
like step across that you know it's on
the ground we battled it a little bit
but these deer they sit there we started
on started on the east and give them
give them that chunk for their side
chops and then we just work your way
less than worker we eat candies here you
go out there to move fast and they just
kind of hang that move off a little bit
and then they just stayed on the stuff
that the cows were on till we got to the
to the end of it that we made they have
some good taken out of it so we
definitely lost part of it too that the
whole north side was it was tough for
the cows you can get it it was bit fluid
it was chest deep on me so but after
after it felt a little bit those house
did go in there hey strangers what they
stood out
you know Casey's and another thing too
with this is your side the paddocks were
yet all right what's it are would you do
it different or what do you think then
like how we productions and jam
everything about space to get around and
everything without number of cows on
there I thought I thought it worked out
real well okay then we did do a Belgrade
this year for the first time so this
about 63 acres that it's kind of between
the windbreak and the PTR in the water
and everything so it stays open to the
cows over here so we just got to be I
mean every year at discount abused well
what we did is we planted it back grass
we took their first cutting hay off of
it this year we took bailed off and then
we decided well let's let's go ahead and
bail green so we took that we're going
to go build back out and and we have
never thought of but I I got there on
the loader
Cory but all that plug them all has to
work very very well you can see how
Jesus no is I I was worried about him
getting out around in there but and then
just like Doug today I was cross that
and there's a layer of ice underneath
there that leads to put keep a thin
layer a on it
this year will probably rest it our
bowls get a little anxious that right
along with highway 83 so it was the
reading time they like to venture out or
else we're going to bring them up and
grade this with them just kind of just
equipment for up to three weeks and then
that will rest goes for the ended here
and then we'll decide whether we want
the other grades again this year or
arrested much
this is just kind of the layout so this
is the farm here this is where we build
race here this is our feed yard here
this is corn stocks this is winter wheat
so this will go back to a to agreement
cover this is going to be our post even
just kind of a layout the thing that
I've learned the most since I've gotten
back even on the grass pasture group if
you have a plan going into something
you're a lot more likely to do it rather
than just saying well maybe I should do
this you set yourself up with some some
sort of a plan anything you can go
deviating from that whatever but have
some type of plan in place I need to
work a lot for us because it's so easy
to say well yeah let's go ahead and move
in taos today or whatever Jeff if you
know what direction you want to go with
it it's a lot easier city you know
another thing I want to compliment Casey
Corey on because they came up with the
plan before Kyle did come home and it
was just wherever they wanted to go and
they actually had it where they had a
fence here they ran the corn stalks for
a while we kept them off of here because
this is wonderfully and but excuse me it
is not this wouldn't wait down here
but anyway so this the full season
grades but everything they had a plan on
how they were going to raise them you
know it's old and like you say this is
planted back to Rye I like rye but so
this is corn stocks and the and the
heifers ran they came through the fence
they ran here and they ran here so what
we'll do after corn stocks we want to
keep our carbon up we're big believers
in carbon so what we'll do is we'll come
back with oats
we love oats we love oh so also come
back and then and then we'll actually
didn't come back with the cover after
our oats
so our heifers next year pull teas and
grades which that's just the way it
works and then here and then this will
be corn stocks that right on and then
another thing this is a this is a slough
area of what we call it where they feed
dead for a lot of years and what we do
now is we put a full season cover in
there one thing to you guys on full
season cover when you do a biome out we
get a biomass on this and we send it in
and the clip it at the ground so all the
sudden you say where you are
where are your on nitrates that's
something you've got to be very
concerned about don't ask your neighbor
if it's is safe to graze find out find
out a nitrate test and so what we were
like we were just when
with clipped all the way to the ground
we're right at 1,400 parts per million
so that didn't really concern us because
we knew we're only going to let them
have 2/3 and then KC as far as will they
ever go back to the old paddock
once they grade the paddock and they
move it will they go back they do I mean
that's kind of a good telltale to when
you do when you need to move to is if
you come back to another one but nowhere
every time we move it they seem to go
after the new stuff now after we were
all done we knew we've had so much under
the snow that we love have it for the
whole thing for another week and it
pretty much even expand out but they
they love it up there that's where they
want this is just a picture that this is
going to be next year's cover so we cut
silage and are kind of our goal I don't
know if we'll get away from it right
cases to maybe eliminate silage but I
don't know if we will or not but we
really like to plant right back on we're
in wonderful country but we really
manage your ride we don't let it ride
get very big but it's unbelievable to
what the root structure will be from Rye
you know and Doug talked a lot about
Canada and the round you know and so we
say we can't do this and but they're
doing it but one thing I think and this
is what we need to do I mean I'm not
saying any of these but this is what we
need to do they've got it they've got a
number for their nutrient cycling and we
need to do that as a farm we need to do
that and we will find that out some guys
say well what difference to make take
half a cap I think we really need to to
understand what's going on you can tell
your soils healthy by looking at it has
great texture crumbles like maurice
chocolate cake it will have a smell of
the freshly dug potato so if you guys
ever come to our farm the first thing
we're going to do is we will get some
soil i'm not going to cauldron i'm going
to call it soil i'm going to ask you to
smell it because it will smell if you've
got healthy soil yourself soil tell you
our farm and ranch fields we should do
everything we can to make this a better
world you know we do not ask ourselves
why we know the answer and the picture's
worth a thousand words we've got a
little clip here of the time-lapse
um that we're going to show and it was
kind of neat the NRCS say they put a
camera out when the cover crop was just
tall and it's still out there right now
but they're going to Joshua guns this is
uh in the middle of though like the
third week in November so you can kind
of see what we're up against but you
could see on a normal year where we
would had a pretty good grade even there
we could handle
ladies getting beer in the picture we do
Randy Halverson it was a contract with
NRCS and and and there are a ton Dakota
lakes the cameras are still there and
the cameras still out there so it's
going to be well you can see here now
we're getting to the end I mean it's the
college route to your grazing right now
and you'll be able to see the deer right
see there's a deer right now just so you
think well that's about enough snow so
you can see what we were up against I
mean so I feel really good about what
happened because I don't you Casey still
save a ton of evening by doing all this
and close into the soils and so is this
so is this a one year out of 10 it
probably is that's just like saying is
there going to be dry next year well I'm
not going to go plant my corn very heavy
to that's going to be dry so we're going
to go ahead with things and we're going
to take the average so
you