so we're using a John Deere 1025r with
an ideal 48 inch tiller on the back and
so
any subcompact tractor you know your 20
to 25 horsepower range or typically what
you're going to see using a 48 inch
tiller about the same width as the
tractor but all your Kubota BX series
your massive subcompacts coyote New
Holland LS you're basically going to run
a 48 inch Taylor at 60 inch is just too
large so this is breaking new ground
here and so we're going to go over this
multiple passes because we're gonna go
down and back for the first handful of
passes and and show you what that looks
like and then at the very last pass
we're going to go down back down back so
for four total passes show you the
difference it's breaking up chopping up
all the side all the grass all the roots
that are up on top a few rocks here and
there that you're going to see but in
subsequent years once you have that side
broken up you're not going to have to go
over it nearly as often to have really
great and consistent results but in the
beginning if you're putting in a brand
new Garden or a brand new food plot
you're probably gonna have to spend a
little bit more time that first year
getting everything established