I am Shane Harris with a low-carbon
extension system you've got that raised
bed garden you always been wanting to
put in now you got to think about
planting that raised bed but planning a
rigs bed is a little bit different than
the traditional field or row garden you
don't need any equipment to plant this
garden and the spacing and the technique
is a little different than traditional
gardening let's take a moment and talk
about planting in the raised bed with
raised bed gardening we're going to
plant them on a block planting design
and unlike the traditional three-foot
rows the row gardening has a lot of
space that is wasted in a raised bed
garden we're not wanting to waste any
space for example large crops such as
tomatoes or squash will need to be on 24
inch centers whereas things like cabbage
potatoes or corn are spaced about a foot
apart smaller vegetables such as beans
peas or onions are usually around four
to six inches apart let's use this
illustration to explain the planting
techniques for the raised bed all
spacing is based on a 1 foot square
design and a 1 foot square spacing you
can get 32 plants this will be
appropriate for corn lettuce Irish
potatoes even okra
for larger plants such as cabbage
broccoli peppers and even collards 18
inch spacing is typically used are much
larger vegetables such as tomatoes
squash cucumbers and eggplant require 2
foot spacing many of the vegetables
require only 6 inch spacing
this would include beans peas and
especially carrots onions and even
smaller spaces for turnips or radishes
that's a lot of plants in a raised bed
using the block technique in a raised
bed there are multiple combinations and
planting designs that you can use the
idea is to maximize all available space
so that every foot of space has a plant
in it remember that dense planting
techniques result in higher production
of per square foot in the garden
hopefully more production will equal
success and a delicious harvest
for more information on raised bed
gardening contact your local County
Extension Office our visit us online at
a secede EU