[Music]
my name's Alan Farquhar this is our farm
at Belmondo email jokes
just outside of McCoy we found this
property since about 95 the
fourth-generation grower it's a good
farm down here nice and flat plenty of
irrigation and close to the sea and not
many neighbors which makes it very nice
to live down here as well the project
was initially suggested to me by a Maps
officer I could it sounded like a good
idea so I made contact with pharmacist
and then Shay got in touch and it's gone
on from being Ellen is a really
progressive farmer they've adopted
techniques such as controlled traffic
and minimum till and some legume fellow
crops for a number of years now so
working with Ellen we really had to
focus on the things that were gonna make
the biggest difference for this farm the
first year shaded a complete analysis of
our soil tests over many years and then
came back with fertilizer
recommendations for each block the
nutrient management plan was helpful
because it it gave me a different
perspective on how I could manage the
property particularly the the
intricacies of different blends for each
paddock there's been a few different
opportunities to join seminars and
workshops there's a soil seminar which
was very interesting and gave me a lot
of information about the current
thinking on soil science and how it
relates to cane production and the
nutrient uptake of a crop of cane going
to those Souls workshops and having like
an expert soil scientist sort of
validating what's being said on the
grounds really helps us in our
recommendations and also for the growers
to accept what we're sort of
recommending and giving them that deeper
knowledge of why we're recommending
these application rates it was a Google
Earth workshop which showed me a few
more tips and tricks when it comes to
using Google Earth which is very useful
the Google Earth training is useful as
we give each grower a USB and on that's
all their farm data we put yield maps on
there
locating of their soil samples any ec
mapping that they've done and also their
actual nutrient management plan so all
the details can be saved into Google
Earth and then they can add to to that
program
things like hydrant locations they can
plan a site for a new dam so it's really
a useful management tool they can use in
the future in addition as part of the
pharmacists package I got a few more G
dots for my irrigation system so that
tells me a lot more about my soil
moisture profile through the project we
offer growers either soil test G dots or
some EC mapping Allen he chose the G
dots and they can be a really useful
soil moisture sensor and telling us when
the soil profile is getting dry and
giving an indication of when irrigation
needs to start because Ellen's already
confident in his nutrient plans and what
fertilizer he can apply the G dot was a
good option for him to select as it's a
practical tool that can be used on farm
working with pharmacist gives you
someone else who's hasn't got a vested
interest in selling your fertilizer and
also is on your side as far as
productivity goes the project gives us
confidence that our farm management is
the best it can be and that as well as
working through the BMP project has
given me the confidence that my
operation can withstand any scrutiny
[Music]