hey folks it's Josh Danny rich farmer
welcome to the farm blog today got my
best kid helper here she's filling
buckets of water we're gonna go up and
what are the goats and check on them got
a few chores to get done here around the
house I've got to put a light on my gate
so when folks pull up to my gate I have
a power gate that's powered with a
mighty Mill gate opener and I really
like it but the biggest thing is we can
hit the button from the house up here
but you can't tell whether the gates
moving or not after dark so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna install a motion
light on it and you guys might have seen
the video where I installed some motion
lights on the house back here and they
turned out to be really really good so
come on along with just do some chores
here we've got to work on the rock wall
behind the house got to pick up loads of
rocks and sticks and also we still got
the Stoney Ridge farm shirts for a
limited time
mrs. Stoney Ridge is modeling one you'll
see them in the video so if you want to
get a shirts for a limited time only
there'll be links down in the video
description or you can go onto bonfire
comm and search the word Stoney and
you'll be able to find them so let's go
have some fun all right
[Music]
so first let's give you a little update
on the lights okay so I'll put some
lights here on the house and now I'm in
between my house and my garage and I'll
put these lights they're called litem
lights home brand Li t om they really
worked well I liked them a lot
I put them all the way around the house
there's a couple up there it's really
bright you probably can't see them and I
really liked them a whole lot they
really did a good job and the company
actually saw that I installed those
lights and they said Stoney Ridge farmer
we've got a newer version of that light
we'd like to send it to you and let you
show it on the vlog so here's the newer
version I I've got the box with all the
specs on it but this is the light that
we're gonna put on the gate and we're
gonna put one down here on this sign
that I have posted that says smile your
own camera that way when people pull
down my road that thing lights up and
they're like maybe maybe I shouldn't be
here get all the water's ready they're
ready
somebody nice-looking shirt you got
there thank you self-promotion it's not
nice it's not a nice thing to do on
YouTube everybody hates that Josh so
pretty out right now so beautiful we got
some new rock put down on our road up to
the goats and it looks very nice very
nice
got a baby goat to catch and we get to
watch miss the Stoney Ridge catching
ready ready to catch him better and I
think he's a little calmer poor little
bit don't have any top two goats only
have bottom teeth
the bigger issue we have here guys is we
have too many goats in too small an area
and it's taxing on the goats its taxing
on us and we need to sell some goats so
if any of you guys are local and you're
interested in buying some goats we're
gonna sell off probably four or five six
of them something like that because I
think we're at about 20 goats right now
we just don't need that many goats so
we've got the ladder all loaded up in
the back here we're gonna go down to the
gate and we're gonna install this light
right here so while the gates closed in
here here's the product that I'm
installing it's the light tom 30 LED
motion light this is what it looks like
pretty pretty neat little design there
so I'll post a link down below if you
want to get some for yourself the other
ones work great I haven't used these yet
so I'll be honest with you I don't know
exactly how they're gonna work but I
know they're really bright because we
use them in the living room as motion
lights when we walk through the living
room at night and it worked really good
let's get busy so the challenge here is
to mount this light somewhere on the
back of this wooden sign because I don't
want to screw it into my metal gate this
thing will light up and let us know hey
I hit the button I'm up at the house I
hit the button and the gate started
moving because the light came on and
I'll know trying to figure out the
smartest way to mount this thing so if
you look it's just a little loop a
little hook right there and the screw is
right here and it just hangs OH
that screw pretty simple we'll see
they're not to be perfect just needs to
be perfect
timber dropping screws in the driveway
is not a good thing okay well we got to
turn it on here's how you turn it on
little button right there
find that sweet spot there we go so
since it's on a moving target I want to
make sure it's nice and secure you know
a moving target meaning the gate moves
all the time a mounting system on this
is really really really simple and I
guess if you're mounting it up to the
side of your house it would be just fine
or a tree which is what we're gonna do
next I'll worry about it shaking loose
and getting on my nerves and not being
level and not being pretty right I think
that'll work
so we'll try it out tonight I don't know
if I'll try it out on camera tonight but
we'll let you know in the future vlog
how it's doing I think it'll do just
fine so when you live in a country like
this we don't have a lot of neighbors
and people used to come down here and
park so before all the trees were gone
right here people would come down here
and park and do things that they
shouldn't be doing and you know people
still ride down here from time to time
that aren't welcome so having some
lights it's probably the best security
measure you could ever do around your
house or around your farm or anywhere
having lights when those lights come on
criminals they don't stick around so
right here's my fairly threatening smile
you're on camera sign if you guys didn't
know it Amazon's got a plethora I would
say a plethora of signs like this that
are just threatening to keep people off
your property signs it's a
closed-circuit camera system all sorts
of stuff and we've also got some cameras
up here if you can see them
let's see right there yeah so we've got
some cameras up here we keep track of
everything that goes in the road and out
of the road so if you come down here on
my property and something comes up
missing I got your license plate but
that's it so let's back up to this tree
I'm just gonna back the Gator right up
to it
good thing about John Deere Gator has
this plastic bed which you know plastic
bed wouldn't really sound too appealing
but I can bump into something with it
and not dent it so that's kind of nice
we're gonna bump right into that tree
here we go so for this next light
install we're gonna use a deck screw a
nice heavy-duty deck screw they'll just
hang up there just like that
pretty simple beauty cool just that
simple just that simple to install super
awesome I don't illuminate that sign
right there we got the sign kind of
flopping loose of this tree can grow a
little bit and I also left a little bit
of room for tree growth on that screw I
left it hanging out a little bit further
got my own little department of homeland
security here I think about living out
here in the country like this is when
seconds count the cops get here in
minutes we got to pretty much defend
ourselves and take care of ourselves out
here beautiful beautiful day today guys
the grass that we planted in the fall is
coming up so pretty look at this look at
that what a great stand of grass we did
all the right things the only thing we
could have done differently is the soil
is really acidic here so we probably
could have put a little bit of lime down
but once the soil gets compacted a
little bit we'll be able to bring a big
lime truck in here will spread lime
probably three tons to the acre maybe
even four tons of lime to the acre this
is what you call a lead in a lead into
tomorrow's vlog so I've got two more
loads of gravel coming out I had five
loads brought out and this is the result
of the gravel truck
I'll get the drone out and I'll show you
a little bit of tractor work here on the
driveway
and give you a little bit of driveway
science if you want to know a little bit
about how to maintain and keep a nice
driveway so 32 more tons of rock brought
out tomorrow and I want to expand this a
little bit as you can tell I've got a
lot of vehicles I want to be able to
come through here with a big ol trailer
and turn around and not have any trouble
last hole I'm gonna drill my dogs are
out here eating deer turds like grazing
on deer turds right now I think the
puppy loves to poop on the porch at
night so we keep them up on the porch at
night since my dogs ate my neighbor's
cat we keep them up on the porch at
night and I just totally look forward to
cleaning up doggie diarrhea later on
because they're 20-something deer every
night in this field and they're out
there the dogs are out there grazing on
deer poo
here's your farm reality right there
dogs grazing on here
you know it's not a good job unless
you're bleeding when you get done so
hopefully I have some blood drawn here
in a minute
oh well piece of heaven right there you
got my light these lights are so small I
can put them in our pocket really nice
then a little bit loose tighten it back
up a little bit nice nicely done the
solar panels are right here this is Wes
this is south so I want to get just
enough Sun and then when I walk in here
to access my tractor and everything like
that I'll be able to see so we're gonna
do another one just like this on the
other side
that's it we give you an example of what
it looks like lit so that's the light
that's how much light this thing puts
out I think it's 30 LED lights in there
very nice danger bush hog danger right
there that thing was sticking out of the
ground yeah if you go to clear land this
is the kind of stuff that you're gonna
be finding when you clear your land
people just use any old gully as just a
dumping ground and cinder block pieces
Pepsi is that Pepsi free this is what
you find just garbage so there's a lot
of garbage out of here it's a shame
back in the day people didn't go to the
dump and people didn't have trash
service they had a hole that's what they
did they threw it in there some of you
folks remember grandma's old hole we
used to throw all the trash in post me a
comment down there she's picking up the
heaviest biggest rock she can find tell
her to get the little ones and I'll get
the big ones synlawn listen she's not
listening
stubborn springtime's here we're gonna
start planting soon so look forward to
that getting our garden veggies all
planted up in the house you know getting
them started and then come about April
20th is when we'll put them in the
ground that's probably the last frost
date that we'll have up here and that'll
be cool and we'll get some things going
guys don't forget I've got starting
Ridge Farm shirts they're here for a
limited time only I think they're only
available for 15 more days or maybe 12
more days jump on it get your shirt if
you want one if you don't want one don't
worry about it alright thanks a lot guys
come on back and see us here on the farm
sure enjoyed having you we'll see you
next time all right
bring-bring
[Music]
here at sweet add some way supposed to
be snow Tyrion
[Music]
thanks a lot for watching this today
guys we'll see you next time I'm a
Stoney Ridge Farm appreciate it got to
the channel if you're not already
subscribed you can watch the farm grow
with us
take care