Hello everyone,
My name is Youngsang Cho the founder of JADAM.
In this episode, I'm going to talk about how
to assemble an irrigation system.
There are overall 2 parts one for the external
hardware assembly
And the other one is about the electrical
system.
To begin the assembly, as a major piece of
equipment first you will need 3 pallets to
flatten the land surface where you are going
to locate the tanks.
then one big water tank and 2 medium size
tanks and lastly the 2 motors one for the
water tank and the other one is for smaller
tanks.
and lastly, the water softener.
For this video, I have purchased 2 tons size
big tanks and 2 600liter size tanks.
The first 600 liters
tank will be used as a microbes incubator
and liquid fertilizer.
And the nest one will be used as a pest solution.
There was a lot of controversy on environmental
hormones from the plastic tank,
It was partially true but now all most all
water tank products are eligible to use for
drinking water as well.
Let's first start with assembling the motors.
The first motor is from the company called
Hanil which they are broadly known brand in
south korea.
The first electric water pump's electric power
consumption is 1,500 watts The pressure height
is 15.5 meters.
I'm not an expert on electrical water pumps
so you can always get advice from your nearest
hardware store for more information.
The size of the pump can vary depending on
your land size.
And the second pump's power consumption is
580 watts
Which is better with smaller tanks.
This pump is made for houses, it will automatically
turn off when is not in use.
And this is the water filter called the disk
filter.
when you start using it, expect to clean it
quite a bit
often cause it will get dirtier the more you
use it.
First, let's attach this filter to the main
pump.
And of course, we will use Teflon tape to
prevent leakage.
After this one, let now assemble other pipelines
that will be connected to the other pipes
and water tanks.
If you open the PVC valve,
you will be able to see 3 different parts.
When it comes to Teflon we also don't know
how much the accurate time to wrap the thread
with Teflon,
but with my years of experience, wrap about
20 times on plastic parts and 7-15 times for
steel-made parts depending on the size.
Do wrap the Teflon properly because you don't
want to find a leakage after completing the
assembly.
Then next, I will install this part, for this
one,
You will be needing a 50A 40A connecting nipple,
Because the plastic valve comes in the size
of 40A but the filter's size is much bigger.
And I will repeat the same thing on the other
side.
Then when we come below to filter, there is
another 50A size thread for the pump.
I going to attach a steel connecting nipple.
When it comes to PVC pipe,
there is a specific tool rather than just
a normal wrench.
This is much more convenient for you and you
can get it from the.
Hardware store as well.
Next, I'm going to make a hole to install
the valve.
Before drilling, make sure to drill a little
bit higher so that the valve itself has some
space to rotate freely
or you can put extra pallets to install it
a little more below.
The tool that you need is the hole cutter.
The hole cutter should be a little bit bigger
than the steel fitting so that it will be
firmly installed.
Continue drilling slowly, then when the cutter
reach to tank, give a little more force to
drill further.
Once you complete making holes, there is one
problem.
The fitting that I'm holding should be installed
from the inside.
going into the tank to install that would
be a time-consuming and not smart way to do
it.
And this is where the trick comes in.
Let me show you how.
First, take some thin pipes,
Then insert it into the tank and through the
hole below.
Lastly, just drop the other part of the fitting.
Then hold it until it is tightened,
Keep on installing it until you feel enough.
If the part inside of the tank is rotating
along with the bolt,
Then hold that part and continue until it's
done.
And don't forget to wrap up Teflon on every
single thread.
Then next I will make another hole for the
incubator tank.
Once I'm done, I will repeat the same thing
for installing the fitting.
Then I will be using a 20A size valve in order
to fit the PB pipe.
The most general pipe that we know is the
white clear pipe.
But these are weak in heat during summer,
So I would recommend using the PB pipe which
is much more durable.
You have probably noticed the difference between
the previous black PVC valve and the
current one.
Let me show the difference.
The structure is based on 3 components,
Once you open the bolt,
You will see 3 different rings.
The first one is the rubber fitting,
second is plastic fitting,
then the third one is steel teeth for securing
the pipe.
before pushing in the pipe make sure to put
the steel part inside of the pipe.
Then when I push the PVC pipe in,
there will be a first smooth click.
Then another hard click.
That means it is all fixed in place.
From now on I will connect the pipeline from
the bottom to the top.
When you purchase large quantities it comes
in a roll.
So make sure to stretch it straight before
installing it.
There is a specific cutter for the PVC pipe.
Purchase one of those and slightly force the
lever then cut it through.
Once you are done with cutting,
It is now time to fit right in.
But before that, there is a 3 different parts
after when you open the bolt.
Rubber fitting and 2 diffenrent PVC fittings.
The mechanism of assembling together is pretty
similar to the thin PVC pipe.
It is just little bit bigger.
fit in the PVC parts first, then fit the rubber
fitting to plug it right into the connecting
point.
Once I'm done, let me install the elbow.
After that same procedure is continued.
Next, I will connect the smaller pump from
the tank.
Then from here, I will connect the separator
before installing it all in place.
The single side is for the water goes into
the water softener,
And the other sides are for the future, just
in case you are going to connect some other
tank.
For this one, I will use the 20 A size connecting
nipple, and for the other side I will use
the size converter for 15 A-size components.
Then I'm going to cut the PVC pipe into 49cm
to connect the pipe on the side.
Now let's come to the smaller tanks.
One is for the pest solution and the other
one is for the microbes incubator or the liquid
fertilizer.
The fitting installed on the top is 20 A size
and the bottom is 25 A size in order to drain
the water quick.
I'm going to install the bottom fitting first,
Make sure to calculate the working angle of
the component so that you won't have to release
again and again to fit the angle.
And I will use the same trick to insert the
part.
You might need these small tools depending
on the product.
Now it's time to install the valves.
Then next let me connect the all pipes first
with T joint
Once it is all connected I will make a turn
from here,
If your sink for the water is on this side,
turn the pipe where the sink is located.
The other pipe parts which are already assembled
are for the water softener exit.
The lower pipe you can use with just ordinary
water, and the upper part is for pest solution.
And let's continue with the bottom part assembly.
It is quite simple most of the procedures
are similar.
The bottom pipeline gets a direct connection
from the main tank, and I will install the
filter in order to avoid blockage from any
unknown material.
Then next I'm going to drill a hole in the
existing pipe.
This particular component is called a plumbing
saddle clamp.
It enables me to drill a hole in the pipe
and make a different connecting point for
other components.
There is a rubber packing in the middle, make
sure it is aligned with the point where you
wanna drill a hole.
Then use the screws to hold it together so
that it won't wobble when you are drilling.
For this, I will use a 16mm hole cutter.
Once it is completed, I will move on to the
next step.
Which is connecting the tank with the water
softener.
I will convert the ordinary socket with the
one-touch fitting.
The the same thing with other parts on the
top.
Next is, we need to install other thin pipes
to be connected to the water softener.
For that, I will need 2 PVC elbow because
we are gonna turn twice.
After that let me connect the other PVC pipe
to connect the water softener.
Now, we are almost completed installing all
the parts.
And I will connect the other parts to the
disk filter.
I will install the parts on both sides and
please measure the length before cutting the
pipe.
Then measure the other side as well.
Once it is done, bring the pipeline to be
back of the disk filter.
Then decide which side you will be going to
make a turn.
It really depends on your farmland's design.
Next, I will add another 25mm hose line to
ease the pressure of water for the pump.
To do that I will make 4 different holes.
Let me tell you why we need to install these
pipes.
When you are turning on the irrigation system,
the pressure of each pipe will increase.
And If you release the lever, the irrigation
pipe on the field cannot be sustained due
to its high pressure.
And to secure the pipelines, we need a sub
hose which will reflux the water back into
the pump.
Meaning, the water pressure will be normalized
and prevent any leakage happens.
As you can see there is a main pipeline coming
out from the container, and there is one lever
to control water level.
But also it is connected with the thin pipe
which is connected to the other water tank
for liquid fertilizer.
If you release the big lever all at once,
of course, it will just flow into the ground.
But If you release a little bit, the pressure
will absorb the water from the fertilizer
tank.
So it is capable of irrigating water and fertilizer
at the same time.
And this specific part is not very necessary.
But if you have it, then it would be great
to connect water pipes and water tank along
with it.
This small water pump is automatic and whenever
there is a tank with the lever opened,
it will water it until it's full.
But it will be closed if the tank is already
full or the lever is closed.
As you can see the inside of the water tank
is not visible.
And it's because of moss if the tank gets
direct contact with sunlight.
But with this blue tank, we don't know exactly
how much water is inside right?
So I'm going to install some parts which will
enable us to see the water level.
Once you are done, right down the indication
of the amount so that you won't have to look
into
side to check every time.
And here install one of the short pipes inside
the tank.
Bent down the hose with fire then install
it.
Then you will able to see all.
The water gets drained out of the tank.
Use the marker to indicate which hose is coming
from which pump and water softener.
You can use these two tanks for both pesticides,
microbial solution, and liquid fertilizer.
When you would want to use the both the tank,
release all the levers down below which are
connected with the main water pump.
And let's talk about the floating valve.
The big tank needs a big floating valve because
of its size.
And of course small valve for the small size.
There are a lot of products for stopping the
water such as the electric floating vale but
this one is so far cheapest and most reasonable.
As you can see our setup includes three major
pieces of electric equipment.
The main pump, small sub pump, and electric
heater for microbial incubation.
But you can also add some more such as electrically
powered spray.
And to run all of that of course we will be
needing some electric distribution board to
cover the circuit from the rain.
For that, I will make another video on how
to make one.
Speaking of the electric heater.
You can get these from amazon or aliexpress.
This is needed when the temperature drops
below 18 C . because of active microbes.
Chose the one which fits the tank perfectly.
Don't choose something long or very short.
Using microbial solution is the key factor
to maintain healthy soil conditions.
So make sure to irrigate often as possible.
There is no right temperature indication with
this piece of machine.
If it gets too cold,
you have to increase the temperature even
higher.
So please keep that in mind.
And lastly, when you are using this tank for
the first time, make sure to pour the water
in.
and
during winter, please release all the water
out to prevent freezing.
There is going to be some problem with the
automatic pump when you use it for a longer
period
of time.
If that happens, check the part behind the
motor to fix it.
Thank you for watching and I will see you
guys in the next videos.