everyone welcome to the afternoon
sessions The forers
Forum my name is David trinkin I'm on
the faculty of the pl Sciences unit
University of
Missouri it's my pleasure to moderate
the first uh three hours worth of
sessions to begin with I would like to
introduce my colleague Dr San Jen goo
who is state vegetable extension
specialist as well as a faculty member
at Lincoln University in Jefferson
City before Dr Goo arrived in Missouri I
don't think many missourians at least
heard of the concept of vegetable
grafting much less tomato
grafting since his Ral it's been kind of
a standard best management practice and
today he's going to give us an update on
some of the research he's been carried
out in in grafting Dr
Goo thank you
div I give one presentation before I
mean this morning for the seminar and uh
let me let me get this started uh this
morning I talked about uh uh hold on let
me let me move to the other
one you can see the outline over there
just for today whole day so this morning
I talk about uh the introduction part
and what why and then we talk about how
and this afternoon I'm going to talk
about
uh my research at the linol University
um before you before we start
um for those who were not able to make
to my presentation I do have a handouts
which is actually our newsletter
articles and my two assistants Sean and
C going to uh distribute them to you
there to be two and there should be
three articles but I'm still working on
the third one so the first one is
introduction about vegetable grafting uh
the second one is about tomato
grafting uh this morning I discussed in
detail about how to do grafting in
general not only for tomatoes but also
for pepper for for eggplants for
watermelon cucumber and curbage stuff so
if you are interested in my presentation
uh send me email so I can send you a pdf
version um so um just give you a
pre-warning this afternoon's talk will
be my research update and it will be
really dry so you'll see a lot of
figures in the graphics stuff so it's
not going to be so colorful with
pictures like this
morning and also um I wasn't able to get
all the data analyzed for this year um
we made some mistake there and by not
including the
controls so so the result will be
primarily from last year
but um uh you you find what we did last
year so how many of you have uh attended
my seminar this
morning okay um so how many of you think
you are very confident with the grafting
part
already one hand two hands three hands
pretty good so like I said today and
this afternoon will be research update I
will not give you a lot of information
about the general General uh grafting
technology
stuff uh it will be just some
research
okay again my name is sanin and sanin
with linkoln University extension uh I
have been with I've been in Missouri
for almost five five years now time F
time just passes fast okay um what we
did last year we did two research at
least to research projects number one is
the grafting compatibility study with
heirloom tomatoes because we I
introduced the idea to our Farmers about
uh tomato grafting they always ask me
questions whether you know if I have a
heirloom can I just go try them you know
do you have any research data to see
where they're going to take because you
put two things together there is a good
chance they will not attack so that's
the reason behind this research of
course people are interested in U in in
uh High tunnel uh or field airom tomato
production especially for organic or for
or for farmers markets um so that's why
I did this research and uh um for those
who those of you who don't really know
about grafting yet um I can tell you
some Advantage number one it'll have a
uh disease especially Sor born disease
resistance because of the root stock and
number two if you choose a good roof
stock you usually have a enhanced Vigor
and your yield usually be enhanced to be
increased uh and also uh High tunnel has
been getting popular and we use high
tunnel for season extension especially
in win uh in early fall or uh early
spring or later spring so we want to
catch maybe two more months time to
produce more warm seeding vegetables as
well as some of the cold seeding
vegetables so grafting uh with correct
roof stock you do enhance your s on um
code hardness so just some background
information for you okay um for this
research what we did uh this is just
introduction part we don't have to go
through this again um what we did last
year we choose about
21 uh heirloom
tomatoes and we grafted them on two root
stocks uh bufort and a maxi for so we
use the tubing grafting method we tried
all those um aom Tomatoes you can see
some of
them like a Kentucky beef steak Branny
wine uh pink heart I like this one
actually so what we did briefly we used
the tubing Masters this shows you how
you do it and for those of you who went
to my talk this morning is should look
familiar uh this picture was from uh
those pictures were from Dr uh revert
from uh can Kansas State University and
basically what you do you grw your your
roof stock and your s on the similar
size you cut your roof stock and either
before about or up below or uh over the
cuton Lance I prefer this one because
later you don't have to remove suckers
and put a tube on it this is called a
tube graphing method because the tubes
were designed specifically for this
method and you slide this tube in and
then you cut your cion different angle
45° and you slide this in make sure the
two surfaces contact each other and
that'll be it of course later you have
to move into a growth chamber to to heal
them um so basically for this uh in
clamation process for day one to three
you keep to close to 100% darkness and
close to 100% humidity and after 3 days
you slowly reduce darkness and keep
relatively high humidity and then after
7 to 10 days they are as normal if they
take uh one lesson I learned from this
year was uh the temperature even though
it's not listed here the temperature
plays very important role in the
survival I guess um you don't want to
keep your temperature before 80°
Fahrenheit and the uh room temperature
will be actually very nice uh the story
was for for my my observation was before
a meeting um I grafted something for
some kids and uh I just dropped them in
my office and then they came back 7 days
later they all survived without any
cover so that gave me the hand that the
temperature is very very critical uh my
office temperature in summer time is
about 70° or lower so the this survived
really well and humidity maybe just less
than 50 so keep that in mind okay um we
did the greenhouse research this is my
growth chamber we did just build some
frame and cover with some plastic that's
it I do have a a household humidity fire
inside uh this is just show you the
picture of the
grafted uh transplant and those are
survived transplants so those Greenhouse
study and I graph them and to see uh the
survival whether they are successful or
not so here's the result like I said
it's all graphic stuff and this is my
heirloom variety and this is my survival
rate rate with one is 100% so this is on
Buford the roock bford you can see the
lowest one is The Branding one red is
actually not too bad 80% by the way I
gravitated all this by
myself it took me a lot of time so most
of them close to 100% take so it was
really really good and for Maxi for
however I did this some difference and
uh you can see this mortgage lifter and
the um I don't I don't even know how to
read it the h55 they were particularly
low I tried to find out why it was this
low I guess I probably was just too
tired I don't know so uh however if you
see the
statistics you see even those 90 80% on
bord survival and the 72% on Maxi for
by uh the uh statistic analysis they are
not significantly difference so even
though there are some exceptions there
uh we will see in general uh there's not
there was not at least in the greenhouse
uh setting incompatibility issue so
which means you can grab them they can
take really well and they can grow and
then whether they going to be okay in
the field or not we don't know because
earlier just like a just like the uh uh
the grips you grab them they look really
well you plant them some of them you
know they they will die or slowly reduce
the Vigor after 10 15 years so we did
the greenhouse study just to see whether
crafting is successful or not and then
we plant them in the field to test them
in the real um environment especially in
the open field and last year was a good
year to test because it was hot and dry
uh so we we planed those successfully um
survived uh graphity transplants in the
field this is how we did it in OB field
it was really dry and we we measured the
grow and yield and yield dat is not
available yet I believe because last
year we just didn't have a Tomatoes
until later in the growing season and
when the weather was cold and we
harvested a lot Green Tomatoes not not
red ones so we we measured the uh stem
diameter and then we measured the stem
diameter above and below the graph Union
trying to find index to see uh to
measure the uh compatibility so so
here's one picture showing this any wi
pink graphy Buford you can see the roads
and here is graft Union here is graph
Union here's graph Union and some of the
plants we actually planted a little bit
too too deep uh however you don't see a
lot of roots growing out above the graph
Union you know which was okay we don't
want any rules come out from from the S
part okay um I split this this graph
Union and uh you see the picture here uh
you do see a kind of a diagonal line
here showing the graph Union but even
those here so in this so this one is non
grafted you see visually you don't see a
lot of
difference so which means they they do
really well if you see the the
connection here this is a scon this is
your root stock there's no obvious stop
stop there even though you can see
something there so I draw a line there
just to show the graphity unit over
there and for stem diameter we always
tell people that if by choosing the good
roof stock uh your growth the your s
growth rigor can be enhanced so we
measure the stem diameter you can see on
bu for or Maxi for all those stems were
bigger than the non-gravity control so
with does show the difference on the on
your on the thickness of your your your
stamp that's one way to say you have a
enhanced Vigor uh then for the diameter
ratio above and below of course non-ra
will be zero I mean it will be one and
for bord and maxfor the graph Union
actually did something to the plant see
above the graph unit is a little bit
thicker than the lower one even though
visually by your bare eyes you don't see
the difference if you measure with
measure them with the caliber you
actually see the difference so we do see
some difference over
there and the conclusion here is um um
well here is
uh well this is about the the greenhouse
trial uh we had a better luck with
maxford than
Buford and then we know I just said that
we had a bigger or thicker uh stems for
the graphic
ones so the most important conclusion
for this part is a grafting
compatibility seem not to be an issue so
at least in the tested 21 varieties so
if you have a heirloom tomato I'm I'm
thinking I'm about maybe 90% sure you
will not have
incompatibility if you for for for uh
Tomatoes you know the reing
incompatibility is so important
uh just
because uh if you think about it you do
grab you you grab the watermelon or
cucumber or Melon you know if you add
some bitterness to your watermelon I
don't think people like it but for
tomatoes I don't think it's a big
challenge so um then again that last
year we we did some uh um uh airom trial
with graft with grafting in the high
tunnels and uh we I have two High tels
one is double layer poly uh the other
one is single layer poly so we did some
research on
that and uh the with some uh what we
want to do to find out uh if grafting
will enhance the heirloom tomato
production in high tunnels and number
two to find out whether single layer
versus double probably will do some diff
do something to the earum tomatoes
especially graphite ones in the High
Time
and uh I I placed one sentence here
tomato gravity and the high tunnel could
be a perfect
combination uh the reason behind that
you know people started to do uh High
tunnels uh well largely because the NCS
got involved they get they get they got
involved with the the cost share program
so we have seen a lot High tunnels
everywhere almost in the middle west so
when people try to use new high tunnels
they don't have a at least they don't
maybe just beginners like I don't know
but their soil is kind of new they don't
have a lot of soil born disease problems
but in the future since high tunnel is a
little bit cost costly to build to
maintain and it give you more money so
you tend to produce more of your cash
crop like tomatoes and the rotation is
limited in the high tunnel and you want
plan you want to apply more manures or
compost so sooner or later your soil
disease will build up your soil salinity
May Will May uh May build up if you're
not careful enough so by doing that you
cause a lot of trouble for your
production and then and you cannot use
mes bomide anymore because it's banned
for it environment to damage so you
cannot use f Fant to do that the new one
not be uh as well as the one we used
before like M bomide or they may have
some environmental issue as well or
simply because you are organic or all
natural farmer you don't want to do
anything with that so but doing hype
doing but but adapting the grafting
technology you can avoid those uh
fumigation
part so that we we did we use two s
variety we have an ananas in the German
pain two big fruit uh type variety um
pretty good quality and uh we graft them
into bufort emperador and Maxi for this
year I wasn't able to find this variety
and for some reason seed companies don't
carry over uh seeds over years anymore I
don't know why so I couldn't find this
one uh for roof stock I have
a bu for and this and for the
combinations for German pink I do have a
self-grafted German Pink as control I
have a non-grafted
grafted on itself as control but for ANS
I didn't have enough seeds so that's the
uh uh combination of grafting grafted
tomatoes and um I can tell you I didn't
take this picture I didn't really um
it's a little fuzzy but this is German
pink and this this is anus Nora it's
very tasty
variety and same thing we do the tubing
graphing method we graphing the
greenhouse last year we were late so we
planted them in May usually we be in
this area we will plant them in the high
tunnel late week of March or early April
but we were late uh we were not getting
the seeds in time for some reason the
seed company agreed to send me the seeds
they forgot to do it
so anyhow and then the first batch of
the the grafting graphed stuff uh it
were killed with one weekend uh my I
guess my technician was not on campus
and the student worker didn't do a good
job they just they just cooked in when
they were in the chamber so in the green
house with sunny light with black stuff
on it they were killed so um people ask
me did you fire fire your uh student
worker as no I didn't give give him
another
chance uh another story so this is my
highight tonal 30 by 96 uh with Rich
vent and uh this is single layer this is
double layer it's uh it's a li men's
brand yeah remember we're in zone 5B and
uh like I said we plan them late and
then we ran right into this heat uh uh
weather so for quite a few while we
didn't have a uh we didn't have a
harvest because it was too hot but
however we kept them there or kept them
going until later fall so um we do have
some data for last year and this is how
my plans look like I do have automatic
system to to drop the curtain down and
up and also a controller to control the
r event so I had a pretty good system um
to automatically manipulate my
temperature just because I cannot be
there every day neither did my
technician so you know this is a When I
Was preparing this talk yesterday um I
used one previous presentation I have a
the extreme hot and dry summer in 2011
but it wasn't true anymore this year was
even bad so I removed that word but
still tells you you know in late June to
to almost the early part of August we
have a really really to this part as
well really bad uh weather and know we
know that I think I have another line
here you know pretty much here
75 uh you see the plant growth for
tomatoes get influenced about 97 I think
pollination will will stop and if about
1202 degree the whole plant may just may
just not grow so this is especially true
for for heirloom tomatoes which
primarily is just in
indeterminate so you can see I do have
some heat tolerant varieties there
unfortunately this is my variety trial
part that's not the the grafted part but
other just like this for a long time no
fruit because pollination was was
impossible so we do see some temperature
difference between the two high tunnels
the single layer versus double layer
basically in the early in the early in
the morning well in in the morning the
the the single ler has higher
temperature and then the night at night
you you double at a higher temperature
this is
May uh and then the pr is the
photosynthetic activity radiation you
see the difference between the two uh
ler system you know in the high tunnels
so if you um if you think about um
maintaining the Heat in a high tunnel
you may think about using double layer
but in the in zone 6 b or above I don't
think it's necessary just give you some
um environmental factors there to help
explain the uh explain the result so for
the yield this is single layer you have
a we have a green uh German pink German
pink on German pink and then on three
roof stocks you see pretty much similar
from U August here the basically you
don't have I didn't have any Harvest and
then we I do have a some Harvest
starting in the late uh where early part
of October until uh the frost came well
not a frost the freeze temperature came
in um I was actually in Pennsylvania for
a meeting where my technician students
are Harvest those tomatoes so you see
really you don't see a lot of big
difference for double year you do you do
see some difference here for this one
the green line is the German pink on
bufor and we always see the the Maxi
Fort will uh transfer the most Vigor to
your s but u under that condition you
know it is so hot bu for is less
vigorous variet roock variety actually
didn't did better than others and uh for
this one you can see the non- graphit
one overall perform the worst so we
still see some difference in double year
poly for for for the ananas you see the
the similar chain but you don't see a
lot of big difference here so for the
double year uh this ones on this EMP
paror roof stock did a little bit better
than others similar to this one so if
put this in together
for for the an German pink we see very
difference uh between uh the root stock
treatment you know different root root
stock and S of combinations for example
this one the double layer seem to be
better for this one as well but others
may
not so so it varies depends on the
variety but
for ananas the other variety you see the
double or did better so we do see the
difference between the two type of high
tunnel
when you graft those
Tomatoes uh so this is result know
generally speaking I don't see a lot of
difference between the grafted ones and
non-grafted ones even though for for uh
I think for for NS nor uh one Ro stock
vary performed better and we see the
difference you know the the non-grafted
tend to be lower yield but because the
heat last year it didn't show the
potential difference so I cannot see the
significant different
um and but in the field in in the in the
greenhouse I did see that the graphed
ones were more
vigorous here is the arrow so
temperature was different between the
single double e or high tunnels so
basically the tick home message for you
is uh grafting can enhance Vigor number
one number two uh the Double year will
be better and the weather you know the
three for whether the the grafting had a
benefit or advantage on this trial uh
you I cannot tell you but this year we
may have a better result however well
this year we tried the same variety on S
on different root stock 1 2 3 4 five
however we when I was trying to analyze
data found out the control uh were not
included there I mean we were data was
there but were for the arrange data were
not there so wasn't able to do the stats
analysis statistic analysis so I'll
present the data probably at the great
PLS conference in January and also going
to post the result on our website so you
get this sooner or
later okay um this is a just quick
update and again this is just a result
research results I think I have a couple
minutes for
questions
first
yes I saw where you're doing melons and
cucumbers has anybody done this or is it
does cantaloupe fall in the same
category as
watermelons
uhal yeah his question is um um whether
people have been doing research or or or
demonstration with uh curbage stuff like
watermelons cucumbers and I haven't done
this yet I have collected uh uh three
cucumber uh roock varieties which can
also be used for watermelon and the
melon
so I'm going to do some research with
cucumber the English cucumber type this
year uh Dr hin Jaw from un University of
Florida she's been doing uh melon
cantaloup grafting study and there's
another USD guy doing watermelon so
there's big uh special crop research
initiative Grant um it is looking at
different aspect of grafting so uh that
Grant started last year I'm I'm assuming
results will start to come out next
year but in China they grabbed all
watermelons and cucumbers and melons in
the uh uh in the greenhouse and high
tunnel
settings they are doing great yeah simar
cucum it's a similar process as melons
and cucumbers yes yes for for all cubits
the graphing message will be similar and
uh the result may vary because if you're
talking about watermelon and melon
you're talking about the sugar content
so the sometimes if you're not careful
and choose the wrong variety variety the
the the quality may be may be reduced
however the research done by USD people
with watermelon they found out know if
you grafted them it enhance the shelf
life other questions
question um what about as far as like
other online Resources with little you
know uh you know the indepth specifics
of grafting and planting schedules and
that kind of
thing is there like any more like online
resources or books that you might
suggest for vegetable grafting in
general um there are quite a few
Publications for Farmers is extension
Publications um there are some research
projects as well uh I know in in in
heart science in heart technology there
are some Publications on grafted
tomatoes
and there is a review in heart science
on grafted watermelons and Artic cbits
so uh our I don't know how good you are
with uh scientific journal but at least
you can try if you want to you want to
do the uh uh scholar.google.com
uh you can get a lot scientific
information there