a significant Milestone is being marked
this week with the official commencement
of infrastructural works for the
national agriculture Innovation and
Technology Center this state-of-the-art
facilties is poised to revolutionize
local agricultural practices by
integrating cuton Edge technology and
sustainable farming methods through
Hydroponics a five member technical team
from Guyana is currently on island to
spare head the installation of a highly
Advanced agronic system an initiative
that symbolizes the beginning of a
transformative collaboration between St
Lucia and Guyana for agricultural
technology adoption and Innovation what
we are seeing here today is the
beginning or the foundation of the
Agricultural Innovation and Technology
initiative that our ministry is hoping
to stretch out to youth or to expose
more young people as it relates to new
in new production methods or
techniques and this has all been made
possible
and we are so grateful to the guyes
mission for coming in and starting us
off so when more more of these new
technologies come in we are able to take
it on on our own and show our young
people from start to finish what they
could accomplish and how far agriculture
could take them on this lot we hope to
establish I believe one to Hydroponics
green houses the Hydroponics Center is
also expected to serve as a model for
local Farmers demonstrating modern
techniques that maximize crop yield
while minimizing environmental impact
officials from both countries emphasize
that knowledge sharing and capacity
building will be key outcomes of this
initiative fostering a stronger original
partnership in Agricultural Development
so five of us came to assist you guys um
St lucians uh to set up two Shar houses
um there will be tunnel houses and uh
we're we're uh going on well uh we're
almost finishing one of them today um we
want to start the other one tomorrow so
hopefully by Saturday so we can be
putting on the Plastics on these these
houses the national agriculture
Innovation and Technology Center is
expected to set the foundation for
future advancements in smart farming
data- driven agricultural Solutions and
climate adaptive practices with
construction now underway stakeholders
remain optimistic about the center's
impact on food production
and economic growth from the Ministry of
Agriculture this is Amanda Clark
reporting