boredom folks this Josh Stoney Ridge
farmer son is up and it's peeking
through the trees beautiful spring
weathers here
trees are starting to blossom and we're
getting some leaves on them and we've
got day number nine here on the land
clearing projects and I'm going to take
you over here I'm gonna update you what
they're doing today is they're hauling
off some big brush piles in the dump
truck moving them to the other side of
the farm
and we're going to go over here and
basically direct traffic not direct
traffic out in the road but actually
direct them to what we want them to do
with these huge rocks out on the pond
and I'll show you we're gonna go over
here we're gonna put huge rocks out on
the pond so we'll have a place to like
hop rock to rock to go fishing you want
to finish the project off nicely we want
to have beautiful landscape and part of
finishing this land clearing project
behind me here is landscaping so we put
some big stones up here and we'll just
take you around and show you and we'll
place these rocks I'm along today and
we'll show you the progress and we'll
show you the project alright let's have
some fun
[Music]
alright guys we're gonna follow the
excavator
over here actually we're gonna beat the
excavator over
so he's coming down the hill here with
the excavator and all this may seem kind
of silly to you but it's what I want and
I want to be able to hop rock to rock
out here and fish in my fish pond so
that's what I want so let's watch him do
it I'm gonna direct rock traffic should
be fun can't have fun what good's life
send him right there take that one and
set it out as the next step and then
we'll take bigger and bigger out to the
next steps leave about that much space
in between them if you can this guy's
looking at me like I'm an idiot paying
200 bucks an hour here and I want to
have some fun with it folks don't forget
click that like button down there just
pound it pound that like button right
now boom hit it okay it helps the
channel a whole lot help support the
channel and helps get these videos out
there so other youtubers can see them
alright
[Music]
the pond is swallowing them up more than
I thought it would if the danger here is
that the excavator could actually tip
over into the pond but we got bulldozers
we can get it out
these boulders are thousands of pounds
biscuit biscuit
[Music]
this is the most dangerous rock it's the
biggest one it runs a risk of tipping
I don't know if you saw that or not he
told me if it starts the tip I'm
dropping it
I told them to just start piling rocks
just start making a big pile out in the
water back here and hopefully by the end
of the pile you'll finish off with some
nice big smooth rocks it's gonna be
really cool I might even mount like a
fighting chair out there where you can
just sit down and rotate fish catch a
big bass be awesome
I think a little more thought needs to
go into this
they just keep sinking up or falling
over in the water I think probably the
best thing to do would have been to put
the really rough rocks on the bottom and
make a pile and then put the pretty rock
on the top while we're working here guys
I'll tell you what's going on today
today most of the burn piles on this
side of the farm have gone out and
what's happening is these picking up
these burn piles and he's taking them
over across on the other side of the
farm with the dump truck and what we're
doing there is eventually once they get
cold once they're not burning anymore we
have a big gully and we're gonna fill in
that gully now we're not gonna make
pasture out of that gully we're just
gonna fill in that gully with the old
stumps and stuff like that just makes
sense so that's why you'll see in the
drone footage I'll walk you through and
talk you through what's going on there
[Music]
one of the cool things about doing this
right here is that it's gonna make good
fish habitat and it's also going to make
a place for the turtles to crawl up on
so what a beautiful farm beautiful place
and good habitat for wildlife
so we're about to wrap it up right here
we got one more rock we're gonna put on
here it's a big old flat rock that's
about it so we'll take you over with the
drone walk you through what's going on
the process that's going on the thought
process and see you next time hopefully
we'll be digging with a disc harrow to
try to loosen up the land and then we'll
run over it with the seed drill a
no-till seed drill would be real fun so
come on back and see me all right so you
stand on the Stoney Ridge guys all right
so we've got a view of the farm right
here and this is just an overview across
from our house if you look up right in
the center of your screen that's the
next area that we're gonna be clearing
off for field for pasture and you see a
couple hay bales in the middle of the
field this spot we're traveling over
right now was a spot that was gully
washed and we had him fixed that we're
gonna drill seed down in that and we'll
pop over the dump truck here and watch
the caterpillar 963 B go at it here it's
a cab model six-cylinder caterpillar
basically he's scooping up remnants of
where we had a fire and pretty much
he'll just go along all the way through
the farm anywhere they're remnants of
where we had a fire he's scooping it up
putting it in the dump truck and taking
it over to a gully on the back side of
the farm and dumping them out and then
pushing them over into the gully to fill
that in just a spot on the farm where we
needed a hole filled in and it's better
than leaving them out there in the
middle of the field for another two
years like the previous piles they all
just kind of set out there so pretty
good shot of the caterpillar at work
right here and that's it just want to
let you guys know what's going on here
stay tuned for the next vlog or so and
you'll see the progress as things have
gone on they'll clean this up and we'll
take a huge disc harrow and drag over
the fields and loosen the dirt and then
we'll go through and seed it so the next
vlog should be cleaning up the fields
[Music]