foreign
[Music]
Jane I'm the head of content here at
Food unfolded economic instability is
one of the greatest struggles farmers
face it is also one of the greatest
barriers to more sustainable food
protection if farmers are to meet
legislative and consumer demand for
producing more with minimal impact or
even positive impact on the environment
we need to First address the realities
and challenges related to the costs of
farming
of running a farm varies depending on
the size and product of the farm you can
probably guess certain expenses like
fertilizers pesticides hired labor
tractors and Machinery feed if it's a
livestock farm and so on but what about
land use fees like rent or mortgage fuel
crop insurance loans on new Investments
repairs and maintenance veterinarian
costs software and other monitoring
tools depreciation certification and
compliance costs and soap these expenses
are all necessary to keep a farm up and
running and ultimately affect the
remaining income and profitability of a
farm
so how much do you think a farm makes on
average in 2018 the average net income
in the EU was 22 500 euros this amount
includes subsidies production and labor
costs and depreciation but excludes
income tax the most significant income
differences are Regional and product
specific the Netherlands Denmark and
Luxembourg had the highest income on
average while Hungary Poland and
Slovenia were lowest when it comes to
products the ranking of income highest
to lowest was Farms specializing in
granivores pigs and poultry wine
Horticulture Dairy while permanent crop
farms like almonds and pistachios
grazing livestock farms and mixed Farms
were below the 2018 average another fact
to consider is that many farms
traditionally rely on unpaid labor in
the form of family labor and in the EU
unpaid family labor accounts for 7 24
percent of total Farm labor hours to
help support farm income many
governments issue subsidies while there
are issues related to subsidy
distribution see our previous video on
how subsidies and policies impact food
production these payments are intended
to cushion the impact of fluctuating
market prices and provide some stability
for Farmers but it's still often not
enough with Farmers juggling thin profit
margins growing expenses loans and
increased interest rates many of them
have chosen to close down and sell their
Farms between 2005 and 2020 the EU lost
around 5.3 million Farms 87 percent of
these were small farms under five
hectares and today all farmers are
facing another challenge of inflation
with climbing Fuel and fertilizer prices
many farmers struggle with financial
forecasting can they invest in new
technologies new infrastructure or can
they even afford to change their
practices to be more sustainable which
often requires an initial investment of
time and money Farmers from lower income
regions will struggle with additional
social impacts as increased expenses
means less money available to higher
labor and less money to improve housing
education or Health Care some of these
farmers will turn to other activities
like cutting down forest trees and
commercializing wood
to create alternative sources of income
some Farmers have turned to carbon
farming in which they receive subsidies
or payment schemes for sequestering
carbon dioxide from the atmosphere via
planting specific crops or trees in
Europe farmers are also hosting
educational events creating campsites on
their land or even producing artisanal
food on site like cheese or oil Farmers
might also switch to organic production
or other sustainable production
practices as such products generate
higher prices and more financial support
from subsidy programs like the eu's new
common agricultural policy which rewards
Greener practices and despite lower
yields compared to Conventional
production Organic Farms have saved 75
to 100 on pesticide costs per hectare
and 45 to 90 percent of fertilizer costs
per hectare when including the price of
their products and subsidy support EU
organic farmers saw a higher or similar
income can consumers like you and me can
also support Farmers by directly buying
their products either at markets or
through subscription services this cuts
out the intermediaries and allows
Farmers to keep a greater percentage of
their profit if you're interested in
learning more about the origins and
sustainability of our food subscribe to
food unfolded on YouTube Instagram and
visit our website at
www.foodinfolded.com