it's fine
[Music]
so this place as you can see is a pretty
big castle but we're only a small part
of it so we're just starting our
permaculture project here at discussion
of Fuji let that permaculture is a way
that that tries to work nice with nature
instead of working against it so it's a
lot of observing nature and then trying
to interfere only in the slightest ways
we're digging trenches for our pony
tunnel so what we're gonna do the next
days is to put the plastic foil on top
of this metal frame and then the cornice
will be dug in and for this we need
trenches this multifunctional tool also
doubles as a backscratcher so good I
coordinated the gardens in a colony for
three and a half years yeah we met each
other in a colony five years ago and
that's where I first got into touch with
gardening and my passion or a medicinal
plants the last year's we were basically
just like you guys traveling in our bus
I went to visit this place with Sina and
after some long discussions here we
decided to to come here to set up the
garden side - Rafa all day - batches and
the patches the dresser is it tight on
the plants in added the setter where she
sang also claiming Pittsburgh so
exponent Mesa
Varma soon Mike centered on the hill I
need a chef knelt in heart fervently
chief after seeing a fortune I hope it's
a good health it's all spa days dune has
[Music]
beautiful plants grow it's about two
months ago that Hilden Oscar left us and
we just wanted to show you how our
garden looks after two months and the
tunnel that we built together with them
it comes - yes thank Estill I stopped
the drag vector still is any glaze no it
kill Dracula the cost was cold we should
have who means crazy and it's already in
the name we should add somehow so it's
it's a crazy castle first it was not
really a castle it was like a hunting
house and then the previous owner added
some castle-like features yeah exactly
the castle is just a meeting point like
that's how I feel it nowadays it's just
a meeting point for a lot of people for
the first time in my life I'm preparing
a bed for sewing sacrum I listen as I my
future it's out up in the baqia and his
eyes life on the site comes and the
pockets are chopped coated in a hockey
here and a fourth of here in the fill
and I work at the site we eventually
also want to teach courses and host
people have a little cafe and experiment
with new methods of gardening well we're
going to plant nitrogen-fixing plants
like trees and shrubs lower bushes and
the idea is that those enrich the soil I
love working with the ground working
with the soil working with my hands also
it just really grounds me
yeah makes me feel more connected the
idea is that there is in the future will
be a more permanent group here and
that's really what I what I like just to
live with a group of people that you can
inspire each other and everybody has his
own qualities that's just wonderful you
can share those qualities with each
other so if you enjoyed this video share
it with everyone you know and don't know
and type some commands do it now and is
there a donate button somewhere yeah
there's a donate button guys you know
what we were pressed you basically did
also forum and it's now time to say
bye-bye to all you folks and see you
next time