not sure if this is the best way to get
a hold of Courtney but if so I
appreciate your time reading this and
hopefully getting some feedback I
followed and watched most of your
YouTube videos and you're really one of
the reasons I want to get serious about
selling tractor attachments uh-oh this
might be backfiring I'm I'm inspiring
competition I live in North Carolina I
bought and sold used attachments for a
while on Marketplace in some occasions I
buy them broken fix them and sell them I
really enjoy doing it and it brings in
some extra cash I have a full-time job
that I also love and pays well too this
is where I need your feedback or at
least what you think I want to get into
buying and selling used and new
attachments as a real business I guess I
should just get an LLC how do I go about
selling new how do I even make money
selling new I see attachments and it
looks like it would be cheaper to just
buy them off of marketplace nope sorry
sorry I see attachments and it looks
like it would be cheaper to just buy
them off the
manufacturer yes that's that's pretty
straightforward there I feel like I need
a lot of money just to even place an
order to have some attachments in stock
if that's how it works is there a
minimum number of attachments that I
have to buy do I have to be a dealer I
really don't know how it works I visited
and talked to the owners of two local
farm equipment stores I talked to them
and both roughly said not to get into
the business jokingly I think they were
nice guys but a little disappointed on
what they told me I'm hoping they were
just too busy to talk to me for that
long I have a local company that sells
attachments I can start with them I
don't mind the work it's just I don't
know where to start
you don't really have to answer every
single question above I just don't know
what the right question is to ask I
appreciate you taking time to read this
thank you okay so a lot going on here
and I I'm joking about helping the
competition I mean
I I'm confident enough in my abilities
to know that I I've got my own market
and that there's a ton of tractor
attachment dealers out there that really
only sell locally and there's some you
know I have some online competition too
I'm I'm not I'm fully aware of that and
that's the way of the world and it does
complicate things quite a bit more if
you're going to go online and and sell
Nationwide but in
general how I started out selling was
Finding attachments that I wanted to
sell right so let's just take pallet
forks for example and those are one of
the most popular tractor attachments
that are out there and there's probably
100 or 150 manufacturers that make those
and they're all going to be at different
price points you know different weight
ratings configurations and um areas of U
the countries of origin where where
they're manufactured and and yada yada
yada so the other issue is that you're
going to have some manufacturers that
will sell directly a lot of
Manufacturers that uh will sell through
Distributors that maybe like a
distributor covers Michigan where I'm at
for example then a different distributor
covers Indiana you know and so maybe you
have to go through that layer um some
manufacturers just sell directly and so
you you can't even work with them and so
it's take that times every single
attachment you want to sell and you have
to go through that process and then
see what's going to work for you what
kind of relationships you can get what
kind of minimum buys you have to buy
everyone's going to be different there's
not going to be a a standard answer for
every brand that you're working with we
actually manufacture some attachments
and sell uh to dealers as well and so
we'll do bundle buys with minimum
quantities and since we ship Nationwide
you know normally when we had stuff
shipped into us from our fabricator that
manufactures for us it's you know on a
pallet that contains a set quantity of
whatever that item is so that's how we
do our our sales with dealers is that
they need to buy based on the pallet
quantity because it's it just comes in
like that it's set like that it's easy
to ship out it's already prepackaged and
then we give a bundle discount based on
that to to send out to dealers and so
you're going to
find I don't think most manufacturers
work it that way they're just going to
tack on freight based on whatever it is
you order at the end of the year like
say now a lot of Manufacturers will give
you an incentive an extra incentive to
place an order for next spring but
there's
no the only way that you can find this
stuff out is doing it so you need to
reach out and call and this applies to
any industry this isn't just tractor
stuff if you want to sell computer parts
or anything else it's it's the same kind
of a concept where you're going to find
that there's no standard way that every
single manufacturer in your segment is
operating with a a set of the same set
of rules they all have different rules
they all have different price points and
I will say that the closer you can get
to the manufacturer and get out of the
Distributors typically the better
pricing you're going to have um
sometimes the manufacturers are aware of
that and will just make their price a
bit higher and keep some more profit for
themselves which more power to them but
otherwise if you have to go from a
manufacturer to a distributor and then
to you for example well that's more
people that need to make money on top of
it keep in mind you then have to Market
up to sell to a an end user as well and
and that's going to work against you the
cheaper the price point maybe not the
cheaper or lower quality product but
just the lower the price point in
general the more likely you are to sell
that product too so that just comes with
putting the time in talking to people
you know and comes with the weeks the
months the years that go by on
understanding how that gain is played so
let's let's move on to the next point or
next question that he had folks we are
proud to be sponsored by rimgard
Solutions a liquid ballast weight it
goes right inside your tires completely
hidden we're big on safety on this
channel these tractors are just too
light and Tippy right out of the factory
not only is it going to help with safety
keeping those rear tires planted on the
ground it helps with loader efficiency
and traction too the benefits of rim
guard include being the heaviest
allnatural liquid balast weight on the
market it's not going to corrode your
rims like the old calcium chloride it's
not going to freeze and it's available
at over thousand dealers Nationwide find
the dealer near you at rimgard
solutions.com he asked if he should get
an LLC and yeah I mean I would contact
your accountant and and maybe an
attorney uh to do it the right way or
just go to Legal Zoom or at least
something on there and get set up you
want to have protection for your
business to separate that from your your
personal accounts and everything else so
keep that separation there get set up
for taxes and and everything else
separately and take advantage of um
those policies when you can feel like
you need a lot of money to even place in
order to have some attachments in stock
well yes and no uh it does really it
does take money to make money in my
opinion at least a significant amount
but once you become credit worthy with a
lot of different well within your
industry you're going to find that you
can get credit terms it's not going to
be a cash basis where if you place an
order you have to pay for it right then
before it's delivered but you can get
maybe uh 30 60 90 day 180-day terms
depending on what it is and you could
potentially if you know what you're
doing have all of your inventory sold
and have that cash come in by the time
that you have to make the payment in 180
days or 90 days whatever it is so you
potentially could use no cash of your
own at a certain point but that is going
to be tough to do upfront without any
kind of creditworthiness in the industry
and then finally he doesn't know where
to start and that is a good place to
start is asking the questions you can't
be
afraid well I think a lot of folks would
be afraid to go into a a tractor
dealership like he did with a couple of
play and ask them how to do this because
you're asking your competition how I can
compete against you and I don't blame
those dealers for not giving him a lot
of information and I also told this
gentleman I'm not going to give you all
of the secrets right it's you know
I again it comes back to don't be afraid
to ask the question but expect to be
told no and when you're not told no then
great take advantage of that opportunity
and glean what you can from it but
that's the only way you're going to grow
is putting yourself out out there and
taking risk like we've talked about
before and this risk really isn't I mean
maybe it affects some of your ego and
that's about it right it's it's it's
costing you a little bit of time but
you're going to learn something from it
either way I mean every interaction you
have you're going to learn something
from it and that doesn't mean you're
learning something from a dealer that
tells you go away I'm not going to help
you out at all but maybe then you know
how to approach the situation
differently the next time around too and
so you can get better from that you can
improve from that and you're going to
find that you become more efficient with
your own time the more often that you do
it so hopefully that helps some other
folks out there that are thinking the
same things that this guy took the time
to email me about and I appreciate him
doing so and I applaud him for doing so
and for you guys out there as well keep
on churning you know again it doesn't
have to be tractor stuff it could be any
Market segment that you're into the same
Concepts apply and you can't beat hard
work now if you are in the market for a
tractor or tractor attachments we would
love to help you out you can check out
goodworkstractors docomo sell and ship
all over the country every day the week
I want to thank you for taking time out
of your day to stop by and until next
time stay safe we'll see you
[Applause]
[Music]
soon