[Music]
okaywe I want to thank Sarah for giving
us the grant to do this project a little
bit of a spoiler alert a lot of it
wasn't really successful but the whole
thing is meant to be a learning
experience right education is you know
the last word in ser so this has been an
education for us so Rebecca and I were
on her family land she's a fourth
generation farmer we're located in North
Kansas City about 45 minutes this is our
farm down there in the left corner we
hit that's where our house is we have a
barn with our packing room our certified
kitchen we have a greenhouse passive
solar we have one high tunnel we have
two movable chicken coops we have a
irrigation pond there with solar panels
so this is kind of some of the details
we met on a CSA farm back in 2001
Rebecca wanted to come back to her
family farm and to you know improve it
and to keep it from just becoming
another lot of houses and so the CSA was
really the model for us at our peak we
were up around 100 close to 150 members
for 31 weeks we have about five acres
five and a half that's actually able to
be cultivated over about a twenty acre
area that we grow on this is some of our
vegetables you know we have a
diversified operation which is really
nice model you know was been talking
diversity is always good and for us you
know we get to eat a diverse diet
because we're growing all these things
our CSA models participatory our members
come out and they help with the harvest
we have what's called a core group they
help to manage the CSA
that's the model of the farm where we
met and it's just a great way to get oh
you know the host of generations even
from one family to come out and
participate in agriculture this is our
certified kitchen that we had built and
right after it was completed 2016 we
decided to kind of diversify our farming
operations and to have a firm a team
that's so that would mean we need to
grow a lot of brassicas so we wanted to
look at different ways to raise the
brassicas without having to do a lot of
mulching we're in our it's like our
second year of of fermenting we like to
say we have a kitchen without a stove in
there it was a good model you know it's
a low-energy type of value-added product
you chop everything at room temperature
the fermenting happens at room
temperature and then you store the
product back in the cooler until you
need to jar it so we already have a
cooler and we only we didn't need to
have a stove or heat stuff up and we're
on the shelves on a a handful of retail
outlets in Kansas City area as well as
selling to our members in a farmers
market so our fertility plan
everybody that's talking about soil it's
gonna be pretty much the same thing and
and like Jeff was saying you really need
commitment so we make sure we feed the
soil a diverse and balanced meal we try
to amend every bet each year with some
type of cover crop or we buy compost
mineral Edition we now have two Lane
flocks of about 7080 hens and they we
fence in the yard fifty by a hundred
feet you know we can leave them in an
area for about two months and moving
them around the farm so we can fertilize
a good acre of land just with our our
hens and we do like I said a lot of
cover cropping you know we
this is like our Sudan grass and cow
peas or crota larrya so we have a flail
mower normally what we would do is we
would grow it we chop it down we have
it's called a spade er it kind of digs
that digs it in it helps it doesn't
create the hard pan that like a tiller
will so we call this our chewing step as
we've been doing more and more farming
we're trying to do this less you know
not use the Spade or just to tilt stuff
in but to mainly use it as a way to
incorporate cover crops we incorporate
them we also do a lot of hey this is
compost from a company called Missouri
organics they're local Kansas City
company that's been growing and we were
able to get truckloads of compost
sometimes we'll use a you know a dry bag
fertilizer we use for trel it's kind of
handy at times if you want to add some
fertility to a bed and it's kind of been
out of the rotation or you haven't been
able to time things properly and then
here's our our hens we really like it
when we can raise a cover crop and put
the hens in and have them to eat the
cover crop or we run them through our
high tunnel in the spring after we're
done with our extended season of the
previous fall and spring they've been a
great way to improve the fertility and
the high tunnel you know they provide a
lot of phosphorus don't the things you
learn then realize what it is is that
they don't really process phosphorus
sowing the phosphorus and the feed kind
of goes through them and it's where we
are that's one of them are limiting
nutrients is the phosphorus and so this
has been our our results just using our
farming practices as you can see I've
been farming for 16 years I used to be
an environmental engineer I used to do a
lot of environmental sampling and
analysis and treatment system design and
monitoring so around 2004 I believe it
was I decided well I should maybe plot
our soil organic matter
and it's been really instructive it
shows that it bounced around between 2
and 3 percent for a long time and it
actually kind of went down and then
after 2008 it's it's been trending up
and one of the things we're trying to do
in promoting our CSA and promoting art
ferments is to talk about that how the
value that's in that and I think next
door they're talking about how to
quantify that value and I think that's
important so for the cover crop project
the idea was rather than mulching as you
saw doing on our brassicas we were able
to we've been able to raise cover crops
historically raise cover crops roll it
down and and plant into that so we were
going to do that for cabbage cauliflower
and broccoli and then we also have
tomatoes that we wanted to do so we
started out in 2014 actually 2013 is
when we started by raising our crops the
rive edge we dr. Ron Morris from
Virginia Tech he was our Technical
Assistant and so he helped us kind of
helped us build the no-till planting aid
and he gave us some advice so that's
just a flail mower where we turned off
the blades you know it's got a big heavy
roller on it we're able to roll down the
cover crops so this was like step 1
everything looked like it's gonna be
perfect it rolled down really well was a
real good mixer Ryan betch we were
really happy
the vet came back but you know that was
fine we didn't care too much we mowed it
down did that a couple times and it kind
of disappeared and but then the weeds
started so bindweed was a big issue
where we were doing this turns out we
had a heavy fine weed problem we had
some other areas where we were doing it
you know we're all in the grassland area
in the middle of you know June July
every seed of grass is going to start to
come up
no matter what and so in talking to dr.
Morris you know we said you really need
a stale seed bed if you're gonna do this
you know his work was down at Virginia
Tech kind of up in the mountains and
it's really a whole different soil
growing season and what's favored so all
this was happening but we're thinking oh
this is a test we need to kind of see
what we can do so first thing we did is
we took our farm throughout there and we
weeded and kept track and I think it
took you know eight hours worth of work
just to do like this 40 foot stretch of
two beds so you know got that on the
record it's like okay hand weeding isn't
gonna work and then we tried organic
herbicides we're not certified organic
but we follow NOP and we tried two
different types of basically kind of you
know citric acid type insecticide but
all it does it just burns off the top
growth that did nothing to stop the
growth so we kind of had to abandon that
we tried it again we'll talk about other
attempts but basically you know we can
get good stands to cover crops and
they're easily rolled and crimped with
the flail mower the the weed pressure
and June and July it was significant
so our cover crops are rolled down like
the maybe the last week of May or so
somewhere in there that's kind of
typical from where we are we're not
going to plan our brassicas we don't
start them in the greenhouse until the
first second week of June so that whole
time period that rolled down is just
sitting there and that's when all this
weed pressure comes up I'll show you
though what times where it's hard to do
and like I said the weeding and the
organic herbicides really weren't a
solution so the next step was this
no-till planting aid so you roll it down
any ideas you can just cut furrows in
the rolled down cover crop and then we
were going to bring our transplant or
through
and have it spaced at that same two foot
spacing and plant so at the beginning I
thought all we had this whole piece of
equipment laying around from what I can
tell it all be we'll just be able to
kind of see redo this well doctor Moore
said those Coulter's were way too small
once I put that toolbar on our tractor I
realized it was a diamond pattern
instead of a square pattern and I had
bought a square clamp and so there were
all sorts of you know just farm hack
complications I hooked it all up to kind
of see how it might look
and the Coulter was so big that it
wasn't long enough so we had to do we
did an extension to put the fertilizer
shoe on and then that still wasn't good
enough so then we ended up putting a
getting another piece of steel that
extended the length of it so we could
separate all those and so in the end we
got it built and it worked well see it's
a little tilt II there we got an old
tractor but it would drag through and it
would cut the furrow you'd have to watch
about stuff kind of get snagged you know
we kind of rigged that up so there'd be
some things we would trim it up trim off
to keep from snagging and you can kind
of see there it the shovel went in there
the fertilizer knife they cut a nice
furrow so if we were going to come
through with transplants we would have
been able to do that so the no-till
planting aid farm hacking was fine
rather than buying a new one but if I
had to do it again we'd probably go to
equipment supplier and and try and
fabricate it from new pieces of
equipment it was really a great tool we
may use it in the future too if there's
a really wet period and we can't get in
somewhere and we don't want to do any
serious tilling we could always kind of
maybe drag that through to create a
planting row we held a couple feet field
days - it was tough - time doing the
roller crimping with our field days but
we're
able to to show some equipment at the
same time that we were having our field
days so 2015 was a seriously wet year so
I know if you can read all this but from
from May 5th until July 20th we had 35
inches of rain over 74 days and so it
was just consistent I mean it was really
bad
that was the year I decided I was gonna
start collecting records so I was kind
of glad I did that it really showed this
that's a year's worth the rain for us
we even had a hailstorm one point
through there right there in strawberry
season and they just Rebecca said it
looks like little fairy punches on the
strawberries so kind of destroyed that
you know we were trying to to still do
things you know probably shouldn't have
this is an example of this area had been
I don't think we even really had a
chance to roll it down or I might have
tried rolling that down and it was just
a mess so talk to Joan is like okay this
year we're you know we're extending the
whole project and that was fine so 2015
was kind of off the books another part
of it was the cedar evaluation we were
just gonna buy a regular grain drill you
know it's one of those things everybody
so you can buy them they're all over the
place and I went looking over and over
over again so we have like six foot beds
six foot wide beds and you know I really
wanted like you know get eight rows in
that six foot eight nine rows and have
something that's designed to put grain
seed in the ground and just could not
find anything anywhere used that size so
we decided to do was to buy some
vegetables Cedars and so these are for
coal you know Planet jr. vegetable
Cedars bought a new tool bar hook that
up the idea was well we'll do like two
passes and that'll be our cover crop
so what we also do and normally we've
always done in the past is to use a
broadcast seeder and then come through
with a Harrow we would mix our cover
crops ahead of time and knock you late
the legumes and then add the grain mix
it up and then just spread it all
together just one thing is an aside you
know talking about sticking with game
plans Jeff was and improving we have a
Seine on our farm which is from a dr.
Deming who was a quality engineer and
proved constantly and forever so we're
always doing that and was at a
conference
the PFI conference and you're talking
about with cover crops having a more
diverse mix you know if you have up to 8
see different seeds you may actually be
able to plant and have stuff to even
come up in the grout in a drought just
the that diversity creates this
communication that we still haven't
learned about that makes the whole grow
better so we like doing a mix of cover
crop seeds you know it's pretty much
legumes and grain Harrow it in so with
the grass seed there with the the
vegetable Cedars at first I was looking
at putting just an individual like
that's a vet seed and one hopper and
then something else in the other then
I'd have to calibrate them all because
the vegetable planters don't say you
know vet seed and in the end I decided
to mix them so we could just okay
everything's at hole 32 and and that's a
good mix for for all this that's a
little crooked but you can see we've
pulled it across and you know we'd get
decent I kind of wanted a little few
more rows and stuff grew
halfway decent and then later I went and
just decided to ship them all the one
side and go up and back because they
were kind of going on top of each other
they weren't quite staggering the way I
want and with cover crops you know it's
difficult to sometimes get them in at
the same time
you've kind of stale seed bedded so that
was one of the big things that we need
to work on more and more so this is
Sudan grass and cow peas we did a couple
as part of the study was to compare
these two seeding methods and you know
weigh the cover crop and see which works
better so broadcast seeding versus the
cold so in June that was more with a
spring cover crop I believe would have
been like oats and peas the the cedar
did better 13 percent but then the the
when it was done in the summer we
actually better with the broadcast and I
think the reason for that is because
part of the broadcast seeding is a
harrowing to put the seeds into the
ground so depending on your timing of
one you were able to get in there and
cultivate that kind of last Harrow I
think helped with keeping the weed
pressure down so we haven't used the
coal anymore but we got a new full-time
farmer somebody's worked with us before
and so we may go back to trying to use
the tractor to do more of our seating
because a consistent cover crop is is
one of the things that we try to work
with like last year didn't rain at all
and if we didn't maybe he had better
seed to soil contact somehow we might
have had better germination of our cover
crops there's just some more pictures of
the cover crops so this was one where it
worked well you can see that's cow peas
and Sudan grass so it's something to
still consider you may have other pieces
of equipment that you can seed your
cover crops with on your farm so makes a
conclusions you can use a vegetable
cedar I would blend seeds and just have
one seed hole or whatever your equipment
uses
I couldn't quite get everything evenly
spaced and then the harrowing isn't
necessarily a bad thing to do so then in
2016 we tried it again and you can see
what came up was mainly vets you know we
we seeded this in the fall of 2015 and
for some reason we've had this happen
before the ride doesn't come up that
well but the vet does but we still
worked with it and rolled stuff down
that's the flail mower we are able to
get that as part of the project it's
really nice to have a it's a good
quality Alamo and we had some of the
same problems with buying weed so it was
kind of abandon it these are the same
conclusions as the other one and then we
just still had a lot of rain issues so
one of the other things we were trying
our no-till for tomatoes so with our CSA
we raised Tomatoes
and then we like to have a second
planting just because the first one kind
of dies off and doesn't do as well so we
always have we have some summer heat set
tomatoes that we use Bella roses a
variety they're a caged tomato also a
determinate so we don't have to do all
the stringing you can raise them plant
them put a cage around it and you know
necessarily forget them but it there
they take less care and they're more
like a grocery store type tomato but if
you leave them on the vine long enough
and let them ripen you know using
organic growing methods and improving
your soil they do have some some good
flavor and texture
so the
so that whole area had Ryan betch and so
we rolled rolled stuff down and on one
bed for the tomatoes and then the other
one we tilled the cover crop in like we
would normally do we tried to do that
ahead of time and let it rest and then
we came through and we planted our
Tomatoes everything's at two foot
spacing I think somewhere in here I see
I think we had close to 50 Tomatoes per
row and so the one on the Left we we get
a lot of hay we're able to get hay from
other farmland that Rebecca's hormones
her family owns hey mulch and then on
the right we did I believe somewhere in
there at some point do a little bit of
extra mulching but that's the role down
cover crops so you can see that the
mulch ones on the left they're a little
more robust than the ones on the right
and over time you know we didn't do a
lot of weeding on the ones on the right
we did some just to keep him away from
the plants but the idea was to try and
have it be a minimal care system and you
can see that the ones that were in the
cover crop that was turned under did
better they they had nice fruit set and
so here's the data so with the hay mulch
we had almost three times the amount of
tomatoes that we were able to harvest so
their old print crops you know they help
keep the weeds down during the early
growth stage everything kind of got
established pretty well but the baited
and hay mulch beds gave us three times a
year and you know thought with us is
that maybe in a more mature no-till
system that you might get better
nutrient uptake but we feel that by by
spading in you know all that veg and
everything and kind of getting more of a
mixing of the nutrients we're able to
get more nutrients released and that's
part of the reason why we got higher
yield and so here's some costs that were
associated with the project
so the no-till planting aid you know
doing kind of the farm hack and the
likes cost us about eleven hundred bucks
imagine if you did it from scratch it
might be you know closer to two thousand
dollars and then we got a use flail
mower and then we had to we had about
four thousand dollars figured in for the
cedar and I thought I'd be able to find
a used grain drill but we couldn't so
that's what that took and that was all
brand-new equipment
and yeah I think that got plenty of time
here for questions then that's pretty
much it so you have some questions
the question is how much horsepower it
took to pull the no-till planting aid so
that tractor that we were using
that's Rebecca's grandfather's tractor
it's a farm all 504 and it has about 45
horse and it so you know at least
probably 20 horsepower per per Coulter
and fertilizer shoe because it did you
know you could definitely feel some drag
on it but I don't know what the limits
were so question was will we use a sweep
to maybe
undercut all the mulch and no we hadn't
really thought about that I think the
idea of the rolling down is that
everything's kind of all attached and so
we didn't really look at that we've been
using sweeps more and more on the farm
to reduce our tillage like we'll have
our chickens run through an area and
there will be next to nothing there but
you can't quite plant so we will try and
use a sweep just to break up the first
inch so it's kind of more of a shallow
tillage and then I don't know if I have
a picture of it here so we have a Alice
this was another field day in
allis-chalmers G tractor it's a 1948
model tractor and there was another
Sarah project long time ago Ron Colson
in New York he electrified it so we have
48 volts on that tractor it's basically
a golf cart size engine and we use that
all the time you can see those are
that's a cultivator on it right now the
the G is belly-mounted implements so you
can see what's going on one of the other
things we do a lot with it as we use
discs on this a lot so we have a tool
bar that goes right out to the edge of
where the wheels are and they're discs
and so we'll drive along and it will
basically make a raised bed now we have
a lot of heavy
soils we have less soil but then clay
and glacial till not far underneath so
when we get those heavy rains if we
don't have our beds shaped all that
water will just smear everything over
but if the beds are shaped well water
will at least run down the gutters and
stay in the gutters and we'll have some
nice fluffy soil on top so we are like I
said we're moving as much as we can
towards a more reduced tillage and
mainly using our tillage to incorporate
cover crop yeah
we moved it to different areas yeah you
know the one year with all the water
some of the areas we were trying we
weren't even able to do that with but
yeah we have friends in Kansas City
other farmers that do no-till and they
have a lot of a lot of luck but they've
actually gone to hogs right now to kind
of go across their land because they
have a perennial weed pressure so
no-till doesn't have that issue but if
you're able to build up you know more of
the mycorrhizal fungi in the soil there
may be a lot of the benefit to really
doing as little disturbance as possible
what was the planting death depth in the
cedar with the those earth ways they
pretty much just have this like shoe
that hangs down and we didn't really
adjust it too much as long as it would
kind of cut an opening and then be able
to drop the seed down the chute and then
it has a little follower that that
covers it up so yeah you know it
probably wasn't much more than an inch
to an inch and a half you know because
it's a vegetable cedar so you're really
not going too deep
coal planet jr. yeah uh-huh yeah well
you know we've kind of seen to that
you know those they're not no-till cedar
they don't really drill seed and so I
may act different if we if you were
doing an area that had been faded not
too long ago you know so dependent on
the the the soil condition what had
previously happened question was what
it's our cropping system so yeah we had
150 members CSA at this time to
full-time apprentices and sometimes we
have other farm help too and so we were
farming close to five acres and with
that every year we would try and like
when the broccoli came out of production
in the spring make sure we put down
cover crops of a summer cover crop and
then right now we scaled back so we're
only growing about two to two and a half
acres and in 2017 we cook took what we
call sabbatical year we cut our CSA in
half it's only every other week so we
could concentrate on our fermenting
business our business model the idea is
to get back to the point where we're
making the same amount of income half of
its the CSA and then half of it is the
ferments and we spend a lot of 2017
trying to stay all seed bed a lot of our
beds so we had some areas we left them
open and then we'd go through with like
a sweep cultivator and and try and knock
down the weeds just as they were we're
starting and then depending on the time
of year so our spring will plant either
oats or barley with with field peas in
the summer
it tends to be sorghum Sudan grass with
crota larrya or cow peas and then in the
overwintering we do the ryebeck but then
sometimes we also do oats and peas near
the end of summer to have a cover crop
that we can maybe turn in before winter
so one thing we do just because we're
vegetable farmers and you
kind of a prepared bed in the spring to
plant in will do a certain amount of
cover cropping in the fall and then turn
that under kind of as late as we can
maybe the first week of October or
spring and or fall cover cropping and so
to actually be won't have anything
planted in it over the summer or over
the winter but then all that free
stalling makes it like a perfect soil to
plant in in the spring we got to see
beets and carrots or do different things
so and as you can see our organic matter
has gone up so we feel that it shows
that it's a it's a productive system as
far as the soil and I say we try and
turn it under right before winter so
biological activity starts but a lot of
that biomass is still in there so that
it gets released a little bit more in
the spring and summer
yeah so you know it's it's a little
inexact but it was just something more
kind of a good-faith effort to
demonstrate that our soil organic matter
is going up so it's whatever samples we
take in a year we have two different
fields if you went back to like the
first picture
so the fields on the left over here
there's what we call our home field they
they tend to be drier in the spring and
then we we call this our the pond field
so we've gotten to the point where we're
going back and forth now with soil
samples and so that's kind of what the
data is is just whatever we had for that
year well you know we're growing for our
ferments and for the CSA and because I
had one thing that I'd like to try a
little bit different with the cover
crops is a more diverse mix you know
it'll still be like a grain and a legume
but maybe we'll do four types of seeds
or five and I'm kind of looking more
into that so they will do the croud
alaria and the cow peas along with
sorghum sand and grass and find some
other warm season grain that might work
and have like four or five different
seeds that were planting at a time and
just keep trying different things and
with the chickens you know I said we
we've gone more and more to as much
reduced tillage as we can the chickens
have really helped because they
basically do a lot of tilling and so we
can get in there and just shape beds and
maybe just till the top inch so the more
we can do that the better sunhemp yeah
yeah yeah it's nice it grows really well
you know hot and dry as long as you can
get it to germinate question is whether
we sell it market so we sell our
ferments at market our vegetables we
could only grow enough vegetables for
our CSA based on what we know our
membership is so if we have a good year
they might get more of something we can
also have excess we have what's called a
bulk list so we're we have a small farm
central anybody familiar with that it's
an online system it's kind of made for
CSA farms so we use that system people
can sign up online they can keep track
of their own account
so you're not like trying to keep track
or double entering information that
people send you and then they also have
a place where you can kind of sell
online so if we have extra lettuce we
can just put that up and send out an
email it's like if you want extra
lettuce buy it online and we'll deliver
it to your CSA distribution and then
there's an organic farmers market in
Kansas City called Brookside farmers
market and so we go there every other
week to sell the ferments so we're 45
minutes from kind of downtown Kansas
City which is really a really good
distance for us being a participatory
CSA you know a family is going to come
out to do their work requirement farm
work you know it's a little Drive in the
country they're not driving two hours so
you know we're lucky that were
peri-urban as they say we have the farms
one pickup site we have two locations in
the city that we drop off at we have
what we call a core group that manages
the CSA and then a most of the core
group members are distribution captains
and so if there's a distribution site
there's like five people that instead of
coming out to the farm to work they will
rotate and go to the distribution site
and we'll go drop off crates they set it
all up they break it down and make sure
everything works well and then when we
come back the next week
we take the empty crates and deliver the
fresh produce so it's nice for us we
just drive into town then you you know
work in other errands and stuff and with
the ferments it'll allow us to maybe do
some drop-offs there so it helps make it
efficient for us to to drive in
it's been pretty good we're normally 75%
or more we'd our renewals going on right
now and we only opened it up to the last
year's members to start with and we have
100 we're going for 100 members this
year and I think Rebecca said we're up
to you know 65 or so already so I think
we'll be on track for that and since we
went to every other week people have
actually liked that has helped us as
farmers we got this whole extra week
where we can kind of concentrate on
farming more we've worked it out so the
harvesting isn't that big of an issue we
have a Wednesday drop-off as our first
for the week and a Monday is the last
for that distribution week so there's a
handful of days in there that we can
kind of plan stuff we have a 12 by 24
inch cooler that we built as part of our
fermenting project so that helps to we
can store a lot of stuff
[Music]