[Music]
[Applause]
good morning and welcome to Wholesome
roots today I'm going to teach you how I
poed up my tomato plants and some tips
and tricks along the way so in my seed
starting video I told you about how I
start seeds and now it's time for these
tomatoes to be potted up we start our
tomatoes in 128 cells trays that way we
can fit a lot higher number of seedlings
on the heat mat under the light for best
germination so now that theyve all
germinated and they're starting to get
their real leaves their true leaves we
know that it is time to begin pulling
them out of these tiny cells that dry
out every day and move them up to the
next stage so we're not moving up to a
much bigger size we're using the 72 tray
size cuz a lot of these seedlings I
dropped two or three seeds in and all
two or three seedlings germinated so
they need to be separated out into their
own cell so this is a little bit bigger
won't dry out as fast and we'll give
them a chance to grow on their own so
their Roots won't intertwine I recommend
letting your Tomatoes get their first
set of true leaves before you begin
transplanting so that's where we are at
at right now and let me show you the
difference between the seed leaves and
the true leaves so every seed that
germinates has its own seed leaves these
long flat leaves are seed leaves or
otherwise known as
calans they provide the first nutrients
that the plant needs then as the plant
starts to develop they get these leaves
in the center that look more
like tomato leaves so the first step is
to make sure that your potting soil is
adequately moist you don't want it
soaking wet but you don't want it dry
and Dusty or you will not be able to
moisten it at the proper level after
it's in the cells so we always do this
before adding it to the cells and we're
going to go ahead and fill those up and
begin the transplant
so there you go we've filled up we made
sure we didn't miss the corners or the
edges and then we swipe off the excess
and then we just drop it on the table to
Tamp it down make sure that none of them
drop down a good bit if they did we
would top it off and that's it that's
how you fill a tray for seeding or
transplanting
[Music]
so although these larger Sals allow me
to start more seeds at once they do
provide some hiccups we have a lot of
drying out right there in the center of
the tray so we're going to be real
careful with those but you can see here
how big some of these have gotten and
how there's multiple seeds in a
cell and and they need to be
transplanted right away so although
tomato plants are very strong and very
easy to transplant you still have to be
careful with them so what we do is let's
I'm going to go after this row that's
really thick and robust this is green
vernisage or Veris not sure the
pronunciation is correct there but I'm
going to go ahead and I'm going to take
the label and I'm going to move it to
the tray that I'm moving it to and then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
pinch on the bottom of that cell and you
see the soil just pops right out then
I'm going to grab right at the base
right at the soil line making sure other
plants aren't woven into these two and
I'm going to pinch both at the same time
and gently pry them up out of the soil I
didn't water yet this morning because I
didn't want them to be too W to make it
hard to come out so you can see we have
two side by side all we're going to do
is again grabbing from the base you
don't want to grab from the leaves or
from the top of the stem because you can
crack the stem other seedlings are more
sensitive tomatoes are a little more
hearty and you just very gently pull
them away from each
other allowing the roots to untangle
themselves and now you have two
seedlings to plant
now I so I don't lose track of what I'm
doing usually go ahead and pull
out every
plug of that variety and lay it on the
tray that I'm going to be planting it
into this prevents me from mixing them
up with other varieties because we have
over 50 different heirloom varieties we
are
growing so I'm just taking them and
pulling them out of the plug so I just
pinch at the bottom of the plug Pinch at
the bottom of the
plant raise it up from the soil pinch
the plug again oh I was pinching the
wrong plug see that's why it didn't
release easy pinch
Again
release and lay it on the
tray until I'm ready to get them all in
there so something I do is I go through
and I poke my fingers in you can use a
pencil or poker but I just use my
fingers and I poke every single cell
down then when I come through I just
drop the roots into the hole so I may
fill up a whole tray before going back
through and covering up those roots but
you want to do this quickly so that the
root don't dry out and tomatoes should
be planted as deep as you can get them
Tomatoes will be planted all all the way
up to the first set of leaves this whole
area below here will root the stems root
easily you do see that there are hairs
along the stems those are not root hairs
I've heard that often said about
tomatoes that those hairs will turn into
Roots but that's not actually the case
those are tricomes which actually
produce the essential oils that Tomatoes
produce to repel insects from damaging
them so they're not actually root hairs
but the roots will develop all along the
step
[Music]
so I just pushed the root ball down into
the bottom of the tray so that the rest
of the stem can root oops those two got
tangled got to watch out for
that so I just press it down to the
bottom layer and then I'm going to fill
up these cells the rest it
away with soil and I'm not pressing hard
if I press too hard I'm going to damage
the roots and I don't want to do that so
I'm just giving them a nice gentle shove
and that's another reason why it's good
to have your soil already
moist and then I'm just coming back
through and covering up that root
ball and when I water this tray in I'm
going to make
sure that that I look for any Pockets
that
developed and refill any soil that
loosened up so some of you may have
noticed that I just buried some leaves
that is not
intentional that is the result of trying
to film with one hand and demonstrate
with the
other I don't have a uh cameraman like
some YouTubers
do it's just me doing the best I can so
then I go back and I try to Center them
and kind of Tuck the
soil around them to make them a little
bit more centered in the center of the
pot so that the roots can have as much
room as they need to expand in that
cell this is the same way you would do
it if you were planting it into a pot
just picture it on a larger scale I
probably will not get to the pot stage
as we will will be probably
transplanting these straight into the
garden once they have recovered for a
couple of weeks and our frost date has
passed all right and then when you get
to your next variety which is pink
bernis you just do the same thing you
set your marker there and you begin your
row going that way and you just continue
on changing your marker when you get to
a new variety works out pretty well this
way so once you have them in the tray
you just water them in really really
well I'm going to drench them really
good this first watering while they
fight through the Battle of uh coming
back to life if they have any transplant
shock having them good in moisturiz will
help with
that make sure you don't miss the
corners and the edges those tend to be
the ones that dry out the
easiest or if you're using a heat mat in
the center I have turned my heat mat off
now due to that drying out pattern I was
seeing this my
friends is what
540 tomato seedlings looks like after
transplanting they are bouncing back
pretty well the first day I'm keeping
them right inside the door with just
enough light to keep them from going
crazy without the light
look at that they're so they're standing
up so well already that was the first
tray I did so they are bouncing back
going to give them a day or two in here
where I can monitor them um I may set
them out here in my hardening off
area and
then I move them to the
greenhouse it may not be big but it is
sure useful and helpful for us so when
potting up tomato seedlings it's
important to remember that these are one
of the hardiest seedlings you're going
to transplant other things might be a
bit more fragile but tomato seedlings
usually bounce back within 3 days after
transplanting when you transplant a
tomato seedling you should keep it in
the same conditions it was in for a good
2 or 3 days after transplanting and make
sure that that first initial shock has
TN off before you move them to a new
location we are going to be careful and
keep them here in the growroom and then
they're going to go out to the
greenhouse after that it's also
important that you do not fertilize
right away after transplanting a plant
has to reestablish its root zones and
start to develop new Roots before you
give them any fertilizer they're not
going to be able to use the fertilizer
during this stage and it could cause
more harm than good so remember these
tips and tricks you have to have moist
soil before you begin transplanting and
you should always bury your Tomatoes
deeper than they were originally that
helps them produce more Roots along the
stem not along the tric Combs remember
tric Combs are for essential
oils and then you have to make sure that
you water them in really good after
transplanting I usually pretty much soak
them and that then I let them dry out as
they're starting to not dry out all the
way but just dry out enough that they're
not too wet where there's going to be a
fungus issue then you wait a good 2 or 3
days before moving them anywhere else if
you're in a Zone where it's time to
plant your Tomatoes outside remember to
harden them off for a good week or two
before you plant them in the ground I
have a great video on hardening off
plants that you can find on my beginning
Garden series
playlist after you have hardened them
off for 2 weeks and there's no chance of
frost it's time to plant them in the
ground I can't wait mine are a few weeks
behind for my zone so I will be planting
mine later than I normally do but
they're still going to catch up and grow
beautiful tomatoes in no time at all
Tomatoes can be planted as late as July
where I live here in Georgia in zone 8
so we feel completely confident that we
are just right on time even if we're not
on the exact calendar we planned on I
hope these tips and tricks on planting
tomatoes seedlings and potting them up
have helped you and if you have any
questions leave them down in the
comments and we'd be sure to get back to
you on those questions also if you have
any further questions that you would
like to discuss in more detail feel free
to post it on our wholesome Roots
Farmstead friends Facebook group it's a
great group full of knowledgeable people
and we're always there ready to answer
questions we pride ourselves here at
wholesome roots on getting back to
people and answering questions in a
timely fashion so if you haven't heard
back from us after sending us a question
or a message please reach out again and
ask us again and just so you know email
is not as good of a way to get in touch
with me as Facebook messaging or posting
to our group is I hope you continue to
enjoy our gardening series and and if
you have any suggestions for future
videos you'd like to see us make for the
gardening series let us know down in the
comments thank you guys for watching
please like share comment down below
subscribe if you haven't already and
we'll see you next time on wholesome
Roots I want to say it too you want to
say it too till next time on H Roots
good job