hi welcome to Uncle Tim's Farm I'm Uncle
Tim and today I'm going to show you how
I built this Barrel tumbler that I use
to make my t13 seasoning in 40 pound
batches
so right here I'm working on the base
and the two flat spots on top there are
going to be for the pillow block
bearings and you'll see that
here in just a few minutes
foreign
block bearings I was talking about
earlier and I'm just marking where I'm
going to drill the holes
okay here I'm building the I don't know
what you call the basket I guess that's
going to hold the barrel and be the part
that actually tumbles I'm welding on one
of the axles
foreign
the other axles squared up so that I can
get it welded on and as you see I have a
nice sturdy base torque with
foreign
here I'm continuing to work on the
basket by adding sides to it so that the
barrel will be held in place and won't
fall out the sides
foreign
just doing a real quick balance test
all right I'm going to be putting the
uprights on the sides here and I'm using
my Fireball tool Square to try to make
sure everything is
straight and square
takes me a little bit to get this all
put together but eventually I get it
squared away and it works quite well
now that I've got both sides welded on
I'm just doing a real quick test fit to
make sure everything's gonna work as it
should
okay now I'm welding on the top bar
hinges this is going to be where I'll
open it up and be able to put the Barrel
in and then latch it down
I'm welding an end cap on this tube so
that I can attach part of the latch to
it you'll see that in a few minutes
this is the part of the latch that I was
talking about and you'll see how it all
goes together shortly
and now I'm attaching the bottom part of
the latch I'll zoom in here and give you
a little bit closer look so you can see
how it works
foreign
cross members to the top and they'll
have little
flanges that hang down to keep the sides
from bowing out
while in operation
foreign
these are the flanges I mentioned
earlier this is just to keep those
uprights from bowing out at the top once
it's loaded and tumbling around
here I'm working on the base getting it
nice and square and secured together so
that it doesn't flop around
foreign
[Music]
now it's time to put this together and
see how it works
looks like it's working pretty well I'll
grab the barrel here in a minute and
give it another test
foreign
I have some pads that I'll be adding to
this later to keep it from slopping
around like that inside there
so here you can see I've added the
sprocket onto the side and then I've
also added a
counterweight on the bottom so that it
when it stops spinning it will stop with
the bottom on the bottom and the top on
the top so that it can load the barrel
before with the extra Hardware on top
with the latch it was stopping with the
top on the bottom
another Quick Test run
here I'm welding a little axle together
that will screw on to the windshield
wiper motor to help turn this thing
and now it's time to test it with the
motor just I'm just holding it just to
make sure that it will actually turn
this thing
so now I'm welding on the motor mount
that's adjustable so that I can
keep the chain tight and what I found
out after getting this all put together
and actually putting some weight in the
barrel is that this windshield wiper
motor was way
way underpowered it turns this empty or
even with the Empty Barrel in it just
fine but once I put
40 pounds of
seasonings in the barrel it wouldn't
budget
so I ended up having to order
a much larger motor and as you can see
here this is a two horsepower motor and
this is just a a quick test to make sure
it will actually work I just have it
cobbled into place
and it does have
seasoning in it and it is plenty
powerful enough to make it work
once I verified that that motor was
going to work I went ahead and built a
motor mount for it got everything lined
up and then went ahead and painted it as
you can see here
time for the first test run
with it all put together
and it works like a champ and there is
seasoning in that Barrel that's an 18
gallon barrel and I have it's not a full
40 pounds because I've pulled some out
of there to use but it does have quite a
bit of weight in it and this two
horsepower motor will have no problems
I'll do another video here in the near
future of me actually mixing up a whole
batch of seasoning
thanks for watching and see you next
time
foreign
[Music]