let's say you have a massive amount of
water and you have a bunch of different
pipes and you need to get that up real
up but of course you don't want to put a
bunch of pumps over here because that
will be a waste of resource well there's
one cool trick just utilize something
called a water tower all you got to do
is take a water extractor a bunch of
different pumps and pump that one line
all the way to the top once it gets to
the floor that you need it to go to all
you're going to do is you're going to
bring it straight down now that's on the
original floor that you needed to be on
what you're going to do is you're going
to take it to your water plant then
you're going to take the pump and put it
all the way to the end of the system
this is going to push this pump all the
way to the top but what about the rest
of them all you got to do is just hook
it over to the next one and then hook
that one to the next one then hook that
one to the next one and soon this
massive water pump plant is going up up
and away with only one two or three
pumps depending on how tall you're going
so if you like what you see don't forget
to subscribe and a copy of the map will
be in the Discord if anybody wants to
check it out later