[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
[Music]
foreign
ographical characteristics of the Canary
Islands in the middle of the Atlantic
and close to the African continent
determined that water has always been a
matter of fundamental importance for the
people that have lived in the
archipelago
unable to count on sufficient Water
Resources the supply of the population
livestock industry and agriculture have
been common concerns throughout history
therefore it is not strange that there
has always been a great interest in
studies related to water and customs of
hydraulic Technologies washing
agriculture Irrigation in part because
the problems have never been solved as
is evident today due to water pollution
scarcity and Rising prices
in this sense water has always played a
fundamental role for the Canary
Islanders in religious symbols and
rituals in food Customs for Hygiene for
animals and Agriculture and as a source
of energy for Industries
by studying the history of water use in
a geographical space like the Canary
Islands we are exposed to the decisive
way in which settlers have intervened to
change the landscape of the islands
Islands were forced to put in practice
different strategies to circumvent
existing obstacles and to obtain
hydrological resources
all this has been a long journey
which has gone from the use of water
that ran along the surface
to the use of water provided by trade
winds to water extractions from the
aquifers
deep below the Earth's surface
all in search for the water necessary
for life
[Music]
all
right
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]